<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. WARNING TO GOVERNORS ON ENFORCING POLLUTION PLANS</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="28448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, LEE M (ADMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD123EF93BA35757C0A961948260" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. WARNING TO GOVERNORS ON ENFORCING POLLUTION PLANS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency warned governors today that the agency would soon disapprove some of their air pollution control plans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency warned governors today that the agency would soon disapprove some of their air pollution control plans.</p>
        <p>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency warned governors today that the agency would soon disapprove some of their air pollution control plans.</p>
        <p>The official, Lee M. Thomas, also said the agency would have no choice under the law but to ban construction of new sources of pollution where a state failed to enforce a pollution control plan approved by the agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas did not say which plans would be disapproved. The agency said it would announce those next month.</p>
        <p>The actions would be the agency's first substantive steps this year toward bringing the nation into compliance with Federal air pollution standards, notably for ozone, by a Dec. 31 deadline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas warned last year that many cities would fail to meet the deadline for reducing ozone pollution. Meeting the deadline is an acknowledged impossibility for some areas such as Los Angeles. New York is high on the list of metropolitan areas where additional attention to ozone is needed.</p>
        <p>A construction ban would not stop a large factory from adding a new process that produced pollution as long as it could make offsetting reductions in emissions at the same site. But it could bar construction of a new plant if a permit had not already been requested.</p>
        <p>In addition, the agency intends to disapprove ''a number of plans which cannot provide a persuasive demonstration that they will attain the standard in the near term,'' Mr Thomas wrote in letters to the governors. In these cases, the agency has discretion to cut off Federal highway and sewer funds, something it has rarely done.</p>
        <p>These plans are awaiting agency decisions. Some have been pending for California areas since 1983, when former Administrator William D. Ruckelshaus decided not to rule on their adequacy because of their inadequacy..</p>
        <p>Ozone, a key constituent of smog, is formed by the reaction in sunshine of unburned hydrocarbon fuels and similar chemicals with a combustion product, oxides of nitrogen. In high concentrations, it can cause breathing difficulties and worsen respiratory diseases.</p>
        <p>The agency estimates that 76 of the nation's several hundred air pollution control areas do not meet the current standard for ozone. Most could comply through relatively minor action, such as auto pollution inspections or vapor recovery nozzles at gasoline stations.</p>
        <p>But about 20 areas will have grave difficulty of ever meeting the standard without drastic reduction in motor vehicle use and controls on many small polluters such as bakeries, the agency believes.</p>
        <p>Letters went to governors and the mayor of the District of Columbia, with technical letters to state and local air pollution authorities.</p>
        <p>Arkansas, Hawaii, Mississippi, North Dakota, South Dakota, Vermont, West Virginia and Wyoming got no letters because those states have no areas that exceed Federal air pollution standards.</p>
        <p>Letters to Alaska, Idaho, Minnesota, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New Mexico and South Carolina concerned only carbon monoxide, another pollutant produced by burning fossil fuel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
