<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sequim Journal; Upside-Down Climate in Washington</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="71601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SEQUIM (WASH)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DUNGENESS RIVER VALLEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TURNER, WALLACE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DE103CF937A3575AC0A961948260" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sequim Journal; Upside-Down Climate in Washington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALLACE TURNER, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TURNER, WALLACE</byline>
      <dateline>SEQUIM, Wash.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The climate seems to get turned upside down here in the rain shadow of the Olympic Mountains, and one result is the slow evolution of a community dominated by people who retired early, sometimes in their mid-50's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The climate seems to get turned upside down here in the rain shadow of the Olympic Mountains, and one result is the slow evolution of a community dominated by people who retired early, sometimes in their mid-50's.</p>
        <p>The climate seems to get turned upside down here in the rain shadow of the Olympic Mountains, and one result is the slow evolution of a community dominated by people who retired early, sometimes in their mid-50's.</p>
        <p>''I'd say 75 percent of our sales last year were to people coming here to retire,'' said Charlotte Bidstrup, manager of a real estate sales office here. ''A lot of them rent for three or four months to see how they like it, and they almost always end up buying.''</p>
        <p>Federal statistics indicate that upward of half the people living here in the Dungeness River Valley, 50 miles northwest of Seattle across Puget Sound, draw monthly retirement checks from the Social Security Administration.</p>
        <p>The Pacific Northwest is widely known for its rainy weather, but this valley averages only 16.8 inches of rainfall a year, to Seattle's 39 inches. Rain-producing winter storms carried by southwesterly winds lose much of their moisture over the 8,000-foot-high Olympic range before descending on Sequim and its valley. By way of comparison, San Francisco has 19.5 inches, New York 41.5 and Miami 59.8.</p>
        <p>Temperatures in the valley range from a maximum of 45 and minimum of 31 degrees in January to a maximum of 72 and minimum of 49 degrees in July.</p>
        <p>The name of Sequim is derived from the Clallam Indian word for ''quiet water.'' But even before people learn how to pronounce the name properly (as if it were spelled Squim) they come here because they've heard of the inviting climate. The population of the town has grown from 1,164 in 1960 to 3,400 at the latest count, and 17,000 people now live in the valley on land that was dairy farms 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>''My wife and I traveled in our trailer all over Washington and Oregon looking for land to buy after I retired in 1978,'' said Jack L. Mauck, who for 30 years was a deputy sheriff and police officer in Los Angeles. ''We pulled into Sequim one day, and we never left.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mauck, 61 years old, says that in the first year or so he went fishing three or four times a week. Then he began to grow restive. ''I found I was going to town a lot,'' he said. ''A policeman's life is a people business, and I wasn't seeing many people.''</p>
        <p>He said he began to sell real estate but found he was working too hard. Then he took over as executive director of the Sequim-Dungeness Valley Chamber of Commerce, a job he said keeps him busy, but not too busy. ''We find when we move here that we get laid back, whether we plan it that way or not,'' he said. ''Your life style just changes.''</p>
        <p>In a time when people in many careers qualify for early retirement, the Sequim area's population includes former teachers, firefighters, police officers, Foreign Service officers and airline pilots, Mr. Mauck said.</p>
        <p>Mary Puhl is a new arrival. Her husband, Charles, was an airline maintenance mechanic in San Francisco. When he retired several years ago they sold their home in Daly City, Calif., and moved into a retirement village between San Francisco and Sacramento.</p>
        <p>''I didn't like it,'' said Mrs. Puhl. ''Nothing but old people. I want to hear the kids yell. Our daughter told us about Sequim. We got here June 4, and they're building our new house right now.''</p>
        <p>Acting Mayor Stan Foster, 73, was a truck driver for the Seattle city engineering department and took early retirement at the age of 58 to come here and take up life in the house he built on a lot he bought when he was 50. ''I couldn't wait to get here,'' he said. Four of his six colleagues on the local City Council are retired, and one of those still working is an 82-year-old of whom the Mayor said, ''If he quit working it would kill him.''</p>
        <p>Because of its remote site, Sequim and its climate went unnoticed, people here say, until about 1972, when Modern Maturity, the magazine of the American Association of Retired Persons, mentioned it in an article that praised the Pacific Northwest generally as a retirement area.</p>
        <p>People come here to find more than a park bench in the sun. They may be drawn by the hiking in the Olympic National Park, the fishing in lakes or the Strait of Juan de Fuca, or sometimes the simple act of beholding beauty.</p>
        <p>At dusk one day not long ago, as the snow on the Olympics to the south and the Cascades to the east turned golden in the sun's last rays, tiny fish broke the surface of Dungeness Bay. About 400 seagulls wailed as they swooped down to feed and then retreated to a sandbar.</p>
        <p>As darkness turned the sea black, a freighter's shadow moved toward the Pacific through Victoria's lights across the strait in British Columbia. And another day ended for the people of Sequim, with the special brand of peace that they had come here to find.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
