<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A GEORGIA PORT WITH A ROYAL PAST</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="47293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRUNSWICK (GA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUNKE, LEWIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DE1E3AF934A35755C0A961948260" item-length="2831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A GEORGIA PORT WITH A ROYAL PAST</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEWIS FUNKE; Lewis Funke is a former drama editor for The Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUNKE, LEWIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Most Florida-bound travelers heading down Interstate 95 usually regard Brunswick, Ga., as nothing more than the last overnight stop before crossing the border into the promised land. Yet, it is considerably more than that. In addition to being the gateway to three of the romantically described ''Golden Isles'' of Georgia,</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Most Florida-bound travelers heading down Interstate 95 usually regard Brunswick, Ga., as nothing more than the last overnight stop before crossing the border into the promised land. Yet, it is considerably more than that. In addition to being the gateway to three of the romantically described ''Golden Isles'' of Georgia,</p>
        <p>Most Florida-bound travelers heading down Interstate 95 usually regard Brunswick, Ga., as nothing more than the last overnight stop before crossing the border into the promised land. Yet, it is considerably more than that. In addition to being the gateway to three of the romantically described ''Golden Isles'' of Georgia, Brunswick has a legitimate claim to historic recognition.</p>
        <p>The city, on a peninsula in the Brunswick River, was founded in 1771 by the crown colony of Georgia as a port. Its name honors the British royal family's connection with the German house of Hanover, whose ancestral home was Braunschweig; in other ways as well, Brunswick's early affinity for the motherland remains in evidence today.</p>
        <p>This is especially true of the city's south end, known as Old Town Brunswick, which is listed in the national register of historic places. The original town, laid out in squares and streets similar to the planned city of Savannah but on a smaller scale, recalls pre-Revolutionary Britain's nobles and heroes in such place names as Halifax Square (Earl of Halifax), Gloucester Street (Duke of Gloucester), George Street (King George III) and Howe Street (General Lord Howe, who fought in the French and Indian War and later against Washington in the Revolutionary War).</p>
        <p>Brunswick's importance as a port made it a particular target during the War of 1812, when it was captured and damaged, and during the Civil War, when it was nearly destroyed. The oldest buildings in town are the L. T. Pace residence at 908 Union Street (circa 1860), which was floated down to Brunswick from South Carolina after the Civil War, and the Curtis N. Neeld home at 811 Union Street (1869). A number of delightful Victorian homes in the Old Town testify to Brunswick's prosperity in the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>Two especially interesting buildings are the Old City Hall at 1229 Newcastle Street and the Court House in Court House Square at Reynolds and G Streets. The red brick and gray city hall, built circa 1888 by the Savannah architect Alfred S. Eichbert, is an eclectic mixture of Queen Anne and Victorian design, with elaborate arches, chimneys, gargoyles and turrets from which cherubs smile sweetly. The courthouse, erected circa 1908, is said to be one of the most beautiful in the South. Constructed of gray concrete and marble, it has huge circular columns and, at the top, a cupola with a large clock on each of its four sides. The square itself is remarkably beautiful. Labels identify the unusual trees as tung, Chinese pistachio, dahoon, moss-hung live oak, pecan, grape myrtle, laurel oak.</p>
        <p>From Court House Square it is a short ride down Norwich Street to the intersection of Albany and Prince Streets for a moment of sentimental reverie. Here stands Lover's Oak, where, according to legend, an Indian youth and his maiden used to meet by moonlight. The oak, more than 900 years old, has long been popular with neighborhood children who like to climb, as well as with artists.</p>
        <p>Another illustrious Brunswick tree is the Lanier Oak at Gloucester Street and Glynn Avenue, honoring the great Georgia poet. Under its branches Sidney Lanier was said to have been inspired to write some of his finest poetry. From here one can look out across the broad marshes of which he wrote in ''The Marshes of Glynn,'' one of the masterpieces of 19th-century American poetry. Protected by law, the marshes retain the pristine beauty that inspired Lanier in the 1870's. As a buffer between ocean and mainland, they prevent coastal erosion, and they are also important as a spawning ground for shrimp and other kinds of marine life.</p>
        <p>From Brunswick, Georgia's Golden Isles are a proverbial hop, skip and jump.</p>
        <p>Inexpensive toll roads, traversing blue inland waters, connect with St. Simons and Jekyll, and from St. Simons a toll-free road leads to Sea Island, one of the country's distinguished resorts.</p>
        <p>The largest of the three is St. Simons. Aside from its attractive climate, its recreational facilities and its semitropical beauty, with miles of gorgeous white sand beaches, the island is laden with history.</p>
        <p>The area around Gascoigne Bluff in St. Simons' southwestern portion was headquarters for English warships in 1736 when trouble between England and Spain began brewing over Caribbean trading rights. The quarrel erupted into war. On July 7, 1742, at what was to become known as the Battle of Bloody Marsh, a British force, outnumbered five to one, ambushed and defeated a Spanish column bent on taking Fort Frederica, the British stronghold six miles to the north. Bloody Marsh may not have been a big battle, but it was the first decisive one in the New World. Defeated, their morale shaken, the Spanish forces retreated to their base in Florida, never again to venture north along the coast.</p>
        <p>Marking the battle site, just off Demere Road, is a monument with a plaque inscribed with the words of Gen. James Oglethorpe, Georgia's founder: ''We are resolved not to suffer defeat. We will rather die like Leonidas and his Spartans if we can but protect Georgia and Carolina and the rest of America from desolation.'' A recording describes the battle.  Fort Frederica - a fortified settlement on the Frederica River, named for Frederick, Prince of Wales and only son of George III - was set on a bluff overlooking a sharp bend in the river from where its guns commanded all water approaches. Behind the fort was the settlement, which, at its peak, embraced a population of 1,500 and could claim the distinction of being ''the largest, most regular and perhaps most costly fortification in North America.''</p>
        <p>The war with Spain ended in 1748, and General Oglethorpe disbanded his regiment the following year. With the military's payroll gone, the town's economy soon declined and the shopkeepers and tradesmen moved elsewhere. The Great Fire ten years later destroyed most of the buildings, and when the last soldiers withdrew from the fort in 1763, Frederica ceased to exist.</p>
        <p>Today the ruins of the fort and the town, first excavated in the 1950's, are superbly maintained as a national monument by the National Park Service. In the visitor center, with its little museum, a half-hour film is shown throughout the day. Along with a walking tour of the grounds, it provides a fascinating glimpse into life in pre-Revolutionary coastal Georgia.</p>
        <p>Just beyond the entrance to the center is the old burial ground, where, except for four raised tombs and one vault, unmarked graves cover the bones of those who died at Frederica. Near the fort is Christ Church, Frederica, erected in 1820. It was at Christ Church's previous location that, on March 9, 1736, Charles Wesley - a leader in the development of Methodism - had begun his ministry; later, John Wesley preached there as well. Following the near destruction of the church at its present site during the Civil War, it was rebuilt by Anson Green Phelps Dodge Jr. as a memorial to his first wife, Ellen. The building is cruciform in design, with a trussed roof. Stained-glass windows commemorate incidents in the life of Jesus and the early history of the church. In the yard, former rectors are buried alongside early settlers and residents from plantation days.</p>
        <p>A few last bits of St. Simons history: Aaron Burr fled here after his duel with Alexander Hamilton. Fanny Kemble, the renowned British actress, wrote many of her antislavery letters while living on the Hamilton Plantation, now the site of one of the seven shrines of world Methodism, Epworth-by-the-Sea. And it was from this island that timber was cut for the first ships of the Navy, including the U.S.S. Constitution.</p>
        <p>Sea Island is truly another world from St. Simons. Sea Island Drive, with its magnificent homes and manicured grounds, is perhaps one of the most beautiful residential streets in America. History seems to have barely touched the island - it was not developed until the late 1920's. If its visitors and inhabitants have their say, it will remain exactly what it is: a lush garden of flowering shrubs, ancient oaks, palms and pines, a year-round resort brushed by the Atlantic and home of the internationally celebrated Cloister Hotel.</p>
        <p>The state-owned Jekyll Island claims among its other assets 63 holes of golf over four courses, as well as 10 miles of white sand beach dotted with sand dollars, seashells, pelicans and sea turtles. Unlike its exclusive and expensive neighbor, Jekyll Island offers accommodations in various price ranges, jogging and bike trails, programs during the summer for youngsters, plenty of tennis courts and lures for bird watchers and photographers. Nature has been generous, and the Jekyll Island Authority, which supervises development, has done a good job of protecting the island's gifts, including the wild turkey, quail and deer that populate the woods.</p>
        <p>What gives the island a special distinction, however, is its historic district. Declared a national historic landmark in 1978, the 240-acre area was once the heart of the ultra-exclusive Jekyll Island Club, the special winter refuge of men who, at one point, were reputed to control one-sixth of the world's wealth. (Consider some of the names that appeared on the roster over the years: Rockefeller, Morgan, Astor, Vanderbilt, Pulitzer, Gould, Goodyear, Crane.) The club was born in 1886 when a group of tycoons from the Northeast and Midwest, seeking a private resort for themselves and their families, bought the island for $125,000. They selected the noted landscape architect Horace W. S. Cleveland to lay out the plans for the subdivision that would contain both the grounds for the clubhouse and plots for members wishing to build homes. Architect Charles A. Alexander was assigned to create the design for the clubhouse, which would function as the island's hotel and social center. By Nov. 1887 the work was completed, making 1987 the club's centennial year.</p>
        <p>Part of the yearlong celebration, which includes lectures, special exhibits, lawn parties and a croquet tournament, will be the reopening of the clubhouse as a world-class hotel and resort. Closed since 1972, it has been faithfully restored at a cost of $17 million. Its 136 rooms and suites represent a careful blending of turn-of-the-century charm and modern convenience. According to the club's manager, Max Wohlferth, the renovation was financed by private investors, the federal government, the city of Brunswick and the Glynn County-Brunswick Development Authority. It is being operated as a franchise of the Radisson Hotel Corporation.</p>
        <p>Subsequent to the construction of the clubhouse, a number of members built their own homes, which they called cottages, though in truth they are mansions of no mean proportions. Eight are open to the public. Among these is Indian Mound Cottage, built in 1892 and purchased by William Rockefeller (one of the original members of the club) from the Gordon McKay estate in 1904.</p>
        <p>The exterior of Indian Mound is not especially ornate, though it does bespeak wealth. It has dormers, formal columns on the porches and a porte-cochere, or covered driveway, at the main entrance. As members were expected to dine in the clubhouse, the homes usually did not have kitchens; in Indian Mound, though, as in some others, there was a warming pantry where food cooked and brought from the clubhouse could be prepared for serving in the dining room. There are eight family bathrooms and several baths in the house, plus six servants' bedrooms on the two main floors. The furnishings are a combination of Rockefeller pieces, some pieces from other club buildings and assorted items that might have been in a home of this type. Of particular note are a desk chair and a rocking chair (documented Rockefeller pieces), a safe concealed by a door, a portiere and a hand-operated elevator.</p>
        <p>Mistletoe Cottage, named for the shrub once found around the cottage site, was built for Henry Kirk Porter, a senator from Pennsylvania, in 1901. It is constructed of wood with a gambrel roof and contains 15 rooms, 5 baths and a dumbwaiter. On the first floor is the living room, library, sun porch, dining room, butler's pantry and two kitchens. On the second floor there are three servants' rooms and four family bedrooms. The ceiling in the sun porch is made of bamboo, silk-screen and rice paper. The brass globe lights in the sun porch are original fixtures.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most expensive cottage was that built for Richard T. Crane Jr. (of plumbing-fixture renown) in 1917. The construction contract was valued at $100,000. Many of the elements that the architect, David Adler of Chicago, incorporated into the cottage were copied directly from Italian villas built during the 16th century: enclosed courtyard arcade, sunken garden with fountains, entrance doorway and balcony above it, niches in the entrance hall, beamed ceilings, tile roof, vaulted ceiling in the dining room and mantel designs.</p>
        <p>The English Gothic-style Faith Chapel, erected in 1904 as an interfaith house of worship, is notable for its stained-glass windows created by two of the foremost glassmakers of the time: Louis Comfort Tiffany and D. Maitland Armstrong. At the east end of the chapel, behind the altar, is the ''Stickney Memorial Window,'' by Armstrong, depicting the Adoration of the Christ child. The Tiffany window, called ''David's Window,'' represents David proclaiming Solomon his successor.</p>
        <p>A 90-minute guided tour by antique trolley begins at the Jekyll Island Museum's Orientation Center. At the center itself there is an audiovisual presentation depicting the life style of the ''captains of industry'' who lived here - their lawn parties, their antique autos.</p>
        <p>The demise of the Jekyll Island Club is attributed to a number of factors, including a report that the families vacationing there in 1942 were ordered off the island out of fear of kidnappings when enemy submarines were sighted off the coast. The Great Depression of the 1930's and the lack of interest on the part of the younger set, who had found the attraction of European spas more to their taste, were probably more to blame, however. In 1947 the island and structures were sold to the state of Georgia.</p>
        <p>It would be a mistake to leave Jek-yll Island thinking that nothing more important than bowling, badminton and lawn parties ever took place here. It was inevitable that, with such eminent and powerful men in residence, there would be some talk of serious matters. It was here, in 1910, that the first draft of the 1914 Federal Reserve Act was drafted. Here, too, the president of A.T.&amp;T. made the first transcontinental telephone call, speaking to President Woodrow Wilson in Washington and Alexander Graham Bell in New York. And it was on Jekyll Island that George F. Baker became friends with Bishop William Lawrence, chairman of the Harvard Fellows; Baker later built the Harvard Business School.  WHERE TO SLEEP AND EAT  RESTAURANTS</p>
        <p>Captain Joe's Seafood Restaurant, Junction I-95, U.S. 25 and 341, exit 7B, Brunswick; 912-264-8771. Well-prepared seafood. Dinner, $5 to $12 a person.</p>
        <p>St. Andrew's Landing, in the Jekyll Inn, 975 North Beachview Drive, Jek-yll Island; 912-635-2531. Fresh seafood and beef. Dinners, $9 to $15 a person.</p>
        <p>The Greenery, in the Holiday Inn, 200 South Beachview Drive, Jekyll Island; 912-635-3311, extension 506. Steak and seafood. Dinner, $6 to $14 a person.</p>
        <p>Blanche's Courtyard, 440 Kings Way, St. Simons Island; 912-638-3030. Seafood specialties and beef. Dinner, $9 to $14 a person.</p>
        <p>Emmeline and Hessie, on the causeway between Brunswick and St. Simons at the Golden Isles Marina; 912-638-9084. A handsomely rustic dining room with a view of the sea. Seafood is the specialty. Dinner, $8 to $24 a person.  ACCOMMODATIONS</p>
        <p>Holiday Inn, Junction I-95, U.S. 23 and 341, exit 7B, Brunswick, Ga. 31520; 912-264-4033. $56 to $65 for two.</p>
        <p>Ramada Inn, Junction I-95, U.S. 25 and 341, exit 7A or 7B, Brunswick, Ga. 31520; 912-264-3621. $48 to $50 for two.</p>
        <p>Jekyll Island Club, 371 Riverview Drive, Jekyll Island, Ga. 31520; 800-843-5355 in Georgia, 800-822-1886 outside Georgia. $85 to $250 for two. Pool, tennis courts, golf.</p>
        <p>Jekyll Inn, 975 North Beachview Drive, Jekyll Island, Ga. 31520; 912-635-2531. $59 to $90 for two in season. Bicycles may be rented.</p>
        <p>Seafarer Motel and Apartments, 700 North Beachview Drive, Jekyll Island, Ga. 31520; 912-635-2202. $45 to $65 for two in season.</p>
        <p>The King and Prince Beach Hotel and Villas, Arnold Road and Downing Street, St. Simons Island, Ga. 31522; 912-638-3631. $65 to $120 for two in season. Sailboats, tennis and bicycles.</p>
        <p>Queens Court, 437 Kings Way, St. Simons Island, Ga. 31522; 912-638-8459. $43 to $53 for two year-round.</p>
        <p>Seagate Inn, 1014 Ocean Blvd., St. Simons Island, Ga. 31522; 912-638-8661. $55 to $100 for two year-round.</p>
        <p>The Cloister, Sea Island, Ga. 31561; 800-732-4752. A full-service resort with sports facilities and beach. $192 to $304 for two with meals.  L.F.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
