<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SOVIET CALLS THE TUNE IN A DUET SET IN GERMANY</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="57878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="GLASNOST EXTENDED: KREMLIN SANCTIONS HONECKER'S FIRST VISIT TO BONN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROMYKO, ANDREI A (MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VON WEIZSACKER, RICHARD (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHAM, JAMES M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DE123CF93AA25754C0A961948260" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SOVIET CALLS THE TUNE IN A DUET SET IN GERMANY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES M. MARKHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKHAM, JAMES M</byline>
      <dateline>BONN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN dealing with West Germany, the Soviet Union has traditionally reached for the carrot and the stick, seeking to lure the pivotal country of the NATO alliance eastward and then beating up on it when it failed to respond with sufficient docility. Yet these conflicting impulses have bedeviled Moscow's efforts to come up with a coherent</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN dealing with West Germany, the Soviet Union has traditionally reached for the carrot and the stick, seeking to lure the pivotal country of the NATO alliance eastward and then beating up on it when it failed to respond with sufficient docility. Yet these conflicting impulses have bedeviled Moscow's efforts to come up with a coherent</p>
        <p>IN dealing with West Germany, the Soviet Union has traditionally reached for the carrot and the stick, seeking to lure the pivotal country of the NATO alliance eastward and then beating up on it when it failed to respond with sufficient docility. Yet these conflicting impulses have bedeviled Moscow's efforts to come up with a coherent German policy.</p>
        <p>Last week, it became strikingly clear that Mikhail S. Gorbachev has resolved to give the carrot precedence over the stick. Six years after he had first been invited to Bonn - and after several humiliating Soviet vetoes of his travel plans - Erich Honecker, the East German leader, said he would be coming in September. The first visit by an East German Communist chief to West Germany will be an emotionally charged event that in East and West will be watched nervously, and probably erroneously, for symptoms of rising pan-German sentiment. But the announcement, in fact, lost some of its drama because it was plain that Mr. Honecker was not bucking Moscow's line but implementing it.</p>
        <p>Moscow's political choreography dictated that, before the Honecker visit could be announced, President Richard von Weizsacker had to make a visit of his own to the Soviet Union. The West German's sojourn this month allowed the Russians to terminate the withering polemics against Chancellor Helmut Kohl, who four years ago ignored Soviet threats and accepted the deployment of American medium-range missiles. In Moscow, too, Mr. Gorbachev effectively told the West German President that, contrary to perfervid speculation in certain right-wing circles in Bonn and by some officials in Paris, he had no intention of upsetting Europe's postwar order by offering West Germany reunification in exchange for neutralization. The Russian affirmed that two German states were a historical reality.</p>
        <p>Like his predecessors, Mr. Gorbachev does not appear to want a neutralized West Germany, but a pliant, self-doubting and weak-willed one in the heart of NATO. By taking a softer line toward Bonn, he seemed last week to be already reaping dividends. The small Free Democratic Party, the junior coalition partner in Bonn, chastised Horst Teltschik, a senior aide to Chancellor Kohl, and then Defense Minister Manfred Worner for spoiling the honeymoon with Moscow by suggesting in public that the Red Army might still harbor aggressive designs on the West. And Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher, the Free Democrats' senior figure, dropped a broad hint that he would be ready to abandon 72 Pershing 1-A missiles held by the West German Air Force if that would enable Moscow and Washington to reach an arms control agreement. The Russians have singled out the short-range Pershing 1-A's as a major obstacle in the stalled Geneva talks.</p>
        <p>In stitching together his new German policy, Mr. Gorbachev and his advisers evidently hope to cash in on the Russian leader's extraordinary popularity in the Federal Republic. Gerhard Simon, a West German authority on the Soviet Union, remarked that the rush of sympathy for Mr. Gorbachev was born of lingering guilt feelings for Hitler's invasion of Russia, ''fear of the big neighbor to the East, uncertainty about our own future and a certain anti-Americanism.''</p>
        <p>''It is an underground sentiment that is politically irrational,'' said Mr. Simon, ''and it doesn't really have anything to do with Gorbachev. We have to seek its roots in ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Gorbachev came to power, Soviet leaders sought to cow West Germany with threats and nuclear overkill capacity. Mr. Gorbachev apparently hopes to sway West German opinion through smiles and massive cuts in Europe-based nuclear systems that will enhance the Soviet Union's conventional superiority. Yet in the warming political climate Bonn has garnered dividends that have nothing to do with grand strategy. There has been such a sharp rise in the number of German-speaking emigres from Poland and the Soviet Union that a reception center in Lower Saxony has in recent weeks been swamped; already 4,542 ethnic Germans have legally emigrated from the Soviet Union this year, compared with 312 in 1986.</p>
        <p>Trade-offs lay behind the Honecker trip as well. The visit would not have been thinkable had the Kohl Government not swung behind a NATO consensus and endorsed the abolition of both medium- and short-range missiles in Europe - a goal first enunciated by Mr. Gorbachev. But Mr. Honecker has come through on matters of interest to Bonn. He plugged a hole that had permitted third world asylum-seekers to flood into West Berlin from East Berlin's Schonefeld Airport. And, much more significant, the East Germans have sanctioned a huge jump in the number of East Germans below retirement age permitted to visit West Germany. This year a record million may come, compared with 573,000 last year. East Germany allows pensioners to leave at will, hoping they will settle in West Germany and burden it with the cost of their old-age benefits.</p>
        <p>At 74, Mr. Honecker is old enough for a pension himself; his services to the insecure East German state include overseeing the construction of the Berlin Wall in 1961. But when he arrives in Bonn Sept. 7 he will almost certainly be wearing a Gorbachevian smile.</p>
        <p>GLASNOST EXTENDED: KREMLIN SANCTIONS HONECKER'S FIRST VISIT TO BONN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
