<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN A VERY COLD CLIMATE, A DISPUTE GENERATES HEAT</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="20497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="YELLOWKNIFE JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHWEST TERRITORIES (CANADA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NUNAVUT (CANADA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DENENDEH (CANADA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Yukon, the Northwest Territories and Nunavut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDD163BF932A25750C0A961948260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN A VERY COLD CLIMATE, A DISPUTE GENERATES HEAT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>YELLOWKNIFE, Northwest Territories</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Outside the Hudson's Bay fur trading center here, creaking in a sub-Arctic gale, is a painted sign attesting to the establishment of the company on May 2, 1670.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Outside the Hudson's Bay fur trading center here, creaking in a sub-Arctic gale, is a painted sign attesting to the establishment of the company on May 2, 1670.</p>
        <p>Outside the Hudson's Bay fur trading center here, creaking in a sub-Arctic gale, is a painted sign attesting to the establishment of the company on May 2, 1670.</p>
        <p>To the passer-by huddled in a fur-trimmed parka, it is a reminder of how long it has been since the first European adventurers began trading with the native peoples of the far north.</p>
        <p>It is also a measure of how climate, remoteness and sparse population have delayed the evolution of the Northwest Territories, the huge, forbidding terrain that lies between the temperate regions of Canada and the North Pole.</p>
        <p>It is a land of legend and hope, so far mostly unfulfilled. But sometime this year the 51,000 people who inhabit the 1.3 million square miles between the Yukon and Baffin Island will be asked to vote on a new political arrangement that will mark a step away from the semicolonial status that has prevailed here toward a future in which local voices hold commanding sway. A Change in the Map</p>
        <p>After a decade of testy negotiations, an agreement was signed early this year that would strike the Northwest Territories from the map, perhaps as early as 1991, and substitute two new domains, Nunavut to the east and Denendeh to the west. In as little as 20 years, the new territories could be the basis for two provinces, adding to the 10 that now make up what locals here refer to as ''the outside,'' the southern two-thirds of Canada.</p>
        <p>Among officials in Ottawa, 2,000 miles away, the ''division'' has been hailed as a historic watershed. But around Yellowknife, the territorial capital, and across the ''barrenlands'' that lie between here and the Arctic Sea, the deal has provoked bitter controversy.</p>
        <p>In the more populated parts of Canada, there is a common feeling that the territories should either remain as they are or be divided by allowing the existing provinces to extend their boundaries northward. And among the ''non-natives'' who make their homes in the north, the division plan is almost universally disparaged.</p>
        <p>''By and large, in the west, we don't even want it,'' said Yellowknife's Mayor, Michael McGrath, looking out of plate-glass window in the modern City Hall toward a snowscape where heavily clad schoolchildren were gamboling about in temperatures of 30 degrees below zero. ''We see more of a future in a united territory.''</p>
        <p>''The people of Canada are already pouring money in here, and now they're going to be asked to put in even more,'' the Mayor said. ''We simply ask, 'Is another government up here really necessary, or is it something for the politicians?' ''</p>
        <p>The ''politicians'' are those representing the two principal ''native'' groups, as they prefer to be known. In the west, these are the Dene, or Indian, people, and the numerically smaller Metis, people of mixed European and Indian descent. To the east, mostly, lie the Inuit, or the Eskimos. Inuit Favor the Plan</p>
        <p>Under the new arrangement the Dene and the Metis would be concentrated in the western district, Denendeh, and the Eskimos would mostly live in the east, in Nunavut.</p>
        <p>The new domain is strongly popular among the 18,000 Inuit, who represent more than 85 percent of the population to the east of the the proposed boundary line.</p>
        <p>Among the Dene and Metis people, however, the idea of division seems to have mixed appeal. For one thing, it will leave them as a minority in the west, where the 15,000 whites outnumber the combined Dene and Metis population by about 3,000. For another, acceptance of the new boundary is bound up with complex negotiations with Ottawa over land claims that have fostered major tensions among the Dene themselves.</p>
        <p>At the center of the dispute is Stephen Kakfwi, 34 years old, the president of the Dene Nation, the group that represents Dene interests. Mr. Kakfwi sees the boundary deal that was largely negotiated between himself and the Inuit leader, John Amagoalik, as the basis for a Dene revival.</p>
        <p>Since the 1930's, when Indians came into regular contact with non-native culture, traditional social patterns have given way to high rates of alcoholism, drug addiction, unemploymwent and family breakup. ''Perhaps,if we can get some control over our own lives, financially and politically, our people can regain the strength they need to pull themselves out of this dive,'' Mr. Kakfwi said. Charges of a Sellout</p>
        <p>But more radical elements among his people accuse Mr. Kakfwi of ''selling out'' for accepting a boundary infringing on traditional Dene hunting grounds and by favoring a land deal that would give the Dene title to 70,000 square miles, against the 450,000 originally sought.</p>
        <p>Younger leaders favor blocking any boundary deal until more land is offered and the Dene-Metis are guaranteed a decisive voice in the affairs of the future Denendeh.</p>
        <p>Almost everywhere that ''southerners'' in the territories gather, a view emerges of the native people outreaching themselves. Much is made of the fact that the ''south'' - meaning Canadian taxpayers - contributes more than 80 percent of the territories' budget.</p>
        <p>Native people have numerous assistance programs, including one that provides free houses costing the Government as much as $220,000 when built in remote Arctic communities.</p>
        <p>The wife of a senior territorial official described how a Dene woman and her newborn child, flown to the territorial capital for the birth at Government expense, demanded and got first-class hotel accommodations, again at Government expense, when their return flight was canceled because of bad weather.</p>
        <p>''When you've grown up with the Government doing everything for you, you simply don't think about cost,'' the official's wife said. ''It's the same with the 'division' issue. Nobody stops to ask who will be paying for it.''  YELLOWKNIFE JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
