<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parched Conditions Drying Northwest's Economy</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="88468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOOD AND WOOD PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHWESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DE143FF932A35752C1A961948260" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parched Conditions Drying Northwest's Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Everywhere you look in the Pacific Northwest, in the year of the worst drought since records have been kept, nature appears to have been turned inside out and the economy turned upside down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Everywhere you look in the Pacific Northwest, in the year of the worst drought since records have been kept, nature appears to have been turned inside out and the economy turned upside down.</p>
        <p>Everywhere you look in the Pacific Northwest, in the year of the worst drought since records have been kept, nature appears to have been turned inside out and the economy turned upside down.</p>
        <p>Stranded and battered salmon, which are to the Northwest what oil is to Texas, languish in warm pools, their passage to their spawning grounds cut off by bone-dry river beds.</p>
        <p>Winter wheat seedlings, usually dependent on a douse of fall rain for early life, are dying in the ground. And loggers, Christmas tree farmers, orchard growers and ski resort operators are expecting multimillion dollar losses as the browning of the Northwest continues.</p>
        <p>''Things have gotten so bad that you wake up in the morning, see the sunshine, and say, 'Damn, another nice day,' '' said Jim Bucknell, who is in charge of monitoring the drought for all Washington state government agencies. Deciding Who Gets Water</p>
        <p>The drought has led to agonizing decisions over which industries will get the scarce water.</p>
        <p>In the Yakima Valley east of the Cascades, Federal officials were recently forced to cut off irrigation water to orchards and vineyards to provide enough water for migrating salmon. The growers rely on fall water for startup moisture in the spring.</p>
        <p>The entire $500 million Washington salmon industry could face a catastrophe if the rains do not come in three to six months, said Joseph Blum, the Director of Fisheries for Washington State.</p>
        <p>''We're looking at a maximum loss, a complete wipeout of one year of fish,'' Mr. Blum said. The salmon are worse off on the west side of the Cascade Range. This weekend, state fisheries officials plan to use prisoners to dig trenches in in four shallow Olympic Peninsula rivers to help the stranded salmon.</p>
        <p>Seattle water officials opened their reservoir dam for one day in an effort to flush the Cedar river and fool the salmon that have been milling about in Lake Washington, waiting for a barometric signal.</p>
        <p>The largest sockeye salmon run in the continental United States passes through the inner-city lake. Thus far, only 70,000 of the estimated 200,000 sockeye have gone upstream. Fishermen Transport Salmon</p>
        <p>Indian fishermen, whose culture and economic well-being are tied to the salmon, say they are netting and transporting some salmon upstream by hand.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday, we counted 5,000 to 6,000 fish stranded in one little mountain creek alone,'' said Tony Meyer, a spokesman for 19 tribes and 23,000 Indians operating under fishing treaty agreements.</p>
        <p>Those fish that do reach their spawning grounds are laying eggs in shallow pools that could be wiped out by spring runoff, eaten by predators or killed by pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meyer said the tribes were angry at city officials in Tacoma for refusing to take conservation measures until a few weeks ago, long after the Green River, a main chinook salmon river and source of the city's water reservoir, was reduced to a trickle. City officials said they did not want to restrict water to the Simpson Tacoma Kraft Company's pulp and paper mill, which uses 40 percent of Tacoma's water. No Work for Loggers</p>
        <p>But now, with drastic water restrictions in effect, the mill has laid off 165 workers, demonstrating the ripple effect of the drought. When there is not enough water to run the mills, logging operations shut down. The Simpson mill provided boxes for apple growers, now finishing a record harvest. And some of the state logging sales, now canceled, provided money for the schools.</p>
        <p>At one point, up to 7,000 loggers were out of work because of the closing off of forest lands in Washington. The woods are now open on a limited basis.</p>
        <p>Some Christmas tree growers, now harvesting their trees for overseas markets, say they have been hurt by the closing of forest lands because of the drought.</p>
        <p>''We are getting lots of cancellations from back east because people heard the trees are all dried up,'' said Jean Moore of the Douglas Fir Christmas Tree Company in Shelton, Wash., a town that calls itself the Christmas tree capital of the world. She said the trees received enough moisture to be of good quality.</p>
        <p>Seattle, which normally gets about eight inches of rain from June to October, has had only 1.8 inches of rain in that period. Portland, Ore., has had on 1.4 inches of rain, less than one-fifth of the normal level. Seattle's reservoir in the Cascade Mountains is down to 17 percent of its normal level for this time of year.</p>
        <p>The cause of the parched conditions, according to officials of the National Weather Service, is a periodic warming of the Pacific that South American fishermen have named El Nino, after the Christ child, because it was first noticed around Christmas. The atmospheric changes caused by warmer ocean water have pushed low pressure storms well to the north. Such storms usually pummel the Pacific Northwest at this time of year.</p>
        <p>The bad news for farmers and fishermen is that the drought is expected to continue through the winter.</p>
        <p>''When you have an El Nino, the effects are strongest in the Northern Hemisphere during the winter, so the pattern you have going into the winter tends to persist,'' said Tom Swift, a Federal meteorologist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
