<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NORTHEAST OPENS DRIVE TO CUT BACK OZONE POLLUTION</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="94949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUTANE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D8113DF932A15752C1A961948260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NORTHEAST OPENS DRIVE TO CUT BACK OZONE POLLUTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Impatient with Federal efforts to control smog, New York, New Jersey and the six New England states are starting a major effort to reduce ozone by requiring changes in gasoline sold in the region in warmer months, beginning next summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Impatient with Federal efforts to control smog, New York, New Jersey and the six New England states are starting a major effort to reduce ozone by requiring changes in gasoline sold in the region in warmer months, beginning next summer.</p>
        <p>Impatient with Federal efforts to control smog, New York, New Jersey and the six New England states are starting a major effort to reduce ozone by requiring changes in gasoline sold in the region in warmer months, beginning next summer.</p>
        <p>The changes, which involve removing more butane in the refining process, would increase the cost of gasoline by 1.5 cents a gallon, or at least $44 million, in the period from May 1 to Sept. 15, says Bruce Maillet, the Massachusetts official in charge of air pollution control.</p>
        <p>Officials of the eight Northeastern states met in Hartford this week to sign a memorandum of understanding to set the new standard. The memorandum is meant to assure that all states will contribute to the cost of the program. Refiners Want National Rule</p>
        <p>Refiners would prefer a national rule from the Environmental Protection Agency, which is currently accepting public comment on a similar requirement covering a much larger area. The agency is also considering requiring cars to carry filter canisters that would reduce the evaporation fumes.</p>
        <p>Oil industry representatives also said the new state rules would increase the nation's bill for imported oil because it takes more crude oil to produce gasoline meeting the standards. They argued, too, that it would make cars harder to start, especially in cool weather or at higher elevations. This contention was disputed by officials in California, the only other state with the requirement.</p>
        <p>Michael Deland, the E.P.A. administrator for New England, said: ''I would support any effort by individual states or groups of states to take measures which will help to solve the ozone problem.'' He added, however, that he did not know if the action might be deemed to interfere with interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>The states' changes would cut by 15 percent the vehicle exhaust emissions of a family of compounds that react with sunlight to form ozone, which is a a health risk for children, the aged and infirm and an irritant to the eyes and throat.</p>
        <p>Controlling ozone has been a particularly vexing problem because its production may occur miles downwind of the ingredients' source. According to experts, cars, trucks, service stations and related sources make up half the problem, meaning that the overall reduction in smog ingredients would be about 7.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Technically, the change involves the tendency of liquid gasoline to turn into a vapor, adding volatile organic compounds to the air. Volatility in gasoline is expressed in terms of its Reid Vapor Pressure. By agreement of an industry group, the Reid Vapor Pressure of fuel sold in the Northeast in summer is 11.5 pounds per square inch. It rises as high as 15 in winter, to help with cold-weather starts. But smog is not a threat then because the atmospheric conditions do not favor its creation. Standard of Volatility</p>
        <p>A voluntary Reid Vapor Pressure standard for each state and for each month is set by the American Society for Testing and Materials, whose members include refiners, auto makers and state regulatory officials, usually those who regulate gasoline sales.</p>
        <p>The Northeast states, including New Hampshire, Maine, Rhode Island, Connecticut, Vermont and Massachusetts, would cut the Reid Vapor Pressure to 10 next summer, and 9 the summer after. The Environmental Protection Agency has proposed cutting it to 10 in 1989 and 9 in 1992.</p>
        <p>''We think it is a very, very cost-effective way to go, to get an awful lot of reductions,'' said Mr. Maillet. The cost, he said, would come to about $1,000 per ton of volatile organic compounds kept out of the atmosphere. Some factories in Massachusetts have already been required to spend $5,000 per ton on pollution control equipment, he said.</p>
        <p>When the regulators began looking for sources of volatile organic compounds they could control, they skipped any source of less than 100 tons a year. Now, as the fight drags on, they are trying to regulate sources of as little as 3.5 tons a year. In that context, the reductions envisioned by changes in gasoline are great. Cutting the Reid Vapor Pressure to 9 would eliminate about 68,000 tons per summer, according to the Northeast group. Reduction in California</p>
        <p>California ordered a reduction in Reid Vapor Pressure to 9 about 15 years ago, according to Bill Sessa, a spokesman for the California Air Resources Board. ''It's worked without a problem; we have not had any drive-ability problem,'' he said. The state is now considering dropping the limit to 8.</p>
        <p>But reducing the standard to 9 in the Northeast would require some refineries to make new investments, according to William F. O'Keefe, vice president and chief operating officer of the American Petroleum Institute, a trade group. And because some gasoline is moved by pipeline, changing the requirements in New Jersey and New York in practice may require refiners to reformulate the gasoline for Pennsylvania, Maryland and other places.</p>
        <p>A major difference between California's action and that of the Northeast states is that California was exercising control over in-state refineries. Many Northeastern states have no refineries.</p>
        <p>Each one point drop in Reid Vapor Pressure would require about 2 percent more crude oil for the same volume of gasoline, Mr. O'Keefe said. The national E.P.A. program would increase imported oil by hundreds of thousands of barrels a day, he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Keefe said that waiting for Washington to act would be ''quicker than trying to get eight states to try to pass something that affects refineries all over the United States, and may affect gas costs in other states.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
