<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WINE TALK</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="5542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GERMAN WINE INFORMATION BUREAU</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D9123DF932A15752C0A961948260" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WINE TALK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Howard G. Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: MANFRED ROMMEL, the Mayor of Stuttgart, tells the story of a wine-loving student named Hegel, who became a philosopher of some repute. Hegel once turned up so drunk in the university town of Tubingen that his comrades hid him from his teachers. A prefect supposedly warned him, ''Hegel, you'll drink away that little bit of sense you've got left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: MANFRED ROMMEL, the Mayor of Stuttgart, tells the story of a wine-loving student named Hegel, who became a philosopher of some repute. Hegel once turned up so drunk in the university town of Tubingen that his comrades hid him from his teachers. A prefect supposedly warned him, ''Hegel, you'll drink away that little bit of sense you've got left.</p>
        <p>MANFRED ROMMEL, the Mayor of Stuttgart, tells the story of a wine-loving student named Hegel, who became a philosopher of some repute. Hegel once turned up so drunk in the university town of Tubingen that his comrades hid him from his teachers. A prefect supposedly warned him, ''Hegel, you'll drink away that little bit of sense you've got left.''</p>
        <p>Wine, they say, is the elixir of life -but it has its limits. So even Hegel (1770-1831) could not attend the German Wine Information Bureau's presentation of 104 whites from the 1985 vintage in Manhattan last week. But given the many tasty rieslings present, Hegel could have proved the prefect's prediction right.</p>
        <p>A fair number of the 85's, which are steadily flowing into New York City and suburban wine shops, were appealing. With six months' more aging, that appeal may heighten. They are light-bodied, medium in fruitiness and refreshingly acidic. They are low in alcohol and high in extract, such as minerals - or what Johannes Selbach, a Mosel wine maker who is a trade consultant at the Information Bureau, describes as ''the seasonings in the dish.'' (Some of his wines were shown.) Clearly, the 85's play second fiddle to many ripe, spicy, flowery 83's, the most celebrated West German wines since the excellent '76 vintage. A caveat about the 83's: At birth, they were highly touted, justly so, but an unduly large number proved disappointing last year. The sweeter 83's, Mr. Selbach said, are starting to show their potential now.</p>
        <p>For consumers who want to compare the 85's and 83's, lots of 83's remain on store shelves.</p>
        <p>The strength of the 1985 vintage lies in the kabinett (off-dry) and spatlese (late-harvest) categories. Their commercial weakness lies in some prices: Since June 1984, when the 83's were turning up here, the dollar has dropped against the mark by about 30 percent. However, many estates and shippers and, according to Mr. Selbach, ''to a large extent, American importers and wholesalers'' have lowered their prices or kept them stable to help offset the dollar's drop.</p>
        <p>The wines displayed on Thursday came from the Mosel-Saar-Ruwer, a region named for its principal river, the Mosel, and tributaries; the Rheingau, a region just north of the Rhine River; and the Rhinehessen and Rhinepfalz, just south of the Rhine.</p>
        <p>Lamar Elmore, executive director of the German Wine Information Bureau (79 Madison Avenue, New York, N.Y., 10016), said there was little auslese (and, except for one eiswein, no even-sweeter wines) because ''the weather during the growing season was not as consistently hot as in 1983.''</p>
        <p>The harvest was the third smallest in two decades, primarily because of bad weather early in 1985. In West Germany, Europe's northernmost wine-producing country, the vineyards are particularly vulnerable to variations in climate, especially frost, too little sunshine, low temperatures and unseasonable rain and hail. Most face south to sponge up every last beam of sugar-generating sun during the long growing season.</p>
        <p>Kabinett, spatlese and auslese wines occupy the first three rungs in a hierarchical classification that is based on escalating degrees of sweetness and is called Qualitatswein mit Pradikat. This title, in a Gothic typeface on wine labels, usually translates (a bit foggily) as ''Quality Wine With Special Attributes.'' Under West Germany's 1971 wine law, it denotes the best wines. Of course, it cannot guarantee that customers will like them. Virtually any bottle of wine bought blind, German or otherwise, entails risk.</p>
        <p>At the tasting, there were only two wines from Nahe (pronounced NAH-heh), one of the smallest of West Germany's 11 wine regions. One was a pleasing Niederhauser Hermannshohle riesling spatlese, sold at about $7.99. (The other was a Liebfraumilch, a lesser wine.) The scarcity was not surprising; these nuanced, often earthy wines are difficult to find in the New York area, leaving consumers pretty much in the dark when it comes to these fascinating German whites.</p>
        <p>Perhaps one reason for their absence is that people buy popular labels, says Frank E. Johnson, executive vice president of Bonsal Seggerman &amp; Company, importers based in Roslyn, L.I.</p>
        <p>''The Nahe wines come in brown bottles like Rhine wine and look like Rhine wine, so they lack an identity,'' he said. Also, the volume is small. Less than half of Nahe's average 4.01 million cases produced each year are exported. Of these, only a fraction are sent to the United States.</p>
        <p>Bonsal Seggerman carries a small assortment of eye-openers from the Weingut Hohn-Zimmermann and Weingut am Katharinenstift (Korrell), in the Bereich (or district) Kreuznach, that are easily available through retailers.</p>
        <p>In a tasting in November with Mr. Johnson, whites from both estates, especially those made from grapes almost unknown here - Muller-Thurgau, bacchus and Scheurebe -washed away the conventional wisdom that riesling is the only German grape worth attention. At about $7, his Nahe wines are no gamble.</p>
        <p>For the whites to show their stuff best, serve them at 50 to 55 degrees Fahrenheit. Their direct appeal, especially the mingled complexity of fruit and acid, makes them ideal for the entry-level wine drinker. Delicate kabinetts, especially, invite a lingering sip, then another and another.</p>
        <p>As for reds, they are only a bit more plentiful than palm trees in south Jersey, constituting just 12 percent of West Germany's annual production.</p>
        <p>Nary a red was sighted at the tasting - a shame. A blauer spatburgunder (pinot noir) from Assmannshausen, on the Rhine (yes, the Rhine) can be warming on a January afternoon.</p>
        <p>Among the most agreeable bottles tasted at the German Wine Information Bureau were a number from the Mosel-Saar-Ruwer region. They come in green bottles. The suggested prices below represent retailers' standard 50 percent markup; some wines may be found at discount. All of the wines are rieslings unless otherwise noted.</p>
        <p>Kabinetts, from the Mosel-Saar-Ruwer. Ockfener Bockstein, from Weingut Adolf Rheinhart Erben (at $4.99, a good buy); Lilac Seal Piesporter, Deinhard ($8.99); Bernkasteler Badstube, Gutsverwaltung Geheim - Rat Wegler - Deinhard ($7.49); Bernkasteler Schlossberg, Weingut Max Ferdinand Richter ($6.99); Ockfener Bockstein, Weingut Dr. Heinz Wagner Nachf. ($8.99); Brauneberger Juffer, Weingut Christian Karp-Schreiber ($5.99); Ayler Kupp, Gebr. R.u.H. Kramp ($5.49); Saarburger Rausch, Weingut Dr. Heinz Wagner Nachf. ($8.99); Uerziger Wurzgarten, Weingut Joh. Jos. Christoffel Erben ($5.99); and Zeltinger Himmelreich, Weingut Selbach-Oster ($5.99).</p>
        <p>Kabinett, Rheingau. Winkeler Hasensprung, from Gutsverwaltung Geheim - Rat Wegler - Deinhard ($7.49); Hochheimer Konigin Victoria Berg, G.M. Pabstmann Nachf. ($8.50); Hallgartener Hendelberg (blau), Furst Lowenstein ($11.75); and Rudesheimer Berg Roseneck, Weingut Gebr. Grimm ($5.99).</p>
        <p>Kabinett, Rheinhessen. Volxheimer Rheingrafstein, from Phillip und Heinrich Baum Weinkelleri, a blend ($4.75).</p>
        <p>Spatlese, Mosel-Saar-Ruwer. Bernkasteler Badstube, Weingut Geschw. Selbach-Oster ($7.99); Bernkasteler Badstube, Weingut Heribert Kerpen Geschw. Kerpen-Erben ($7.99); Brauneberger Juffer Sonnenuhr, Weingut Christian Karp Schreiber ($7.99); Graacher Himmelreich, Weingut Willi Schaefer ($7.99); Urziger Wurzgarten, Geschw. Albertz-Erben, Alfred Merkelbach ($6.99).</p>
        <p>Spatlese, Rheinhessen. Mainzer Domherr, Phillip und Heinrich Baum Weinkelleri, a blend ($5.99); Niersteiner Auflangen, Weingut F.u.H.A. Strub ($6.99); Saulheimer Schlossberg, Freiherr von Tiesenhausen, a blend ($7.99).</p>
        <p>Spatlese, Rheingau. Geisenheimer Mauerchen, Weingut Schumann-Nagler ($11.99).</p>
        <p>Auslese, Mosel-Saar-Ruwer. Graacher Himmelreich, Weingut Willi Schaefer ($8.99); Urziger Wurzgarten, Weingut Geschw. Albertz-Erben, Alfred Merkelbach ($8.99).</p>
        <p>Auslese, Rheinhessen. Niersteiner Oelberg, Weingut F.u.H.A. Strub ($9.99).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
