<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>India Awaits the Monsoon, a Welcome Cloud</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="153041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GANDHI, RAJIV (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDB1439F931A25755C0A96E948260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>India Awaits the Monsoon, a Welcome Cloud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For days now, Indians have been tracking the progress of a huge saturated mass of air moving from south to north, as if its coming offers hope for relief, prosperity and even political stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For days now, Indians have been tracking the progress of a huge saturated mass of air moving from south to north, as if its coming offers hope for relief, prosperity and even political stability.</p>
        <p>For days now, Indians have been tracking the progress of a huge saturated mass of air moving from south to north, as if its coming offers hope for relief, prosperity and even political stability.</p>
        <p>In fact, the annual monsoon rains are crucial to all three things, especially this year, when India has experienced its worst drought in decades, along with a stricken economy and hundreds of deaths as the heat has soared to as high as 120 degrees in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>So crucial are the rains this year that many associates of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi said the Indian leader can be expected to call elections fairly quickly if the rains come, in hopes that the moonson will help him and his party achieve victory at the polls. A Political Event</p>
        <p>''The monsoon is one of the most important political events of any year,'' said an aide to Mr. Gandhi, explaining that the monsoon alone can insure productivity in the 70 percent of India's farmlands that depend on the rains, thereby influencing economic growth and the pace of inflation.</p>
        <p>One year ago, the monsoon started as it did this month, pouring rain on the southern tip of India. But unlike last year, the monsoon is continuing to dump rain this year as it rolls north toward the central and southern plains.</p>
        <p>''There were a couple days where it started as less weak,'' said Dr. Vasant Gowariker, secretary of the Indian Department of Science and Technology.</p>
        <p>''We were worried that the monsoon was again going to play hide-and-seek with us. So far, there's nothing to indicate that we won't have a good monsoon this year.''</p>
        <p>Indian meteorologists will not know until next month whether this year's monsoon will bring rain to populous central and northern India, where the economy has been hard hit by drought. About a quarter of the Indian rainy seasons in the last few decades have failed to bring much rain.</p>
        <p>This year, India is making its most ambitious scientific effort to understand and monitor the summer monsoon. The Government has assembled a team of scientists to make calculations of local and global weather patterns to determine whether the rains will come. The project was initiated after Indian and other scientists failed to predict last year's poor monsoon. National Dependence</p>
        <p>Monsoon rains are a global phenomenon, but few countries depend on them as much as India for cooling the impossible temperatures and nurturing the crops. The monsoons are caused by the country's unusual configuration as a land mass jutting into the ocean. The tremendous summer heat draws moist air from the surrounding waters, and the huge northern Himalayans prevent the water from dissipating.</p>
        <p>The scientists have developed 15 variables and have studied weather records in India back to the turn of the century. The first meteorological surveys in India started 113 years ago.</p>
        <p>The scientists used computers to examine the relationship between vigorous monsoons and wind patterns at an altitude of three and a half miles over an area of the Indian west coast. Dr. Gowariker said that there was a correlation between a healthy monsoon and a warming trend in the northern hemisphere, and that the scientists studied differences in air pressure over Tahiti and over Darwin, Australia.</p>
        <p>''Our conclusion this year is that out of 15 predetermined parameters, we found in 1988 that 13 of the 15 are favorable for a good monsoon,'' Dr. Gowariker said. He said earlier trackings showed that when most of the 15 factors were favorable in past years, the monsoon was successful. Gandhi's Interest Is Piqued</p>
        <p>So unusual was the Indian scientific effort, Dr. Gowariker said, that when the scientists presented their findings a few weeks ago to Mr. Gandhi, a meeting that was planned for 15 minutes lasted an hour and a half.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister, Dr. Gowariker said, peppered the scientists with questions, including whether they might produce new categories for the monsoon beyond ''favorable'' and ''unfavorable,'' or whether they might predict the monsoon earlier in the year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
