<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heat Spurs Air Pollution Alert in Parts of Midwest</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="159853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREST AND BRUSH FIRES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9153BF93AA35754C0A96E948260" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heat Spurs Air Pollution Alert in Parts of Midwest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Residents of parts of the Midwest were warned yesterday of unhealthy air pollution trapped by a stifling heat wave, and Wisconsin officials said rural school projects would be delayed because the drought would cut taxpayers' income.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Residents of parts of the Midwest were warned yesterday of unhealthy air pollution trapped by a stifling heat wave, and Wisconsin officials said rural school projects would be delayed because the drought would cut taxpayers' income.</p>
        <p>Residents of parts of the Midwest were warned yesterday of unhealthy air pollution trapped by a stifling heat wave, and Wisconsin officials said rural school projects would be delayed because the drought would cut taxpayers' income.</p>
        <p>In a nation made fire-prone by drought and heat, firefighters battling a five-day-old, 16,000-acre blaze near Mount Rushmore National Memorial in South Dakota finally had the weather on their side. Milder temperatures, higher humidity and lower winds benefited the firefighters as they reinforced existing fire lines before digging new ones. In Alaska, 32 fires were burning, four of which had consumed more than 290,000 acres. Fires also burned in Wyoming, Utah and South Carolina.</p>
        <p>On the drought-choked Mississippi, a shallow point in the lower part of the river was dredged near Natchez, Miss., to let barge traffic move again. Senators Seek Relief</p>
        <p>Thirteen senators from states along the Mississippi asked President Reagan to authorize an emergency diversion of water from the Great Lakes to help the diminishing river, a plan the Canadian Justice Minister, Ray Hnatyshyn, opposes. Senator Jim Sasser, Democrat of Tennessee, urged the President in a letter to direct the Army Corps of Engineers to increase the flow of Great Lakes water to the Illinois Waterway and the lower Mississippi from 3,000 cubic feet per second to 10,000 cubic feet per second for 100 days.</p>
        <p>The senators' request came after Government officials met in Memphis with members of a newly formed committee of towboat company executives. They say shipping delays caused by the low water will cost their industry $60 million this summer.</p>
        <p>There was immediate opposition to the diversion from several Midwest lawmakers, led by Senator Howard M. Metzenbaum, Democrat of Ohio, who said such a move would be illegal unless approved by all Great Lakes Governors.</p>
        <p>The White House said President Reagan will travel Thursday to the Midwest to talk to farmers.In addition, the Transportation Secretary, Jim Burnley, announced the creation of a special unit headed by Vice Adm. John Costello of the Coast Guard to deal with transportation problems that develop because of the drought.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, temperatures broke records again yesterday. Louisville, Ky., tied its record of 102 degrees; Huntington, W. Va., hit a record 101 and records of 100 were listed at Alpena, Mich., and Harrisburg, Pa. Nashville tied a record of 101 that was first set in 1874. The Nati</p>
        <p>The hot weather has been blamed for At least 39 deaths since June 1, 22 of them in Missouri. Others were in Kansas, Georgia, Illinois, Kentucky and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Three areas of Illinois, including Cook County, were advised yesterday that heat-related air pollution was at unhealthful levels for the second straight day, said Bob Swinford, supervisor of air quality analysis for the State Environmental Protection Agency. Heavily industrialized southeastern Michigan, including Detroit, also remained under an air stagnation advisory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
