<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bratislava Journal; Much Ado About Brown Coal on the Blue Danube</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="124041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CZECHOSLOVAKIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRATISLAVA (CZECHOSLOVAKIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DD1439F930A35750C0A96E948260" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bratislava Journal; Much Ado About Brown Coal on the Blue Danube</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>BRATISLAVA, Czechoslovakia</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: They call it Corn Island, a verdant oval embraced by the Danube and an appendix, the Little Danube, that part, meander quietly, then rejoin some 45 miles downstream on the Hungarian border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: They call it Corn Island, a verdant oval embraced by the Danube and an appendix, the Little Danube, that part, meander quietly, then rejoin some 45 miles downstream on the Hungarian border.</p>
        <p>They call it Corn Island, a verdant oval embraced by the Danube and an appendix, the Little Danube, that part, meander quietly, then rejoin some 45 miles downstream on the Hungarian border.</p>
        <p>It was just a sleepy place gazed at from the boats that ply the Danube, but now it is the site of immense rechanneling and power plant construction that officials here say is needed to supply electricity and that environmentalists say is going to destroy the region.</p>
        <p>Maybe it was the bright baroque facades streaked with black, or the sweet smell of the brown coal burned by homes and factories in the region, that prompted Bratislava's Ecology Club members to judge they had seen the future and it was smog-gray and polluted.</p>
        <p>The result was a project last autumn by club members, scientists, scholars and even government officials to gather statistics and other material, much of it unpublished, into a 60-page report pointedly called Nahlas - the Slovak equivalent of glasnost, or openness - that chronicles the perils to the region's environment.</p>
        <p>Reflecting the view that environment means whatever surrounds us, it examines Bratislava's air, water and soil, but also services like health care and housing, producing unsettling details about decay and criminality in the huge Petrzalka housing project that was built across the river from the historical center to counter a critical postwar housing shortage. The Changing Times</p>
        <p>It was a remarkable thing, even if it could be produced only for the club's internal use, in a place where such independent activity is viewed much the way other communities would look upon arson or well poisoning.</p>
        <p>The report was a kind of sign of the changing times. Maybe it is all the talk in the Soviet Union about change; maybe it is just the opening that has come from people traveling through, or from the Hungarian, Austria and Soviet television broadcasts that can be received here. Whatever the causes, there are stirrings here.</p>
        <p>The official unions of writers and artists hold little attraction for the young, so writers produce small journals, which start, flourish for a bit, then often flop. Artists produce works in what is locally called the wild style, probably evoking West Germany's Neue Wilde school of painting, with little chance of their being shown publicly. Minorities, too, have grown more vocal.</p>
        <p>But the ecology report also says something about the way independent activity cuts in and out of the Communist Party, blurring the desired clean lines between rulers and opposition. Vladimir Minac, a member of the Slovak party's Central Commitee, was among 90 people who constructively criticized a rough first draft produced by the report's 23 authors. Report's Authors Censored</p>
        <p>Perhaps it was just that blur that prompted the final official reaction. The report was ultimately confiscated and its authors censured publicly. A petition to permit public discussion, the main purpose, was cut short by the authorities.</p>
        <p>But actions like this one have made the party more sensitive, and officials are at pains to tell how much is being done.</p>
        <p>Daniel Matejko, head of the region's administration, described in an interview plans to construct sewage disposal plants and install filters at the big Slovnaft chemical works, at the western end of a pipeline from the Soviet Union that carries 10 million tons of Soviet crude oil a year for processing into chemical products. North of Bratislava, a costly project is under way to clean up Czechoslovakia's largest aluminum smelter.</p>
        <p>''If it was once true that Slovakia was beautiful in its poverty,'' Mr. Matejko said, ''it is now true that we have many problems in the midst of our wealth.''</p>
        <p>He said Slovakia was spending the equivalent of $2 billion a year to clean up the environment, and the amounts increase from one five-year plan to the next.</p>
        <p>But all the cataloguing for Western visitors does not mask the fact that the Government will not permit independent discussion. Party officials, after letting the report languish for several months, confiscated 2,000 of the 3,000 copies printed, then denounced it in the Slovak Communist Party paper, Pravda.</p>
        <p>Pravda's deputy editor, Vojtech Vesely, acknowledges some of the problems. Discussing the river project, he said: ''For sure, ecological influence will be there. For example, those meandering Danube branches will disappear, and people who admire these things will miss them. We lose some things, we gain some things.''</p>
        <p>But he argued that the river project was necessary if Czechoslovakia and Hungary were to abandon brown coal, the cause of heavy pollution, as a source of energy and still meet future electricity needs.</p>
        <p>Those among the report's contributors who will talk about the project ask that their names not be used, for fear of reprisal. Nevertheless, a lawsuit is now pending to force the Government to give back the confiscated reports.</p>
        <p>''The atmosphere in town is changed,'' one contributor said. ''People are talking, even in official circles.'' He said Pravda had run its article under the headline, ''Nothing New Under the Sun,'' suggesting that the action recalled the Prague spring of 1968 that led to political disaster.</p>
        <p>''But that is entirely wrong,'' he said. ''The people active now are too young. These are new people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
