<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Greening of the Red Planet</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="149854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL SPACE COOPERATION AND VENTURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">EDITORIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DD1F3AF933A05756C0A96E948260" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Greening of the Red Planet</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: During President Reagan's visit to Moscow this week, his host will engage him in serious talk about a favorite subject, the stars. ''Drop 'Star Wars,' '' Mr. Gorbachev will say. ''Let's have our countries go together to Mars instead.'' Mr. Reagan won't lightly abandon his missile defense project but he might be tempted by the Mars mission, which Mr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: During President Reagan's visit to Moscow this week, his host will engage him in serious talk about a favorite subject, the stars. ''Drop 'Star Wars,' '' Mr. Gorbachev will say. ''Let's have our countries go together to Mars instead.'' Mr. Reagan won't lightly abandon his missile defense project but he might be tempted by the Mars mission, which Mr.</p>
        <p>During President Reagan's visit to Moscow this week, his host will engage him in serious talk about a favorite subject, the stars. ''Drop 'Star Wars,' '' Mr. Gorbachev will say. ''Let's have our countries go together to Mars instead.'' Mr. Reagan won't lightly abandon his missile defense project but he might be tempted by the Mars mission, which Mr. Gorbachev has lost no time in proposing.</p>
        <p>Leave aside for a moment the cost and risk of sending humans to Mars. What would they do when they got there?</p>
        <p>Mars is a cold, dry place, swept by hurricane-force dust storms. Its atmosphere, one-hundredth as thick as Earth's, has almost no oxygen. The first task would be to make Mars more habitable.</p>
        <p>From bases on a Martian moon, engineers could fabricate giant mirrors to orbit the planet. These would direct sunlight to melt the polar icecaps. The flow of vapor would thicken the atmosphere, enabling it to trap more heat, like a greenhouse. Genetically engineered plants from Earth would spread across the planet, creating oxygen.</p>
        <p>It might take a millennium, but one day people could venture out from the bubble domes of the early colonies into air more like Earth's. ''Over the coming centuries,'' writes James Oberg in ''Mission to Mars,'' ''the blood-red planet . . . could be gradually replaced in the skies of Earth by a soft-colored, gleaming, green-tinted jewel.''</p>
        <p>Maybe, but could a mission to Mars possibly be worth the investment? The considerable scientific payoffs cannot by themselves justify a manned mission; robots could do the job more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Going to Mars jointly with the Russians adds a new dimension. Involving the bureaucracies of both countries in a large, long-term venture could create a common interest and give politicians many shared goals to celebrate. The cost of the mission needn't be too great, especially if the Russians picked up half the tab. A crash program would be expensive, but a deliberately paced venture staged over 20 years would present more acceptable annual costs.</p>
        <p>No one suggests abolishing the U.S. space agency. Yet its annual $9 billion budget is mostly wasted as NASA gropes for a sense of purpose. When the space shuttle flies again and the palatial space station takes shape, Congress will have to double the budget just for the hardware.</p>
        <p>At present, NASA has a mishmash of missions designed to appeal to all possible constituencies. Scrap those; focus attention on Mars, and the project needn't cost much more than NASA will otherwise waste on its present, visionless course.</p>
        <p>The Russians seem firmly committed to exploring Mars. Mr. Reagan may spurn Mr. Gorbachev's extended hand now, but how might he feel if the Soviet leader then seeks Japan or Europe as his partner? By going to Mars with the Russians, Mr. Reagan might save his successors from a more costly race against them.</p>
        <p>Besides, what better legacy could any statesman hope for than to green the red planet named for the god of war?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
