<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stock Pickers Up Yonder</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business World Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Business; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="153285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STOCK EXCHANGE, MONTREAL</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">STOCK EXCHANGE, TORONTO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">STOCK EXCHANGE, VANCOUVER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, ARTHUR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WONG, MILTON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCAVITY, IAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JARISLOWSKY, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD6153DF931A25755C0A96E948260" item-length="3109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stock Pickers Up Yonder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Arthur Johnson; Arthur Johnson, the author of ''Breaking the Banks,'' writes about business from Toronto.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, ARTHUR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHILE THE CONCEPT OF globalization, with its lure of distant and sometimes exotic stock markets, has captured the fancy of many investors in the United States of late, some of the most astute have not forgotten a foreign market just across the border. Canadian stock exchanges began outperforming the United States markets early in 1987.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHILE THE CONCEPT OF globalization, with its lure of distant and sometimes exotic stock markets, has captured the fancy of many investors in the United States of late, some of the most astute have not forgotten a foreign market just across the border. Canadian stock exchanges began outperforming the United States markets early in 1987.</p>
        <p>WHILE THE CONCEPT OF globalization, with its lure of distant and sometimes exotic stock markets, has captured the fancy of many investors in the United States of late, some of the most astute have not forgotten a foreign market just across the border. Canadian stock exchanges began outperforming the United States markets early in 1987. And when the crash came in October, the Toronto Stock Exchange suffered a milder plunge than its New York counterpart. So far this year, Toronto has rebounded with more vigor than New York.</p>
        <p>The Canadian securities market is the sixth largest in the world. The Toronto Stock Exchange handles 77 percent of the nation's dollar volume in equities trading, concentrated in 35 blue-chip issues. Subsidiaries of American companies make up the single largest component. The Montreal Exchange, fastest growing in terms of share volume, has also pushed heavily into futures and options trading. The Vancouver Stock Exchange, which claims to be North America's largest market for raising venture capital, is the speculators' playground.</p>
        <p>More than 30 percent of the shares traded in Canada are those of resource companies. Metals, oil and forest products are the mainstay of the economy. Traditionally, the profits of these companies rise at the end of a booming economic cycle and on expectations of rising inflation; hence the market's takeoff after the bull has been on a global tear.</p>
        <p>The advance of the Canadian dollar against the United States dollar after nearly a decade of decline has meant a double benefit for American investors in top-performing Canadian securities.</p>
        <p>A more permissive environment for takeovers is another incentive for American investors to consider Canadian stocks. According to William S. Allen, president of Allenvest Group, a Toronto-based institutional brokerage house, ''Takeover laws in the U.S. are rigorous in protecting management. Shareholders' interests are being completely ignored.'' Indeed, he says, ''Canadian securities laws, to the extent that they prohibit the payment of greenmail, make Canada a superior place to invest.''</p>
        <p>Since the Progressive Conservative party came to power in September 1984, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney has moved to make foreign capital more welcome in Canada. His first step was to dismantle the federal agency that screened (and sometimes blocked) acquisitions of companies by non-Canadians.</p>
        <p>Another warming sign in the investment climate is the historic free-trade agreement Prime Minister Mulroney signed with President Reagan last January. One likely result may be the enlargement of Canada's small group of world-class, multinational corporations. Some major Canadian corporations, such as Inco Ltd., the nickel giant, and the Seagram Company, the liquor conglomerate, are already familiar to American investors. Others, such as the Campeau Corporation and the Cineplex Odeon Corporation, are becoming known because of their acquisition activities in the United States.</p>
        <p>Canadians have always been prodigious savers, squirreling away roughly twice as much of their disposable income as Americans. And they save mightily for retirement. Private pension funds and retirement plans now hold about $155 billion in assets, a fivefold increase over the last decade. One consequence has been an elite group of pension-fund managers and advisers wielding extraordinary clout in the marketplace. Two who have established outstanding records for shrewd choices and accurate forecasts are Stephen A. Jarislowsky in Montreal and Milton K. Wong in Vancouver. In outlook and operating style, they are almost direct opposites. Ian M. T. McAvity, a newsletter publisher and leading gold bug, is a freewheeling technician based in Toronto. He and Wong are known to many American investors through their appearances on the television program, ''Wall Street Week.''</p>
        <p>A PERSONAL NET WORTH OF more than $32 million, based on sole ownership of his Montreal-based investment counseling firm, does not require Stephen Jarislowsky to be modest. As the 62-year-old Jarislowsky is the first to admit, self-effacement has never been his style.</p>
        <p>''It must seem to the outside world that I'm on an enormous ego trip,'' says Canada's most consistently successful pension-fund manager. Jarislowsky achieved a 16.2 percent compounded annual return over the last 10 years on assets now worth $7.6 billion, entrusted to him by 200 pension funds - the nation's largest pool of retirement money. In addition, Jarislowsky, Fraser &amp; Company manages $800 million in private accounts. Yet Jarislowsky insists that his frequent appearances in courtrooms and interviews in newspapers and on television as a champion of shareholders' rights are simply a matter of getting the best possible return for his clients.</p>
        <p>From his plainly furnished (some would say shabby) offices in Montreal, Jarislowsky has been able to thwart corporate reorganization plans that offend his sense of investment fair play simply by making a few telephone calls to other large institutional shareholders.</p>
        <p>When management resists, Jarislowsky is prepared to fight. He comes armed with powerful ammunition - the large positions some of his pension-fund clients hold in a dozen major Canadian companies.</p>
        <p>In 1986, Jarislowsky led a move to block a management buyout of Canadian Tire. The bid excluded holders of nonvoting shares of which his clients held a significant 6 percent. The Ontario Securities Commission took their case to the Supreme Court of Ontario and won. Jarislowsky also expressed his displeasure by withdrawing his not inconsiderable business from Merrill Lynch Canada and the Gordon Capital Corporation, the investment houses that structured the bid. ''People shouldn't run their companies figuring I'm a cheap source of financing and can be dispossessed at any time,'' he says .</p>
        <p>Jarislowsky was born in Berlin, where both his father and grandfather were merchant bankers. When he was 5 years old, his father died. His mother remarried and the family came to the United States in 1941.</p>
        <p>Jarislowsky took a mechanical engineering degree at Cornell University, and after serving with United States Army intelligence in Japan, he earned a master's degree in Far Eastern studies at the University of Chicago. At the age of 21, he inherited $100,000 from his father's estate. ''My idea was to make $1 million by the age of 40. I reached that status at that age.'' His first step toward that goal was enrolling at the Harvard Business School. After receiving an M.B.A. in 1949, he took a job with the Alcan Aluminum Company in Montreal. In 1955, Jarislowsky set up shop as an investment manager.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a stock picker,'' he says. ''My strategy is to diversify my portfolios, not to make a killing on an individual stock.''</p>
        <p>Jarislowsky is known for seeking out undervalued growth stocks and hanging onto them. ''If you concentrate on high-quality growth stocks that are noncyclical, priced under 14 times earnings, with good management, you usually have a good purchase,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Among the growth stocks in his portfolios are communications companies. He holds large positions in Telemedia, a publisher of consumer magazines, and in Toronto Sun Publishing, which owns tabloid newspapers in three Canadian cities and a majority interest in a Toronto business daily, The Financial Post.</p>
        <p>Other Jarislowsky favorites of longstanding include Scott Paper Ltd., UAP Inc., an automobile parts dealer, and the Canadian book publisher McGraw-Hill Ryerson.</p>
        <p>More recently, he has spotted bargains in the depressed energy sector - namely, Imperial Oil and Pan Canadian Petroleum.</p>
        <p>Jarislowky is one of several major investment managers lobbying the Ottawa Government to loosen a requirement that Canadian pension funds keep 90 percent of their equity holdings in domestic stocks or pay a heavy tax penalty. He concentrates his foreign purchases on American securities in noncyclical industries. Among the issues Jarislowsky has purchased are Hospital Corporation of America, Tandy, Caterpillar, American Home Products, Pfizer, Eli Lilly, Dow Chemical and Melville, a shoe manufacturer.</p>
        <p>Well before last October's crash, Jarislowsky decided that stocks were overpriced. He started buying short-term commercial paper and long-term provincial government bonds. More than 60 percent of his funds are currently in debt securities; he has seen little to convince him to rush back to equities. ''This is not a dirt-cheap market, overall,'' he says. ''I think the life insurance stocks are cheap because everyone is scared of AIDS. And you can still find oil on the stock market cheaper than by drilling.''</p>
        <p>Judging by history, he says, the stock market meltdown of last fall is bound to be fol-lowed by a recession. ''It could be this year, but not if the politicians in the U.S. can help it. They don't want it in an election year.'' Canada will hold elections in 1989.</p>
        <p>At any rate, before he again becomes enthusiastic about the stock market, Jarislowsky says, ''I'd like to see people really scared out there, blood on the street.'' And when disaster strikes, he will be there to pick up bargains for his pension funds.</p>
        <p>WHEN MILTON Kwong Wong was a student at the University of British Columbia in 1962, his older brother, Jack, gave him $7,000 with which to play the stock market. ''I blew it,'' he says. Within a year, his stake was down to $2,000.</p>
        <p>Despite that inauspicious beginning, Wong, at the age of 49, has become one of Canada's leading money managers. In 1980, after 17 years as a senior pension-fund administrator for National Trust Company of Toronto, he went into business for himself in Vancouver.</p>
        <p>The offices of M. K. Wong &amp; Associates are in the upper reaches of a skyscraper overlooking the harbor. On almost every wall is a print depicting the Great Wall and other Chinese scenes. Wong currently manages $2.4 billion in pension assets - the seventh largest pool of such monies in Canada - in both segregated and pooled funds. He also runs two personal pension funds available to the public.</p>
        <p>Wong has developed a reputation for making large swings in his portfolio strategies, and for amazing accuracy in predicting interest rates and currency movements. By calling the bond rally of the early 1980's correctly, he achieved average annual returns of 14.4 percent to the end of 1987.</p>
        <p>But last October, Wong had good reason to reflect on his misadventures as a student. Caught up in the emotion of a rising market, he had committed more than 65 percent of his pension funds to stocks. ''We made it all in the first three quarters and lost it all in the last quarter,'' he says. As a result, his overall return for 1987 was 1.2 percent. ''When he makes a call, he makes a wholehearted call,'' says Trevor W. Wilson, a Vancouver partner in Loewen, Ondaatje, McCutcheon &amp; Company, a Canadian brokerage. ''When he's wrong, he's really wrong.'' Wong has since reduced his equity holdings to about 55 percent of his portfolio (36 percent is in bonds, the remainder in cash). More than a year ago, he began buying shares of the Nova Corporation, an oil company, and the Polysar Energy and Chemical Corporation, a petrochemical company. After Nova made a bid to acquire Polysar last January, the prices of both securities appreciated substantially above his cost. The fund manager also profited from the rise in nickel prices; he bought Inco at $20, sold it at $29 and moved on to Falconbridge Mining, another nickel company.</p>
        <p>Wong believes that Canada will continue to prosper over the next year or two, even if the world economy sputters a bit. ''In many areas,'' he says, ''Canada has become the world's most cost-effective producer.'' He is particularly enthusiastic about MacMillan Bloedel, the forest products company. ''Over the past several years they've become leaner and meaner,'' he says. ''And with the Canadian dollar down relative to many other currencies, MacMillan Bloedel has a double whammy in terms of exports.''</p>
        <p>Wong and his six portfolio managers are in constant touch with traders and economists around the world to assess what impact global trends might have on Canadian investments. In 1985, he began to shift from bonds into equities. The trigger, he says, was the decline of the United States dollar relative to the yen and other hard currencies. Since pulp and many other Canadian exports are priced in United States dollars, Wong reasoned that exports would boom.</p>
        <p>The events of last fall have not shaken Wong's confidence in the Canadian economy. He believes that the Canadian stock market will surge ahead this year, propelled by a continued decline in interest rates and by an unceasing flow of foreign capital. He points to the $58.7 billion that foreign investors have poured into Canada during the last five years. However, 84 percent of that money has been invested in debt instruments and late last year foreign investors became net sellers of Canadian stocks.</p>
        <p>Wong is the only major Canadian investment manager of Chinese origin. His father left Canton in 1908 for Vancouver where he became a tailor. ''Most immigrants to Canada now will be non-Caucasian,'' says Wong. ''This has tremendous ramifications for investment. People and the flow of funds go together.''</p>
        <p>Vancouver is indeed a gateway for capital from Asia but Wong maintains that most of it has gone into real estate rather than the stock market. Wong avoids the Vancouver Stock Exchange. ''The V.S.E. is really a medium that allows venture capital to be found,'' he says. He feels that most stocks traded on the exchange are far too speculative to be included in pension portfolios.</p>
        <p>Wong approves of the privatization programs instituted by conservative governments in Britain and France. Thus far, the Mulroney government has sold only a tiny fraction of nationally owned businesses to private interests; its plan, announced in April, to offer 45 percent of the stock of Air Canada to the public has prompted a political tempest.</p>
        <p>IN ALMOST EVERY RE-spect, Ian McAvity is an extremist. At the age of 46, he smokes three packages of cigarettes a day. It's been years since he's taken so much as a week's vacation, and working 36 or more hours at a stretch is a fairly regular occurrence in his otherwise irregular life.</p>
        <p>In the midst of roaring market advances, McAvity has been known to sound like the voice of doom, warning of a crash ahead. In the depths of a slump, he has forecast soaring prices. ''He's usually a little early, but more often than not, he's right,'' says William B. Cooper, a partner in Cockfield Cooper Cunningham Investment Counsel, a Toronto money management firm. McAvity's market calls have won him an international following. Twice a month, from his office in Toronto, he publishes Deliberations, a highly opinionated commentary for investors. The eclectic range of his subject matter and his blunt, humorous style, heavily laced with historical comparisons, has attracted a readership ranging from small investors in Alberta to bankers in Zurich.</p>
        <p>His technical analysis of cyclical movements in gold, interest rates, currencies and share prices for the Deliberations research service enabled him to predict the bear market of 1980, the bull market that began two years later and the subsequent crash.</p>
        <p>During the summer of 1986, McAvity became convinced that the market had peaked and was headed downward. ''The market kept going hellbent for leather for another year,'' he says. ''I regularly exit markets early.''</p>
        <p>McAvity, the son of James M. McAvity, a former president of Seagram's, was born in Toronto. He attended prep schools in Port Hope, Ontario, and in Montreal before enrolling at the University of New Brunswick. ''I was a barely adequate student,'' he says, adding that he dropped out after one semester. He trained at the Bank of Montreal and at a brokerage house in Montreal. In 1972, McAvity moved to a small brokerage firm in Toronto where he headed the technical research department and began writing Deliberations. He continued the publication on his own after he left the firm three years later.</p>
        <p>McAvity regards Deliberations almost as an intellectual exercise. ''I write it for my own self-discipline,'' he says. These days, 85 percent of his time and attention are focused on gold. In an uncertain world, he maintains, gold is without parallel as an investment. ''It's the only one around that isn't someone else's liability,'' he says.</p>
        <p>For the past two years, McAvity has been president of the MVP Capital Corporation, a closed-end gold fund that finances junior gold mining companies. MVP lost two-thirds of its value last fall and has not yet recovered. He is also an adviser to Central Fund of Canada Ltd., a gold and silver fund.</p>
        <p>In his view, the global economy is extremely shaky, and even the prediction of a severe recession might prove to be an optimistic scenario. ''We haven't started to undo the debt bubble,'' he says. ''I've been scared stiff for a year.'' The safest course, he recommends, is to have ''a disproportionately large holding of gold and gold stocks.'' Moreover, he suggests that investors hold 50 percent of their assets in treasury bills or the equivalent.</p>
        <p>In forecasting price movements, McAvity says he is ''principally driven by a perception of trends with a good sense of the fundamentals.'' He believes that economies move in four-year cycles. In the case of the United States, for instance, the economy tends to be buoyant in the last two years of a presidential term and dip during the first two years of a new term.</p>
        <p>These days, he is decidedly pessimistic about stocks. ''I don't expect another crash-type day,'' he says. ''But what comes next is the hamburger grinder - when the market goes down and down and just grinds people up.'' Despite his bearish view, McAvity says a few of the big Canadian oil companies are worth considering, especially those like Shell Canada and Imperial Oil that have extensive reserves, good cash flow and successful track records.</p>
        <p>McAvity is lukewarm about the large Canadian gold mining companies such as Placer Dome although he has revised his opinion about LAC Minerals, which he now considers to be a takeover candidate. He is attracted to small companies such as Canamax Resources and Muscocho Explorations that have the potential to evolve into major producers. These stocks are MVP's two largest holdings.</p>
        <p>For the widest play in the Canadian resource market, he says, one might consider Canadian Pacific. With its railroad, mining and forest products divisions, hotels and manufacturing, he says, ''It's everything this country has to offer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
