<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calgary Tries a 'Snow Dance'</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="115017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1988)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINTER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALGARY (ALBERTA)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta/Calgary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DD1639F931A35751C0A96E948260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calgary Tries a 'Snow Dance'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>CALGARY, Alberta, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With the start of the Winter Games 12 days away, everybody around here has been talking about the weather. One person did something about it. As his personal contribution to insuring cold temperatures and a white landscape, Iain Baxter, a local artist, choreographed a ''contemporary snow dance'' the other day, by inviting 440 people listed in the Calgary telephone book to the Olympic Plaza downtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With the start of the Winter Games 12 days away, everybody around here has been talking about the weather. One person did something about it. As his personal contribution to insuring cold temperatures and a white landscape, Iain Baxter, a local artist, choreographed a ''contemporary snow dance'' the other day, by inviting 440 people listed in the Calgary telephone book to the Olympic Plaza downtown.</p>
        <p>With the start of the Winter Games 12 days away, everybody around here has been talking about the weather. One person did something about it. As his personal contribution to insuring cold temperatures and a white landscape, Iain Baxter, a local artist, choreographed a ''contemporary snow dance'' the other day, by inviting 440 people listed in the Calgary telephone book to the Olympic Plaza downtown.</p>
        <p>These were not ordinary people. Their surnames were either White, Winter or Snow, and more than 500 people showed up.</p>
        <p>Upon arrival, each received a helium-filled balloon with the word White, Winter or Snow on it. Then, at Baxter's direction, they moved into three configurations - first, forming the letters of their names to make the phrase, ''White, winter snow''; then into a bull's-eye, with the Snows in the middle, surrounded by the Winters and the Whites; and finally into a jumbled group from which they cheered: ''White winter snow. White winter snow. Let it go.'' With that, they unleashed their balloons. Human Good-Luck Charms</p>
        <p>''I thought it would be a nice gesture for the Games,'' Baxter said today in an interview. ''I figured all the people would be good-luck charms, sort of a new way to solicit snow, kind of like a contemporary snow dance.''</p>
        <p>Baxter is a 51-year-old English-born artist who teaches at the Alberta College of Art. He has been blending people into artistic settings for some time. Once, he said, he met a man named Kettle and a man named Wood at the same time. He wanted to photograph them.</p>
        <p>''So I asked Mr. Kettle to sit on Mr. Wood,'' he said. ''I liked the concept.''</p>
        <p>''I have always been into language, the visual arts and how they collide,'' he added. ''It's very interesting, celebrating the ordinary in an extraordinary way.'' The Elusive Chinook</p>
        <p>Whether it is Baxter's work or someone else's, the weather in recent days has been ideal for winter Olympics: if anything, too cold. For years, the fear has been that the Games would fall victim to a Chinook, a warming wind out of the west. And they might yet; for long stretches of the last two Februarys, Chinooks have melted whatever snow there was and left residents to wander about in shirt-sleeves.</p>
        <p>The last Chinook came and went early last week, replaced by below-zero temperatures and a brief snow Friday night. Today's high was 2 below zero.</p>
        <p>Calgarians seem used to it, at least those involved with preparations for the Games. At the three outdoor sites - Canada Olympic Park (ski jumping, bobsled, luge), Mount Allan at Nakiska (Alpine skiing) and the Canmore Nordic Centre (Nordic events, biathlon) - work crews were busy refining whatever needed to be refined. Grooming the Slopes</p>
        <p>At the Olympic Park, workers were monitoring bobsleds and luges on their runs to see which part of the course required more scraping or more ice. During periods of precipitation and cold temperatures, ice builds up on certain parts of the track and breaks off on others. Last week, the deformities were so severe that workers used axes and scrapers to return the track to international specifications.</p>
        <p>''The work is almost complete,'' said Francis Saville, the venue chairman. ''We're into the final phase now, fine-tuning the turns. We want it as perfect at we can get it.''</p>
        <p>At Nakiska, about an hour west of the city, crews are manicuring the ski slopes, which benefited from last week's snow. While only an inch or so fell in the city, the higher elevations got 12 to 16 inches.</p>
        <p>''We look like real heroes,'' said Mike Collins, the venue manager there. ''Our only problem right now is a tent. There was so much snow, it bent the frame.''</p>
        <p>The snow also helped the Nordic course at Canmore, where many Olympic athletes are already training.</p>
        <p>The greater problem for cross-country skiers and biathlon athletes is the temperature. Because their events take so much longer than Alpine events, they can be affected more by exposure. During each day of competition, a technical committee will decide whether to commence, based on the temperature. Anything at 4 below or colder would result in a postponement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
