<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About Men; Shoveling</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="108431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUDDLE, DAVID</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT MEN (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D61E3DF933A25752C0A96E948260" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About Men; Shoveling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Huddle; David Huddle teaches writing and literature at the University of Vermont. His book of short stories ''High Spirits'' will be published next summer by David Godine.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HUDDLE, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE MEN WHO LIVE ON MY ONE-BLOCK street are a banker, a lawyer, a television ad writer, an obstetrician, a librarian, a retired ophthalmologist and another college prof like me. On mornings after a big snow, three or four of us will be out there at more or less the same time, shoveling the stuff out of our driveways and off our walks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE MEN WHO LIVE ON MY ONE-BLOCK street are a banker, a lawyer, a television ad writer, an obstetrician, a librarian, a retired ophthalmologist and another college prof like me. On mornings after a big snow, three or four of us will be out there at more or less the same time, shoveling the stuff out of our driveways and off our walks.</p>
        <p>THE MEN WHO LIVE ON MY ONE-BLOCK street are a banker, a lawyer, a television ad writer, an obstetrician, a librarian, a retired ophthalmologist and another college prof like me. On mornings after a big snow, three or four of us will be out there at more or less the same time, shoveling the stuff out of our driveways and off our walks. Now and then, one of us will wave or call out a remark to another:</p>
        <p>''Good morning, doc, it never ends, does it?''</p>
        <p>But unlike our summer afternoons of yardwork, these mornings are not social occasions.</p>
        <p>We're usually at it after the younger kids have gone to school, but college students often stride by, rosy-cheeked, greeting us with smiles that overtly suggest they're seeing their own old dads in us, shoveling out the old driveway back home. And in these insufferably free young people, to whom we can barely grunt a reply, we see what we have lost forever - those exhilarating mornings when snow had refreshed the world and we couldn't get dressed fast enough to get out there and walk up the street to school.</p>
        <p>Hefting one shovelful after another, I'm given to carrying out personal inventories: I'm 45 now, about 25 pounds overweight. I've got a shoulder that bothers me a lot and a lower back that tightens up. Racquetball and tennis keep my legs in fair shape, but my stamina is down, and cold weather often kicks up an old asthma problem. I've taken years of pleasure from my body; now I'm beginning to understand what, in the years to come, it means to give me back.</p>
        <p>If it's heavy snow, I take a break about every five minutes, prop the shovel up with a straight arm, stand still, huffing and puffing, and inspect the neighborhood. To stretch my back muscles, I lean back and gaze into the clear sky. I want to be more patient, more open to the world and more alive, but my nose is running and my shoulder hurts. From the other side of the lawyer's house I hear his shovel scraping concrete at a pace too fast for his own good. I know he's late for work. When I start again, I force myself to move slowly.</p>
        <p>No man over 40 shovels heavy snow without thinking about a heart attack. I've had the personal acquaintance of only one man who died while shoveling snow, but every winter I read or hear about somebody else. As deaths go - ''graduating,'' my brother calls it - that one seems to me desirable for its speed, but lacking in dignity. As I work, the vision of myself pitched forward in the snowbank by the garage makes me shake my head and murmur the appropriate mantra, ''If it comes, it comes.'' I feel myself break into a sweat. Ordinarily, I'd take another break right now, but I'm on the last section of the driveway, and besides, the sweat feels pretty good.</p>
        <p>The librarian owns a snow blower, and earlier this morning he opened up the driveways of all of us, cleared out the deep ridge of crusted snow and ice bequeathed us by the truck that plows the street. I'm grateful to the librarian, but I wonder what I ought to do to repay him, wonder what the other guys will do, wonder if he'll feel obligated to do the same thing every time it snows from now on, wonder how his act of generosity will affect the delicate web of neighborhood politics. This stupid line of thought finally makes me snort and fling a load almost to the flower bed at the side of my house; I lecture myself: learn how to accept a gift.</p>
        <p>We shovelers are mostly men. Upper body strength is the real issue here, but when I'm cold, tired and in pain from this work, I get resentful that my wife is indoors while I'm out here suffering and dying. In the past, when she has come out to offer her help, I've been too prideful to let her. I've given her a stoic ''No thanks'' and set myself to swinging the shovel at a pace so vigorous I can barely sustain it until she's gone back indoors. Still, this morning when I'm finished and feeling sweaty and righteous, I come stomping into the kitchen and drop a question in what I think is my most tellingly deadpan voice, ''Now what is the feminist position on shoveling snow?'' ''Want me to buy my own shovel?'' she responds. That shuts me up for a while. The truth is I like evidence of work accomplished; I savor the sight of my driveway scraped clean, my swept-off porch, and even the little passageway I've cut in the snowplow ridge at the front of the house for the postman and the paperboy. I wouldn't like it nearly so much if somebody had helped me. This morning when I walk into the living room and glance out the front window, I'm nagged by the knowledge that the librarian did the hard part for me. As if she can read my mind, my wife calls from the kitchen, ''Joe helped you some, didn't he?''</p>
        <p>Between spouses, a silent response to a question is often the most substantial answer of all, and today, warming myself at the radiator by that window, that's the option I choose. In the moment, I see snow shoveling as one of the most mortal experiences available to me these days; as with war and sex, reticence about it is never inappropriate. A man ought not to speak casually of his lost childhood, ruined body and inevitable graduation. Out loud, a man can't say that what snow falls to him is his, and he'd prefer to shovel it himself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
