<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Variety of Plants to Suit Any Climate</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="109292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="A GARDENER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LACY, ALLEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DB1F3BF937A25752C0A96E948260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Variety of Plants to Suit Any Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN LACY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LACY, ALLEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: COMPLAINT plays an important part in almost every gardener's life. We complain about problems we can solve with a little work, like chickweed or crabgrass in the flower beds. We also complain about matters beyond our control, mainly the weather. Chief among these meteorological complaints are those concerning the plants we cannot grow because we live in a climate they find too taxing or unfriendly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: COMPLAINT plays an important part in almost every gardener's life. We complain about problems we can solve with a little work, like chickweed or crabgrass in the flower beds. We also complain about matters beyond our control, mainly the weather. Chief among these meteorological complaints are those concerning the plants we cannot grow because we live in a climate they find too taxing or unfriendly.</p>
        <p>COMPLAINT plays an important part in almost every gardener's life. We complain about problems we can solve with a little work, like chickweed or crabgrass in the flower beds. We also complain about matters beyond our control, mainly the weather. Chief among these meteorological complaints are those concerning the plants we cannot grow because we live in a climate they find too taxing or unfriendly.</p>
        <p>Southerners envy those of us who live up north our peonies and white birches, even our yews. Northerners, meanwhile, are jealous of the South's gardenia hedges, oleanders and luscious crape myrtles.</p>
        <p>City gardeners lament the tall buildings nearby that may grant them only five hours of direct sunshine. Suburban gardeners envy their urban counterparts the absence of a lawn to mow. None of us are quite content with the limitations imposed by our circumstances or conditions.</p>
        <p>But wisdom counsels against complaint. The fact is that unless a gardener sets up shop on an iceberg or a sand dune in the Sahara, the range of plants that he may grow is so vast as to be intimidating. Limitation is a gardener's best friend. It simplifies his choices enormously.</p>
        <p>If he gardens in a wooded shade, he will have to forgo sunflowers and day lilies, but he can still have anemones and azaleas and so many other shade-loving plants that he must make hard choices. If he gardens in a sandy coastal area, he may not be able to enjoy the cool shade of oaks, but he still may have rugosa roses, beach plums, bayberries and a huge assortment of ornamental grasses. IT is catalogue time once again. The bright wish books from dozens of nurseries and seed companies are spread out before me, as are the lists I've made. They come to hundreds of plants and a grand total, thus far, of $1,475.95, plus shipping. The lists exceed both the capacity of my pocketbook and the ability of my garden to absorb a tidal wave of plant immigrants.</p>
        <p>Limitation must be imposed, and since most gardening in January is a mental, not physical, exercise, I am playing with an idea. In my imagination, I will buy only plants and seeds whose names start with L. My choice of L is not entirely arbitrary. Neither Q nor X would make much in the way of a garden. Besides, I owe a debt to the letter L: without it, I would be named Aen Acy.</p>
        <p>A garden built on this letter could be a varied place. It would have its noble trees: larches and lindens and liriodendrons or tulip poplars. There could be hedges of lilac and ligustrum. There would be no tulips nor daffodils in the spring, but lilies by the hundred would make recompense in summer, as would larkspurs and lupins, liatrises and liglarias.</p>
        <p>There might be no sweet fragrance of jonquils or hyacinths in April, but the lilacs would be heady in May, as would sweet peas, since they're known botanically as Lathyrus. The hot days of summer would be redolent with the heavy scent of lavender (a plant especially beloved by the British and the bumblebee).</p>
        <p>My tiny pool out by the deck would have its lotuses, of course, and the gain would be considerable, since I've long wanted lotuses but have always forgotten to order any.</p>
        <p>As for lobelias, there are so many - perennial forms and annuals, tall ones and creepers - that one could almost make a whole garden of them. Since their colors embrace red, white and blue, they could express some patriotism. Likewise the lysimachias come in such variety that they could fill out a huge section of the perennial border.</p>
        <p>In truth, this alphabetical limitation imposed on the craft and art of gardening could lead to innovation and adventure. As it happens, one of my keenest discoveries last year was a plant whose name starts with the canonical letter.</p>
        <p>A member of the Mallow family, which also includes the hollyhock and the hibiscus, lavatera turned out to be an annual highly worthy of a spot in the garden. Untemperamental and unbothered by pests or diseases, it covers itself for almost two months with single five-petaled blossoms, deep rose pink or glistening white, according to the kind. Its bushy habit and its height of under two feet made it a wonderful choice to fill six large clay pots marching up a flight of steps in a sunny spot.</p>
        <p>Not being much impressed by edelweiss - Julie Andrews and ''The Sound of Music'' notwithstanding - I won't put Leontopodium alpinum on my list, although lewisias are appealing.</p>
        <p>There are also some mysteries to explore. I can try out Lawrencellias and Leschenaultias, and see what the lychnises have to offer.</p>
        <p>And there could even be a secret to this imaginary garden. Unless I told them, I doubt that any of my family or friends would be able to guess the principle on which it was founded.</p>
        <p>A GARDENER'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
