<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rays and Fumes in the Air and in the News; Expand Ethanol Use</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="132522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDF1E3FF932A35757C0A96E948260" item-length="387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rays and Fumes in the Air and in the News; Expand Ethanol Use</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In your report on Colorado's high-oxygen fuel test (news story, March 1) and the state's clean-air program, which mandates the use of oxygenated fuels in winter months, you quote an Amoco spokesman, Jerry Levine, as saying, ''We were very surprised - we thought there'd be more consumer backlash.''</p>
        <p>It is no wonder that Mr. Levine was surprised: the company worked hard to undermine the program. In addition to their usual scare stories about the impact of ethanol, oil companies created and financed an organization called the Consumer Environmental Awareness Project, whose goal was to question whether the clean-air program had consumer backing.</p>
        <p>With such a concerted effort by the oil companies, Amoco was undoubtedly surprised and disappointed to discover that consumers ignored their negative campaign and supported the program, which proved a success. Consumers apparently realized that antiethanol claims by oil companies are deceptive and self-serving.</p>
        <p>Before the Colorado program began, auto dealers and their mechanics who believed the oil company message expected widespread mechanical problems and reduced mileage. However, as you indicate, dealers learned what ethanol proponents have been saying all along: the use of oxygenated fuels such as ethanol does not impair vehicle performance.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the oil companies blocked ethanol from most of the Denver market by shipping gasoline containing methyl tertiary butyl ether, or MTBE, an alternative oxygenate that cannot be blended with ethanol under Environmental Protection Agency restrictions.</p>
        <p>Since ethanol use reduces carbon monoxide emissions by twice as much as MTBE, Colorado residents would breathe easier if the oil companies stopped trying to prevent consumers from using ethanol and allowed it to take its place as the fuel of choice for environmental reasons.</p>
        <p>Other cities with carbon monoxide problems may also want to learn the lesson of Colorado. Just as carbon monoxide pollution obscures the view of the Rocky Mountains in Colorado, the campaign of the oil companies against ethanol obscures the truth about ethanol's benefits to America. The expanded use of ethanol can clear up both problems at the same time. RICHARD J. DURBIN  Member of Congress, 20th Dist., Ill.  Washington, March 4, 1988</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
