<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOCUS: Anchorage; Homesteading Is Still Alive in Alaska</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="199706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARR, ROGER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DB173BF933A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOCUS: Anchorage; Homesteading Is Still Alive in Alaska</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER STARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STARR, ROGER</byline>
      <dateline>ANCHORAGE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: HOMESTEADING - acquiring ownership of government land by the sweat of one's brow - was a dream of millions of Americans 125 years ago. Even today, some older cities give tax-forfeited, deteriorated working-class homes to striving families who pledge to restore them. That's called Urban Homesteading, a pale imitation of what still exists in but one state -</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: HOMESTEADING - acquiring ownership of government land by the sweat of one's brow - was a dream of millions of Americans 125 years ago. Even today, some older cities give tax-forfeited, deteriorated working-class homes to striving families who pledge to restore them. That's called Urban Homesteading, a pale imitation of what still exists in but one state -</p>
        <p>HOMESTEADING - acquiring ownership of government land by the sweat of one's brow - was a dream of millions of Americans 125 years ago. Even today, some older cities give tax-forfeited, deteriorated working-class homes to striving families who pledge to restore them. That's called Urban Homesteading, a pale imitation of what still exists in but one state - Alaska.</p>
        <p>On a recent trip, a cab passenger in Anchorage learned that the driver was a wilderness homesteader toiling in his off hours on an isolated 40-acre tract 35 miles from downtown.</p>
        <p>The cabby knew the state would give the land to him and his heirs in perpetuity, as it will to 21,000 other Alaskans in pursuit of the same hope, if only he heeds the requirements imposed and administered by the Alaska Division of Land and Water Management.</p>
        <p>What he did not know was that most settlers lured westward by the Homestead Act of 1862 found that their dream of economic independence through land ownership was a tragic delusion.</p>
        <p>Pluck, those settlers learned, brings no rain, nor does hard work make unpromising soil fertile. No more than a third of the homesteaders made a go of farming; some found cattlemen who bought their dry land, but most were beaten by topography, weather, disease, lack of capital and, though only rarely, by Indian resistance.</p>
        <p>Today, says Gary Gustafson, director of the Division of Land and Water Management, the state does not expect wilderness homesteading to lead to private affluence and general economic development. It does its best to persuade prospects that they make an arduous commitment with little possibility of financial reward.</p>
        <p>But the state constitution explicitly encourages widespread land ownership in the furtherance of Alaska's democratic ideals.</p>
        <p>''The people who cherish solitary independence and want to escape the pressures of competition and technology will get their own reward, but only if they have the courage, skill and capital to work hard for it,'' said Mr. Gustafson, who has built his own wilderness cabin, though not on homestead land.</p>
        <p>Instead of using Conestoga wagons, drawn by horses or oxen, modern wilderness homesteaders transport their necessities by float plane in summer, snowmobile in winter. Instead of herds of bison, they may confront oversize bears. And instead of chopping their own logs, roofing their homes with sod, warming themselves around buffalo-chip fires and dispelling the dark with oil lamps and candles, they can fly in with gypsum board, fiberglass insulation, electric generators, gasoline-powered chain saws, stoves and refrigerators to make life a bit easier.</p>
        <p>Yet, gradually, despite initially high hopes, the new homesteaders find the Alaskan topography and climate in their own way as daunting as the conditions encountered by their earlier Western prototypes. New technologies are helpful in some respects, but costly. And they leave many hardships unabated - not the least, mosquitoes. The state offers warnings of the hardships ahead. It does not and cannot promise homesteaders a steady income from farming 160-acre agricultural homesteads or an opportunity to sell 40-acre home sites at a fancy future price.</p>
        <p>Land values have risen precipitously within 35 miles of New York's Times Square and Chicago's Loop. But the same will not occur within 35 miles of Anchorage unless thousands of migrants decide to move to the area and someone builds highways or railroads to accommodate them.</p>
        <p>WHEN Alaska achieved statehood in 1959, it was given 105 million acres of federally owned land, more than a quarter of its total land surface. Land-rich and development-poor, public or private agencies could finance transportation facilities only if investors felt that economic development would follow, a dubious proposition.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Gustafson points out, his division must balance the state's desire to put small parcels of land in private hands against the undesirable consequences of encouraging people to risk their time, savings and even their lives in a venture for which they are not qualified. The invitation is circumscribed: To qualify for the program an applicant must have lived in Alaska for at least one year immediately before the auction. Even so, when it decides which wilderness areas it will tender to homesteaders each year, the state must hold a lottery to winnow the applicants. Lottery winners who hope to meet the requirements of agricultural homesteading may claim 160 acres; those who want homesites can claim 40.</p>
        <p>Lottery winners pay a processing fee of $5 an acre for a permit to enter and stake out the land they want (first come, first served). Brush must be cleared from its boundary lines. All homesteaders must have a professional survey of their property. Those who are prepared to pay for the land may buy it outright within two years after they stake it, paying the original state appraisal. Those who do not buy within two years have three more years to buy it, but only at the then-current appraisal price, and only after building a habitable 190-square-foot, all-weather house. Those who do not want to pay anything for the land must not only build the house but also must live in it for 25 months within the five years. Then they get clear patent title.</p>
        <p>The state's homestead law went into effect in 1985 and Mr. Gustafson and his staff now find that at least one-third of the 21,000 who received entry permits or took steps to acquire property have already defaulted or been foreclosed.</p>
        <p>Stanley Bogdan, a part-time driver for one of the two largest taxicab companies in Anchorage, is one whose claim is very much alive. When not showing rural Alaskans their most modern metropolis, he can be found - but only with difficulty - on his homestead site. He staked it out after winning in the first lottery, in 1985. By investing $7,000 in construction materials and seaplane transport, he has been able to give up the tent that was his first shelter and move into his minimal house. Call it a cabin, he says modestly.</p>
        <p>A bachelor, Mr. Bogdan chose a site at Lockwood Lake, an uninhabited section of Alaska's tundra. He spent $1,350 on three widely separated trips in DeHavilland float planes, each carrying about one ton of material to the lake.</p>
        <p>He carries a shotgun and a .44 magnum automatic just in case one of the indigenous black bears or the migratory browns becomes too inquisitive. He is conscious of the dangers - and they abound; snowmobiling, using a chain saw and chopping wood in icy weather are three of them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bogdan said he expects to spend two months on the homestead by the end of this year, catching the end of the moose season, panning for gold, cutting and stacking firewood, improving the cabin and hunting.</p>
        <p>HIS present concern is whether he can accumulate the required 25 months of site living without losing the cab - his only visible means of support.</p>
        <p>''When it rains,'' he said, referring to a not unusual Alaskan phenomenon, ''I'll catch up on my reading. After it freezes I can travel by snowmobile.''</p>
        <p>While he sounds like a sourdough, he was actually born and raised in Tuckahoe, a Westchester County suburb of New York City. He left New York for Florida in 1970, intent on making his grub stake in real estate. From Tampa he went to Houston, from Houston to Alaska, arriving in time to meet the lottery residence requirement.</p>
        <p>As he talks about economic potential in the wilderness, it is clear his hopes are based as much on a romantic vision of himself as the pioneer from the East as on any hard fiscal calculation. ''Some day,'' he says with apparent confidence, ''Alaska will have to build a road through here, and this is going to be one of the world's prime vacation resorts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
