<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Pollution Is Found at Peak In Summer Heat</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="166448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D91138F932A05754C0A96E948260" item-length="1468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Pollution Is Found at Peak In Summer Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The mass of hot, dirty air that has lingered over much of the country this summer increased ozone pollution in many cities to the highest levels this decade, according to preliminary readings from government monitoring stations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The mass of hot, dirty air that has lingered over much of the country this summer increased ozone pollution in many cities to the highest levels this decade, according to preliminary readings from government monitoring stations.</p>
        <p>The mass of hot, dirty air that has lingered over much of the country this summer increased ozone pollution in many cities to the highest levels this decade, according to preliminary readings from government monitoring stations.</p>
        <p>The readings underscore the fact that in reducing the pollutants specifically cited in the Clean Air Act of 1970, the nation has done a poor job in lowering pollution from ground-level ozone, a major component of urban smog, a known contributor to respiratory illness and a significant cause of damage to crops and trees. Health Threat Seen Rising</p>
        <p>The urban ozone readings come as new medical studies indicate that ozone may constitute a more serious threat to public health than was previously recognized. Though it has long been known that high levels of the pollutant pose a health threat, new research points to dangers from lower concentrations over periods of six to eight hours.</p>
        <p>Instead of progressing toward the goal in the clean air law of reducing ozone to safe levels, the country appears to be losing ground.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency had been projecting that 68 major metropolitan areas would miss an Aug. 31 deadline set last year by Congress for compliance with the ozone standard. With this summer's high ozone levels in many cities, particularly in the East, a substantially higher number of cities are likely to miss the deadline, officials of the environmental agency said recently. They added that it was too early to determine exactly how many.</p>
        <p>Ozone is an unstable form of oxygen in which three atoms, rather than the normal two, atoms bind together. Most of the ozone at ground level is formed when pollutants, particularly hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides from a wide variety of sources, including motor vehicles, factories and small sources like paint shops and dry cleaning stores, react with sunlight. Sunlight Helps Build Smog</p>
        <p>The resulting ozone and solid particles and other pollutants constitute smog and odor. The more sunlight and the higher the temperatures the more ozone and smog are formed. Low wind velocities and poor air circulation also cause ozone levels to build up.</p>
        <p>In the upper atmosphere, ozone forms naturally and is beneficial, screening the earth from ultraviolet rays that can cause skin cancer, eye problems and damage natural systems. A recent treaty calls on nations to reduce output of industrial chemicals that are believed to deplete ozone in the upper atmosphere. Because ozone is so unstable and tends to break up at night in the absence of sunlight, little of it formed near the ground finds its way to the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Researchers had long established that ozone causes breathing problems for asthmatics and people doing heavy exercise who are exposed to a high level of it over a brief period. Now tests conducted at laboratories of the Environmental Protection Agency are finding that exposure to lower levels over a period of six or eight hours can also cause substantial respiratory problems in healthy people as well as in people with lung diseases. Animal Lung Damage Cited</p>
        <p>Even more troublesome, in the view of public health officials interviewed this week, are recent animal studies that suggest that chronic exposure causes permanent damage to lungs.</p>
        <p>''Until recently we had the impression things were improving, but what we see this summer shows us we are back where we started from,'' said Dr. Morton Lippmann, professor of environmental medicine at the New York University Medical Center. Dr. Lippmann was recently the chairman of the environmental agency's Clean Air Science Advisory Committee and is still a member of the panel's ozone subcommittee.</p>
        <p>Because of the high levels of ozone and the new evidence of potentially serious health effects, many medical doctors, scientists and environmentalists are calling for a reduction in the legally allowable exposures, and for more efforts to curb ozone-creating pollution.</p>
        <p>Under present standard, if the ozone level of a city exceeds an hourly average of .12 parts per million more than once a year, it is in violation. Environmental agency officials are considering an additional standard that would set allowable exposures at lower levels for eight-hour periods. No changes are planned as yet because the agency believes more data are needed. There is no thought being given to regulate chronic exposure to ozone over a period of a year or more, according to an agency spokesman. Proposal Would Extend Deadline</p>
        <p>But because of the extreme difficulty of controlling the diverse sources of ozone pollution, many cities, including New York, have been unable even to comply with the current standard. A few cities, notably Los Angeles, would not be able to meet the standard for decades without imposing draconian measures like restricting automobile use.</p>
        <p>Legislation now before Congress would extend the deadline for meeting the present ozone standard. The proposal would, however, establish a rigorous schedule for compliance by cities that the E.P.A. found were not making a strong effort to meet the standard. If Congress does not act to amend the law this year, the E.P.A. intends to act on its own to extend the deadline and to put cities that are not in compliance on an enforceable schedules toward meeting the current standard.</p>
        <p>Failure to meet the often-deferred deadline supposedly brings automatic economic sanctions by the Federal Government. But agency officials said sanctions would be imposed only on those areas that the E.P.A. found were not trying to comply with the law, not those that are trying to but failing. Conditions Ideal for Ozone</p>
        <p>This summer, with its very hot and generally dry weather and stagnant air, has been ideal for the creation of low-level ozone. In addition, the pollution sources of ozone are growing with the population and expanding economy. The warming of the planet, caused by other industrial pollutants, seems likely to worsen the ozone problem, too, said Richard E. Ayres, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council and chairman of the National Clean Air Coalition.</p>
        <p>Because of public concern this summer, the E.P.A. conducted what Don R. Clay, its acting assistant administrator for air and radiation, called a ''quick nationwide survey of this summer's ozone problems.'' Agency staff members in the field provided data from those monitors that showed the highest ratings. Mr. Clay emphasized that the findings did not represent comprehensive or scientifically validated results.</p>
        <p>The official ozone levels for 1988 will not be ready for more than a year. The survey reported only peak concentrations recorded through June 30 by monitors in areas where high levels of ozone were being reported.</p>
        <p>What the survey did show, Mr. Clay said, was that those peak concentrations were higher in a majority of the sites than the peaks reached in 1983, until now the year with the worst ozone pollution in the 1980's. Readings Show Record Levels</p>
        <p>And Bruce Jordan, the chief of the environmental agency's ambient standards branch, said that in the past, the highest ozone concentrations had tended to appear in August and September. But this year, by early July, measurements at a monitor at Queens College, Flushing, indicated that the peak ozone level in New York City this summer was 11 percent above the 1983 peak. In Washington, this year's peak was 22 percent higher than in 1983. In Cincinnati the peak was 31 percent higher and in Chicago 36 percent.</p>
        <p>There are no comprehensive data yet on the the effects of these high ozone levels, but anecdotal evidence suggests that there has been a significant impact on public health. Dr. John Penek, a pulmonary specialist and medical director of the Breathing Center, a respiratory clinic in Morristown, N.J., said that there had been a ''tremendous increase'' in the number of people coming to the center with problems over the past few months.</p>
        <p>Dr. Paul J. Lioy, director of the human exposure division of the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, said that a ''new wave of information is now coming in suggesting that it is not just the one-hour peak exposure to ozone that can cause acute health effects but that these effects can occur with lower peak levels spread over a longer time.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lippmann of N.Y.U. said recent clinical studies on rats showed that long-term exposure to ozone caused biochemical and structural changes in the lungs of the animals, including a stiffening of the lung walls in a way that parallels aging. He also said humans seem to be more sensitive to ozone than rats.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lippmann said it might eventually be necessary to set annual limits on exposure to ozone. For now, he said, the data are too skimpy to provide a basis for such regulation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
