<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Frontier Spirit Lives On</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAGLE (ALASKA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">OLDS, MARK (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D9143EF933A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="2502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Frontier Spirit Lives On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK OLDS; MARK OLDS is an adjunct professor of communications at Fordham University.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OLDS, MARK (PROF)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON Dec. 5, 1905, a man bundled in furs against the 60-degree-below temperature stepped off a sled on the frozen Yukon River, walked into the town of Eagle and asked where he could send a telegram. The message he sent (over a telegraph line constructed five years before to send military communiques) announced the discovery of the Northwest Passage; it was signed ''Roald Amundsen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON Dec. 5, 1905, a man bundled in furs against the 60-degree-below temperature stepped off a sled on the frozen Yukon River, walked into the town of Eagle and asked where he could send a telegram. The message he sent (over a telegraph line constructed five years before to send military communiques) announced the discovery of the Northwest Passage; it was signed ''Roald Amundsen.</p>
        <p>ON Dec. 5, 1905, a man bundled in furs against the 60-degree-below temperature stepped off a sled on the frozen Yukon River, walked into the town of Eagle and asked where he could send a telegram. The message he sent (over a telegraph line constructed five years before to send military communiques) announced the discovery of the Northwest Passage; it was signed ''Roald Amundsen.'' The small white frame cabin where Amundsen lived for the next two months is still standing in Eagle, on what is now called Amundsen Avenue. Down the street, in front of the log building that serves as post office to this town of 150, gleams a two-foot-high stainless steel globe of the world, with a plaque commemorating the explorer's achievement.</p>
        <p>Eagle's history, which put it on the National Register of Historic Places in 1970, is the major reason for making the long, difficult journey to this tiny Alaskan outpost 144 miles from the nearest town. It's not the only one, though. While one foot is still planted in its flamboyant gold rush past when its population zoomed to 1,900, the other stands independently in a today that is lean and tough but rewarding and is a reminder for the 1,000 or so annual visitors that the frontier spirit lives on.</p>
        <p>Eagle works hard to keep its past alive. Seven days a week at 10 A.M. a volunteer from the Eagle Historical Society shows up at the old courthouse to conduct a two-hour tour of this and the other restored historic buildings.</p>
        <p>As my wife and I waited with a handful of other visitors, a gray-haired, weathered-looking woman wearing jeans and running shoes, who appeared to be in her 70's, rode up on a bicycle to lead our tour. She had arrived in Eagle for the first time in 1953. The vehicle she and her husband drove was the first commercial truck over the Dawson Highway; they kept coming back, and in 1973 they became full-time residents.</p>
        <p>She pulled a potato from the basket on her bike, as large as any Idaho I'd ever seen. ''Look!'' she said. ''Still six more weeks to go in the growing season, and look at the size of it!'' The growing season is short here, less than 100 miles from the Arctic Circle, but because summer days provide as much as 23 hours of sunlight, fruits, vegetables and flowers do well.</p>
        <p>Our little group walked over to the big front porch of this stately two-story white frame building, trimmed in dark green, set back from a large lawn. Once inside, we were transported back to the turn of the century, when Theodore Roosevelt made Eagle the first incorporated city in Alaska's interior, and the legendary Judge James Wickersham was sent out to bring order to the untamed boom town. The Federal court he established in 1900 was the first in the interior.</p>
        <p>In the courtroom, with its massive wooden judicial bench, pot-bellied stove and engravings of outdoor scenes and territory notables on the wall, it was easy to visualize the grizzled sourdoughs, the Han Athabaskan Indians from Eagle Village three miles upriver and the back-country trappers waiting on the hard chairs, fur caps in hand, for the judge to render justice. A far cry from what they had been used to - a show of hands at a rude miners' council.</p>
        <p>THE judge enjoyed his few years in Eagle, although an early diary entry revealed his unhappiness at first with jurors whose sympathies were with the prostitutes and gamblers brought before the court rather than with the law of the far-off United States.</p>
        <p>We walked down to the shore of the fast-flowing Yukon, to enter the old Customs House, also white clapboard and green trimmed. The customs officer pursued his duties downstairs and lived with his family upstairs. It is another museum, full of the clothing and furniture of those bygone days.</p>
        <p>The museum's collection, donated by residents, includes a well-preseved wedding gown probably purchased from a catalog and a handmade baby quilt. Photographs of turn-of-the century Eagleites, taken by C. L. Andrews, a customs worker of the time, hang near a glass case exhibiting clothing in the old Indian style made by Sarah Malcolm, an 85-year-old resident of Eagle Village.</p>
        <p>From the museum we went up a long, slightly sloping field, now an airstrip for the half-dozen private planes in town and formerly the site of Fort Egbert, the military post built in 1898 and decommissioned in 1911. In 1905 the fort's population consisted of 146 soldiers, 10 officers, 61 mules, 19 horses and 36 sled dogs. Inside its carefully reconstructed buildings are exhibits that recall military life in those pre-automobile, pre-electricity days; depict the many ways prospectors teased the gold from the ground; and present a collection of old canoes and sleds (one of which had once carried one of the other guides who grew up in Eagle).</p>
        <p>In the 58-stall barn brass nameplates for each animal let us imagine horses and mules named Trixy, Blue, Snake or Beckie eating from the feedbags now suspended from nails on the walls. Also on the walls are skins of bear, wolf, coyote and moose. Around the corner are the dog sheds, where huskies, Malamutes and mixed breeds warmed up on piles of straw, three or four to a stall.</p>
        <p>Eagle's history predates its incorporation. Indians were already living in Eagle Village, then called Johnny's Village, in 1880 when Moses Mercier opened a trading post on Belle Isle, a mud flat grown into a quarter-mile-long island just offshore, in the middle of the broad Yukon. In 1898, 28 miners named the community that they organized for the bald eagles that nested on the bluff. And in 1899 the Army established Fort Egbert to maintain law and order and develop communications facilities. In 1900 Eagle became the communications center of all of Alaska with the completion of the 1,497-mile Wamcats (Washington-Alaska Military Cable and Telegraph System), which enabled messages to be sent to and from the rest of the United States in five days.</p>
        <p>Two of the people on our tour had been to some of these other towns; they had driven up in the morning from Dawson in Canada's Yukon Territory, a four-hour drive of 144 miles over twisting potholed roads that eat up tires and bouncing gravel that pocks windshields.</p>
        <p>We had flown from Fairbanks - a 75-minute, 200-mile trip that brought home to us how much of a wilderness Alaska still is. Ten minutes out of Fairbanks we left civilization, flying low the rest of the way over mostly desolate hills rising above narrow serpentine creeks, with no roads and no human habitation until we reached Eagle. In previous summers, a sternwheeler made a relaxed circuit through the heart of the gold country, stopping here, but last summer the water level in the Yukon was low and the boat was out of commission.</p>
        <p>Eagle's present exerts its own pull. It has been described as ''the loveliest town on the Yukon,'' a phrase one thinks of when looking out the window of the Riverside Motel and seeing the town's setting, nestled at the foot of Eagle Bluff, by a bend in the Yukon where it widens around Belle Isle. One morning I awakened to see a narrow blush of pink bordering the irregular profile of the purple-blue Ogilvie Range in Canada about five miles away. It was 2:25 A.M. At 4:15 A.M. I awoke again, to see the sky striped in narrow bands of pink and blue, and I kept looking until 4:40 A.M., when the sun burst above the mountains.</p>
        <p>THE Yukon-Charley Rivers National Preserve, operated by the Department of the Interior, has its headquarters in Eagle; its two and one-half million acres encompass 115 miles of the Yukon River and all of the 88-mile Charley River basin. Within the preserve roam grizzly bears, Dall sheep and moose; gyrfalcons and peregrines nest on the cliffs and bluffs along both rivers.</p>
        <p>The preserve has the largest number of nesting peregrine falcons west of the Mississippi - 44 pairs. Their recent comeback generated excitement as we looked through a 45-power telescope trained on an inaccessible ledge near the top of Eagle Bluff, to see two black-and-white peregrine chicks jumping up and down, wings fluttering, in anticipation of dinner. The telescope is left out on the grass, eight hours a day, for anyone to use. The preserve is also a favored site for wilderness rafting and canoe trips. You don't have to make that kind of commitment, though, to enjoy some of Eagle's natural beauty. Right in town, by the riverbank, are fat squawking ravens, darting and swooping bank swallows, crows, geese, ducks and an occasional bald eagle.</p>
        <p>The road to the campground, about a mile from town, is fringed with the ubiquitous fuchsia fireweed, as well as spiky blue lupine, foxtail, cow parsnips, rose hips, larkspur, yarrow, anemones, forget-me-nots and bright yellow poppies. Around the 20 campsites, heavily wooded with spruce, birch and aspen, grow wild blueberries and high-bush cranberries. Clear, cold water runs from the same spring that provided water for Fort Egbert. The old pipeline that carried it a mile and a half to the fort and the old warming houses through which it went are still here.</p>
        <p>The people of Eagle are at least as interesting as its other resources. Many were featured in John McPhee's 1977 book about Alaska, ''Coming Into the Country,'' which the townspeople have mixed feelings about. We heard comments like ''He wrote it the way he saw it - and he told the truth'' and ''He emphasized the wrong things and spoke to the wrong people.''</p>
        <p>SOLD in Eagle, the book is attracting new residents as well as tourists, who shop in Eagle's four stores, buying crafts made by residents of Eagle and Eagle Village, and eat at the Riverside Cafe, enjoying Sheila Layman's home-baked pies and mammoth chocolate chip cookies and her shepherd's pie, meat loaf and fried chicken and biscuits.</p>
        <p>One of the society's projects is the reading room in the Eagle Public Library, where you can pore over historic documents. One night we wandered into the library (surprisingly well stocked for such a tiny town) to see videotapes taken during Eagle's annual winter festival, with residents taking part in contests for chum-chucking (throwing a frozen fish), paddling canoes with poles and sticks on the frozen Yukon and racing in teams of four on one pair of skis.</p>
        <p>Eagle is a tiny dot of a community on the edge of a vast wilderness. Just a few miles out of town is untracked forest, the range of bear, lynx, caribou, moose, marten, beaver and wolf. Those who settle here have come to test themselves against the extremes of weather and climate, to see whether they can survive the minus-60-degree winters with only a few hours of light a day and the 90-degree summers swarming with enormous mosquitoes. They can count only on themselves; there's no auto mechanic down the street when a car is sick, no doctor when they are.</p>
        <p>Somehow these few people get by, even in the virtual absence of regular jobs. Subsistence is the goal - shooting your moose for the year, making crafts items during the long dark days of winter, growing and preserving your own vegetables, having more than one bow to your money-earning string. There's no movie, no fast-food restaurant, no traffic jams or many of the other features of community living that most of us take for granted. So while most of Eagle's appeal to visitors rests on its history, most of its lure for residents lies in its isolation from traditional mores.</p>
        <p>We thought of this duality as we made a long-distance phone call. Eagle got its first telephone five years ago, and the local directory consists of a mimeographed list of about 50 names and numbers, tacked to the wall next to the only pay phone in town, just outside the Eagle Commercial Company, a general store operated by the owners of the telephone company. As we talked to New York, we looked across the street at families drawing water from the town well house, built in 1910. Our telephone connection was clear, but we had trouble hearing over the din of motorcycles and three-wheeled Hondas diving up and down the circa-1920 dirt and gravel road.  ON PLANNING A TRIP TO EAGLE  Getting There  Two airlines, 40-Mile Air (907-474-0518) and Frontier Flying Service (907-474-0014), fly from Fairbanks weekdays ($86 one way).</p>
        <p>Drivers can take Taylor Highway (State Route 5) 156 miles from Tetlin Junction or go north from Whitehorse or Dawson, on Canadian Routes 2 and 9, through Boundary, onto Route 5. ''The Milepost'' ($14.95 plus $1 postage from Alaska Northwest Publishing Company, 130 Second Avenue South, Edmonds, Wash. 98020; 206-774-4111) gives information on services, road conditions and spots of interest. Roads into Eagle are closed from Oct. 15 to May 24.</p>
        <p>On June 10, Holland America Line-Westours (300 Elliott Avenue West, Seattle, Wash. 98119; 206-281-3535) will begin operating a 49-passenger, 58-foot excursion boat on the Yukon River between Dawson, Yukon Territory, and Eagle, Alaska, a four-hour trip downriver and a six-hour trip upriver. For the present, passage will be limited to Westours clients.  Room and Board  Room rates at the following establishments are for two people for one night.</p>
        <p>Riverside Motel has nine rooms with private shower and bath ($50). All rooms are spacious, accommodate up to four people and have TV and views of the Yukon and the mountains. Reserve with Sheila and Dennis Layman, Post Office Box 36, Eagle, Alaska 99738; 907-547-2220.</p>
        <p>The Riverside Cafe is open from 7 A.M. to 8 P.M. Prices are reasonable, especially for Alaska (for two, breakfasts and lunches run about $12; dinners, $16 or $24). No wine or beer is available, since Eagle is dry.</p>
        <p>Eagle's Nest rents out three cabins (four to six beds in each, showers, toilets and tubs) at $45. It also operates a small restaurant and grocery store. Post Office Box 127, Eagle, Alaska 99738; 907-547-2212.</p>
        <p>Village Store has one family-style apartment ($50) with a double bed and a king hide-a-bed, full bath and kitchen. Frank and Mary Lynn Robins, 907-547-2270.</p>
        <p>Eagle Campground has 20 campsites. Information: Yukon-Charley Rivers National Preserve, Post Office Box 64, Eagle, Alaska 99738.  River and Camping Trips  Tatonduk Outfitters (Mark Lynch, Post Office Box 55, Eagle, Alaska 99738; 907-547-2221) runs canoe and raft trips lasting 5 to 11 days.</p>
        <p>Other trips are operated by Yukon Explorer Tours, 201 First Avenue, Fairbanks, Alaska 99701; 907-452-8251, and Midnight Sun Tours Booking, Post Office Box 103355, Anchorage, Alaska 99510; 907-276-8687. Shopping  The Eagle Commercial Company, the Village Store and Gallery, the Artists' Co-op and the Eagle Trading Company sell crafts and jewelry by local artisans, including buttery-soft beaded moccasins from Eagle Village, scrimshaw earrings made from walrus and mammoth tusks, miniature constructions of fishwheels and other Indian structures, hand-knit wool caps and scarves, kuspuks (Indian women's parkas) for Cabbage Patch-type dolls and ice worms, which are little beady-eyed strips of fur that wriggle when you run your finger along them. M. O.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
