<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World Watches Europe, the Power That Will Be By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="166434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ON TO 1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, WEST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY (EEC) (COMMON MARKET)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD1338F932A05754C0A96E948260" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World Watches Europe, the Power That Will Be By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE European Community's rapid march toward removing its maze of internal economic barriers began with fears that it was falling hopelessly behind the United States and Japan. But as the movement picks up speed, leaders in the rest of the world are beginning to wonder what life will be like - politically as well as economically - if Western</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE European Community's rapid march toward removing its maze of internal economic barriers began with fears that it was falling hopelessly behind the United States and Japan. But as the movement picks up speed, leaders in the rest of the world are beginning to wonder what life will be like - politically as well as economically - if Western</p>
        <p>THE European Community's rapid march toward removing its maze of internal economic barriers began with fears that it was falling hopelessly behind the United States and Japan. But as the movement picks up speed, leaders in the rest of the world are beginning to wonder what life will be like - politically as well as economically - if Western Europe indeed emerges as a united superpower.</p>
        <p>For many Europeans and others, the movement represents the most important development on the Continent since the Marshall Plan.</p>
        <p>''The uniting of Europe will come,'' Willy de Clerq, the community's Commissioner of External Relations said last week. ''As far as I am concerned it is written in the stars.''</p>
        <p>Having set a deadline for lifting all economic barriers by the end of 1992, the European Community has raced ahead in recent weeks to eliminate a large number of obstacles. As a step toward permitting the free flow of people, it approved a plan for mutual recognition of university degrees, so a doctor trained in Portugal could work in Denmark and vice versa. The community agreed to end restrictions on the movement of capital that nations such as France and Italy established to prohibit their citizens from depositing savings abroad. In addition, the community hopes to remove all internal border posts so that people can drive from Munich to Malaga without stopping at customs. And this is only the beginning. Predictions that an all-powerful European president could emerge and hold his or her own against the United States and the Soviet Union are exaggerated, or at least premature. Still, the implications of the economic integration of 12 European nations are immense.  A New Competitor</p>
        <p>When the United States decided to commit its economic might to rebuild Europe after World War II, it was clearly the pre-eminent world power. Today, however, with the American economy challenged by Japan - as it is on many other fronts - a number of Americans are not so eager to see the Old Continent suddenly rejuvenated.</p>
        <p>Viewed another way, the establishment of a single continental market is essentially a deregulation plan, inspired in part by the exhortations of President Reagan and Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain.</p>
        <p>''Europe will expand faster, which will help the world economy, and if the world economy grows faster, the United States will benefit,'' said Pierre Jacquet, chief economist with the French Institute for International Relations.</p>
        <p>Still, some Americans feel more fear than flattery at seeing supply-side economics transplanted to Western European soil. Business executives already worry that the Europeans will gain an enormous impetus by reducing their costs as they create a home market of 320 million people.</p>
        <p>American officials, along with those in Japan, also worry that while there will be fewer barriers within Europe, the periphery of the market might be surrounded by one large protectionist wall. Denying the possibility of a ''fortress Europe,'' Mr. de Clerq has nonetheless said that the community is demanding ''reciprocity,'' meaning that foreign businesses would not be granted free access to the market unless their home countries were just as open to European companies. While European officials chastise Washington for its huge trade deficit, the possibility of more protectionism could make it harder for the United States to increase its exports.</p>
        <p>Of course, American multinationals with a large European presence stand to benefit from the 1992 program. Caterpillar and Dow Chemical, for example, are enthusiastic about what is happening.  Political Overtones</p>
        <p>Although the unification plan was established with economics in mind, it will inevitably have vast political repercussions. Some Europeans say economic integration will erode nationalism, smoothing the way to an eventual political union.</p>
        <p>As the 12 nations adopt uniform rules, the European Parliament, the legislative body that votes on community-wide matters, will continue to increase its power. But hardly anyone expects it to supplant national legislatures in the near future. And the president of the European Commission, the community's executive branch, is unlikely to soon become a heavyweight who can stand in the same ring with a Reagan or a Gorbachev, or even with a Kohl, a Mitterrand or a Thatcher. Robust national identities will undoubtedly remain long after the customs houses fall.</p>
        <p>Amid all the clamor and hype about 1992, some Europeans are ambivalent about the plan. German unions, for example, worry about losing jobs to countries like Spain and Portugal where wages are lower. The environmentalist Greens worry that the drive to harmonize conflicting national standards could result in watered-down pollution rules.</p>
        <p>And yet, many Europeans - not only financial magnates - have long been frustrated by a balkanized Western Europe. The problems range from the irritating to the profound. The lack of a single currency means, according to one study, that a traveler who started with $100 and changed it in each country of the community would end up with $47 because of money-changers' fees. Executives complain about clashing standards for toy safety, televisions and testing new drugs. Individually, the nations of Europe find it hard to be seen as equals by the superpowers. It might be a different story with a united Europe of 320 million people.</p>
        <p>As Europe comes together, many analysts predict more efforts to establish a joint defense policy, such as the recent formation of an experimental French-German brigade.</p>
        <p>While a more self-reliant Europe worries some American officials, others say European unity might make it easier for Washington to shift some of its huge defense burden.</p>
        <p>''It is of utility to the world that Europe should be stronger and more integrated,'' said Peter Ludlow, who is director of the Brussels-based Center for European Policy Studies. ''This doesn't mean it won't be at times uncomfortable for the United States, which is used to dealing with partners that are smaller than it is.''  ON TO 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
