<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARCO Offers New Gasoline to Cut Up to 15% of Old Cars' Pollution</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="275638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEAD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC RICHFIELD CO (ARCO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE1639F935A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARCO Offers New Gasoline to Cut Up to 15% of Old Cars' Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a first step in its strategy to make gasoline environmentally competitive with cleaner alternatives, ARCO announced today that it would replace leaded gasoline at its California pumps with a ''reformulated'' fuel that could cut pollution from cars manufactured before 1975 by as much as 15 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a first step in its strategy to make gasoline environmentally competitive with cleaner alternatives, ARCO announced today that it would replace leaded gasoline at its California pumps with a ''reformulated'' fuel that could cut pollution from cars manufactured before 1975 by as much as 15 percent.</p>
        <p>In a first step in its strategy to make gasoline environmentally competitive with cleaner alternatives, ARCO announced today that it would replace leaded gasoline at its California pumps with a ''reformulated'' fuel that could cut pollution from cars manufactured before 1975 by as much as 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The new gasoline could also be used in off-road vehicles, construction equipment and other vehicles that use leaded fuel.</p>
        <p>The changes involved in devising the new fuel for older cars involve no new ingredients, were simple and could have been made long ago, ARCO acknowledged. The company did not do so because it felt no pressure to create a cleaner fuel.</p>
        <p>''We're already selling all the gasoline we can make,'' said James S. Morrison, executive vice president of the Atlantic Richfield Company. He said the company's incentive for devising the new formulation now was the threat posed by regulations in California and proposed rules in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>Industry experts said other companies were likely to follow ARCO's lead in introducing fuel formulated for low pollution, known as ''designer'' gasoline. The proposals in Washington and California would force auto makers to design and sell large numbers of cars using methanol, compressed natural gas and other alternative fuels to meet new clean-air standards. 'The Writing on the Wall'</p>
        <p>''They are seeing the writing on the wall,'' said Bill Kelly, a spokesman for the South Coast Air Quality Management District in Los Angeles, which confirmed ARCO's claims about the new fuel. ''They want to remain players here. They think they can do it through pushing gasoline formulation and technology.''</p>
        <p>The fuel that ARCO announced today will cost about 2 cents a gallon more to produce. ARCO said it would absorb the cost, apparently to protect its position as the low-cost leader among gasoline companies.</p>
        <p>ARCO is the leading marketer of gasoline in Southern California, the region of the nation with the strictest environmental controls. The company also said it hoped to introduce reformulated gasoline for newer vehicles that use unleaded gasoline in three to five years.</p>
        <p>The company said the changes to improve the environmental performance of unleaded gasolines were also thought to be relatively simple. But it said that extensive testing was needed and that refineries would have to be reconfigured, at heavy expense.</p>
        <p>The gasoline companies face tough targets. Methanol can cut the air pollutants emitted from new cars by 50 percent. But they believe that a much smaller saving might make their product environmentally competitive because it could be quickly introduced on all cars.</p>
        <p>ARCO said that in tests its new fuel for pre-1975 cars reduced evaporative emissions of smog-causing chemicals from them by 21 percent, cut carbon monoxide by 9 percent, nitrogen oxide by 5 percent and hydrocarbons by 4 percent. Pollution From Pre-1975 Cars</p>
        <p>Such reductions are among many that are important in reducing overall vehicle pollution, like the introduction of equipment at gas stations to reduce evaporation when cars are filling their gas tanks. Pre-1975 cars are thought to account for as much as 30 percent of all vehicle pollution in Southern California, where mild weather allows vehicles to last longer, and California officials hailed today's announcement.</p>
        <p>''This gasoline will be most helpful in reducing emissions from older cars that do not have sophisticated emission-control systems,'' said Jananne Sharpless, chairwoman of the California Air Resources Board.</p>
        <p>A 20-year-old car puts out 8 to 10 times as much pollution as a new car, Ms. Sharpless said.</p>
        <p>Jerry Martin, a spokesman for the board, said the board's staff was working on proposed regulations for cleaner-burning fuel. ''We'd like to see the entire fuel industry move in the direction that ARCO has,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The new fuel will have the same octane as leaded fuel, 88, Mr. Morrison said, but it will have less butane, making it less prone to evaporation. Evaporation of unburned fuel is a leading source of the chemicals that combine, in the presence of sunlight, to form ground-level ozone. California has already forced refiners to cut the butane content lower than other areas of the country. Ozone-Producing Chemicals</p>
        <p>The new ARCO fuel also cuts olefins and aromatics, a group of chemicals that help make ozone. It cuts benzene, one aromatic, by 50 percent and sulfur by 80 percent. The company also added methyl tertiary butyl ether, known as MTBE, an additive used by many refineries to raise octane. MTBE raises the oxygen content of the fuel, which promotes cleaner burning. Cars will perform as well or better, the company said.</p>
        <p>ARCO said it was naming the new gasoline, which will be introduced Sept. 1, Emission Control 1, or EC-1. ARCO said it would sell the fuel at its more than 700 stations in Southern California, from Santa Barbara to San Diego. It will be dispensed from the pumps that now hold leaded fuel. Since those pumps have a wide nozzle - designed to prevent the introduction of leaded fuel into cars that need unleaded - EC-1 will not be available to drivers of newer cars.</p>
        <p>Industry experts said other oil companies, spurred by President Bush's proposal for fleets of cars running on anything but gasoline, are developing similar products.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is looking at reformulated gasoline right now,'' said Gere Smith, a spokesman for Philips Petroleum, in Bartlesville, Okla. ''Everybody is looking at whatever it's going to take.''</p>
        <p>Terry F. Yosie, vice president for health and environment at the American Petroleum Institute, said, ''It's an indication of how seriously the industry's taking the clean-air issue, and looking at its own products.'' 'It Really Registered'</p>
        <p>ARCO said it started work in March, after California's South Coast Air Quality Management District proposed a 20-year plan that would eliminate gasoline-powered cars in favor of vehicles using methanol, ethanol, compressed natural gas and electricity. ''It really registered that we were going to have to do something,'' Mr. Morrison said.</p>
        <p>That plan was approved today by the California Air Resources Board in Sacramento.</p>
        <p>Nationally, 13 percent of the gasoline sold is leaded, said the American Petroleum Institute, and that 13 percent fuels about 18 percent of the cars on the road. Old cars consume a disproportionately smaller share of the gasoline because they are driven fewer miles each year than new cars, experts say, but even driving those short distances, they produce more than their share of pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morrison said that ARCO hoped others would follow its lead, and that his company would provide the specifications to the new fuel to any refiner that asked. But there is no secret to the new formulation, he said. ''They could buy a gallon and analyze it,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
