<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Missions Face Maze of Red Tape</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="313151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED9103DF932A05751C1A96F948260" item-length="1112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Missions Face Maze of Red Tape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: PROSPECTIVE tenants in New York often have to contend with costly real estate brokers, cranky landlords and choosy co-op boards. But foreign governments at the United Nations in search of new office or living space have an additional complication: the United States Government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: PROSPECTIVE tenants in New York often have to contend with costly real estate brokers, cranky landlords and choosy co-op boards. But foreign governments at the United Nations in search of new office or living space have an additional complication: the United States Government.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTIVE tenants in New York often have to contend with costly real estate brokers, cranky landlords and choosy co-op boards. But foreign governments at the United Nations in search of new office or living space have an additional complication: the United States Government.</p>
        <p>This partly explains why, after three years of searching, the East Germans are still looking for a place to put a new mission and residential complex. It also may explain why they won't talk about it.</p>
        <p>Under the Foreign Missions Act of 1982, all foreign missions are required to tell the State Department whenever they want to buy, sell or rent property in the United States. As an arm of the State Department, the Office of Foreign Missions imposes restrictions on foreign missions in the United States on the basis of national security and treatment of American personnel abroad, or reciprocity.</p>
        <p>Given the elaborate process that governments must go through to acquire property in New York, it might seem easier to pitch a tent. First, a government must submit a diplomatic note to the United States Mission, stating interest in a particular site and its intended purpose. The note is then passed on to the Office of Foreign Missions in New York, which relays it to the Office of Foreign Missions headquarters in Washington, which in turn consults with the State Department about whether to approve the proposal.</p>
        <p>According to the State Department, the diplomatic notes are evaluated with an eye to international, Federal and municipal interests, historic preservation and the ability to provide security and off-street parking. Countries must also meet local building codes and, if a mission and consulate are to be included in one site, the Office of Foreign Mission insists that the buildings have separate entrances and exits.</p>
        <p>The New York City Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps often helps missions navigate New York City building codes, informing them about zoning laws, safety requirements and issues of tax exemption. If, for example, a building will be used for a residence as well as a mission or consulate, governments are only partially tax-exempt.</p>
        <p>Most requests from foreign missions and international organizations are accepted. According to the State Department's June 1989 annual report to Congress on the implementation of the Foreign Missions Act, of 377 requests the Office of Foreign Missions processed in 1988, six were denied.</p>
        <p>Beyond the basic considerations of security, reciprocity and zoning or land-use laws, the Office of Foreign Missions would not elaborate on its criteria for specific countries. Nor is the United States Government obligated to inform countries as to why their proposals were rejected, and often they do not.</p>
        <p>''There is no hard and fast rule,'' said Jack McClennon, the property manager at the Office of Foreign Missions. ''An approval may depend on bilateral relations or treaties we have with a country - it's a very, very loose thing.'' Specific criteria, he said, do not have to be met before a proposal is approved.</p>
        <p>In 1984, for example, the State Department delayed approval of a new Libyan mission and residence because it was concerned that the building could be used for terrorist activities, as was the Libyan Mission in London.</p>
        <p>''We wouldn't approve an Arab mission going next to an Israeli mission, we wouldn't want the Libyans next to the Irish Republic,'' said Stan Lagg, the New York director of the Office of Foreign Missions. ''We would like to tell you everything, but we can't afford to.''</p>
        <p>SOME governments are bitter about being kept in the dark, and others seem to feel that the office is mired in a cold-war mentality, particularly when the world political climate has been warming. ''There are some complaints from countries who feel that O.F.M.'s restrictions are two or three years behind reality,'' said Gillian Martin Sorensen, the New York City Commissioner. ''They don't understand why they have to seek permission. Some countries feel it's harassment, an obstacle course, a steeplechase, almost.''</p>
        <p>The Office of Foreign Missions has 60 days to respond to a diplomatic note and governments may not enter into contract or lease agreements before being notified by the office or before the 60 days have elapsed.</p>
        <p>When countries violate this obligation, the Office of Foreign Missions is entitled under the Foreign Missions Act to divest them of their property. But to date the office has only gone as far as to get a court injunction to stop a purchase from being completed. ''We've never seen an instance where we've gone to the mat and put a lock on the door,'' Mr. McClennon said. ''We don't want an episode where we have to do anything more.''</p>
        <p>The proposals of the German Democratic Republic, for example, have been rejected several times by the Office of Foreign Missions over the last three years. Originally, the East Germans wanted to buy property for a residential and mission complex on First Avenue at 33d Street. But upon discovering that the soil was contaminated by seepage from a neighboring Mobil station, they withdrew their proposal.</p>
        <p>Their next bid was for residential property at 52-54 Park Avenue, down the block from their mission at 56-58 Park Avenue, at 37th Street. Mr. McClennon said the Office of Foreign Missions turned them down on the ground that the building could hold only 30 families and ''would not have provided the East Germans with their total needs.''</p>
        <p>Looking outside New York City, the East Germans found property they liked in New Rochelle but had difficulty seeking variances from the local authorities and backed out. Most recently, the Office of Foreign Missions rejected the German Democratic Republic's request for a site in Scarsdale, but the East Germans have appealed to the State Department to reconsider.</p>
        <p>The East German Ambassador, Siegfried Zachmann, refused to comment on the situation. His deputy, Kurt Kutschan, said: ''So far, we are not in a position or ready to speak about this problem. Before a concrete and official answer from the State Department, there is no sense in it.''</p>
        <p>There are three missions with buildings currently under construction: Hungary's on East 52d Street and those of Nigeria and India, on East 44th Street. Mr. McClennon said that several other countries at the United Nations are looking for new property, including South Africa, Bulgaria and Libya, and that about a dozen have expressed interest in the building that houses the Office of Foreign Missions at 801 United Nations Plaza.</p>
        <p>''Everybody wants to be on top of the U.N.,'' Mr. McLennon said. ''And there is not much that is available.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
