<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Draft of Anti-Pollution Bill Falls Short, Critics Say</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDE1339F931A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Draft of Anti-Pollution Bill Falls Short, Critics Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration's draft legislation to amend the Clean Air Act drew criticism today from some Congressmen, environmentalists and state officials who contended that it falls short in several important areas, including limiting emissions from automobile tailpipes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration's draft legislation to amend the Clean Air Act drew criticism today from some Congressmen, environmentalists and state officials who contended that it falls short in several important areas, including limiting emissions from automobile tailpipes.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration's draft legislation to amend the Clean Air Act drew criticism today from some Congressmen, environmentalists and state officials who contended that it falls short in several important areas, including limiting emissions from automobile tailpipes.</p>
        <p>They asserted that as written, the requirement that industry install technological controls to reduce emissions of toxic substances was weaker than the one promised by President Bush in a speech last month.</p>
        <p>In addition, they said, the draft bill provided ''loopholes'' for cities that would enable them to evade a new requirement to reduce smog by at least 3 percent a year.</p>
        <p>The Administration's proposals are in a 286-page draft unofficially circulated on Capitol Hill and among environmental and industry groups and state officials.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, some industry spokesmen said the provisions in the draft appear to be more burdensome and costly than they had anticipated after the President's speech. Letter and Spirit of Pledge</p>
        <p>But Administration officials said the legislation being drafted meets the letter and spirit of the President's pledge and would aggressively tackle the nation's air pollution problems. They also said the drafting process is not completed and changes could still be made before a bill is sent up to Capitol Hill. A final version of the legislation is scheduled to be completed by July 21.</p>
        <p>The drafting of the measure reportedly involved the same kind of infighting that took place before the President announced his clean air proposals. Environmental Protection Agency officials continued to press for strong pollution-fighting measures but were opposed by other Administration officials who were concerned about the costs of regulatory measures, senior officials said.</p>
        <p>The draft provision causing the most concern among critics would change the present rules governing pollution from motor vehicle tailpipes. Under current law, every automobile must emit no more than the maximum amount of pollutants like hydrocarbons, carbon monoxide and nitrogen oxide from its exhaust system. As drafted, the law would be changed to require that automotive fleets, rather than individual cars, meet the standards for maximum tailpipe emissions.</p>
        <p>For example, if pollution from one line of General Motors cars was brought below the maximum level required by law, the automaker could allow another line of its cars to go above the maximum allowed amount of pollution. Or, General Motors could sell the rights to the additional pollution to the Ford Motor Company or any other auto manufacturer. Theory and Reality</p>
        <p>In theory, the fleet average would lower pollution by as much as a requirement that all cars meet a maximum pollution standard. But Michael Walsh, who formerly headed the E.P.A.'s office that regulates motor vehicles, said the provision would allow automobile pollution to increase.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh, who is now a private consultant on automobile pollution matters, said in a memorandum to members of Congress and others that auto manufacturers now build in a margin of safety to insure that all their vehicles meet Federal pollution standards. If fleet averaging were permitted, he said, the margin of safety would be eliminated and pollution would rise to the maximum permitted.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and their allies on Capitol Hill also criticized what they said were loopholes that would allow many cities to evade a requirement that they reduce air pollution by at least 3 percent a year. The draft would allow a city to bypass the annual reductions if it shows it can reach its clean air goals by the final time limit. 'A Major Retreat'</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat who is chairman of the House Energy Committee's Environment and Health Subcommittee, said, ''The legislative language I've seen is a far cry from the aggressive and full requirements that will be needed to deliver on the President's commitment to achieve clean air for every American.''</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, a senior lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council and former Assistant Administrator of the E.P.A. for air programs in the Carter Administration, said the draft legislation, particularly as it affected the auto industry, was ''a major retreat from the President's promises.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for an industry coalition trying to influence the clean air legislation also criticized the draft. William D. Fay, administrator of the Clean Air Group, said it ''goes far beyond what the President announced,'' does not give industry the flexibility it needs to reduce pollution and would cost far more than the $14 billion to $18 billion a year projected by the Administration last month.</p>
        <p>But William G. Rosenberg, Assistant Administrator of the E.P.A. for air, said, ''I believe that the negotiations on the language are going very well and that the bill that emerges will follow the letter and spirit of the President's commitments.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
