<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Greece of Forests And Mountain Lakes</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="222633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREECE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MACEDONIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EPIRUS (GREECE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAPLAN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Macedonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED91631F931A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="2160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Greece of Forests And Mountain Lakes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. KAPLAN; ROBERT D. KAPLAN, a writer based in Athens, is the author of a book on Afghanistan to be published by Houghton Mifflin.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAPLAN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR years, my vision of Greece consisted exclusively of naked, sun-scorched rock and pristine sugar-cube villages rising out of an expanse of blue sea. Then, gradually, I became drawn to another, more subtle Greece, not Mediterranean but Balkan; an autumnal land of fir forests, stately poplars and dark green mountains grooved with snow, evoking the background of an old master's painting rather than the usual watercolor sketch of sea and stone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR years, my vision of Greece consisted exclusively of naked, sun-scorched rock and pristine sugar-cube villages rising out of an expanse of blue sea. Then, gradually, I became drawn to another, more subtle Greece, not Mediterranean but Balkan; an autumnal land of fir forests, stately poplars and dark green mountains grooved with snow, evoking the background of an old master's painting rather than the usual watercolor sketch of sea and stone.</p>
        <p>FOR years, my vision of Greece consisted exclusively of naked, sun-scorched rock and pristine sugar-cube villages rising out of an expanse of blue sea. Then, gradually, I became drawn to another, more subtle Greece, not Mediterranean but Balkan; an autumnal land of fir forests, stately poplars and dark green mountains grooved with snow, evoking the background of an old master's painting rather than the usual watercolor sketch of sea and stone.</p>
        <p>While the Aegean islands have become synonymous with summer lust and youthful self-discovery, the regions of Macedonia and Epirus in northwest Greece recall early childhood dreams and stimulate the reflection that comes with old age. ''Macedonia,'' wrote Rebecca West in ''Black Lamb and Grey Falcon,'' ''is the country I have always seen between sleeping and waking.''</p>
        <p>It is the country that Americans, reared on standard travel poster images and the Greek seaboard odysseys of such writers as Henry Miller and Lawrence Durrell, have little firsthand knowledge of. Last summer, traveling through northwest, Greece, I encountered quite a few Greek and European tourists, all in small, quiet family groups. But I saw almost no Americans, and none of the backpackers who frequent the islands. Since then I have returned to Macedonia and Epirus twice, in early autumn and again in winter, when there were no tourists except myself.</p>
        <p>The air approach into Kastoria, 20 miles from the Albanian border in western Macedonia, is in my opinion the most dramatic of any entry in Greece, save for sailing into the volcanic island of Santorini at dawn. Outside the plane window is a dizzying world of vertical drops; snow-capped mountains and velvety, olive-green slopes that flatten out into beech and evergreen forests and reddish-brown farm fields traversed by rushing, willow-braided streams.</p>
        <p>The town of Kastoria boasts a spectacular situation at the foot of the Vitsi and Grammos mountains, at the edge of a lake that has the mysterious, toneless quality of a dusty mirror.</p>
        <p>The lake gets its name from Orestes, Agamemnon's son, who according to legend founded Kastoria during a grief-stricken, self-imposed exile after murdering his mother, Clytemnestra, and her lover. Kastoria was occupied by Bulgars, Serbs, Albanians and Turks before being restored to Greece in 1912. The mountains behind the town were scenes of important battles in World War II and the subsequent Greek Civil War. Walking along the lakefront in early December under a leaden sky and hearing only the wind, the flapping of swans' wings over the water, and the crunch of dead poplar leaves underfoot, it was easy to imagine the harsh winters of war and privation endured by Kastoria's inhabitants during the 1940's, a period that pricks the heart of every Greek and still influences the country's politics, but which most tourists, focusing only on the classical period, know little about.</p>
        <p>Scattered throughout the town are over 50 small Byzantine churches, dating from as far back as the 11th century, with lovely frescoes and several hundred 17th- and 18th-century mansions built in the traditional Balkan style, featuring overhanging upper floors, wooden balconies and red tiled roofs. Kastoria's wealth, then as now, derives from the fur industry, especially the sewing together of small scraps into coats, stoles, slippers, hats and other items that can be bought at relatively cheap prices from stores all over town.</p>
        <p>From almost whatever direction one walks out of Kastoria, or out of most other towns in northwest Greece for that matter, trekking conditions are excellent from May through October. The climate is fresher and cooler than in the coastal areas and rarely does it rain during this period. But if you care to linger for several days in one place, without a doubt the most beautiful and well-equipped town in the region for tourists is Metsovo.</p>
        <p>Metsovo, deep in the Pindus mountains in Epirus, is a sort of Balkan version of Mykonos; an immaculate, architecturally-pure village perched on a hillside, with winding, cobbled streets and traditional gingerbread houses, noisy with donkey and goat bells, that suggests the landscape of childhood as it exists only in fairy tales. In place of the sea, as in Mykonos, are beech trees, holm oaks, horse chestnuts, hawthorns, cypresses, poplars and Balkan firs.</p>
        <p>In summer, the wooden balconies of Metsovo are filled with pots of geraniums, marigolds, begonias, petunias and other flowering plants. In autumn, the foliage, though less spectacular than in North America, has an unrivaled subtlety born of grays and browns and yellows. And I have had few moments in Greece as pleasurable as waking up on a winter morning in Metsovo, in a well-heated, wood-paneled hotel room, and opening the curtains to see the mountains coated with fresh-fallen snow.</p>
        <p>Metsovo's several thousand inhabitants are Vlachs, originally from Rumania, who speak their own Latin-based language as well as Greek. The town owes its original wealth to an incident in the 17th century, when a Turkish vizier, out of favor with his sultan, was given refuge by a local peasant. The vizier later came to power and returned the favor by granting Metsovo virtual independence and tax-free privileges, a circumstance that led many wealthy Christian families to settle here and build mansions.</p>
        <p>The preservation of Metsovo as an outdoor museum of traditional architecture, costumes and handicrafts is due to the generosity and wisdom of several local philanthropists, especially the Averoff-Tosizza family. Their endowments encouraged the high-quality rugs, embroidered coverings, wood carvings, and silver and gold work that fill the town's numerous handicraft shops.</p>
        <p>The Tosizza Mansion, a magnificent stone building overlaid with wood, whose foundations were laid in 1661, functions as the Museum of Popular Art for the Epirus region. It is one of Greece's best small museums (open 8:30 A.M. to 1 P.M. and 3 P.M. to 5 P.M. daily except Thursday). The mansion's 10 rooms contain the finest examples of locally made weapons, pottery, jewelry, wine cases, costumes, carpets and such household items of the era as a hand-carved wooden cradle, a narghile, donkey bells and saddles and braziers for holding live coals. The richly colored carpets and tapestries are similar to those seen throughout the neighboring Balkan countries, except, like everything else in Metsovo, the quality here is higher and the setting more cheerful.</p>
        <p>A room on the top floor of the mansion contains a collection of 16th- and 17th-century Byzantine icons. In a corner of this room is my favorite spot in Metsovo. The sunlight streams through the tree branches against the stained blue and green dormer windows, warming the embroidered cushions and bedspread of a spacious couch. Lying on the couch one would see the mountains through the window, in one direction, and the icons and an oriental carpet in another. The dusty glass intensifies the sunlight: I could almost smell the sweet aroma of pine outside. It seemed the perfect place to lie down and take a long nap, or to die even.</p>
        <p>Metsovo, like all good holiday resorts, is a great place to sleep; even in summer there are relatively few motorcycles, which have become the bane of many formerly peaceful Greek islands. The pleasures of food and walking are also unquestioned here. My own afternoon ritual is to take a stroll part of the way down the gorge of the Metsovitikos River, before buying a portion of smoked cheese (tiri kapniestos) for which the town is famous, and a bottle of locally made, red Katogi wine ($7 in a grocery shop and $11 in a restaurant). Then I return to my hotel room and devour it all on the balcony with a good book in hand. The wine is dark, full-bodied and smooth, lacking the coarseness of many other Greek wines. A bottle puts one in a delightful stupor.</p>
        <p>In the evening, I always go to the Galaxy taverna, which has a porch with tables overlooking the cobblestone expanse of the main square that is, thankfully, empty of cars at night, and filled with old women in traditional embroidered dresses and old men in black suits and wonderfully big moustaches, holding hand-carved walking sticks. A full meal for two at any local taverna rarely costs more than $20. A late-night coffee or Metaxa brandy can then be taken in the cozy lobby of the Hotel Egnatia, which, like the other hotel lobbies in Metsovo, is decorated with lacquered wood paneling and traditional Balkan weaving, as though it were a room in the museum.</p>
        <p>Metsovo is conveniently situated; equidistant between the city of Ioannina, the regional capital of Epirus, to the west, and the fabulous Meteora monasteries, clinging to pillars of sheer rock, to the east. These monasteries are among the most popular tourist attractions in Greece on account of their precarious situation. But I could never understand why almost all the guidebooks recommend coming to Meteora by bus from Athens through the stiflingly hot and nondescript town of Trikkala; a seven-hour ordeal that offers little worthwhile scenery. A more exciting and less-tiring way to visit Meteora would be to fly to Ioannina (the round-trip air fare from Athens is under $90), then board a bus for a 90-minute journey through the heart of the Pindus mountain range to Metsovo, where one can linger a day or longer, before taking another 90-minute ride through the 5,600-foot Katara Pass to the monasteries.</p>
        <p>Ioannina, like Kastoria, sits by the edge of a lake at the foot of a mountain, making it the most scenic of Greece's large cities. Here was where Lord Byron began his epic poem, ''Childe Harold's Pilgrimage,'' while visiting the court of the Turkish tyrant Ali Pasha in 1809.</p>
        <p>ALI PAShA ran a virtually independent kingdom in northwest Greece, and his victories included a defeat of Napoleon's forces in 1798 at Preveza, on the Ionian Sea. According to certain accounts, the lake here is filled with the skeletons of Ali Pasha's concubines, who were tied up in sacks and thrown into the water if they displeased him.</p>
        <p>The walls of Ali Pasha's fort enclose the quiet, rambling lanes of Ioannina's old city. There is a synagogue built in 1790 (closed on the day I visited it), and a 19th-century Turkish mosque that commands a fine view of the lake and houses an eccentric little museum containing all sorts of bric-a-brac: antique guns, icons, rare editions of the works of Rudyard Kipling, and old black and white photos, buckling in their frames, of the heroes of the local struggle for independence against the Turks.</p>
        <p>The tavernas on the lakefront, just north of the fort area, are the best places to eat a lunch before catching an eastbound bus to Metsovo or a northbound bus to the Zagoria region, whose well-preserved little villages, especially Papingo and Monodendri, offer the best and most scenic hiking trails in all of Epirus and Macedonia. If the bus schedules are inconvenient and you don't want to rent a car, remember that taxis between towns in this part of Greece are cheap and easily available. For example, a private taxi to cover the 45 mountainous miles from Ioannina to Metsovo should cost roughly $30. (For such journeys Greek drivers rarely use the meter, preferring instead to set a fixed price.) Epirus and Macedonia offer the atmosphere in summer that Greek islands used to offer before the tourist explosion of the 1960's. They are regions where the traveler can still be alone without feeling lonely. Up in these mountains, the other tourists you meet tend to be like yourself, quietly exploring a deeper level of the Greek experience after growing out of their island fixation.  GETTING AROUND THE NORTH</p>
        <p>There are daily flights between Athens and Ioannina, but one should book in advance in summer.  Hotels and Dining</p>
        <p>The main hotel in Metsovo is the Egnatia (telephone 41263), costing $26 for a single and $31 for a double in summer and during Christmas week; prices the rest of the year are $20 and $24.</p>
        <p>However, my favorite hotel in Metsovo is the Bitouni (41217 or 41545), which has the atmosphere of an alpine lodge and is run by a friendly family. Singles and doubles throughout the year are $18 and $29 respectively. Breakfast is not included, and the best place to eat breakfast in Metsovo is at the Cafe Irini (Peace), where fresh yogurt and honey are served on a terrace.</p>
        <p>In Kastoria, the Europa Hotel charges $22 and $29 a night for singles and doubles. In all these places, there are pension-style hotels.  Sights</p>
        <p>Byzantine churches in Kastoria are open from 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. and closed on Monday. The monasteries in Meteora have various hours. Generally, they are open from 9 A.M. to noon and from 2 to 4 P.M. The mosque in Ioannina is a museum, open from 8 A.M. to 3:15 P.M. every day. The synagogue is open from 9:30 A.M. to 12:30 P.M., on Friday additionally from 5:20 to 7 P.M., Saturday from 8 A.M. to 5:20 P.M. - R. D. K.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
