<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Auto Makers' Plea on Pollution</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="267718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D7173AF932A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="1500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Auto Makers' Plea on Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, July 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As the Bush Administration prepares to disclose the details of its recent proposal for a new clean-air bill on Friday, auto industry executives are striving to focus the debate on the high cost of a number of changes that they concede are - or soon will be - technically feasible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As the Bush Administration prepares to disclose the details of its recent proposal for a new clean-air bill on Friday, auto industry executives are striving to focus the debate on the high cost of a number of changes that they concede are - or soon will be - technically feasible.</p>
        <p>As the Bush Administration prepares to disclose the details of its recent proposal for a new clean-air bill on Friday, auto industry executives are striving to focus the debate on the high cost of a number of changes that they concede are - or soon will be - technically feasible.</p>
        <p>The President's proposal last month, which also dealt with pollution from factories and power plants, called on the automobile industry to produce cars that have lower tailpipe emissions and can run on cleaner alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>Detroit is mounting a lobbying effort, however, to convince Congress that some of the specific standards and timetables in the White House's proposals do not make sense economically or technologically. They stress, for example, that some measures to reduce auto pollution are likely to set back efforts to improve auto mileage - another goal of the Government as it tries to reduce the nation's dependence on imported oil. Few Benefits Seen</p>
        <p>Auto executives also say that shifting quickly to alternative fuels is too risky, since fuel distribution networks are not yet established. And they warn that the simplest and least costly steps to make cars run more cleanly have already been taken. They conclude that removing the last traces of tailpipe emissions is likely to produce few benefits at a very high cost, which customers may balk at paying.</p>
        <p>''The average person doesn't understand that reducing a very small amount of emissions by 50 percent doesn't really do too much,'' said Robert C. Stempel, president of the General Motors Corporation, the nation's largest auto company.</p>
        <p>Although they are not unanimous on whether alternative fuels represent the best solution, most environmentalists disagree with Detroit's argument that remaining tailpipe emissions are insignificant compared with the effort required to remove them.</p>
        <p>''I think the companies are being overly pessimistic,'' said Richard Ayres, head of the National Clean Air Coalition, based in Washington. ''The only responsible policy is to give the industry a directive and a lead time. We're not going to limit public health objectives according to what the companies say they can do.''</p>
        <p>One pressing question for Detroit is whether the clean-air bill that finally emerges from Congress - probably next year - will require that all cars must be improved equally. The auto makers are hoping for a system allowing them to improve some cars more than others, for a gain that is acceptable on average. That is the approach currently used in Federal fuel efficiency laws.</p>
        <p>The key, said Donald E. Petersen, chairman of the Ford Motor Company, is to ''permit the industries to work on these goals with a sensible set of priorities on a timetable that is efficient.''</p>
        <p>But even as they protest the high costs of meeting the Bush goals, Detroit's auto companies are scrambling to anticipate the changes that may be demanded. Here is a summary of the state of technology in the three key areas of automobile performance that have risen to the top of the Bush Administration's environ-mental agenda for the industry.  Tailpipe Emissions</p>
        <p>Auto makers have already improved cars enough to reduce tailpipe emissions of volatile hydrocarbons, the largest air pollutant, by 96 percent. Carbon monoxide emissions have also been cut by 96 percent and oxides of nitrogen by 76 percent. Thus, as older cars are scrapped, air quality should improve even without further changes.</p>
        <p>The biggest gains now, they say, could come from work to prevent unburned gasoline vapors, a major source of pollution, from escaping into the atmosphere. Auto makers say they can install a new form of charcoal-filled canister under the hood to collect gasoline vapor, as well as redesign the fuel system to further prevent evaporation.</p>
        <p>But the E.P.A. says further controls on tailpipe emissions are also needed, and both sides agree that the technology exists to do it. Most tailpipe pollution is emitted in the first minutes of a vehicle's operation, before the catalytic converter, a device that promotes more thorough burning of the engine exhaust, has had time to get hot. Engineers may address that concern by moving the converter closer to the engine or by installing a system that pre-heats it before ignition.</p>
        <p>Adding precious metals like platinum and rhodium to catalytic converters and more sophisticated controls to regulate the burning of fuel can also lower emissions. But the additional metal would add to costs and the added weight of new controls and changes in the way fuel is burned could penalize fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to make sure all cars have the latest hardware, including electronic fuel injection, state-of-the-art computers, exhaust gas recirculation and maybe air pumps for the exhaust,'' said Kelly M. Brown, an executive engineer at Ford. ''But we can't go hog wild, because if we bolt all that stuff on we know we're going to be short on CAFE,'' he said, referring to Corporate Average Fuel Economy, the Federal fuel-efficiency requirements.  Alternative Fuels</p>
        <p>General Motors, Ford and the Chrysler Corporation have already tested engines based on methanol, ethanol, propane and electricity, among others. Ford and G.M. are monitoring thousands of state government cars in California that run on methanol but can also use gasoline or any combination of the two. Early test results on performance and reliability are promising. But there are many unanswered questions, such as how customers may react to the fact that a tank of methanol will get 40 percent fewer miles than a tank of gasoline.</p>
        <p>Methanol, derived from natural gas, coal or wood, burns much more cleanly than gasoline. It has been used in racing cars for years to reduce the danger of explosion and is the alternative fuel favored by the Big Three.</p>
        <p>Conventional engines can burn methanol, natural gas or ethanol with some minor adjustments. For the two California test fleets, G.M. and Ford have developed sensors that can tell the engine whether it must burn methanol, gasoline or a combination of the two. Chrysler and foreign car makers are also conducting research on such applications.</p>
        <p>Flexible-fuel engines could make it easier for drivers to switch to alternative-fuel cars before a strong fuel distribution network evolves. Chemical and petroleum companies say they are reluctant to commit money for new plants and pipelines until they know the extent of the market.</p>
        <p>Because methanol contains less energy than gasoline, a conventional car using methanol would run out of fuel in about half the time it would if it used gasoline. A much bigger fuel tank could alleviate the problem, but there is not much unused space in today's cars. Engineers have developed special plastic that resists methanol's corrosiveness and can be molded to take advantage of unused nooks and crannies. But eventually, fuel tanks might need to grow larger, reducing trunk or interior space.</p>
        <p>While the burning of methanol is much cleaner, it produces other harmful substances, like formaldehyde. And methanol must be mixed with gasoline to create a fuel that vaporizes easily enough to start an engine on a winter morning in cold regions.</p>
        <p>Methanol is currently 20 to 70 percent more expensive per mile driven, according to the environmental group Inform. But the price could drop if the fuel were produced in large volume.</p>
        <p>Detroit is confident it can produce the 500,000 alternative-fuel cars a year that the Government has mentioned as a tentative target for 1995, but it worries about consumer acceptance of them. ''If they'd pass a law saying people had to buy methanol cars, that would be a neat deal,'' said Donald Runkle, head of advanced engineering at General Motors.</p>
        <p>But that is not likely. ''The public may be willing to absorb a couple hundred dollars extra in price,'' said Richard Wilson, director of the E.P.A.'s office of mobile sources, when asked about flexible-fuel cars. ''If not, the industry will have to work out promotional pricing to get the right sales mix.''  Air-Conditioners</p>
        <p>Air-conditioners that operate without chlorofluorocarbons are expected to be larger and heavier, forcing Detroit to redesign some auto models to make space for them and reducing fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>The Bush proposals do not address the problem of chlorofluorocarbons, but the United States and other nations agreed in Montreal in 1987 to cut the use of of the chemicals in half by 1998. Vermont has passed a law banning the substance in cars by 1993.</p>
        <p>One alternative refrigerant for air-conditioners is tetrafluoroethane, commonly known as 134A and produced by E. I. Du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company and other chemical companies, but not yet in quantities that the car makers need. Du Pont has said it will step up production next year. Scientists are also designing new lubricants that will be needed before 134A can be used effectively. G.M. said it hoped to be able to equip cars with 134A-based air-conditioners in the mid-1990's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
