<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAR MAKERS WEIGH GASOLINE CHANGES TO CUT POLLUTION</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="282608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE1231F931A2575AC0A96F948260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAR MAKERS WEIGH GASOLINE CHANGES TO CUT POLLUTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Big Three auto makers are close to joining leading oil companies in testing the feasability of using reformulated gasoline instead of methanol or other alternative fuels to meet stricter clean-air standards proposed by the Bush Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Big Three auto makers are close to joining leading oil companies in testing the feasability of using reformulated gasoline instead of methanol or other alternative fuels to meet stricter clean-air standards proposed by the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>The Big Three auto makers are close to joining leading oil companies in testing the feasability of using reformulated gasoline instead of methanol or other alternative fuels to meet stricter clean-air standards proposed by the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>The Administration proposal, submitted to Congress in June, calls for the auto industry to begin producing up to a million vehicles annually by the mid-1990's that would burn an unspecified ''alternative fuel.''</p>
        <p>Officials of the Environmental Protection Agency, as well as some officials in Southern California, are thought by the oil and auto industries to favor methanol, but those industries have serious reservations. Pilot Models Being Tested</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company, the General Motors Corporation and the Chrysler Corporation have all expressed confidence that they can build methanol-burning vehicles in quantity, if required to do so, by the mid-1990's; Ford and G.M. are now testing pilot models in California.</p>
        <p>But auto executives also worry that short of a law requiring the purchase of such vehicles, consumers may ultimately reject methanol vehicles, leaving the companies to bear the financial brunt of the law.</p>
        <p>The research project under discussion would examine various reformulations of gasoline, as well as fuels like methanol, ethanol, natural gas and perhaps others. Tests would provide data on the nature of emissions and performance characteristics of the fuel when burned by engines now built by Detroit, said Helen O. Petrauskas, a Ford vice president. Vote by Early 1990 Seen</p>
        <p>Mrs. Petrauskas said she hoped the project could begin ''within a few months'' so a great deal of data would be accumulated in advance of rule-making hearings that would start 18 months after the passage of a bill. Many in the industry and the Government believe a bill could be put to a vote by early 1990. ''The sooner we get started, the more data we'll have when rule-making starts,'' she added.</p>
        <p>In the past, the auto makers and the oil companies have conducted joint research on other issues of mutual interest, like motor oils and lubricants, through committees of the Motor Vehicles Manufacturers Association. But few projects have held as much potential for making an impact on the way cars are designed - of the way fuel is processed and delivered - as the project under discussion.</p>
        <p>Oil companies have billions of dollars invested in gasoline refineries in the United States and abroad, and industry officials say they prefer to comply with provisions of any new law by providing a reformulated gasoline.</p>
        <p>''What we're looking for is a level playing field so that every fuel that might be a cost-effective solution to the problem might have a chance to compete,'' said Keith McHenry, a senior vice president of the Amoco Corporation, a major oil refiner. ''We want to find the truth. We'd prefer to sell reformulated gasoline, but if the research shows that methanol is the best solution, we'll sell methanol.''</p>
        <p>Privately, Federal environmental officials insist that oil industry lobbyists are waging a behind-the-scenes political battle to remove methanol and other non-gasoline alternatives from consideration. Many Issues Not Resolved</p>
        <p>Conversely, auto and oil industry officials believe E.P.A. officials are predisposed in favor of methanol, even though many technical and other issues have not been resolved, like how to inhibit emission of formaldehyde from methanol-burning engines. Another serious drawback of methanol is that it contains less energy than gasoline, and thus vehicles would have to be redesigned to carry a significantly bigger tank of fuel to equal the range of current models.</p>
        <p>''The oil companies are working hard to get the alternate fuels provisions killed,'' said Richard D. Wilson, director of the E.P.A.'s office of mobile sources. ''We know for sure that ethanol, methanol and compressed natural gas can meet the emissions targets we've set. If the oil industry can come up with a reformulated gasoline that can meet the standards, it's fine with us.''</p>
        <p>Gasoline is a combination of many hydrocarbons, sometimes more than 100, that can be varied in amount to affect the fuel's properties, like volatility or how easily the fuel evaporates in the atmosphere. Statement by Sununu</p>
        <p>One Big Three lobbyist in Washington, who preferred to remain anonymous, said the companies had been told by John Sununu, the President's chief of staff, that the Government has not already decided the case in favor of methanol. ''Sununu has told us it's a level playing field and may the best and most economical fuel win,'' the lobbyist added.</p>
        <p>Although the specific emissions standards would be set in the rule-making phase of the legislative procedure, the President's bill would generally lower the amount of hydrocarbons, carbon monoxide, oxides of nitrogen and other particles that could be emitted legally from a car's tailpipe. Auto makers have said they are not sure whether such reductions will do much to clean up the air, but they have said they will support the legislation.</p>
        <p>Auto makers have suggested for some time, however, that reformulation of gasoline could reduce so-called running losses, or gasoline evaporation, which contributes to air pollution. Recently the oil industry has begun to respond. The Atlantic Richfield Company, a major gasoline marketer, last month announced a lower-polluting formulation of a new fuel for cars that still burn leaded gasoline; the company said it was working on a version for cars that burn unleaded fuel, too.</p>
        <p>Denying a report in the automotive trade press that the purpose of joint research was to kill methanol as an alternative fuel, Arthur E. Wiese, a spokesman for the American Petroleum Institute, said: ''We're not against methanol per se. We're against doing it before we can answer the various technical and environmental questions.''</p>
        <p>Several major oil companies are testing reformulated gasolines -sometimes referred to as ''designer'' gasolines, while others, including ARCO and the Sun Company, are test-marketing methanol in areas where experimental vehicles are being studied.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
