<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pollution Warning From California</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="235997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLUMENTHAL, RALPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DA1F30F933A05750C0A96F948260" item-length="1392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pollution Warning From California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLUMENTHAL, RALPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The drastic and costly air-cleansing rules mandated in Southern California this month should serve as a warning to the New York metropolitan region, where some measurements of air pollution are almost as bad and others are worse, Federal and local officials say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The drastic and costly air-cleansing rules mandated in Southern California this month should serve as a warning to the New York metropolitan region, where some measurements of air pollution are almost as bad and others are worse, Federal and local officials say.</p>
        <p>The drastic and costly air-cleansing rules mandated in Southern California this month should serve as a warning to the New York metropolitan region, where some measurements of air pollution are almost as bad and others are worse, Federal and local officials say.</p>
        <p>They say the New York region has avoided such stringent regulations by producing anti-pollution plans that have been satisfactory to the Federal Government, even though the region has failed to achieve the goals set forth in the plans.</p>
        <p>The California measures, adopted for the smog-shrouded Los Angeles basin, provide for a three-phase air-pollution control program that will cost the region an estimated $2.8 billion a year for the first five years. Rules for Lawns and Barbecues</p>
        <p>The measures would ban most free parking, barbecue starter fuels and gas-powered lawn mowers as early as this year. They would also restrict the chemical formulations of paints, solvents and household cosmetics; phase in cleaner-burning methanol as an alternative fuel, and leave open the possibility of a ban on all gasoline-powered vehicles by the year 2007.</p>
        <p>''We haven't reached that stage here,'' said Ray Werner, who heads the air programs branch of the Federal Environmental Protection Agency's regional office in New York City. But he added, ''We are not far behind.''</p>
        <p>He said the California model should stimulate further action in the New York region, which is engaged in a court-ordered search for its own new strategies to combat worsening air pollution. New York and New Jersey have been ordered to produce a new compliance plan by September 1991.</p>
        <p>''They've done a lot of the easy things,'' Mr. Werner said of the New York region. ''The next steps will be a lot harder.'' Fees and Tolls Contemplated Among these, he said, could be ''California-type'' driving restrictions and higher auto-use fees and tolls. But he added that these would be for the regional authorities, not the Federal Government, to impose.</p>
        <p>Tom Allen, acting director of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation's Division of Air Resources, agreed. ''A lot of things California is considering will be considered here,'' he said. Among them, he said, would be requiring taxis and fleet vehicles to run on alternative fuels like methanol.</p>
        <p>Already, six Queens express buses to Manhattan are experimenting with methanol; in another experiment, two buses are running on natural gas.</p>
        <p>''Anything is on the table,'' said Mark Silver, special counsel to the New York City Transportation Commissioner, Ross Sandler. ''We could say right now, 'Okay, everybody out of Manhattan,' but we're not going to do that.'' He said the city is about to order a $2 million study to examine the potential impact of various traffic-control measures.</p>
        <p>These might include the long-debated options of restricting private auto traffic into Manhattan at various times and limiting goods deliveries.</p>
        <p>Southern California, which had no federally approved anti-pollution plan in place before the regulations were imposed, leads the nation by far in ozone, a toxic form of oxygen. At 10 to 15 miles up in the atmosphere, ozone serves as a protective shield against ultraviolet rays from the sun. But it is also a pollutant dangerous to life on earth. Highly reactive, it combines with chains of carbon and hydrogen atoms to create eye-burning and lung-searing smog that geography has turned into a particular problem in the Los Angeles basin.</p>
        <p>The New York metropolitan region reaches ozone levels of about 1.5 times the Federal standard of .012 parts per million on an hourly average. The region exceeded the standard on 19 days in 1987, a slightly better record than Philadelphia and Houston. The Los Angeles area records ozone levels of almost three times the standard, and in 1987 it exceeded the standard on 141 days.</p>
        <p>At the same time, New York City leads the nation in carbon monoxide levels - just over twice the standard of 9 parts per million. The colorless, odorless pollutant stems largely from automobile exhaust. In 1987 the city exceeded the standard on 86 days. The Los Angeles region recorded levels of almost twice the standard and exceeded the standard on 40 days.</p>
        <p>A third pollutant of concern called particulates - carbon-based soot particles carrying toxic substances - has been re-evaluated to take account of new findings showing that small particles are more worrisome than large ones. Readings at 46th and Madison</p>
        <p>The only street-level device in New York City to measure particulates, on Madison Avenue between 46th and 47th Streets, showed that the pollutant was at a level slightly above the Federal standard. The device measured an average annual accumulation of 50 micrograms, or 50 millionths of a gram per cubic meter, according to preliminary data for the first half of 1988.</p>
        <p>Acting under the orders of Federal District Courts in Manhattan and Newark, the Environmental Protection Agency directed New York and New Jersey this year to come up with new strategies by September 1991 to bring levels of carbon monoxide and ozone into compliance with air-quality standards. It did not set a date by which the strategies would have to be carried out.</p>
        <p>The Federal agency also directed both states in the meantime to step up enforcement and plug loopholes in their current plans.</p>
        <p>The court orders also called for the recovery of gasoline vapors from service station pumps, a practice now well under way in New Jersey and New York; rules requiring the use of less volatile paints; closer supervision of auto body workshops, and closer monitoring of small polluters like printing shops and dry-cleaners. Standards Called Unrealistic</p>
        <p>''The days of the manana syndrome are over,'' said Eric Goldstein, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental law group that filed lawsuits against New York and the Federal E.P.A. The suits led to the stepped-up anti-pollution measures in the region. A companion lawsuit was filed by the American Lung Association of New Jersey. The suits won on summary judgments in the Federal courts.</p>
        <p>But New York-area environmental officials say that Federal standards were often unrealistic. The officials contend that much pollution comes from outside the region or, as in the case of certain cosmetic products like hairsprays, cannot be feasibly controlled by local authorities.</p>
        <p>The Federal Clean Air Act of 1970 directed the E.P.A. to set pollution standards and the states to prepare plans within three years to meet those goals.</p>
        <p>In 1973, New York submitted a sweeping air-pollution-control plan involving strict traffic-control measures. Among these were the collection of tolls on the Harlem River and East River bridges and severe restrictions on parking, taxi cruising and daytime deliveries of goods. Though sharply attacked by interest groups, the plan was ultimately affirmed by the United States Supreme Court in 1977. But by that time political support for the most controversial measures had dwindled, and the plan was shelved. Revised Expectations</p>
        <p>Congress meanwhile came to believe that the Clean Air Act's compliance timetable had been overly optimistic. It then amended the legislation to direct states to complete plans to meet existing clean air standards by the end of 1982. But it made an exception for carbon monoxide and ozone, extending the deadline five years, to 1987, if the states had committed themselves to every available strategy. During that time New York and New Jersey filed plans that were approved by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>But at the same time the Natural Resources Defense Council and the Lung Association of New Jersey filed their lawsuits, charging that the existing plans in New York and New Jersey were not being properly carried out, and that the Government was not requiring either state to devise a strategy for meeting the ozone and carbon monoxide standards.</p>
        <p>Connecticut had a weaker anti-pollution plan to begin with, said Mr. Goldstein of the Natural Resources Defense Council, and so there was less opportunity to challenge that state's non-compliance.</p>
        <p>As a result of the lawsuits, the E.P.A. agreed to establish and enforce the new 1991 deadline. By then New York and New Jersey must submit strategies to meet the Federal carbon monoxide and ozone standards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
