<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Town Fights With Neighbors Over Burning of Tons of Tires</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="291113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVOIRS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">STERLING (CONN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RHODE ISLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9113DF936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Town Fights With Neighbors Over Burning of Tons of Tires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>STERLING, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In this poor rural town near the Rhode Island border, officials say they have found a solution to their financial woes that would also help clean up much of the Northeast: a power plant that burns 10 million discarded tires a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In this poor rural town near the Rhode Island border, officials say they have found a solution to their financial woes that would also help clean up much of the Northeast: a power plant that burns 10 million discarded tires a year.</p>
        <p>In this poor rural town near the Rhode Island border, officials say they have found a solution to their financial woes that would also help clean up much of the Northeast: a power plant that burns 10 million discarded tires a year.</p>
        <p>Not only would the plant pay nearly $1 million a year in property taxes, nearly doubling Sterling's tax revenues, officials say, it would also provide a regional solution to one facet of the nation's growing garbage crisis.</p>
        <p>''The plant is the answer to a town that would have died without it,'' said Trenton Wright, Sterling's coordinator of economic development. Worrying About Next Door</p>
        <p>But as Sterling hails the power plant as its economic salvation, many neighboring towns fear the incinerator will draw more truck traffic onto narrow country roads and spew toxic smoke; 10 miles downwind are reservoirs that provide most of Rhode Island's drinking water. Debate rages over the right of one town to shape its own destiny at the expense of its neighbors.</p>
        <p>''Sterling is looking for a quick fix to its economic problems, but they're not worried about what's happening next door,'' said Dr. Jerald Kupperberg, a pediatrician in Foster, R.I., and president of a group of Rhode Islanders who have sued to block the plant.</p>
        <p>Thomas E. Steahr, a professor of demography at the University of Connecticut, said there is a conflict between a town's autonomy ''and its negative consequences in surrounding communities.'' Poorest Town in Wealthiest State</p>
        <p>The conflict here can be seen in different forms throughout the Northeast as local officials struggle to assert local control over development that has a regional impact.</p>
        <p>Near Princeton, N.J., the Route 1 corridor is choking on traffic largely because several towns approved office complexes without considering what their neighbors were building. In New Haven, city officials have fought malls in nearby suburbs, fearing that new shopping centers would lure away what downtown stores remained.</p>
        <p>In Sterling, the poorest town in the wealthiest state, the argument boils down to economic survival. Sterling, with 2,100 people, has a per capita income of $8,710, the lowest in Connecticut. The statewide average is $14,090.</p>
        <p>Unemployment here is 6.9 percent, more than twice the state average of 3.4 percent.</p>
        <p>The Revere Prints Textile Corporation mill, the town's largest employer, burned down in 1980. Sterling now has a couple of general stores, two post offices and six churches. The last gas station closed a few years ago.</p>
        <p>''We need industry,'' said Ed Morneau, a poultry farmer and greenhouse operator here.</p>
        <p>That was the idea in 1985 when Sterling opened a 70-acre industrial park on town land that offered tax incentives to prospective companies. The power plant was the park's centerpiece.</p>
        <p>But not everyone in Sterling embraced the plan. In February 1986, residents voted 423 to 368 to reject the plant. A month later, after campaigning by the plant's supporters, residents approved it in a second vote, 513 to 424. #25 Tractor-Trailers a Day This summer, after nearly three years of tumultuous hearings before the Connecticut Siting Council, a regulatory agency, and the state's Department of Environmental Protection, the plant received its final permits.</p>
        <p>The $100 million plant, to be built over two years by the Oxford Energy Company of Santa Rosa, Calif., would burn about 10 million tires a year. Every day, 25 to 30 tractor-trailers would bring discarded tires to the plant from tire dealers, bus fleets, junkyards and towns within a 200-mile radius.</p>
        <p>The plant would use the tires as fuel to produce 26.5 megawatts of electricity, enough power for 25,000 homes, which would be sold to the Connecticut Light and Power Company.</p>
        <p>Sterling officials say the plant will help the town in several ways. Oxford expects to hire 200 to 250 local workers to build it. ''Our lunch business would be outrageous,'' said Steve Zienowicz, who bought Whitford's General Store here three months ago. #50 Jobs, $1 Million in Taxes The plant has attracted other companies to the industrial park. Mr. Morneau plans to buy the lot next to the incinerator and pipe in excess steam from the complex to heat an expanded greenhouse business.</p>
        <p>Some of the 50 permanent jobs at the plant will go to town residents, but the main contribution by Oxford will be nearly $1 million a year in property taxes.</p>
        <p>First Selectman Robert P. Jordan said the town would probably use the money to reduce property taxes, expand Town Hall and equip its offices with computers, build new ball fields and recreation centers and buy new firefighting equipment.</p>
        <p>''It'll be a great boon to the community,'' said Brian Keith, president of the Sterling Board of Education.</p>
        <p>Some of Sterling's neighbors, however, have serious concerns. In nearby Plainfield, a town of 14,000 that wanted the plant but lost to Sterling, residents now worry about truckloads of tires rumbling through their streets. Hunting, Fishing, Property Values</p>
        <p>''We're concerned that the routes that will be used aren't safe,'' said the First Selectman, Joseph D. Taverna, adding that Plainfield will have to hire two more police officers to deal with the traffic.</p>
        <p>The greatest fears, however, center on the plant's environmental safety. People who hunt and fish express concern that emissions could harm lakes and streams.</p>
        <p>''People are also afraid it will devalue their property,'' said Rachel Allard, a hotel clerk who lives near the border of Plainfield and Sterling.</p>
        <p>Prevailing winds would carry emissions into Rhode Island, where residents fear pollutants could contaminate the Scituate Reservoir, the main source of drinking water for 60 percent of Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>''Connecticut seems to be getting whatever good out of this and we're getting all the pollution,'' said Deborah Stein, a 29-year-old mother in Foster. Complied With All Requirements</p>
        <p>Officials from Sterling and Oxford say that the plant poses no environmental hazard. Connecticut and Rhode Island environmental officials agreed, after analyzing data on the emissions of sulfur dioxide, nitrous oxides and hydrocarbons from a smaller incinerator that Oxford operates in Modesto, Calif.</p>
        <p>The Sterling plant has ''complied with all the state and Federal requirements, and has probably gone beyond those,'' said Mark M. Hultman, an air pollution control engineer with the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>Indeed, before the department issued permits for air emissions, solid waste and water discharge this summer, the agency required Oxford to agree to install $2 million in additional downwind monitoring equipment to protect the reservoir.</p>
        <p>Oxford officials argue that the plant provides an environmentally sound answer to tire disposal. Right now, there are an estimated 2 billion discarded tires in this country. Recycling efforts have been slow and with landfill space around the country shrinking, experts have been searching for a safe and efficient disposal method. Trapping Gray in Gray Smoke</p>
        <p>Using technology introduced at its two-year-old California plant, Oxford plans to install a pollution-control system in the incinerator here that would trap three major pollutants that could be recycled. Steel from belted tires would be sold to scrap metal dealers. Fly ash - the gray in gray smoke, heavily laden with zinc oxide - would be captured by a large vacuum cleaner and sold to zinc smelters.</p>
        <p>Finally, scrubbers to control air emissions would spray lime on the emissions. The lime would combine with the pollutant sulfur to form gypsum, a building material. Furnaces burning at temperatures between 2,000 and 2,500 degrees Fahrenheit would incinerate the tires without any noticeable smoke or odor, state officials said.</p>
        <p>''I don't feel like we're creating problems for our neighbors,'' said Mr. Jordan, who visited Oxford's tire-burning plant in California. ''There's no black smoke. There's no smell. It's clean.''</p>
        <p>Despite assurances from environmental experts, many Connecticut and Rhode Island residents and officials remain wary. ''Tire-burning is an unproven technology,'' said Allan Rydberg, president of the Concerned Citizens of Sterling, a community group that opposes the incinerator and urges more research into tire recycling. 'Only Time Will Tell'</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that we're still going to get a lot of emissions from the plant and only time will tell what impact that will have on the people of Rhode Island,'' said Anna F. Prager, senior policy analyst for the Governor, Edward D. DiPrete. ''It doesn't make Sterling the best neighbor.''</p>
        <p>As a result of the Sterling plant, Rhode Island enacted a state law last summer than prohibits shipping tires across state lines for burning.</p>
        <p>''There are alternate industries -they can't be that desperate,'' said Blanche Fraser, 61, who is selling her house in West Greenwich, R.I., five miles from Sterling, partly out of fears of air pollution.</p>
        <p>Not all of Sterling's neighbors, particularly in eastern Connecticut, think the incinerator is such a bad idea. ''They could put one right next to my house and it wouldn't bother me,'' said Willis G. Maynard, the First Selectman of Voluntown, a town of 2,000 on Sterling's southern border that was an alternative site for the plant.</p>
        <p>Other officials, convinced that the incinerator technology is safe, expressed hope that if the region's poorest economy can improve, the entire area will profit.</p>
        <p>''We all benefit when there's industrial growth,'' said R. Thomas Homan, the town manager of Killingly, just north of Sterling. ''The question becomes, what is acceptable growth?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
