<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cold War's Thaw Might Reach Clear to South Pole</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="309881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D9123CF934A25751C1A96F948260" item-length="1220" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cold War's Thaw Might Reach Clear to South Pole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>McMURDO STATION, Antarctica, Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For the first time in the two centuries since human beings set foot on the continent, Antarctica is poised to become a world center for scientific research, scientists say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For the first time in the two centuries since human beings set foot on the continent, Antarctica is poised to become a world center for scientific research, scientists say.</p>
        <p>For the first time in the two centuries since human beings set foot on the continent, Antarctica is poised to become a world center for scientific research, scientists say.</p>
        <p>But the exploitation of Antarctica's vast scientific potential will be so costly, some here believe, that expenses must be shared among participating nations, particularly the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>In the past, scientists and the men and women supporting them have had to devote so much effort to simply surviving in the world's most hostile environment that resources were drained from research. Much of the research that was conducted centered on the unusual coastal wildlife: penguins, deep-diving seals, freeze-resistant fish and other regional oddities.</p>
        <p>Today, mankind has a dependable foothold on ''The Ice,'' as its inhabitants call Antarctica. The continent is now considered a fit setting for something more than ''survival science.'' And the new political climate in the Soviet Union has prompted some senior American scientists to call for full-scale scientific collaboration here.</p>
        <p>In the last three decades, American and Soviet scientists in Antarctica have often shared information as well as vodka, but the two groups have always maintained a discreet distance. Even after a devastating midwinter fire at a remote Soviet station four years ago, the Russians declined an offer of American help. Preparation for Mars Mission? But Americans here say they believe that attitudes are changing. And successful joint operation of Antarctic bases would be one indication that scientists from the two countries are ready for the cooperative conquest of Mars and other objectives in space, some scientists contend.</p>
        <p>In the last several years Antarctica has been identified as a crucial vantage point for monitoring changes in the atmosphere that could herald warming of the planet, a deadly increase in ultraviolet radiation from the sun or other events likely to affect billions of people.</p>
        <p>Recently, Antarctica has also become a center for investigations of the origin of the universe, the mechanisms of star formation, the behavior of the earth's magnetic field, the history of terrestrial geology, the sources of meteorites, the human threat to oceanic food chains and other questions of high scientific priority.</p>
        <p>Dr. John T. Lynch of the National Science Foundation, science director of the United States South Pole Station, believes that the situation calls for a change in the kind of installation traditionally used for polar research.</p>
        <p>''We need to start planning now for the continent's first truly international station, which we could build at high altitude on the East Antarctic ice sheet,'' Dr. Lynch said.  Pressurized Environment He envisions a new station on the polar plateau at about 82 degrees south latitude and 45 degrees east longitude, about the same distance from the United States' South Pole Station as is the Soviet Union's Vostok Station. The new station would be the highest in Antarctica, ideal for astronomical research requiring as little atmospheric obstruction as possible.</p>
        <p>Because of the altitude and the cold, ''We would probably have to pressurize the entire station,'' he said, ''because you can't work or think very well when you are persistently starved of oxygen. But pressurization would add immensely to the cost, and that's one of many reasons the project should be international.''</p>
        <p>Costs could be reduced by extensive solar heating during the 24-hour-a-day sunlight of the polar summer, he said. Dr. Lynch has demonstrated the idea by modifying a small wooden building at South Pole Station using plastic sheeting and black paint. Without any other form of heating, the structure's interior is hot enough to use as a sauna, even though the outside temperature is far below zero degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Despite the brutal cold at the site of the new station, (probably below minus 120 degrees Fahrenheit in winter), the site would have virtually no precipitation and only mild winds all year long.</p>
        <p>The station's position would place it within overland range, some 800 miles, of both the South Pole, which is supplied by ski-equipped American aircraft, and the Soviet Vostok Station, which is supplied from the Soviet coastal station of Mirnyy by tractor-drawn sledge trains. Another Site Possible</p>
        <p>Soviet-American collaboration might also make possible the opening of a new base at a scientifically important site near the base of the Antarctic Peninsula.</p>
        <p>In 1986 the United States decided to close one of its four year-round Antarctic bases, Siple Station near the base of the Antarctic Peninsula. It was the most remote of the four permanent American stations from any supply line. Despite the station's importance for the study of the magnetosphere, the area in space affected by Earth's magnetic field, supply problems made Siple impractical to maintain.</p>
        <p>''Siple was bleeding us dry,'' said Erick Chiang, senior United States representative in Antarctica, who also serves as the deputy manager of polar operations for the National Science Foundation.</p>
        <p>''Supply flights by our LC-130R Hercules ski transports from McMurdo to Siple had to carry so much fuel that their payloads were severely limited,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But a new station at or near Siple operated jointly by Soviet and American scientists might solve the problem, Mr. Chiang said. Moscow's Attitude Is Unknown</p>
        <p>''The Russians could supply it relatively easily from their Russkaya Station on the Sulzberger Coast,'' he said. ''Together, we could significantly advance scientific understanding of the magnetosphere.''</p>
        <p>Although two American scientists are stationed as visitors at Vostok Station this year, officials here do not know whether Moscow is ready to collaborate in the joint operation of a new station. Officials at the Soviet Embassy in Washington had no comment on the proposal for joint research in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Lynch and others believe that the proposal by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev to join the United States in a mission to Mars is a hopeful sign.</p>
        <p>''Antarctica has much in common with Mars,'' Dr. Lynch said, ''and this would be a logical place for Soviet-American collaboration in space missions to start.''</p>
        <p>It seems doubtful that all 39 of the nations subscribing to the Antarctic Treaty of 1959 would agree to collaborate in research. One problem is that six nations - Argentina, Australia, Britain, Chile, France and New Zealand -lay claim to large and overlapping parts of the continent. New Zealander Casts Doubt</p>
        <p>Although these claims are in abeyance at least until the treaty comes up for renegotiation in 1991, none of the six have renounced claims. Joint operation of an Antarctic station may therefore prove diplomatically undesirable for them.</p>
        <p>At New Zealand's Scott Base two miles from here, David Geddes, his country's senior representative in Antarctica, discounted the possibility of founding an international station in the immediate future.</p>
        <p>''Coordinating the staffing of such a station would be difficult,'' he said, ''and before we could get that far, the Antarctic Treaty nations would have to organize a permanent secretariat. But New Zealand feels that we should have such a secretariat, whether or not an international station came of it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
