<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MEXICAN-U.S. PACT REACHED ON TRADE AND INVESTMENTS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="288215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEXICO-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEXTILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STEEL AND IRON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO CITY (MEX)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALINAS DE GORTARI, CARLOS (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Mexico City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDA103FF937A35753C1A96F948260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MEXICAN-U.S. PACT REACHED ON TRADE AND INVESTMENTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the latest sign of closer ties between the United States and Mexico, Presidents Bush and Carlos Salinas de Gortari signed an agreement today intended to enlarge trade and investment between the two nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the latest sign of closer ties between the United States and Mexico, Presidents Bush and Carlos Salinas de Gortari signed an agreement today intended to enlarge trade and investment between the two nations.</p>
        <p>In the latest sign of closer ties between the United States and Mexico, Presidents Bush and Carlos Salinas de Gortari signed an agreement today intended to enlarge trade and investment between the two nations.</p>
        <p>The accord, the highlight of a five-day visit here by Mr. Salinas, is the broadest economic agreement ever reached by the two countries.</p>
        <p>At a White House ceremony, President Bush spoke of benefits for ''both sides of our border'' and Mr. Salinas said the initiative ''opens up additional sources of employment in Mexico for Mexicans.'' 'Concrete Results' Cited</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas, who arrived in the United States on Sunday for his second visit since he took office in December, said the trade accord and an environmental agreement signed during the same ceremony showed that the two countries' friendship ''leads to concrete results.''</p>
        <p>The environmental accord calls for the Governments to deal with air and other pollution problems in Mexico City and in urban areas at the border.</p>
        <p>Mexico is the third-largest market for American goods, after Canada and Japan, while Mexico sends about three-quarters of its exports to the United States. Trade between the two countries totaled $44 billion last year. Rebuffed Until Recently</p>
        <p>For years the United States had sought closer trade and consultative links with Mexico, but until recently had been rebuffed by Mexico's political leadership, which was entrenched in policies of trade nationalism.</p>
        <p>Under President Salinas and his predecessor, Miguel de la Madrid, Mexico slowly began developing policies of greater openness in trade and investment. Mr. Salinas, who has a doctorate in political economy from Harvard, served as the minister of budget and planning in the de la Madrid administration.</p>
        <p>The first sign of the shift was Mexico's signature in August 1986 on the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the world's free-trade charter, to which nearly 100 other nations subscribe. Since then Mexico has announced a number of measures to cut tariffs and to dismantle other trade controls. Earlier this year, it removed large parts of foreign investment from official oversight by declaring that acquisitions under $100 million would not need preliminary approval.</p>
        <p>Under the new trade and investment agreement, Mexico and the United States are to decide by November on specific industrial sectors that could benefit from lower tariffs. These might include autos and auto parts, telecommunications, petrochemicals, computers and related equipment and processed foods, an American official said.</p>
        <p>By July, negotiators are to complete a first round of talks on such provisions. Beneficiary of Brady Plan</p>
        <p>In the American view, Mexico is not only more cooperative in trade matters, it is also a model of how a developing country can through market-oriented policies begin to ease its foreign debt burden.</p>
        <p>Its programs to convert state-owned companies to private ownership and its deregulatory policies and lower tariffs have made it a principal beneficiary of a debt-slashing plan put forward by Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to continued progress and additional proof of how Mexico and the United States can work together toward common ends, toward positive results,'' Mr. Bush told his guest today. On Sunday, Mr. Salinas was his guest at an informal dinner at Camp David. No Free-Trade Pact Seen</p>
        <p>Still, American officials said they did not expect the trade agreement, formally known as the Understanding Between the Government of the United Mexican States and the Government of the United States of America Regarding Trade and Investment Facilitation Talks, to produce anything so far reaching as the free-trade agreement with Canada signed last year.</p>
        <p>''What we have is a series of negotiations in specific product sectors, which, of course, could develop their own momentum, but any free-trade agreement between the two countries is a long way off, if ever,'' an Administration trade official commented.</p>
        <p>A free-trade agreement might well arouse more opposition in both countries than the accord with Canada. In Mexico distrust of the United States has been pronounced over the years, and American labor and business are both sensitive to competition arising from cheap Mexican labor. A 'Significant Evolution'</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, today's agreement, which broadens a 1987 accord providing for consultative talks on trade disputes, is a ''significant evolution'' in the two countries' trading relationship, American officials said.</p>
        <p>The Governments also reached agreements today on steel and textiles and declared that their negotiators had found ''an improved and constructive atmosphere on matters concerning the protection of intellectual property rights to promote technological innovation and investment in Mexico.'' Protection for patents, copyrights and other intellectual property in Mexico has been a matter of dispute between the two nations for many years.</p>
        <p>On steel, Mexico signed an agreement to limit its shipments to the United States at an undisclosed level over the next two and a half years and to work toward eliminating trade-distorting practices in the sector.</p>
        <p>Mexico is one of 29 countries that have reached new restraint agreements with the United States. Although no specifics of the Mexican pact were available, it was expected that Mexico would be permitted to ship more steel here than it has under its past quotas.</p>
        <p>On textiles, the United States committed itself to ''review and improve'' an import restraint agreement by the two nations. According to a joint communique, the textile agreement provides for ''continued expansion of trade in textiles and apparel in an orderly and nondisruptive manner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
