<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nozzles for Cutting Pollution Arrive at Jersey Gas Stations</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="212150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D9173CF934A35752C0A96F948260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nozzles for Cutting Pollution Arrive at Jersey Gas Stations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>PARAMUS, N.J., Jan. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This week was the first that New Jersey's largest gasoline stations were required to do their part to reduce air pollution by using pump nozzles designed to trap gasoline vapors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This week was the first that New Jersey's largest gasoline stations were required to do their part to reduce air pollution by using pump nozzles designed to trap gasoline vapors.</p>
        <p>This week was the first that New Jersey's largest gasoline stations were required to do their part to reduce air pollution by using pump nozzles designed to trap gasoline vapors.</p>
        <p>Because New Jersey does not permit self-service stations, many motorists here in Bergen County and elsewhere may not have noticed the new nozzles that have been installed at many stations. The nozzle, with accordion-like necks and rubber collars, fits tightly over a car's gasoline-intake pipe. There it traps the vapor as gasoline is pumped and returns it through a suction tube to underground storage tanks.</p>
        <p>''I would say the majority of people have heard of vapor recovery, but not many know much about it,'' said Art Hanley, the manager at Northview Exxon on Route 17 here. Price Increase Foreseen</p>
        <p>Customers, however, are likely to soon see the cost of installing and maintaining the pumps reflected at the pumps; environmental and industry officials and station managers predict prices will rise one to two cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>Similar vapor-catching equipment has been in use in Los Angeles, San Francisco, Washington D.C. and on Long Island. But New Jersey is the only state that has ordered that the equipment be used statewide, said Jorge Berkowitz, the director of the Division of Environmental Quality of the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>''In New Jersey, we have four different air-quality regions, and because each of these regions has shown ozone levels that are unacceptable and violate Federal standards, we have required vapor recovery throughout the state,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The new regulation, issued in late 1987, ordered 2,500 service stations to install the vapor-recovery system by Dec. 30, 1988. The stations each pump an average of 40,000 gallons of gasoline or more a month.</p>
        <p>As of Thursday, about 90 percent of the stations were believed to have complied. That figure was based on the number of installation permits the department granted and on inspections by about 150 state and local officials, Mr. Berkowitz said. Smaller Stations Can Wait</p>
        <p>Another 2,000 stations that pump an average of 10,000 to 40,000 gallons a month have until Dec. 30, 1989, to install the system.</p>
        <p>Stations that pump under 10,000 gallons a month are exempt from the regulation, Mr. Berkowitz said.</p>
        <p>Under intense sunlight, gasoline vapors combine with nitrogen oxides to form ozone, which can cause severe respiratory distress, Mr. Berkowitz said.</p>
        <p>For 40 days last summer, the state exceeded Federal ozone standards of .12 parts per million, reaching as high as .24, he said. About 70 regions in the country now exceed Federal standards, he said.</p>
        <p>Once the vapor-recovery system is in effect throughout New Jersey, it will eliminate 36 tons of hydrocarbons a day that would have escaped into the atmosphere, Mr. Berkowitz said.</p>
        <p>Although other anti-pollution measures must also be taken by the state, the vapor-recovery system will bring New Jersey closer to compliance with Federal standards, he said. He predicted that because of New Jersey's system, air in Connecticut and New York will also be cleaner. The problem, he said, is a regional one that states have only begun to address. Many Dealers Don't Like It</p>
        <p>But many station operators question the system's efficiency and cost, said Jerry Ferrara, the executive director of the New Jersey Gasoline Retailers Association, a trade group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrara said he believed that the proportion of dealers who had not complied with the order was closer to 25 percent, not 10 percent, as Mr. Berkowitz estimated. Mr. Ferrara said many independent dealers had had trouble getting the nozzles delivered because of a rush of orders by other dealers trying to comply with the regulation. And some had been unable to get contractors lay extra piping needed for vapor recovery.</p>
        <p>Many stations will not be able to comply for at least three months, Mr. Ferrara said. And even with state-approved extensions, those stations that tried to act in good faith in making the installation but failed to do so must still pay the state one or two cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>Stations that shirked compliance face up to $10,000 a day in fines. Costs of Maintenance</p>
        <p>The state estimates that the equipment and its installation will cost gas stations $10,000 to $15,000. But Mr. Ferrara said an estimate of up to $22,000 is more realistic. And he estimated that the annual cost of maintenance will be $2,000 to $3,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrara said that many stations, especially the independent smaller ones, will have difficulty coping economically and have to pass on the cost to consumers. For most, two cents a gallon is the net profit.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Quirk, whose Quirk's Gulf Service Station has operated in the heart of Teaneck since 1931 and pumps under 10,000 gallons a month, said that if he were forced to install the costly new equipment, he might have to shut down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanley, the manager of the Paramus Exxon station, said the new equipment was not as cumbersome as he feared, although the nozzle did not fit some cars. Other operators said the nozzle broke and cracked easily and cost up to $300 to replace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
