<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carbon Monoxide Found Harmful at Low Levels</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="303825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D61F3AF937A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carbon Monoxide Found Harmful at Low Levels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Nov. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Levels of carbon monoxide considered safe by Federal air quality standards can create a potentially dangerous oxygen shortage in the hearts of people with coronary artery disease, a study has shown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Levels of carbon monoxide considered safe by Federal air quality standards can create a potentially dangerous oxygen shortage in the hearts of people with coronary artery disease, a study has shown.</p>
        <p>Levels of carbon monoxide considered safe by Federal air quality standards can create a potentially dangerous oxygen shortage in the hearts of people with coronary artery disease, a study has shown.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide was found to affect people with heart disease when it was at a level equal to that in a room full of cigarette smokers.</p>
        <p>''These are definitely adverse health effects,'' said Dr. Thomas E. Dahms of St. Louis University School of Medicine, who took part in the study.</p>
        <p>The study, published today in The New England Journal of Medicine, found a decrease in the amount of work that people with heart disease could perform when their carboxyhemoglobin levels - the combination of carbon monoxide and hemoglobin - reached 2 percent.</p>
        <p>Hemoglobin ordinarily combines with oxygen and carries it throughout the body. But carbon monoxide binds with hemoglobin even more tightly than oxygen does. So when people breathe carbon monoxide, it cuts down the amount of oxygen in their blood, and high doses are fatal.</p>
        <p>The health consequences of very low levels, however, have been less clear. In general, standards set by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency allow enough carbon monoxide in the air to take up 2 percent of the blood's hemoglobin. 'A Documented Effect'</p>
        <p>''What we have shown with this paper is that it's beyond any doubt that there is a documented effect at 2 percent, which frankly was a surprise to us,'' Dr. Dahms said. ''It's such a small amount that one would not think you could see that kind of change.''</p>
        <p>Federal health surveys have found that 5 to 10 percent of all non-smoking Americans have this much carboxyhemoglobin in their blood at any time. The two chief sources of carbon monoxide in the air are cigarette smoke and engine fumes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dahms said a nonsmoker in a closed room with 20 smokers would breathe enough carbon monoxide to have about a 2 percent carboxyhemoglobin level. Someone who smokes a pack of cigarettes a day has levels from 4 to 8 percent.</p>
        <p>The study was financed by the Environmental Protection Agency and the automobile industry.</p>
        <p>In an accompanying editorial in the journal, Dr. Edward M. Dwyer Jr. and Dr. Gerard M. Turino of St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center in New York said it is difficult to set any safe level of carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>''The safest level would be the lowest level achievable in the atmosphere,'' they wrote.</p>
        <p>The study was performed on 63 men with coronary artery disease. They exercised on a treadmill while breathing ordinary air or air that increased their carboxyhemoglobin levels to 2 percent or 4 percent.</p>
        <p>At 2 percent carbon monoxide levels, they could do 5 percent less exercise before the heart showed signs of oxygen deprivation and at 4 percent levels they could do 12 percent less exercise. They also developed chest pain sooner with increasing levels of carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>As people exercise, their hearts demand more oxygen. In people with healthy hearts, their arteries can expand to deliver more oxygen-rich blood and small amounts of carbon monoxide have little effect. But when people have heart disease, clogged arteries do not expand properly. Carbon monoxide can make an important difference by lowering the oxygen load of the blood that gets through.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
