<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Tactics Emerge In Struggle Against Smog</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="225200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATALYTIC CONVERTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D81339F932A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="2057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Tactics Emerge In Struggle Against Smog</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER two decades of progress, the campaign to control smog from cars and trucks is now losing ground because of an enormous increase in the number of vehicles on the road. Experts believe that new anti-pollution strategies may be needed to hold hazardous exhaust emissions in check.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER two decades of progress, the campaign to control smog from cars and trucks is now losing ground because of an enormous increase in the number of vehicles on the road. Experts believe that new anti-pollution strategies may be needed to hold hazardous exhaust emissions in check.</p>
        <p>AFTER two decades of progress, the campaign to control smog from cars and trucks is now losing ground because of an enormous increase in the number of vehicles on the road. Experts believe that new anti-pollution strategies may be needed to hold hazardous exhaust emissions in check.</p>
        <p>Engineers are already conducting research on small demonstration projects to improve catalytic converters, to prevent gasoline vapors from escaping into the air at the pump, to make engines more efficient, and to develop alternative fuels that are cleaner than gasoline and diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>But even these measures may not be enough. Some experts believe that the internal combustion engine must eventually be replaced by cleaner electric power if air pollution is to be brought under permanent control.</p>
        <p>Technical innovations in the United States in the past two decades have substantially reduced some of the pollutants to which city-dwellers are exposed. Since 1970, when the Clean Air Act was passed, emissions of hydrocarbons and carbon monoxide from the average car have been lowered by 90 percent, and nitrogen oxides by 75 percent. The chief tools in controlling automobile emissions have been the catalytic converter, which transforms dangerous gases into less harmful ones, improved engine designs and reduction of the lead content in gasoline.</p>
        <p>But Federal analysts say this progress is being offset by the sheer numbers of cars, trucks and buses added to America's roads each year.</p>
        <p>According to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, the number of motor vehicles in the United States rose to 183 million in 1988 from 147 million in 1977, an increase of about 25 percent. The number of trucks increased 40 percent in this period to a total of 41 million, and the diesel engines of heavy trucks produce particularly hazardous exhaust gases.</p>
        <p>During the past summer, street-level ozone, a measure of the severity of automotive smog, increased to nearly double its 1987 level in many Eastern states and reached unacceptable levels in Los Angeles about half the year. Part of the increase is believed to have resulted from the summer's unusual heat and dryness, but environmental experts agree that America's growing fleet of vehicles is making the smog problem worse each year.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council, a Washington-based conservation lobby, predicts that unless current trends are reversed, the quality of city air will worsen substantially in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Richard Wilson, director of the Environmental Protection Agency's National Vehicle Emissions Program, said in an interview: ''If we hadn't imposed emission controls, automotive pollution would have increased substantially every year. But now, because so many more vehicles are covering so many more miles each year, we're finding that we have to work real hard just to keep the pollution level where it is.''</p>
        <p>By far the most intractable problem created by automotive emissions is photochemical smog, a hazy mixture of microscopic droplets, solid particles and gases. Typically, smog may contain more than 100 different chemical compounds, many of them irritant, toxic or carcinogenic. The brownish photochemical smog that hangs over Los Angeles and many other cities is created primarily by motor vehicles. Vapor From Spilled Fuel</p>
        <p>Photochemical smog arises from three ingredients, hydrocarbons, nitrogen oxides and sunlight.</p>
        <p>Hydrocarbons - chains of carbon atoms linked with each other and with hydrogen atoms - are present in engine exhaust gases created by the incomplete burning of fuel. Gasoline and diesel fuel themselves consist of mixtures of hydrocarbons, and the vapor from spilled fuel is a major contributor to smog.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen oxides are created by any high-temperature combustion process involving air. The two main components of air, nitrogen and oxygen, combine chemically at high temperatures to form a variety of nitrogen oxides, which are themselves pollutants.</p>
        <p>When nitrogen oxides absorb energy from sunlight, some split apart to create individual atoms of oxygen that instantly recombine into molecules of ozone, a toxic form of oxygen consisting of three oxygen atoms instead of the usual two. Ozone and the other products of photochemical processes are highly reactive and they combine with hydrocarbons to form the family of compounds that make up smog. As long as sunlight pumps energy into a mixture of hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides, smog continues to form. The process stops at sunset, but the ingredients may remain to resume the reaction the following morning.</p>
        <p>The gains in smog reduction so far have been achieved primarily with catalytic converters, which remove hydrocarbons and, to a lesser extent, nitrogen oxides from automobile exhausts.</p>
        <p>A catalytic converter is essentially a cylinder full of ceramic beads, through which exhaust gas from the engine is ducted. The beads are coated with thin films of platinum and two other metals chemically similar to platinum - palladium and rhodium. The metals do not participate in exhaust-cleansing reactions themselves. Instead, they gather molecules of exhaust pollutants together with oxygen molecules from the air and induce them to react to form harmless gases. Improving Converters' Efficiency</p>
        <p>Last December, the Ford Motor Company announced that it had developed a catalytic converter that does not contain platinum. Platinum, used mainly as a catalyst and in jewelry, costs up to $600 an ounce and is produced chiefly by South Africa. A Ford spokesman declined to disclose any details of the new platinum-free catalyst, except to say that it would be installed on some of the company's 1989 cars. Ford has not disclosed how effective the new catalyst is compared to platinum, but since it will be installed on production cars, it evidently meets Federal standards. Proprietary catalysts, including those used to control exhaust emissions, are among the most closely guarded of industrial secrets, but experts say new developments are likely to improve the efficiency of converters still further by adjusting mixtures of catalytic metals and refining the shapes of the pellets on which the metals are coated.</p>
        <p>Another proven method for reducing automotive pollutants is the use of special sensors and a computer to monitor and control a car's fuel efficiency and exhaust emissions. American automobile manufacturers have also redesigned engines to squeeze fuel and air mixtures more tightly and to ignite them more more efficiently. Engineers at automobile companies throughout the world continue to strive for these objectives.</p>
        <p>As the federally mandated phase-out of leaded gasoline has brought down the permitted level of tetraethyl lead in gasoline to one-tenth of a gram per gallon, the sale of gasoline containing any lead has declined sharply. At the same time petroleum refiners have added more light hydrocarbon components to their gasoline mixtures to make up for the loss of lead as an anti-knock additive. The use of a higher proportion of light hydrocarbons, which saves the refiners money, has made the gasoline sold in some parts of the United States more volatile; that is, it evaporates more readily. Adding to Hydrocarbon Burden</p>
        <p>Particularly during the hot weather of summer, vapor evaporated from volatile gasoline tends to escape from a car's tank and fuel injection system, adding to the hydrocarbon burden of the atmosphere and contributing to smog. Some of the vapor is captured by canisters of charcoal installed in the fuel systems of all American automobiles, but according to Mr. Wilson of the E.P.A., the more volatile fuel sometimes produces enough vapor to saturate the charcoal and escape.</p>
        <p>''We have proposed an E.P.A. regulation that would limit the volatility of gasoline sold during the summer months,'' he said, ''and we're in the process of putting together the final rules.''</p>
        <p>In another attack on the volatility problem, filling stations in California and the District of Columbia are now required to dispense gasoline from pressurized pumps that prevent gasoline vapor from escaping into the atmosphere. The hose tips of these pumps make a tight seal with an automobile's filling pipe, and vapor is returned to the filling station's underground tank. Several other states, including New York and New Jersey, are preparing to impose similar regulations.</p>
        <p>Federal officials, environmental lobbyists and automotive engineers agree that alternative fuels could eventually reduce automotive pollutants significantly.</p>
        <p>The two fuels under most active investigation are compressed natural gas and methanol, or wood alcohol. Experts agree that both produce significantly cleaner exhaust gases than either gasoline or diesel fuel. Riding on Methanol</p>
        <p>The Detroit Diesel Corporation is manufacturing diesel-type engines modified to run on pure methanol. Six experimental engines have been installed in public buses operated by the Triboro Coach Corporation in Queens.</p>
        <p>Stephen J. Eagar, president of Triboro Coach, said in an interview that a tank of methanol powers a bus only half as far as would an equal volume of conventional diesel fuel. Aside from that, he said, the new fuel has posed no major problems. ''Our company is subsidized by the city, so we don't have to consider the economics of methanol fuel in this test,'' he said. ''But on the whole, I'd say it's easier to handle than gasoline, and it certainly burns cleanly. I doubt if many of our passengers realize they're riding on methanol fuel.''</p>
        <p>Stanley P. Miller, manager of the methanol project at Detroit Diesel, said methanol engines from his company now power 14 experimental buses in New York, California and Canada, and that by April, 51 methanol buses will be on the road.</p>
        <p>Also, General Motors and Ford have developed automotive engines for methanol and natural gas. Although both fuels remain experimental, about 300,000 vehicles are operating on natural gas engines in New Zealand, Italy, Canada and the United States.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn Union Gas Company, which promotes the development of natural gas as an automotive fuel, is already using it in vehicles in New York City. ''More than 200 of our corporate sedans, vans and trucks are modified to run on either natural gas or gasoline,'' a spokesman said. ''The driver just has to throw a switch on the dashboard to change from one fuel to the other.''</p>
        <p>Last July, two buses specifically built to run on compressed natural gas began operating in Brooklyn for the Command Bus Company. At a commissioning ceremony, Mayor Edward I. Koch held a white handkerchief over the tailpipe of one of the buses and showed that exhaust passing through the cloth left no stain. Link to Oil Prices</p>
        <p>Robert H. Gray, an official of the Brooklyn Union Gas Company, said the two new natural gas buses in New York will conform with stringent new emission regulations the E.P.A. plans to issue in 1991. ''No diesel bus now on the roads will meet those standards,'' he said. ''The trick now will be to get the auto industry to mass produce natural-gas vehicles.''</p>
        <p>Automotive industry officials, including Mr. Miller of Detroit Diesel, believe that alternative fuels will never replace conventional fuels until the depressed global price of petroleum rises to several times its present level. ''Obviously we're designing for the future, when petroleum shortages and other factors begin to make alternative fuels economically attractive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But alternative fuels pose some environmental problems of their own.</p>
        <p>John H. Seinfeld, a chemical engineer at the California Institute of Technology who specializes in the problem of urban smog, says that methanol exhaust gases produce only between 20 percent and 33 percent of the ozone that would be created by an equivalent amount of conventional fuel. But, he said, methanol exhaust contains formaldehyde, a carcinogen that must be removed by a catalytic converter.</p>
        <p>William L. Chameides, a geophysicist at the Georgia Institute of Technology who studies smog formation, believes that the problem can never be solved as long as internal combustion engines dominate the roads.</p>
        <p>''In the long run I believe we must get away from all forms of combustion and perhaps go to electric vehicles,'' he said. ''Every other approach is just a stopgap remedy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
