<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Mania: Meat Pudding</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FARE OF THE COUNTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIELY, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB163BF932A25751C0A966958260" item-length="1372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Mania: Meat Pudding</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH RIELY; ELIZABETH RIELY, who recently spent a year in England, is the author of ''The Chef's Companion: A Concise Dictionary of Culinary Terms'' (Van Nostrand Reinhold).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIELY, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''THERE'S nothing I enjoy more than a good go at a steak-and-kidney pudding in the open air,'' says a character in ''The Magic Pudding,'' Norman Lindsay's children's book that has been a best seller in Britain since it was first published in Australia in 1918. Whether outdoors or in, upstairs or down, new-fangled or old-fashioned, most</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''THERE'S nothing I enjoy more than a good go at a steak-and-kidney pudding in the open air,'' says a character in ''The Magic Pudding,'' Norman Lindsay's children's book that has been a best seller in Britain since it was first published in Australia in 1918. Whether outdoors or in, upstairs or down, new-fangled or old-fashioned, most</p>
        <p>''THERE'S nothing I enjoy more than a good go at a steak-and-kidney pudding in the open air,'' says a character in ''The Magic Pudding,'' Norman Lindsay's children's book that has been a best seller in Britain since it was first published in Australia in 1918. Whether outdoors or in, upstairs or down, new-fangled or old-fashioned, most British people share that sentiment.</p>
        <p>You can find the dish year-round in school lunches and on dinner tables, at gentlemen's clubs and in your local public house. Even on the hottest day of last summer's heat wave you could buy the makings - cubed beef and ox kidney, with shredded suet for the crust - packaged together on the shelf of an ordinary supermarket. The steak and kidney pudding properly prepared is a quintessentially English dish. Despite foreigners' disdain, it is as much an exponent of its own national cuisine as boeuf Bourguignon is of the French.</p>
        <p>Savory puddings have been around a long time. For many centuries meat trimmings, leftovers and suet have been mixed with crumbs and packed in casing to make a sausage. According to C. Anne Wilson's ''Food and Drink in Britain'' (Constable), after the Norman conquest the English used the word pudding, from the French boudin, meaning sausage. Inevitably, the bother of cleaning casings led to other containers, especially pastry. In the Middle Ages rye flour was often used for the coffin, or crust, according to Barbara Ketcham Wheaton's ''Savoring the Past'' (University of Pennsylvania Press), since it was strong enough to serve as a container and, indestructible, might reappear at meals over several weeks. By the 17th century the English favored cooking pudding in a cloth bag submerged in or steamed over a cauldron of boiling liquid before turning the pudding out for serving.</p>
        <p>The surprise is to learn how recently the steak and kidney combination has become a part of the English canon. According to Jane Grigson's ''Observer Guide to British Cookery'' (Michael Joseph), the classic first appeared in print in the recipes of Isabella Beeton for her husband's ''Englishwoman's Domestic Magazine,'' gathered in 1861 into her ''Book of Household Management.'' Mrs. Beeton's recipe was contributed ''by a Sussex lady, in which county the inhabitants are noted for their savoury puddings,'' and it calls for ''tender rump steak'' that has been well aged, as all too little English beef is today.</p>
        <p>This good quality beef - not just lesser leftover bits - is cut into one-inch squares and laid on the suet and flour crust with a few pieces of kidney. ''Some add a little flour to thicken the gravy,'' Mrs. Beeton adds, ''but it is not necessary.'' After the top crust is pressed over the first, so ''that the gravy may not escape,'' the pudding is tied up in a flour-sealed cloth and boiled for at least four hours.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beeton said that the pudding may be very much enriched by adding a few oysters or mushrooms. For modern cooks, mushrooms are the more likely addition, especially where households are managed with an eye to economy. As for accompaniment, serve leeks or cabbage or other green winter vegetable, said Olivia Bell, who grew up in the north. ''Some people would have potatoes with it, but for that you'd need to go on a 10-mile hike.''</p>
        <p>''You can use any vegetable, really, potato, cabbage, whatever's going,'' said Amy Dore, a woman who grew up in a large family in Oxfordshire. ''We lived on it. It's warming and filling, just the thing for a winter evening,'' she commented. Mrs. Dore's grandmother would cook cabbage and potatoes with bacon to go with the pudding and give the liquor to the pigs afterward. She agreed with Mrs. Beeton that you mustn't cook the meat first, so that you have all the juices. ''That's the old-fashioned way.''</p>
        <p>Many people lament the recent decline of boiled or steamed puddings, although steak and kidney pies with factory-produced filling - wrapped in single portions in cellophane and guaranteed to sink to the bottom of your stomach - are easy enough to find. (The pie, as opposed to pudding, is baked in a shallow pie dish with a flaky pastry; the meat filling and gravy must be made ahead.) Smaller families, working women and cholesterol counts have all taken their toll. Young British chefs rediscovering their culinary heritage find the classic pudding too uncompromising to update or reinterpret in some nouvelle fashion. The best place to find real steak and kidney pudding is where it always was, in a few venerable restaurants that ignore new styles at the same time that they welcome natives and tourists alike.</p>
        <p>Simpson's-in-the-Strand, in London, with the atmosphere of a private men's club, is just such a place: dark wood, starched white napery, and gleaming silver. Those who can enjoy Simpson's traditional surroundings can relish the steak and kidney pudding offered with mushrooms throughout the year and with oysters in winter. The executive chef, Adam Sherif, a Cypriot who has lived in England for 36 years and inherited his recipe when he came to Simpson's 13 years ago, serves about 50 portions a day in summer, perhaps twice as many in winter. He insists on using veal suet rather than beef because it is ''much cleaner.''</p>
        <p>Fortnum &amp; Mason, the luxurious department store on Piccadilly, is another favorite of tourists, but while Americans may stay downstairs in the Fountain for fanciful ice cream concoctions, natives are more likely to ascend to the third-floor restaurant for smoked Scotch salmon, roast beef with Yorkshire pudding, and steak and kidney pudding regardless of the season. The old Cheshire Cheese on Fleet Street in the City, where Dr. Johnson met with Boswell and Goldsmith, is renowned for its rendition of the pudding. Even in the summer a pub near Lord's Cricket Ground, headquarters of the English national game, offers steak and kidney during midday breaks in matches that routinely last several days at a time.</p>
        <p>''I believe that cuisine developed with the climate,'' said Michel Rosso, until recently general manager of the Copper Inn at Pangbourne-on-Thames, near Reading, which offers the classic during England's bone-chilling raw weather. ''The steak and kidney pudding - what better thing to have on a cold winter day?'' He explained that, in his small restaurant, they tried ''to move forward a little bit,'' but the steak and kidney pudding was traditional. ''I like it very much myself,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Rules, in London, established in 1798, specializes in British food and offers steak and kidney as both pie and pudding. The head chef, Graham Beauchamp, said that, despite the movement to lighter traditional food, you can't do it with steak and kidney. ''We make it just the way we always have,'' with prime Angus beef, field mushrooms, suet paste, but oysters only once a year. They make the pudding with oysters for about two weeks at Christmas to celebrate their purchase of the carcass of the champion of Smithfield meat market.</p>
        <p>''Usually it's the men who go for the puddings, because of the school mums,'' said Mr. Beauchamp, an Englishman himself. ''We give them what they got at public schools. It's surprising, some people have steak and kidney pudding in summer and then follow it with treacle pudding,'' he observed. ''Suet followed by suet.''</p>
        <p>Pudding followed by pudding. In ''The Magic Pudding'' all the characters had slices of steak and kidney, and ''after that they had boiled jam roll and apple dumpling as the fancy took them,'' wrote Norman Lindsay, ''for if you wanted a change of food from the Puddin', all you had to do was to whistle twice and turn the basin round.''</p>
        <p>IF YOU HUNGER</p>
        <p>The following restaurants usually serve steak and kidney pudding, though from time to time they may offer steak and kidney pie instead of, or in addition to, it.</p>
        <p>The Cheshire Cheese (145 Fleet Street, London EC4; telephone 353-6170). Dinner for two with wine and service about $42. Fortnum &amp; Mason (Piccadilly, London W1; 734-8040). $70. Rules (35 Maiden Lane, near Covent Garden, London WC2; 836-5314). $92.</p>
        <p>Simpson's-in-the-Strand (100 The Strand, London WC2; 836-9112). $92.</p>
        <p>The Copper Inn (Church Road, Pangbourne-on-Thames, Berkshire, near Reading; 84-2244). $92.</p>
        <p>- E. R.</p>
        <p>FARE OF THE COUNTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
