<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Christmas Cold In Many Western Cities</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D7173BF935A15751C1A966958260" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Christmas Cold In Many Western Cities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the coldest Christmas on record in many cities across the West, and the week-old cold wave that has caused millions in damage to California produce also nipped some of the flowers needed for the Rose Bowl parade.</p>
        <p>Flood victims in Tennessee began returning home to clean up the damage, but some in Alabama and Mississippi were still kept out of their homes by high water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the coldest Christmas on record in many cities across the West, and the week-old cold wave that has caused millions in damage to California produce also nipped some of the flowers needed for the Rose Bowl parade.</p>
        <p>Flood victims in Tennessee began returning home to clean up the damage, but some in Alabama and Mississippi were still kept out of their homes by high water.</p>
        <p>Weather-related deaths since Dec. 18 have risen to 81.</p>
        <p>The cold also began to take a toll on air quality as people turned to wood-burning stoves and fireplaces for heat. Air in Oregon's Eugene-Springfield area was rated unhealthful yesterday morning because of particulates. Wood smoke is a major source of such pollution.</p>
        <p>Albuquerque, N.M., had its coldest Christmas on record at 1 degree. Eugene, Ore., had a record low of 15, the seventh day in a row that the city's morning low matched or set a record. Yesterday's low of 19 in Portland, Ore., was the fourth record low in five days. Gallup, N.M., awoke to 25 below zero. Temperatures across North Dakota were 10 to 20 below, and wind blowing at 10 to 20 miles an hour made it feel like more than 40 below. The Balmy 50's in Texas</p>
        <p>But Texas warmed to seasonal normals on Christmas Day, with temperatures in southern sections reaching the 50's for the first time since the cold wave began there on Friday. Arizona also warmed up slightly, with lows of 33 in Phoenix and 35 in Yuma.</p>
        <p>A slight warming trend is predicted for the rest of the week in California, but agricultural officials said it was too late for the damaged crops.</p>
        <p>In Tulare County, where most of California's navel oranges are grown, Agricultural Commissioner Lenord Craft estimated a $200 million loss to this year's harvest.</p>
        <p>Claire Peters, a spokeswoman for the cooperative Sunkist Growers Inc., said initial estimates show 50 percent of the citrus crop may be damaged. Some of it may be salvaged for juice, she said.</p>
        <p>Growers said fruit on trees in the southern San Joaquin Valley was a total loss, and trees three years old or younger are themselves probably damaged, the National Weather Service reported.</p>
        <p>Arizona's $70 million citrus crop may have escaped the cold wave with little damage, several citrus experts said. Parade Flowers in Peril</p>
        <p>The cold also threatened some of the flower-covered floats for the Tournament of Roses parade, in Pasadena on New Year's Day.</p>
        <p>Rick Chapman's company is building 11 of the floats, and he said his workers faced two problems: the cold damaged flower crops in California, and fresh flowers from Florida and South America were on trucks somewhere east of California, delayed by snow and icy roads.</p>
        <p>Some 12,000 people in the Santa Cruz Mountains south of San Francisco were without water, partly because frozen pipes burst and partly because of some people's efforts to prevent them from bursting.</p>
        <p>Fred Nitz, the water district president, said many customers let their taps trickle to prevent freezeup, but this drained 900 gallons of water a minute from the system.</p>
        <p>Plumbers in Albuquerque stopped taking house calls to thaw frozen pipes on Monday. "It's been awful," said Jules Appelman of Academy Plumbing. At least two fires in Albuquerque were attributed to homeowners' attempts to thaw frozen pipes.</p>
        <p>"Everyone who came into the store today either had broken water pipes or frozen ones," said Kathy Cushing, owner of a store in Cedar Crest, east of Albuquerque.</p>
        <p>To the north, in Colorado Springs, Barbara Chriswell of Olson Plumbing and Heating said: "We are getting at least 500 calls a day. We have waiting lists. We're swamped. We're working around the clock." Flooding Eases in Southeast</p>
        <p>In the Southeast, the problem was flooding caused by heavy rain that developed ahead of the cold air.</p>
        <p>Tennesseans returned to their homes to clean up after weekend flooding that contributed to several deaths and hundreds of evacuations.</p>
        <p>About 150 families remained out of their homes yesterday in Columbus, Miss., where high water from the Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway and two creeks flooded roads, houses and businesses.</p>
        <p>Two to three dozen families remained out of their homes in Alabama's Lawrence County, which has the rain-swollen Tennessee River as its northern border. Flooding was also reported in several other counties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
