<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazil's Wild West</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE ONIS, JUAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1E3AF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="2169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazil's Wild West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN de ONIS; JUAN de ONIS, a former correspondent of The New York Times, lives in Chile.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DE ONIS, JUAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT was after dark when the bus to Xapuri in northwestern Brazil ran out of gas about a mile from town. An earlier breakdown on the highway from Rio Branco, the capital of Acre state, had stranded the 50 passengers aboard for five hours until a replacement bus arrived. At roadside, as the group shared soft drinks and candy bars, an easy camaraderie sprang up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT was after dark when the bus to Xapuri in northwestern Brazil ran out of gas about a mile from town. An earlier breakdown on the highway from Rio Branco, the capital of Acre state, had stranded the 50 passengers aboard for five hours until a replacement bus arrived. At roadside, as the group shared soft drinks and candy bars, an easy camaraderie sprang up.</p>
        <p>IT was after dark when the bus to Xapuri in northwestern Brazil ran out of gas about a mile from town. An earlier breakdown on the highway from Rio Branco, the capital of Acre state, had stranded the 50 passengers aboard for five hours until a replacement bus arrived. At roadside, as the group shared soft drinks and candy bars, an easy camaraderie sprang up. When the bus shuddered to its final halt, it was all laughter as everyone scrambled out for the moonlight hike into town. ''The Acre express,'' said one traveler, giving the battered bus a farewell kick on the fender.</p>
        <p>Any journey into the immense tropical forest called Amazonia involves uncertainty and lack of comfort, elements that make travel agents label the trip adventure travel. But for those disquieted by the loss of tropical forests and the threat of ''greenhouse'' warming to the world climate, a visit there is an opportunity to see where one of the major environmental conflicts of our time is being played out.</p>
        <p>Having logged some 25,000 miles in the Brazilian Amazon over the last two years to research a book, I have found that although airline and bus services to the main cities are modern, off the beaten path it has helped to be armed with patience and good humor, as well as insect repellent, a mosquito net, soap and toilet paper.</p>
        <p>It's usually sticky hot; rains are frequent and sometimes violent. One can't leave the main highways or large towns without facing mud quagmires on the roads, floods that rip out bridges and ferries.</p>
        <p>But this is what Amazon travel is about. Unless you go as an anthropologist, botanist, bird watcher, mining prospector or missionary, the best reason to visit is simply curiosity. Amazonia is one of the world's last frontiers and its once-isolated environment is becoming rapidly exposed.</p>
        <p>Understanding this frontier requires living in the habitat and observing the people, the settlers, rubber and nut extractors, Indians, gold panners, ranchers, lumbermen, and road builders.</p>
        <p>Take Xapuri. By moonlight, it seemed a ghost town. The latticework balconies on mossy wooden houses overhanging the tree-lined main street spoke of a prosperous past when rubber exports made this a booming river port. But the decline in Brazil's natural rubber exports after World War I, when Malaysian plantations and synthetics took over the market, made Xapuri a backwater. There was no highway then, and few visitors went up the lazy oxbow turns of the Acre River. The immense natural forest was intact. Recently, Xapuri sprang back into the limelight as the scene of a conflict between rubber tappers and an invasion of cattle ranchers. The cattlemen, following a new highway from Rio Branco, cut down the forest to create pasture for cattle, destroying vast stands of rubber trees. The rubber-tapper resistance was organized by Francisco (Chico) Mendes, a rural union leader, who was assassinated by gunmen in December 1988. The shotgun blast that killed Mr. Mendes had worldwide echoes.</p>
        <p>A memorial service held for him on the steps of the Capitol in Washington was attended by leaders of the environmental movement, and his life is to be made into a movie. Xapuri may not be the film's location, but the publicity has put the sleepy town on the map. Xapuri is one of the best places to see what the struggle over preserving the forest is really about. Near the town, there are modern ranches and forest reserves that can be visited by arrangement with the rubber tappers' union, which has an office on the main square.</p>
        <p>I have been to some of these forest reserves by launch on the Acre River or by vehicle when the dirt roads were passable. Under the shade of the closed forest canopy, the tappers collect the latex that oozes from fishbone incisions in the rubber trees. Always accompanied by dogs and carrying shotguns, they hunt for deer and fowl that are part of their simple diet. The tappers like company on their long treks, and visitors wishing to go along should get in touch with them and make arrangements.</p>
        <p>There are three major gateways into the Brazilian Amazon, which occupies 80 percent of this continental basin: Belem, the port at the mouth of the Amazon River; Manaus, 1,000 miles inland, where the Negro, Madeira and Solimoes join to form the great river, and Cuiaba, the capital of Mato Grosso, where some of the great southern tributaries of the Amazon begin. Belem, a market city older than New York, dominates the eastern Amazon where dams, railroads and mines have industrialized the tropics. Manaus, a free port and electronic industrial center, is the natural route to the upper Negro River and the falls at Sao Gabriel, the most intact, accessible forest area left in Amazonia. Both cities have major hotels that specialize in foreign tour groups: the Belem Hilton and the Tropical in Manaus.</p>
        <p>The gateway that I prefer is Cuiaba, which was founded by gold prospectors in the 18th century and is now a city of a million people. It is the commercial hinge between the central plateau of Brazil, now entirely devoted to soybeans, corn and cattle, and the forests of Amazonia.</p>
        <p>Cuiaba is a booming commercial city, with high concrete buildings rising over the red-tile roofs of the old houses, and good highways make it the hub for the western Amazon. Here, along the banks of the Cuiaba River, migrants from all over Brazil have followed the wave of agricultural expansion through Mato Grosso. Nearby are rocky hills that contain the Chapada de Guimaraes National Park, a botanical site.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Aurea is the best of several good hotels, and the restaurant named Rinconada do Bosque is one of the best of Brazil's rodizio barbecue houses. The barbecue restaurants serve as much as you can eat of every part of a cow, plus chicken and pork, and offer an enormous raw bar of vegetables and salads as well as desserts like passionfruit pie. Even when all this is accompanied by ice-cold beer and caipirinhas, the Brazilian julep of cachasa (a raw rum), the cost does not exceed $10 a person.</p>
        <p>ONE of two main roads from Cuiaba into Amazonia is BR-364, a paved all-weather highway in good condition that runs 800 miles northwest through the forests of western Mato Grosso and the new state of Rondonia. The BR-364 has been a major colonization route; it helped open up new towns like Vilhena, Ji-Parana, Cacoal, Ouro Preto and Ariquemes, where sawmills in the great forest clearings are the main industry.</p>
        <p>The new settlers have fought over lands and invaded some Indian reserves. The miners have polluted the rivers. Forests are burned to the ground each dry season. But western Mato Grosso and Rondonia today are the home of three million people who went there seeking land and resources and are permanent producers of coffee, cattle, cocoa and grains.</p>
        <p>BR-364 reaches the Madeira River at Porto Velho, the Rondonia state capital, where over 1,000 floating gold dredges scour the bottom of the river along a stretch of 120 miles. Parallel to the river is the route of the old Madeira-Mamore Railway, the Devil's Railroad, as it was called by the malaria-stricken workers of its American owner, Percy Farquhar.</p>
        <p>The railroad, built between 1905 and 1912 to bypass the rapids at Porto Velho, was abandoned after the rubber boom collapsed. The tracks are now covered by a highway paved by the gold miners. They ride pickup trucks to speed from town to their dredges, which are served by floating stores, cabarets and gold buyers. It is a colorful scene, although the river pollution from mercury used in purifying gold is serious.</p>
        <p>Since the highway opened up Rondonia, Porto Velho has been transformed from an isolated river port into a disorderly but wealthy city. Natural gold, as it comes from the river, can be bought in dozens of gold-trader shops on the downtown streets.</p>
        <p>To find undisturbed primeval forest in Rondonia the traveler must get far away from BR-364. One opportunity is to take a 90-minute flight on a twin-engine Bandeirante from Porto Velho to Costa Marquez, a town of little houses and fishermen's huts beside the Guapore River, a tributary of the Madeira, that is surrounded by ranches cleared from the towering forests. There are flights three times a week; a round trip costs $50.</p>
        <p>Up river from Costa Marquez is the Guapore Biological Reserve. It takes three hours by outboard aluminum skiff to reach the beginning of the reserve, from which point its river frontage extends for another 200 miles. Here turtles spawn on white beaches, pink botos, or river porpoises, frolic in the crystal-clear water, crocodiles share the shallows with cranes, and flocks of river birds sweep across the sky. Local rivermen - who can be found along the waterfront in Costa Marquez - rent dugout canoes with a paddler for about $20 a day.</p>
        <p>Langston James Goree, of Austin, Tex., who spent three days in Costa Marquez after completing an assignment in Brazil for the United Nations, said, ''I felt that I was beyond the frontier in a place that has not yet felt the hand of man.''</p>
        <p>The other highway into Amazonia from Cuiaba, BR-80, runs due north for 600 miles through plains where fields of soybeans and cattle pasture reach the horizon until the pavement suddenly becomes a dirt track. From there on, cattle ranches, mining towns and settlements continue until you cross a bridge over the Teles Pires River and reach Alta Floresta, a pioneer township implanted in virgin forest 15 years ago. It now has a population of more than 120,000.</p>
        <p>Alta Floresta is the creation of Ariosto da Riva, a developer for whom colonization is a life mission. In the Amazon forests, such zeal raises controversy, because Alta Floresta swarms with gold placers (locations where gold is retrieved from the riverbed), burned-out land sites and polluted rivers - as well as farms and ranches amid flora and fauna of great beauty.</p>
        <p>To see these contrasts has been made easy by Victoria da Riva, the founder's daughter, and her husband, Edson de Carvalho, who have built a modern, 60-room tourist hotel, the Floresta Amazonica, in the town. The hotel arrange visits to gold panning sites, the tropical orchards of the da Riva coffee and cocoa farm and to river spots for swimming and boating.</p>
        <p>Ted Parker, an ornithologist at Lousiana State University, specializing in tanagers and antbirds, visited Alta Floresta recently with a birdwatching group. They found 230 species of birds in one day on the Teles Pires River. They also said they detected mercury poisoning from gold panning.</p>
        <p>North of Alta Floresta, toward the Tapajoz and Xingu watersheds, is pure wilderness, an area accessible only with bush pilots, and they are tied up mainly supplying gold-mining camps. TABA, the Amazon regional airline, provides commercial flights that connect Alta Floresta and Belem on an erratic schedule, with stops en route. The stops include Altamira, the main town on the Transamazon Highway, the glorified name for an earth road.</p>
        <p>The charm of Altamira, a township of 60,000, is that it is on the Xingu River, a majestic Amazon tributary. The upper Xingu is the home of the Kaiapo Indians, one of the strongest surviving Amazon tribes. Fishing boats for hire ply the river and provide access to the interior. One day on the river with a local skipper, I passed crocodiles lying loglike in wait of prey, caught three-pound tucunares, a battling fish - with delicious flesh when grilled - and watched a herd of screaming monkeys race through treetops at twilight, putting parrots to flight.</p>
        <p>THE great debate in Altamira now is over construction of a high dam on a big bend of the Xingu north of the Transamazon. The construction and the power to be generated, the promoters say, would make Altamira a major city. The Kaiapo Indians and environmentalists from all over the world, including Sting, the ''green'' rock star, are opposed.</p>
        <p>Joao Augusto da Silva, the owner of the Alta Palace Hotel, on the road into Altamira from the airport, favors the dam. He built his four-story hotel with money made as a gold miner at Sao Felix do Xingu in Kaiapo country. ''We know how to get along with the Indians,'' said Mr. da Silva. ''They just want a share of the take. We gave them power generators and television sets, and we got the gold. It will be the same with the dam.''</p>
        <p>The terrace of the hotel, with its splendid view of the big bend of the Xingu, is a good place from which to reflect on whether a high dam in the Amazon environment brings civilization or corruption.</p>
        <p>PLACES TO STAY</p>
        <p>Rates are for a room for two per day. Xapuri. San Antonio (telephone 068 2283) charges $8. Cuiaba. Hotel Aurea (065 3223377), $20 to $25. Porto Velho. Vila Rica (069 2217297), $35. Hotel Central (O69 2210778), $20. Altamira. Alta Palace (091 5152057), $10-$12. Rio Branco. Hotel Rio Branco (068 2241785), $15. Alta Floresta. Floresta Amazonica (065 521-360l), $35. Costa Marquez. At Girasol Palace, where 4 of 12 rooms have air-conditioners, room rate is $8 for two, with breakfast.</p>
        <p>- J. de O.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
