<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EXPLORING DEVONS'S SECRET GARDENS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DEVON (ENG)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLBORN, NIGEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/Devon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9113AF937A35750C0A966958260" item-length="2631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EXPLORING DEVONS'S SECRET GARDENS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NIGEL COLBORN; Nigel Colborn's books include ''This Gardening Business'' (Cassell).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLBORN, NIGEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Traveling the 120 miles from London to Devon in March is to make the leap from winter to spring. Thanks to the warm waters of the Gulf Stream, England's southwest peninsula begins to bloom weeks before the rest of the country has emerged from gray dampness and night frosts. Wherever you go in Devon, the ocean is not far away, and its influence makes winter a gentle affair with minimal frost, sea mists and lots of rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Traveling the 120 miles from London to Devon in March is to make the leap from winter to spring. Thanks to the warm waters of the Gulf Stream, England's southwest peninsula begins to bloom weeks before the rest of the country has emerged from gray dampness and night frosts. Wherever you go in Devon, the ocean is not far away, and its influence makes winter a gentle affair with minimal frost, sea mists and lots of rain.</p>
        <p>Traveling the 120 miles from London to Devon in March is to make the leap from winter to spring. Thanks to the warm waters of the Gulf Stream, England's southwest peninsula begins to bloom weeks before the rest of the country has emerged from gray dampness and night frosts. Wherever you go in Devon, the ocean is not far away, and its influence makes winter a gentle affair with minimal frost, sea mists and lots of rain. Summers are temperate too. Color comes early to these parts, with brilliant yellow celandines along the lanes from February giving way to wild primroses, which are happier in this cool, wet climate than anywhere else in Britain and grow in profusion, often sharing the wayside with wood anemones and early purple orchids. Through the spring the woodland is carpeted with fragrant wild bluebells, their sheets of blue contrasting with drifts of pink campion.</p>
        <p>Add to the soft climate a topography of deep-cut, sheltered valleys, known locally as combes, each floored with rich alluvial soil and watered with benevolent streams, and, apart from one vital ingredient, you have all the requisites for the perfect English garden. Except the gardener, and Devon has been fortunate in this respect as well. Over the last half century a liberal sprinkling of eccentric horticulturists have flourished here. A spring weekend tour of their creations will acquaint you with some of the most interesting gardens in England.</p>
        <p>Tucked away in the oak-clad Torridge valley just below Torrington (about 45 minutes from Exit 27 on the M5 motorway), Rosemoor nestles in a sheltered haven between the bleakness of Dartmoor to the south and the wild country of Exmoor to the north. Now a regional center for the Royal Horticultural Society, the garden was created over a period of 30 years by Lady Anne Palmer, who was into her 40's before she had learned to tell a rose from an acorn. Descended from Robert Walpole, to all intents England's first prime minister, she is the daughter of the last Earl of Orford. Had she been male, she might have been running Wolterton Hall, a Walpole family estate of some 3,000 acres in Norfolk. Instead, Lady Anne ended up with Rosemoor, a small property the Earl had bought in 1923 to use as a fishing lodge. After an army career, she and her husband settled down there to run a dairy farm, and there they lived, a normal family in a family farmhouse. In those days, in such a beautiful corner of England, with a family to support, a garden seemed almost superfluous.</p>
        <p>Then came the inspiration. In Spain, Lady Anne met the celebrated plant collector Collingwood Ingram. They became friends, and as soon as she got home Lady Anne started collecting plants with an obsessiveness that staggered her friends and family. That was in 1959; since then she has amassed more than 4,000 species at Rosemoor. As her collection grew, the garden had to expand to accommodate it. Dairy pastures were snitched from the farm to make room for lawns and flower borders, and woodlands were thinned to make a wild garden. The family tennis court was converted to a gravel garden with island beds of small conifers and rarities collected from Tasmania and New Zealand.</p>
        <p>Though never planned as a whole, Rosemoor has a pleasing structure. The veteran designer John Codrington - 91 this year and still drawing plans - provided some professional advice in the early days. Collingwood Ingram recommended long, informal vistas, and Lionel Fortescue, whose garden at Buckland Monachorum was already famous, helped with tips on which plants to group together. To all of this received wisdom, Lady Anne has added her own aesthetic talent. Although her planting is, by some standards, a little overcrowded, the results are a delight at any time of year.</p>
        <p>In spring, dwarf rhododendrons brighten gloomy areas below larger trees and a fine collection of ornamental cherries blooms. Dominating the old kitchen garden is a large specimen of Prunus serrula, a Chinese cherry with miserablelittle flowers and bitter fruits but a trunk that glistens like polished mahogany. Elsewhere are the mid-pink Prunus called Kursar, which flowers in early March, and gorgeous Japanese cherries such as the spreading white Shirofugen and the pink-flushed Shimidzu Sakura. Beneath the trees, herbaceous plants are in flower every month - even in January the hellebores bloom freely.</p>
        <p>Looking from the front of the house, the eye sweeps down a long lawn with boldly curving edges. At the end is a pond flanked with irises, and all along the margins of the lawn is a dense planting of trees and shrubs. Stand at the end of the lawn on a sunny spring day - if you're lucky - and watch the slanting light play on the trunks of the birches or pick out the foliage of the shrubs. As the day progresses, the colors and shapes appear to change, shadows alter outlines and different parts of the garden grab attention as a particular group of flowers or patch of foliage catches the light. Such subtleties might be lost in the harsh sunshine of more southern latitudes, but here, where the light is soft and watery, gentle color harmonies give the garden a sumptuous beauty. It doesn't pay to whizz round in an hour. Rosemoor is a place to be lingered in.</p>
        <p>Between gardens, there are many intriguing corners to explore in Devon. Historically, the town of Torrington was a center for glove making, but it is now more famous for the Dartington glass factory, which makes fine crystal. It is open to visitors.</p>
        <p>The River Torridge, which passes the garden at Rosemoor, was where much of Henry Williamson's wildlife classic ''Tarka the Otter'' was written in the 1920's. Tarka was born a few miles downstream, and the mill wheel on which the otter rested before the afternoon of his final and fatal hunt was originally part of the property. A nature trail following Tarka's lifetime itinerary will soon be opened up to walkers, and Torrington is as good a place as any to start along it. Following the two main rivers of North Devon, the Taw and the Torridge, the trail runs inland into Dartmoor, passing through as many different wildlife habitats as exist in Devon. But you'll need stout walking shoes - it stretches for 180 miles.</p>
        <p>But if you are bent on fitting in more gardens, you'll need to travel south, nearly to Plymouth, to the delightfully named village of Buckland Monachorum. Lionel Fortescue made his garden on the site of the old vicarage there, which he bought in 1945 and named the Garden House. When Henry VIII dissolved the monasteries in the late 1530's, the Abbot of Buckland Abbey, to save his own skin, underwent instant conversion to Protestantism. Henry, himself a pragmatist, gave generous handouts to abbots who were quick to embrace the new Anglican church, and the Abbot of Buckland acquired a fine house. Today, little remains of the original building apart from a tower and some old slate walls, all irregular angles clothed with centuries of lichens.</p>
        <p>Fortescue laid out his garden within these walls, on what amounts to a series of terraces. Besides being a clever garden designer, he was a shrewd acquisitor of plant material. It is said that when he visited other gardens, he never came away without a few illicit sprigs in his pockets. All the cuttings that came into his hands took root, however, and multiplied, and the evidence is there to see.</p>
        <p>Before he died, in 1981, a trust was set up to preserve the garden, and today's curator, Keith Wiley, is leaving his own mark by improving some of the vistas and making subtle alterations to the planting so that the garden maintains its charm out of season as well as providing a great climax of color in summer.</p>
        <p>Spring at Buckland Monachorum is a season of carpeting wildflowers to which exotic species have been added with such tact that they, too, look native. North American erythroniums and Mediterranean cyclamen blend with primroses and windflowers. While English songbirds warble overhead you can stand ankle deep in drifts of Yugoslavian Crocus tomasinianus, whose purple flowers contrast with the early daffodil February Gold. ''Lionel's sense of color,'' says Keith Wiley, ''was absolutely unerring,'' but Mr. Wiley has also made fine visual harmonies, such as the spring mixture of sky blue Chionodoxa sardensis and the North American yellow-flowered Viola glabella. With its collection of magnolias in flower above these woodland plantings and drifts of camellias and rhododendrons blooming with total abandon, the Garden House at Buckland Monachorum is not to be missed.</p>
        <p>Moving north again, possibly making a small detour to the ancient tin mining town of Tavistock, the route back to London is more interesting if you follow the North Devon coast. Once you have left the main road, there's no need to worry about remembering to drive on the left. The lanes are so narrow, with high banks on either side, that foliage brushes both sides of the car. Rounding a sharp bend and coming face to face with a huge milk tanker truck will remind you that Devon is one of the centers of Britain's dairy industry. Road etiquette clearly states that foreigners give way to locals, so you will need to know how to find reverse gear quickly. You should also know that in these lanes local drivers never exceed 5 miles per hour in forward gear but always reverse at top speed, usually hotly pursued by milk tankers.</p>
        <p>Above the Taw estuary at Marwood Hill is an extraordinary garden created by an eminent doctor, James A. Smart, who has long since retired and slaves day and night in his 18 acres. Terraces burgeon with spring alpine plants, drifts of daffodils and, as ever in Devon gardens, an abundance of camellias. The garden occupies a valley with lakes at the bottom and the sides planted hugger-mugger with masses of different trees. It's a bit of a muddle and has none of the careful plant association of Rosemoor or the Garden House at Buckland Monachorum, but strangely it works - more or less.</p>
        <p>If, as you stroll through, you spot a tall figure in late middle age and the scruffiest of clothes, gardening at 16 frames per second, that will be Dr. Smart. He has traveled the world and has a particular penchant for the plants of Oceania. There is a small forest of eucalyptus, many species of which are far too tender to grow elsewhere in England but thrive here and even flower. Alongside, because the color of their trunks harmonize so well, he has planted his collection of birches. ''People who say you shouldn't plant Northern and Southern Hemisphere plants together are talking nonsense,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Moving farther up the coast, at Georgeham you can see the cottage and grave of Henry Williamson, Tarka's creator, and just before the Somerset border the villages of Lynton and Lynmouth are tucked into rugged clifftop scenery and have plenty of overnight accommodation. A trip on the Lynton cliff railway, operated entirely by cold-water hydraulics and therefore one of the most environment-friendly transport systems in the world, is essential. The cable stretches and twangs alarmingly when the car is suspended halfway down.</p>
        <p>No excursion in Devon would be complete without a stop for a local cream tea. Native Devonians are charming folk with soft, burry accents and a gentle sense of humor, but the chances of meeting any are slim because most of them seem to have sold their property and gone to live elsewhere. Local hoteliers and business owners are more evocative of Piccadilly Circus than Widecombe Fair, and most of the waiters evidently come from Spain or Cyprus. And the region is not well known for its gourmet delights, and healthy diets have yet to become fashionable.</p>
        <p>But the genuine cream tea - with fresh baked farmhouse scones, clotted cream and real strawberry jam - is an experience good enough to make you forget the cholesterol. Beware cheap imitations: real Devon clotted cream should have a crusty golden surface and be thick enough to spread with a knife. It is made by standing milk in pans overnight, then warming them and cooling them and scooping the floating cream from the surface by hand. Devon cider, often called scrumpy, is treacherously alcoholic and comes in two main flavors: sickly sweet or viciously acid with a metallic aftertaste. Some ciders are worse than others.</p>
        <p>Before you leave Devon, perhaps on the way back to the M5, one last garden, Knightshayes at Tiverton, is an essential stop. The house is open, and if heavy Victorian Gothic appeals, it will delight you. It is too much like the set for a horror movie for my taste, and I could bear it just long enough to note some respectable paintings, including a couple of John Constables, before I ran for the garden, a wonderful blend of formal terraces and wild woodland.</p>
        <p>Although the giant Douglas firs and Turkey oaks tell you that there has been a garden there for years, most of the creation has been perfected since 1946 by Sir John and Lady Heathcote-Amory. The formal areas consist of wide terraces that look over miles of Devon countryside. There are lawns and fine topiary, including a circular hedge clipped into the shapes of hunting hounds enjoying the chase. Deep in the woods, exotic lilies and rhododendrons light up the gloom with their brilliant flowers, so that you feel transported to the Himalayas. Even if you have only enough time to take a brief walk around, and if you're fortunate get a Woodcutter's Lunch with rough-cut pate at the restaurant, Knightshayes is worth the effort.</p>
        <p>There's a postcard of Devon - you may see it in local gift shops - showing two identical drawings of a bedraggled sheep standing in the rain. The twin captions are ''Devon in Winter'' and ''Devon in Summer.'' It takes a lot of rain to make the gardens grow so well, but I have it on good authority that the sun does shine. Quite a lot, as it '' 'appens,'' the housekeeper at my inn told me in flat, Cockney tones as she deftly shoved her vacuum cleaner between me and the door. ''You should have been 'ere last week, mate, it was lovely then. Bloomin 'eatwave!''</p>
        <p>DEVON IN BLOOM</p>
        <p>A violent January storm caused damage to some Devon gardens, in particular Knightshayes. But all remain open or will reopen as planned.</p>
        <p>Rosemoor Garden (The Royal Horticultural Society), Great Torrington, North Devon EX38 7EG (telephone: 805-24067). One mile southeast of Great Torrington on the B3220 to Exeter. Open daily all year, 10 to 5 (6 in summer). Admission is $2.50. The nursery, open daily from 10 to 5, sells rare plants grown from seeds and cuttings taken from the garden; they will ship. Light lunches and cream teas are served in the restaurant.</p>
        <p>The Garden House (The Fortescue Garden Trust), Buckland Monachorum, Yelverton, Devon PL20 7LQ (822-854769). West of the A386, 10 miles north of Plymouth. Open daily, noon to 5, April through September. Admission is $2.50. Cream teas are served in the house; approximately $3 per person.</p>
        <p>Marwood Hill, Marwood, Devon EX31 4EB (271-42528), four miles north of Barnstaple. Open daily, dawn to dusk, except Christmas Day. Admission is $1.65. On Sundays and holidays, cream teas ($2.50 a person) are served by volunteers from the local parish in the Church Room, next door.</p>
        <p>Knightshayes Gardens, Tiverton, Devon EX16 7RQ (884-254665). Two miles north of Tiverton on the A396 Bampton Road. Open daily, 11 to 6, April through September, 11 to 5 in October. Admission to the gardens only, $3. The Victorian house, designed by William Burges, is open from 1:30 to 6, closed Fridays. A combined house and garden ticket is $5.75. The restaurant, in the stable, serves morning coffee, lunches (about $9 for salads and traditional British hot dishes) and cream teas (about $3.50). Plants are for sale in the shop at the visitors' center in the same complex.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
