<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Acts on Pollution in the Garden</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="408464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1230F937A25751C1A966958260" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Acts on Pollution in the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Dec. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opening a new front in the battle against air pollution, California is moving to control some everyday tools of modern American living: gasoline-powered lawn mowers, leaf blowers, hedge trimmers and snow blowers.</p>
        <p>In an action that is believed to be the first effort ever to regulate exhaust from these and other "utility" machines, the state's powerful Air Resources Board is expected to order manufacturers on Friday to reduce pollutant emissions by 55 percent in two steps starting in 1994. The machines produce up to 50 times more pollution per horsepower than trucks produce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opening a new front in the battle against air pollution, California is moving to control some everyday tools of modern American living: gasoline-powered lawn mowers, leaf blowers, hedge trimmers and snow blowers.</p>
        <p>In an action that is believed to be the first effort ever to regulate exhaust from these and other "utility" machines, the state's powerful Air Resources Board is expected to order manufacturers on Friday to reduce pollutant emissions by 55 percent in two steps starting in 1994. The machines produce up to 50 times more pollution per horsepower than trucks produce.</p>
        <p>Given the importance of the huge California market to the $4.6 billion lawn-and-garden industry, the rules are likely to have wide national and international impact as manufacturers modify their products so they can be sold here. Each manufacturer would have to decide whether it wants to make separate product lines for California and for the rest of the country, and many might elect to make only the one, more expensive product. Consumers Would Pay</p>
        <p>Consumers nationwide could ultimately pay for the new technology. For example, the staff of the board estimates that the price of a typical walk-behind lawn mower would rise by $30 in 1994 and $35 in 1999 in an increase of about 25 percent over prices of mowers now on the market.</p>
        <p>But industry leaders maintain that the rules are more likely to double the retail prices of such products by 1994 and to shut them out of the California market altogether by 1999, when the second tier of rules take effect. They argue that the cost of developing the catalytic converter technology needed to comply with the second tier of rules would make the machines prohibitively costly.</p>
        <p>Machines manufactured before Dec. 31, 1993, would not be affected by the proposed regulations, and existing machines would not be banned.</p>
        <p>The nine-member board, an independent agency whose actions can be appealed only through the courts, will hear objections from the industry on Friday in San Francisco. Although some modifications might be made, the board is expected to adopt the bulk of the proposed rules.</p>
        <p>The action illustrates the lengths to which California has been forced to go to clean up its air, which in some sections is the worst in the nation. In October, the board adopted controls on hairsprays, air fresheners, shaving creams, nail polish removers and other products using hydrocarbons as solvents and propellants. "As we get cleaner and cleaner cars and industry, these smaller sources become more important," said Jerry Martin, a spokesman for the board. Rules Cover Many Devices</p>
        <p>Overall, it is estimated that utility machines contribute 5 percent of the hydrocarbon and 4 percent of carbon monoxide emissions in California. The total emissions from such machines are the equivalent of 3.5 million new 1991 model automobiles driven 16,000 miles. In 1989, Americans bought 13.2 million utility machines, including lawn mowers, garden tractors, tillers, shredders, grinders and outdoor vacuums.</p>
        <p>The new rules would apply to these devices and to small engines in commercial machines like concrete cutters, generators, compressors, grinders, stump beaters and pumps.</p>
        <p>In the first step, which will affect machines sold in 1994, the rules anticipate that manufacturers will be able to cut emissions 46 percent by adapting the kind of overhead valve carburetor used in ordinary cars. There are two sets of standards, one set for larger, four-stroke engines in machines like snow blowers and generators, and a less stringent one for smaller, two-stroke engines in hand-held machines like leaf blowers. The engines, which must be lightweight, use a very rich fuel mix. The maximum permissible emissions of hydrocarbons, nitrogen oxides and carbon monoxide would vary with the size of the engine.</p>
        <p>The four-stroke engine requires four strokes of the piston to run its full power cycle. The two stroke engine is a much simpler and lighter device, but much less efficient at the same time.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers say that this first step is technically feasible but that it would be costly. Donald E. Purcell, president of the Portable Power Equipment Manufacturers Association in Bethesda, Md., which represents 26 makers of machines with the smaller engines, said that the modifications would raise the consumer price of a typical trimmer to $180 or $200 from about $90. He added that the industry could lose about half its volume of business in the state.</p>
        <p>Under the second step, beginning in 1999, the permissible level of emissions would be lowered to achieve a total reduction of 55 percent, again with more lenient standards for the hand-held devices. This would require advances in catalytic converter technology.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Purcell, "the 1999 rule puts our industry out of business in California." He said the cost of researching and producing this technology would make the consumer products, whose sales are extremely price-sensitive, so expensive that they would be impossible to sell in California.</p>
        <p>The board's staff counters that a chain saw equipped with a catalytic converter has been available since 1989 in Europe. But Mr. Purcell said that machine operates at too high a temperature level to meet Federal requirements governing the surface temperature of the machines. The rule is meant to prevent forest fires.</p>
        <p>"So we've got a direct conflict between the staff and Federal law," he said. "We have recommended that they delete the 1999 proposal, but so far it has fallen on deaf ears."</p>
        <p>Smog officials argue that the manufacturers could use heat shields, insulate the catalytic converter or cool it with air.</p>
        <p>The California rules are a result of a Federal court order issued in a suit last February by Citizens for a Better Environment, an environmental group in San Francisco. The order directed the state to issue regulations on utility engines in the San Francisco Bay Area by Jan. 7, 1991. Although the order was limited to the Bay Area, one of the areas of the state with the most severe air-quality problems, the board voluntarily broadened its reach to include the entire state. Pollution also is at the state's highest levels in the Los Angeles Basin and in the state's central valley, from Sacramento to Bakersfield.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
