<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health Warnings Issued as Air Pollution Builds Up</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED61638F932A15754C0A966958260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health Warnings Issued as Air Pollution Builds Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Air pollution was worse this week than it has been all year, and health advisories were issued throughout the Northeast as heat and stagnant air helped form ground-level ozone, a major component of smog.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Air pollution was worse this week than it has been all year, and health advisories were issued throughout the Northeast as heat and stagnant air helped form ground-level ozone, a major component of smog.</p>
        <p>Air pollution was worse this week than it has been all year, and health advisories were issued throughout the Northeast as heat and stagnant air helped form ground-level ozone, a major component of smog.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the state Department of Environmental Conservation issued a health advisory for New York City, Nassau, Suffolk and Westchester counties, and it was still in effect yesterday. Such advisories generally recommend that children, the elderly and people with respiratory ailments reduce outdoor activities and physical exertion.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday and Thursday, ozone pollution in parts of Connecticut, including Bridgeport, exceeded the levels that the Federal Government considers safe to health by 50 percent. Bayonne, N.J., had levels one-third higher than the Federal standard on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A Reminder of 1988</p>
        <p>This week recalled the choking summer of 1988, when ozone health standards were routinely exceeded by large amounts throughout the Northeast. Last summer, cooler weather reduced the number of violations, their magnitude and their geographical distribution.</p>
        <p>To date this year, monitors in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut have recorded 59 violations, compared with 41 last year for the same period, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency said.</p>
        <p>But the air has been cleaner than in 1988, when 306 violations had been recorded by this time.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line of it all is, this is a fairly good year, as was last year,'' said William S. Baker, chief of the air program branch in the E.P.A. New York regional office.</p>
        <p>Ground-level ozone can cause wheezing, coughing, a burning sensation in the respiratory tract and, over time, permanent lung damage. Recent research indicates that ozone may be harmful at levels even lower than the Federal standard.</p>
        <p>Sun-Cooked Hydrocarbons</p>
        <p>Ozone is formed when airborne hydrocarbons and oxides of nitrogen are cooked in the sun. The pollutants come from motor vehicles, large factories and even dry cleaners and gas stations. Ground-level ozone is different from its counterpart in the upper atmosphere, a protective layer that filters ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>A typical ozone buildup occurs when an air mass stagnates over a populated area.Such air masses often develop along the East Coast and move north into New England. As a result, even less populated areas can suffer ozone violations. On Wednesday, Kennebunkport, Me., recorded ozone levels one-third above the Federal health standard.</p>
        <p>As the air mass moves, ozone levels can increase, because more pollutants are added along the way and have more time to combine in the sunlight. That explains why ozone levels are frequently higher in Connecticut than in New York City.</p>
        <p>A week ago Friday, Senate and House conferees met for the first time to begin working out a compromise on a more stringent Federal Clean Air Act. It is likely to be a contentious process, and there are doubts the work can be completed in the 40 work days left before the Congress recesses in August. The 20-year-old act has not been revised since 1977.</p>
        <p>''New York City is sitting in the smog and the conference commiteee is already behind a month,'' said Nancy Seidman, acting executive director of the Northeastern States for Coordinated Air Use Management, a regional air pollution organization in Boston. ''They sometimes forget that their lack of action has public health consequences.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
