<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warming Is Killing Coral Reefs, Scientists Say</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD8173CF936A25753C1A966958260" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warming Is Killing Coral Reefs, Scientists Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Warming trends are causing the deterioration of the world's coral reefs, a panel of research scientists told a Senate committee last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Warming trends are causing the deterioration of the world's coral reefs, a panel of research scientists told a Senate committee last week.</p>
        <p>Warming trends are causing the deterioration of the world's coral reefs, a panel of research scientists told a Senate committee last week.</p>
        <p>Scientists have been at a loss to definitively explain the widespread bleaching and evaporation of coral reefs, but they told the senators that contributing factors include pollution, sewage runoff and the warmer temperatures in the last decade. The testimony was the first indication that some scientists investigating the phenomenon of a warming of the earth's atmosphere had reached a strong conclusion about temperature's role.</p>
        <p>''We have found a precise correlation between high temperatures and bleaching,'' said Dr. Thomas J. Goreau, a senior scientist at the University of the West Indies in Jamaica who is president of the Global Coral Reef Alliance.</p>
        <p>Once Bright, Now Ghostly</p>
        <p>But one scientist at the hearing voiced skepticism at that conclusion. Dr. M. Grant Gross, director of the Division for Ocean Sciences at the National Science Foundation, said that while higher temperatures in the 1980's might have been enough to cause coral bleaching ''we cannot yet prove this hypothesis.''</p>
        <p>Coral bleaching results from the expulsion of microscopic algae that normally live in the tissues of living coral animals, causing brightly colored corals to turn ghostly pale. Scientists have known that bleaching is usually caused by environmental stresses like extreme temperatures, low salinity and reduced intensity of light, but have resisted drawing a single conclusion.</p>
        <p>Since 1988, about 80 percent of the coral reefs in the Florida Keys, Bermuda, Hawaii and the Caribbean have suffered, mostly because the last two years were ''the hottest on record,'' Dr. Goreau said. Scientists are finding that many corals are not coming back and are not as resilient as had been hoped.</p>
        <p>''Having suffered repeated bouts of bleaching, coral reefs are beginning to show signs of exhaustion,'' said Senator Al Gore, a Tennessee Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Commmittee on Commerce, Science and Transporation, which held the hearing.</p>
        <p>A Warm Decade</p>
        <p>The scientists presented figures showing mass coral reef mortality in the Keys and the Caribbean, as well as charts showing generally higher temperatures in the last decade.</p>
        <p>Temperature data presented by officials from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, Ala., and by an English climatologist, Dr. Philip D. Jones, showed evidence of a warming trend in the last decade and supported the conclusions of the coral experts.</p>
        <p>''Our atmospheric and surface measurement systems show that the 1980's were warmer than the preceding two decades,'' said Dr. Roy Spencer, a space scientist at the Marshall center.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jones, of the University of East Anglia, said worldwide temperatures in the 1980's were 4 degrees Fahrenheit above those of any other decade on record and said figures from 1990 should continue the trend. The temperature data were based on readings from 33,000 weather stations around the world. The panel urged Congress to set up a coral reef alert center to compile data on disturbances and analyze events of bleaching.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
