<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARLES, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA153BF936A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eleanor Charles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARLES, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>A BOOK OF KELLS</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>A BOOK OF KELLS</p>
        <p>A BOOK OF KELLS</p>
        <p>A new, fine art copy of the Book of Kells, produced by a recently developed process in Switzerland, has been donated to the Iona College Library in New Rochelle and will be exhibited in the early fall, said Patrick Larkin, the library director. ''When we have found a proper case for it and decided on a location we will make a public announcement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The original, completed in about the year 800 after a century of work in an unknown location, has deteriorated to the point where it can no longer be touched. It is kept in a protected environment at Trinity College in Dublin.</p>
        <p>In its 680 pages are the four New Testament Gospels of Matthew, Mark, Luke and John, expressed in scripted Latin text and colored illuminations, and acknowledged to be the most beautiful of any existing medieval manuscript. The original was found buried near a church in the town of Kells, Ireland, in 1060.</p>
        <p>The new limited edition of 500 copies was produced on acid-free rag paper that requires no special climate controls. It mimics the original down to the thick waxiness of the paper, uneveness of the pages, simulated worm-holes, and variations of coloring from vivid to pale, reproduced from thousands of photographs of the original. Trinity College owns the plates and has precluded any new editions for the next 40 years.</p>
        <p>Five of the new copies were purchased at $15,000 each as gifts to various libraries by the Wild Geese, a private group founded in 1981 in Greenwich to foster Irish culture and heritage. University libraries at Harvard, Notre Dame and Fairfield, and the Ferguson Public Library in Stamford are the other four recipients.</p>
        <p>WATCH A SHOOTING STAR</p>
        <p>Craig Stevens, an amateur astronomer and naturalist, will be in charge of a Perseid Meteor Shower Watch at two county parks next weekend. At 7:30 P.M. Friday the watch will begin on the grounds of the Lenoir Preserve in Yonkers. Mr. Stevens's warm-up talk will identify Arcturus, the North Star and other bright stars and summer constellations, accompanied by a recital of the mythological tales they have generated.</p>
        <p>As the sky darkens and weather permits, the multi-colored shooting-star shower emanating from the constellation Perseus should begin. The shooting stars are particles of matter pulled from space by the earth's gravity, and burned up by friction. As many as 60 of them can be seen in an hour. The preserve is on Dudley Street, and there is no charge for admission. For more information, call 968-5851.</p>
        <p>A second session will be conducted by Mr. Stevens at 7:30 P.M. Saturday at the Trailside Nature Museum of Ward Pound Ridge Reservation in Cross River. It is at the junction of Routes 35 and 121, and there is a $5 fee for parking on the grounds. The phone number for more information is 763-3993. Take something to sit on at either location.</p>
        <p>SNIPPING SILHOUETTES</p>
        <p>One of Boscobel's perennially popular events is a visit by the silhouette artist Sally Newcomb, who will be on hand with her scissors and special papers from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. today.</p>
        <p>Those who want silhouettes made of themselves, their children or pets, should call 265-3638 for an appointment before making the trip. Ms. Newcomb charges $27 for a full figure, $13.50 for a head, and animals are priced according to size, disposition and hairiness. She will even do a horse. The completed silhouettes are mounted on acid-free paper ready for framing.</p>
        <p>The practice is named for Etienne de Silhouette, a late 18th-century artist who introduced the form in England and on the Continent. By 1839 silhouettes had arrived in America through the work of another French artist, August Edouart. Their low price and the speed with which a likeness could be created made them immediately popular here.</p>
        <p>Boscobel, the Federal-style decorative arts museum in Garrison- on-Hudson, is on Route 9D, eight miles north of the Bear Mountain Bridge. Admission is $5; for the elderly, $4; children, $2.50; children younger than 6 are free. Tours of the mansion are conducted all day.</p>
        <p>ANIMAL PORTRAITS</p>
        <p>Linda Relis specializes in drawing and painting animals, both on the farm and in the wild. A dozen or so of her pen-and-ink drawings, oils and acrylics can be seen at Muscoot Farm in Somers from 1 to 4 P.M. Wednesday through Sunday, through August 26. They were made from sketches of the farm's resident barnyard animals.</p>
        <p>''I got interested in painting animals in California a few years ago,'' Ms. Relis said. ''They are very concerned about environmental issues out there, and I wasn't really aware of what was going on until I started learning about all the endangered species. It was quite an awakening.''</p>
        <p>While her concern for farm animals focuses on the way they are raised and slaughtered, her paintings depict them in an idyllic state. ''So far, I can't make bold statements about what happens to them before we get the meat in the supermarket,'' she said. ''I'm still too upset. I have to become more objective.''</p>
        <p>Because of her committment to animal art, the National Audubon Society included her work in its 1987 Los Angeles exhibition. More recently she has exhibited at the Mark Gruber Gallery's all-cow exhibition in New Palz, and at Temple Israel of Northern Westchester in Croton-on-Hudson. Prices for her work at Muscoot range from $180 for a 10-by10-inch acrylic to $1,500 for a 30-by46-inch oil.</p>
        <p>Muscoot Farm is an interpretive turn-of-the-century property of the County Parks Department, containing a collection of live farm animals, house and barn and a picnic area. It is on Route 100, and admission is free. Call 232-7118 for more information.</p>
        <p>A BIRTHDAY IDEA</p>
        <p>Coming up with creative ideas for children's birthday parties can wear down even the most resourceful parent. One bright option is the Greenburgh Nature Center's ''Meet the Animals'' program, available at your place or theirs.</p>
        <p>The center's live-animal museum contains 130 specimens, from hedgehogs to boa constrictors, and a staff member will provide a one-hour program designed to hold the childrens' attention. When held at the center, the program is conducted in the discovery room, where the animals are housed. In private homes the animals are transported and shown in cages. The presentation must be held indoors and, according to the center, is suitable for the living room or playroom.</p>
        <p>Ice cream and cake, or whatever refreshments the family supplies, are served in the center's special party room with the help of staff members. There is a refrigerator and a stove for warming, but no cooking area is available. Up to 15 children, who must be at least 4 years old can be accommodated.</p>
        <p>Parties last two hours at the center or at home, and they may be scheduled year-round. The fee for in-house parties is $65 plus a family membership of $35, or $100 plus the $35 membership when the event is held at home.</p>
        <p>Weekend parties, which are reserved months in advance, may begin no earlier than 11 A.M. The earliest weekday starting time is 1 P.M., and bookings are easier to come by. Payment must be made in advance. The center is on Dromore Road off Central Avenue. Call 723-3470 for reservations or more information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
