<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Auto Pollution Has Decreased for a Decade;   Tollbooth Syndrome</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="340327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGES AND TUNNELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOLLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TRIBOROUGH BRIDGE (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, STEPHEN M (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANDRIGAN, PHILIP J (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF133FF930A35757C0A966958260" item-length="437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Auto Pollution Has Decreased for a Decade;   Tollbooth Syndrome</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your March 12 article on the epidemic illness affecting toll collectors and officers on the Triborough Bridge conveys an impression that the symptoms were of psychological origin. The report effectively trivializes concerns about exposure of toll workers to hazardous substances in their working environment.</p>
        <p>Feb. 16 through Feb. 22, physicians in the occupational health center and the emergency room at Mount Sinai Medical Center interviewed and examined 32 of the 34 officers and toll workers in the outbreak of flulike symptoms within one to two hours of onset. From this assessment, it was the physicians' opinion that the workers had been exposed to a toxic gas or fume, which appeared to enter some tollbooths by the ventilation ducts. Symptoms of eye and respiratory irritation, as well as headache, dizziness, nausea and vomiting resulted.</p>
        <p>A similar episode occurred on the Triborough Bridge in December 1988, when toll-collectors developed headache, weakness, nausea and vomiting coincident with an unusual odor in the tollbooths. Environmental monitoring showed that ethylene glycol, the solvent and cooling fluid, had contaminated the ventilation system for the booths. When the ethylene glycol leak was repaired, the symptoms abated.</p>
        <p>In the new episode, environmental monitoring sought evidence for excessive exposure to carbon monoxide and sulfur oxides; neither was found. Other toxic gases, such as solvents or the combustion products of burned plastic, which may have contributed to this episode, were not sought early on.</p>
        <p>If the responsible chemical was volatile and in the air only transiently (as was probable), the more extensive testing five days later could not have detected its presence, as it would long since have dispersed.</p>
        <p>Bridge and tunnel officers must perform repetitive activities under considerable stress, exposed constantly to gaseous and particulate products of combustion. Persuasive evidence from epidemiological studies shows these workers to be at increased risk of death of heart disease from exposure to carbon monoxide and other exhaust products. Only rarely do they report acute symptoms requiring immediate medical evaluation. When such episodes occur, facile attribution of their origins to ''psychological'' causes does a disservice to these men and women, and teaches us little about how to avoid similar incidents.</p>
        <p>STEPHEN M. LEVIN, M.D.</p>
        <p>PHILIP J. LANDRIGAN, M.D.</p>
        <p>New York, March 15, 1990</p>
        <p>The writers are, respectively, medical director, occupational health center, and professor of community medicine at Mount Sinai Medical Center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
