<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Mission at Energy Dept.: Bomb Makers Turn to Cleanup</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="377026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFENSE CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SYNAR, MIKE (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6153FF934A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="1780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Mission at Energy Dept.: Bomb Makers Turn to Cleanup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Less than two years after the Energy Department acknowledged it had caused grave pollution problems at active and inactive nuclear weapons plants in more than 30 states, the department is headed toward becoming the Government's largest environmental agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Less than two years after the Energy Department acknowledged it had caused grave pollution problems at active and inactive nuclear weapons plants in more than 30 states, the department is headed toward becoming the Government's largest environmental agency.</p>
        <p>Less than two years after the Energy Department acknowledged it had caused grave pollution problems at active and inactive nuclear weapons plants in more than 30 states, the department is headed toward becoming the Government's largest environmental agency.</p>
        <p>Accelerated by the end of the cold war, new spending by the Department on its own environmental problems is soaring, while the Environmental Protection Agency is receiving only modest budget increases.</p>
        <p>Nuclear weapons plants that have sustained the worst environmental damage of any Government installation are now base camps for biologists, chemists, soil scientists, hydrologists, engineers and other technical specialists. Lured by multimillion-dollar contracts, they are beginning a research and cleanup program that could cost $200 billion or more over the next 30 years and is destined to become one of the country's largest and most expensive public works projects.</p>
        <p>Test of Government's Ability</p>
        <p>At the Hanford Reservation nuclear plant in Washington State alone, the environmental thrust could swell employment from the current 13,000 workers to 15,000 in a couple of years.</p>
        <p>The cleanup program at nuclear weapons plants is emerging as a costly test of the Government's ability to confront complex environmental problems. And the rush of attention and spending has top Energy Department officials, Congressional leaders and critics worried.</p>
        <p>Representative Mike Synar, an Oklahoma Democrat who is the chairman of a House committee that has spent years investigating the Energy Department, said: ''Is there an anxious feeling in Congress about this cleanup program? You better believe it.</p>
        <p>''We know we're turning this over to the same contractors that caused the problem, the same people who watched it happen and did little or nothing to prevent it. They are being rewarded for the past mistakes. But we have no other choice but to let the fox clean up the chicken house.''</p>
        <p>A Reversal in Priorities</p>
        <p>The enormous spending on environmental programs, which began in 1989 under John S. Herrington, the former Energy Secretary, and has grown under Secretary James D. Watkins, represents a nearly complete turnaround for the nuclear weapons industry. For 48 years, production of nuclear materials for atomic bombs was regarded by top officials and line workers alike as the industry's most important job.</p>
        <p>Evidence of the new priorities came a year ago, when Mr. Watkins said bonuses to contractors who run the weapons plants would be based more on their environmental performance than on meeting production quotas.</p>
        <p>Pushed by the public, by Congress and by its own safety officers, the Energy Department has acknowledged the extent of the problems and is sending technical experts around the country to devise cleanup plans.</p>
        <p>In no other nuclear weapons plant in the United States has the transformation from producing materials for atomic weapons to cleaning up radioactive and chemical wastes come more suddenly than at the 560-square-mile Hanford Reservation near Richland in eastern Washington. Hanford began operating in 1943 to manufacture plutonium for the bomb that destroyed Nagasaki two years later, and continued producing atomic weapon material until December 1988, when its last processing plant was closed for safety reasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins vowed a year ago to turn Hanford into what he called ''a world class environmental research laboratory,'' and has lavished hundreds of millions of dollars on the plant this year for a cleanup program that could last 50 years or more and cost $50 billion, according to some estimates.</p>
        <p>In Richland and its neighboring cities, Pasco and Kennewick, the prices of homes are increasing, office space is becoming more scarce and a boom-town atmosphere is taking hold as contractors move in to share the cleanup money.</p>
        <p>Defense Department, Too</p>
        <p>The Defense Department, which this year will spend $600 million on cleaning up chemical lagoons, water and other contamination, is also awakening to the extensive pollution at its own bases and production plants around the country. In June, Senator Sam Nunn, the Georgia Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, proposed shifting substantial sums from production of equipment to solving environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department acknowledges that its record on large projects has been poor over the last two decades. More than $15 billion was spent since the mid-1970's on new plants that simply did not work or failed to work as promised, department audits show. Billions more was spent on excess costs due to poor management.</p>
        <p>Last month the Energy Department said the cost of cleaning up the weapons industry in the next five years would be 50 percent higher than it estimated just a year ago. The department has sought management assistance from the Army Corps of Engineers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins and his top environmental official, Leo P. Duffy, have said the agency has neither the technical experts nor the technology for the project, which is the most complex the nuclear weapons industry has tackled since the 1940's and early 1950's when the atomic bomb was invented and the industry was created.</p>
        <p>This fiscal year, the Energy Department will spend $2.3 billion to develop plans and start cleanup programs in the weapons industry, almost a quarter of the $9.65 billion to be spent on nuclear weapons programs. The department's total environmental budget this fiscal year is $3.4 billion, the agency comptroller's office said.</p>
        <p>May Overtake E.P.A.'s Spending</p>
        <p>In the 1991 fiscal year, which begins in October, the Energy Department's budget for environmental programs will grow to $4.3 billion, more than four times what it was in 1985. Most of the money, $2.7 billion, is to be spent on programs at the agency's weapons plants and laboratories in 12 states.</p>
        <p>If spending on waste and pollution in the nuclear weapons industry continues to grow at the pace it has for the past two years, the Energy Department may overtake the Environmental Protection Agency as the Government's largest environmental agency in 1992, budget officers in both agencies say.</p>
        <p>The budget for the Environmental Protection Agency, which oversees environmental programs for the entire country, is $3.1 billion this year, including $1.3 billion for the program to clean up the worst toxic waste sites. In addition, the E.P.A. administers $2.4 billion for sewer projects and water treatment plants, bringing its total budget this year to $5.5 billion. In the 1991 fiscal year, the E.P.A. budget will grow to $5.8 billion, according to Congressional and agency estimates.</p>
        <p>Dangers Were Known</p>
        <p>In its 45 years of producing materials for weapons, Hanford's nuclear reactors, processing plants, machine shops and other installations produced radioactive wastes that will remain toxic for centuries.</p>
        <p>The plants managers knew of the danger, Government documents show, but in the 1940's, 50's and 60's they sought to save money and routinely dumped millions of gallons of radioactive material on the ground or into shallow pits, long trenches and ponds. Contamination on the surface is spreading by 20 acres annually, the most recent analysis shows, and radiation is steadily leaking into groundwater and the Columbia River.</p>
        <p>Where the managers took precautions of isolating the most dangerous wastes in tanks, studies have shown that some has leaked. Westinghouse Hanford Company, the Westinghouse subsidiary that has operated the plant for the Energy Department since 1987, has identified 1,100 sites that are contaminated. The Energy Department last year signed an agreement with the State and the E.P.A. that sets a 30-year schedule for cleaning them up.</p>
        <p>''We give Hanford credit for helping the nation maintain its strategic deterrent for so many years,'' Mr. Watkins said last month at a news conference in Washington. ''But now is the time to pay the piper and clean up the 40 years of generation of a variety of waste.''</p>
        <p>The difficulty and expense of the task are illustrated by several projects under way at Hanford that are costing fortunes. In one, slightly radioactive chemicals are being removed from four concrete pools, each about as large as an Olympic-sized swimming pool. The job, begun in 1985, will not be completed until 1992 and will cost nearly $16 million.</p>
        <p>Encasing Wastes in Glass</p>
        <p>The largest environmental project currently planned for Hanford is a $1.44 billion plant that will turn 28,000 cubic yards of radioactive liquid and sludge into glass, an easier form for permanent storage. Compounding the problem is that some of this waste in tanks at Hanford has broken down chemically and could explode, Energy Department specialists say.</p>
        <p>The plant is in its final design stage and could be completed by the end of the decade. A similar plant has been built in South Carolina at the Savannah River Plant but is not operating properly. Robert W. Brown, the deputy project manager at Hanford, promises that ''our plant will work when it's finished.''</p>
        <p>As important as the new equipment is, changing the longtime attitudes of Hanford's workers toward environmental matters is even more vital for the project to succeed. Energy Department officials have been urging Hanford's 13,000 workers for months to replace their fervor for fighting the cold war with new zeal for confronting an opponent many have long regarded with contempt.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the officials are having some success, if only because that is a cause for which they have shown they are willing to spend money. ''Are we all becoming environmentalists? Not likely,'' said Jerry Holloway, a spokesman for Battelle Pacific Northwest laboratories, a division of Battelle Memorial Institute that is one of Hanford's largest contractors and a center of environmental research here. ''But we can see where the money is going and where the jobs are.''</p>
        <p>Only two years ago, as Hanford's military mission ended, economists were predicting a slump in the area's economy. Now some are worried about a housing shortage; employment at the plant is expected to grow to 14,000 next year and could reach 15,000 or more, the highest in decades.</p>
        <p>The money being spent on the cleanup has tempted top Energy Department officials who are pursuing environmental contracts. Michael J. Lawrence, the manager of Hanford since 1984, left the Energy Department on July 28 after a 21-year career to become a top executive at Chem-Nuclear Environmental Services, a subsidiary of Waste Management Inc. that was formed in January to compete for Energy and Defense Department environmental contracts at Hanford and other weapons plants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
