<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Among The Gators</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="OBSERVER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, RUSSELL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DE153FF93BA15751C0A966958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Among The Gators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Russell Baker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BAKER, RUSSELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: We are somewhere in Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: We are somewhere in Florida.</p>
        <p>We are somewhere in Florida.</p>
        <p>Monday we went to see alligators. They were basking in a ditch of muddy water by the side of the road. Afterward we bought postcards on which a cartoon alligator said, ''See ya later, alligator.'' We shall send these to young people who are schoolbound in the wretched North.</p>
        <p>Even before seeing the alligators we knew it was wretched in the North. Cheery television weathermen were full of it. Nineteen degrees in Boston. Ten inches of snow. It was news to gladden the heart of Northerners paying plenty to be in Florida.</p>
        <p>One reason for paying such sums is to have the heart gladdened by this very news, and one of our party went through the house waking others with a happy cry of ''Freezing and misery back home!''</p>
        <p>Soon he was on the phone to New York to verify the good news with a firsthand report from an actual sufferer. ''Yes,'' said the faraway sufferer, ''it's bitter cold up here.''</p>
        <p>After that, seeking alligators seemed like a grand idea. Living alligators in a muddy ditch would be added confirmation that we really had crossed over into a better world.</p>
        <p>This could not be satisfactorily confirmed by jumping into the swimming pool, for, to tell the truth, it was a little too cool to be pooling it up. The delightful nasty weather chilling the distant North had set disagreeable winds romping over Florida, and we did not want the day's pleasure spoiled by emerging from pools to find ourselves covered with goose pimples.</p>
        <p>Other people's weather has always held an unhealthy fascination for visitors to Florida. I used to think this reflected badly on Florida. A state where the biggest news of the day was the temperature in Philadelphia, I thought, must surely be the infamous Back of Beyond.</p>
        <p>Mature reflection on my own frailties has since persuaded me that the emptiness was not in Florida, but in the traveler from the North's concrete grayness. Those who travel only to experience a change in the weather are unlikely to experience travel's mind-broadening benefits.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time people went to California, too, for the weather, but that no longer seems to be what draws so many there. Along the way, California outgrew weather dependency and became a place people visit for the same infinite variety of reasons they visit New York, London or Hong Kong - because it seems like another country.</p>
        <p>Florida is not yet so distinctly another country as California, but it seems to be getting there. The question is whether the country it becomes will be a place anybody will still want to visit for anything but a change of weather.</p>
        <p>Here, for instance, is the capital punishment news. The paper says California, that most progressive of new nations, is on the edge of its first execution since the Supreme Court restored the ultimate punishment in 1976.</p>
        <p>While I was studying this story of California, the television set was running a political commercial in which Florida's Governor, Bob Martinez, boasted that he had already signed 95 death warrants and would not hesitate to sign more.</p>
        <p>Willingness to dispense the death penalty freely since 1976 has been a characteristic peculiar to states of the old Confederacy, which tend toward the romantic view of antique institutions.</p>
        <p>It's curious to find such a taste for it in Florida, a state singularly free of romantic delusions and, indeed, proud of the speed with which it has beaten the bleak industrial states at their own blight. A recent traffic study, for instance, states that by the time today's newborn tots buy their first car, I-95 between Miami and Fort Lauderdale will have to be 22 lanes wide to avert traffic paralysis.</p>
        <p>Half of the Everglades is already lost to real-estate development. Sanibel Island, a natural treasure, is inundated with an endless stream of cars crawling bumper-to-bumper across a bridge that probably should never have been built. Yet talk of building another is now in the air.</p>
        <p>A Fish and Wildlife Service guide lecturing us the other day on a culture of extinct Indians said they had succumbed after flourishing for 1,000 years. Why? Spanish missionaries came to bring them Christianity, but the Indians had no immune defenses against alien European diseases brought by those who had come for their salvation.</p>
        <p>Today's Spanish missionaries in Florida are the real-estate developer and the automobile.</p>
        <p>And already warming up in New York, you say? Alas, nothing but gloom everywhere today.</p>
        <p>OBSERVER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
