<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Modern Opulence in Old Town Houses</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19901216T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="405704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UPPER EAST SIDE (MANHATTAN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COSBY, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERELMAN, RONALD O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEXNER, LESLIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D9173EF931A35751C1A966958260" item-length="1872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Modern Opulence in Old Town Houses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAWN G. KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVENTY-FIVE years after an elegant epoch in domestic architecture created some of New York's grandest houses on the blocks just east of Fifth Avenue, a new generation of affluent owners is putting opulent 1990's-style residences behind their richly embellished facades.</p>
        <p>Many of these buildings had become schools and foundation offices, and the current remodelings represent a return to the single-family occupancy they were built for. But in their new state they will have amenities never thought of by their builders, such as complete climate-control systems, rooms with a panoply of facsimile machines and other communications devices, multiple guest suites and, in one case, separate temperature-controlled wine cellars for red and white wines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVENTY-FIVE years after an elegant epoch in domestic architecture created some of New York's grandest houses on the blocks just east of Fifth Avenue, a new generation of affluent owners is putting opulent 1990's-style residences behind their richly embellished facades.</p>
        <p>Many of these buildings had become schools and foundation offices, and the current remodelings represent a return to the single-family occupancy they were built for. But in their new state they will have amenities never thought of by their builders, such as complete climate-control systems, rooms with a panoply of facsimile machines and other communications devices, multiple guest suites and, in one case, separate temperature-controlled wine cellars for red and white wines.</p>
        <p>In one regard, however, the new owners will live as the the original owners did; they are devoting generous amounts of space to servants' quarters so they can have live-in help.</p>
        <p>At 18 East 71st Street work is nearing completion on a $1.2 million interior reconstruction for the new owner, Bill Cosby. The five-story house had held a succession of small, private schools, the last of them Le Camp Francais, until it was bought by Mr. Cosby in 1987. Real estate records show that the price was $6.2 million. Mr. Cosby and his family have not yet moved in, but most of the top-to-bottom renovation and restoration work has been done.</p>
        <p>Across the street at 9 East 71st Street, Leslie Wexner, who owns the Limited, Lane Bryant and Victoria's Secret stores as well as the Henri Bendel specialty store on West 57th Street, is building a home in the former Birch Wathen School. The school sold the building to Mr. Wexner for an estimated $13.2 million before relocating last summer to 210 East 77th Street.</p>
        <p>And three blocks to the north, the French Renaissance style mansion at 4 East 75th Street, which for 25 years was home to the Harkness Ballet Foundation, is being turned back into a private home. The buyer, was Jaqui Safra, a principal of the Safra National Bank. In yet another recent deal, the Fleming School sold two of its buildings at 35 East 62d Street to Ronald O. Perelman, chairman of Revlon Group and a significant player in the merger and acquisitions arena on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Brokers do not believe these high level transactions signal a reversal of an otherwise weak housing market. Rather, they maintain that the purchases reflect the continuing demand among very wealthy people for huge, prewar houses.</p>
        <p>"There are just not that many properties in the best locations that are also can be used as single-family residences," said Joan Ambrose, a principal of Ambrose-Mar Elia Company, a brokerage specializing in town-house sales. "There will always be people who want to live in a grand manner or who want the freedom to do what they please with their homes without having to consult with a co-op board for each change or addition."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ambrose said many of the town-house properties on the blocks between Fifth and Park Avenues became available for purchase when the schools that owned them realized they were sitting on little gold mines. "Prices for these buildings went so high in the mid-80's," she said, "that the schools saw the opportunity to cash in their assets by giving up prime locations for more space further east or on the West Side."</p>
        <p>These mansions and town houses range in size from about 5,000 to more than 20,000 square feet and are significantly larger than typical family-sized apartments in prewar co-ops.</p>
        <p>Halina Rosenthal, president of Friends of the Upper East Side Historic Districts, a non-profit preservation organization, believes that the return to private ownership of these mansions and town houses offers another layer of a protection for them.</p>
        <p>"We do have the landmark districts," Mrs. Rosenthal said, "and that is the most important part of neighborhood preservation. But when these buildings become private homes there is a better chance that they will be taken care of and not deteriorate to the point where they can't be saved."</p>
        <p>The houses now being remodeled were built at a time when wealthy New Yorkers and their architects looked to Europe for inspiration. Their partiality to neo-classic architecture borrowed from the Italian palazzo and French Beaux-Arts style is evident in the designs of many residences on the blocks off Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Most of the private houses built in the neighborhood went up between 1910 and 1930. But town house and mansion construction slowed after large luxurious apartment buildings started rising along Fifth Avenue in the 1920's and 1930's. The burdens of keeping household staffs, paying taxes and protecting the property when the family was away also contributed to the decline in popularity of single-family residences in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>By the late 1940's many of the mansions and large town houses off Fifth Avenue that had not been converted to multifamily dwellings were being turned into clubs, schools, medical group practices, the missions of foreign governments and office space for foundations.</p>
        <p>WHENEVER a building's use is changed or reconverted from, say, a school or hospital back into a residence, the owners are required to obtain revised certificates of occupancy from the City's Department of Buildings indicating the new use.</p>
        <p>While none of the new owners or their architects would discuss the work being done, documents that are public records on file with the Department of Buildings and the city's Landmark Preservation Commisssion provide some details of their plans.</p>
        <p>Under way at 9 East 71st Street is an $8 million reconstruction of a 21,000-square-foot mansion built in the early 1930's for a heir to the R.H. Macy and Abraham &amp; Straus fortunes.</p>
        <p>Curiously, when the new owner, Mr. Wexner, moves in, he will be the mansion's first private resident. The first owner, Herbert M. Sraus, son of Isadore Straus, a founder of Abraham &amp; Straus as well as Macy's, died in 1933 before the residence was completed. The seven-story building, design by Horace Trombauer, a prominent architect of the time, stood unfinished and empty for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>In 1944, Mr. Straus's heirs turned the residence over to St. Clare's Hospital for use as a convalescence home. In 1962, the Birch Wathen School bought the building and built classrooms, offices, laboratories, a library, a cafeteria and an assembly hall in the mansion.</p>
        <p>Floor plans for the new interior suggest a home designed for an owner who expects to entertain on a grand scale and have frequent overnight guests. The cellar, for example, will have separate storage chambers for red and white wines as well as two room-sized closets where china and silver will be kept. Also to be installed are a dumbwaiter to transport meals from the basement level kitchen to a warming pantry off the dining room on the first floor.</p>
        <p>The fourth floor, reserved for guests, will have three three-room suites as well as a guest sitting room. The reconstructed residence will have five powder rooms and an oval-shaped, two-story reception room.</p>
        <p>Although much of the redesign incorporates a lifestyle of a bygone era -- more than 2,000 square feet has been set aside for staff living quarters and locker rooms -- space-age technology will provide the new owner with a level of comfort and convenience not often found in private homes. In addition to tradional residential living and work spaces, included in the design for the mansion is a communications room, a telephone equipment room and a security room.</p>
        <p>The Landmarks Preservation Commission has approved one significant change to the building's exterior. In order to accomodate the building's new elevators and a new heating, ventilation and air-conditioning system, a rooftop extension had to be built. The entire building will be mechanically ventilated through a system that will draw air from the outside at the top of the building and then heat, cool or dehumidify it as necessary.</p>
        <p>These new mechanical systems required demolition of the existing roof and the construction of new bulkhead for the elevators and heating and airconditioning system. The new work will extend the building's roofline by about eight feet but the bulkheads will be clad in limestone and brick to match the facade.</p>
        <p>ACROSS the street work interior work is proceeding on Mr. Cosby's six-story town house at No. 18. Designed by John H. Duncan, the neo-classical building has detailing borrowed from the Beaux Arts and Second Empire styles. It is a twin of the house next door at No. 16, also designed by Duncan. Both were built in 1911.</p>
        <p>The architectural firm of Doman &amp; Associates was responsible for the renovation project, which included the restoration of the house's slate mansard roof, copper dormers and cornice and stone balustrade.</p>
        <p>The most significant change by the new owner was a four-story addition at the rear which will provide the house with a two-story indoor garden and a solarium. Other newly built features are a skylight, wooden deck and roof garden.</p>
        <p>Plans on file with the Buildings Department show that the former school building's meeting rooms in the sub cellar have been converted to storage space while the office on the first floor was turned into a library. Classrooms have been converted into a living room, a study, six bedroom suites and a top floor entertainment area.</p>
        <p>Although sold to its current owner in June of 1987, work to remodel the mansion at 4 East 75th Street has not started. A canopy bearing the name of its former owner, the Harkness dance company, still stretches from the entrance to the curb. But preliminary plans and a request for interior alteration permits were recently submitted by Paulo Schoichet, a Manhattan architect.</p>
        <p>The structure, which is 50 feet wide and occupies two standard building lots, was built in 1896 for Nathaniel L. McCready. The architectural firm of Trowbridge, Colt &amp; Livingston is credited with the neo-French Renaissance design of the structure, which has nearly 18,000 square feet of space. During the 1940's the mansion served as the residence of Thomas J. Watson Jr., the first president of I.B.M.</p>
        <p>In 1965, Rebekah Harkness, an heiress to the Standard Oil fortune, bought the building for the ballet company and school. The firm of Rogers, Butler &amp; Burgun was hired to turn the mansion into space appropriate for the dance company and school. In the process, a box office and cloakrooms were built in the ground floor entrance hall, a stage was added to the grand ballroom on the third floor and bedrooms and family living quarters on the upper floors were converted to dance rehearsal studios, music rooms and workshops for dance company carpenters and costumers.</p>
        <p>For the past 25 years Harkness House, as the residence came to be known, was a frequent site for dance performances and art exhibitions. The building was also rented for private parties, meeting and weddings.</p>
        <p>Among the changes proposed in the preliminary plans are the addition of a skylight, and the conversion of former ballroom into a livingroom and dining room and the creation of seven bedrooms, four bathrooms and two libraries in the space that held the dance center's studios and workrooms.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 16, 1990, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Dec. 2 about the conversions of Manhattan town houses back into private homes misstated the number of buildings purchased by Ronald O. Perelman. He bought one, at 35 East 62d Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 16, 1990, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Dec. 2 about the conversions of Manhattan town houses back into private homes misstated the number of buildings purchased by Ronald O. Perelman. He bought one, at 35 East 62d Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
