<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The United Nations Comes of Age, Causing Some Anxiety</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SECURITY COUNCIL (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6173EF936A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The United Nations Comes of Age, Causing Some Anxiety</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WITH the end of the cold war, the United States and the Soviet Union are forging a working alliance at the United Nations that offers the organization its first real chance in 45 years to function as it is supposed to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WITH the end of the cold war, the United States and the Soviet Union are forging a working alliance at the United Nations that offers the organization its first real chance in 45 years to function as it is supposed to.</p>
        <p>WITH the end of the cold war, the United States and the Soviet Union are forging a working alliance at the United Nations that offers the organization its first real chance in 45 years to function as it is supposed to.</p>
        <p>The two superpowers and the three other permanent Security Council members - Britain, France and China - are finding that they can play their assigned role as custodians of international order, working together to try to resolve conflicts in the Persian Gulf, Namibia, Central America, Cambodia and the Western Sahara.</p>
        <p>After Iraq's troops stormed into Kuwait last week, the Soviet Union and the United States were shoulder to shoulder again in the Security Council, running their first joint crisis-management exercise in the United Nations. They pushed through a resolution condemning the invasion and threatening Iraq with global economic sanctions if it did not pull out.</p>
        <p>The more cooperative atmosphere within the Security Council is rubbing off on the General Assembly, encouraging the third-world majority there to drop its anti-Western polemics in favor of consensus.</p>
        <p>Over the last year, the General Assembly has unanimously endorsed the importance of free markets and democracy in development, banned ecologically harmful fishing nets, accepted white South Africans' right to safeguards under black rule and agreed to negotiate a treaty on stabilizing the world's climate by 1992, all at the urging of the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>But the superpowers' emerging partnership belies wide differences in their perceptions of the organization. It also arouses the suspicions of third world countries, who fear that the organization will become an instrument for imposing the views of the northern industrialized nations on the developing south.</p>
        <p>''Since the renaissance at the United Nations is closely linked to the strengthened role of the permanent Security Council members, it raises fears in the south of an hegemonic directorate,'' Olga Pellicer, Mexico's deputy representative at the United Nations, said in a recent address.</p>
        <p>In recent years the Soviet Union has gradually set forth a vision of the United Nations as the cornerstone of a more cooperative world order, guided by a powerful Security Council ready to intervene in crises and tackle environmental perils and other new threats to security.</p>
        <p>Moscow has backed its vision with cash, agreeing to pay more than $210 million due the organization. This year it upgraded its presence at the United Nations by appointing a Deputy Foreign Minister, Yuli M. Vorontsov, as its new chief delegate.</p>
        <p>But while Moscow was warming to the United Nations, Washington was lukewarm at best. For most of its two terms the Reagan Administration was openly contemptuous of the organization. President Bush, a former Ambassador to the United Nations, appears more sympathetic, but America's response to Moscow's change of heart remains cautious.</p>
        <p>American diplomats argue that the existing machinery should be given a chance to work and stress the difficulty of financing grandiose initiatives like those suggested by Moscow.</p>
        <p>Many members of Congress continue to view the United Nations and its agencies as inefficient, bloated bureacracies often hostile to American interests. Their skepticism has led to the withholding of $675 million due the organization.</p>
        <p>Ending the East-West Deadlock</p>
        <p>Washington and Moscow also differ sharply over the Middle East, with the United States opposing Soviet demands for a major United Nations role in making peace between Israel and its Arab neighbors.</p>
        <p>In a new Council on Foreign Relations study, George L. Sherry, a former United Nations official, says America's caution may reflect the fact that it is torn between competing impulses.</p>
        <p>After winning the cold war, Washington is tempted to pursue a unilateral foreign policy, he argues, as suggested by the Panama invasion. On the other hand, he says, Washington also knows it now has a rare chance ''to establish a peaceful, civilized world order.''</p>
        <p>Sir Brian Urquhart, the former top peacekeeping official at the United Nations, said he believes that the United States is not moving fast enough to exploit Moscow's changed views and develop the peacekeeping potential of the organization. He likened present arrangements to ''a sheriff's posse'' that rides out only after the rustlers have gone.</p>
        <p>The most dramatic manifestation of the new American-Soviet cooperation at the United Nations came in last year's jointly sponsored General Assembly resolution in which the two superpowers promised to work together to strengthen the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs, John R. Bolton, the top Bush Admninistration official in charge of United Nations issues, said the resolution reflects ''major changes in our bilateral relationship that will end the East-West deadlock at the United Nations.'' Many observers believe that Moscow's enthusiasm for the United Nations stems directly from a commitment to change at home and reflects a belief that a more peaceful world will allow it to cut military spending and develop its own economy.</p>
        <p>''For the Soviets the United Nations is emerging not as a vehicle of retreat but as a less costly and more legitimate way to influence events,'' wrote Thomas G. Weiss of Brown University and Meryl A. Kessler of Harvard University in a new study of Moscow's United Nations policy.</p>
        <p>Although Moscow was looking for a better relationship with Washington before Mikhail S. Gorbachev came to power in 1985, it was only in September 1987 that the Soviet leader set forth his view of a pivotal role for the United Nations. It came in a landmark article in Pravda uninvitingly titled ''The Reality and Guarantees of a Secure World.''</p>
        <p>'A Wilsonian Vision'</p>
        <p>During the cold war, Soviet leaders had treated the United Nations with suspicion, seeing it as at best a platform for anti-Western propaganda, at worst an obstacle to world revolution.</p>
        <p>But in the article, Mr. Gorbachev offered what Prof. Richard N. Gardner of Columbia University calls ''a Wilsonian vision'' of a world ruled by international law, with a reinforced Security Council, expanded use of peacekeeping forces, a stronger World Court and new organs to deal with global challenges.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries fear that the emerging United States-Soviet cooperation means that the superpowers will be tempted to impose the industrial world's priorities, like environmental protection, human rights and fighting the drug trade. Third-world nations fear that their overriding concerns, like debt, falling raw-material prices and developmental aid, will be overlooked.</p>
        <p>''It is always their agenda, not ours,'' Mrs. Pellicer, the Mexican diplomat, said.</p>
        <p>As a result, the third world is now fighting a rear-guard action against the superpowers' growing influence. Developing countries have thwarted efforts to give the Security Council a say in environmental matters and the war against narcotics.</p>
        <p>While the Security Council is resolving some civil wars, Ethiopia, the Sudan, Somalia, Mozambique and Sri Lanka testily resist United Nations mediation in their internal conflicts.</p>
        <p>Many diplomats say that the more assertive third world mood will make it harder to achieve new global agreements, particularly environmental accords that require developing countries to comply with new international standards.</p>
        <p>And if the United Nations cannot produce global solutions, nations may prefer regional answers. As part of its efforts to knit a divided continent together, the 35-nation Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe plans its own institutions for resolving disputes, protecting the environment and enforcing human rights.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
