<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH NAMES PANEL FOR ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DA123CF937A15754C0A967958260" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH NAMES PANEL FOR ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to tap the expertise of groups that have historically been at odds, President Bush today named 25 members to a panel to advise him on how to slow the destruction of the environment but not at inordinate expense to business.</p>
        <p>The panel includes top executives from some of the nation's largest industrial companies, like Dow Chemical, Ford and General Electric, as well as from prominent conservation groups like the Environmental Defense Fund, the World Wildlife Fund and National Geographic Society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to tap the expertise of groups that have historically been at odds, President Bush today named 25 members to a panel to advise him on how to slow the destruction of the environment but not at inordinate expense to business.</p>
        <p>The panel includes top executives from some of the nation's largest industrial companies, like Dow Chemical, Ford and General Electric, as well as from prominent conservation groups like the Environmental Defense Fund, the World Wildlife Fund and National Geographic Society.</p>
        <p>In establishing the President's Commission on Environmental Quality, the White House said in a statement that Mr. Bush planned to use the group to advance his belief that the solution to some environmental problems was not more laws but innovation and cooperation between environmental groups, trade associations and polluters.</p>
        <p>"Over the last 20 years, the nation has made notable progress in addressing many of our environmental problems," the statement said. "However, the costs of the traditional regulatory regime are substantial and many issues do not lend themselves to regulatory solutions." Skepticism on Motives</p>
        <p>But critics of the Administration's environmental policy said today that the panel was simply part of Mr. Bush's political strategy on environmental issues: making appointments that seem to have broad popular support while undermining the Government's environmental regulatory structure.</p>
        <p>"This commission cannot replace the Administration's responsibility to enforce the laws that Congress passed, which requires regulation to reduce pollution," said Representative Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Health and the Environment.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Waxman's subcommittee made public an array of documents that he said showed that the Energy Department and the White House had improperly influenced the Environmental Protection Agency and gained exemptions from the Clean Air Act for old coal-fueled power plants. Under the proposed new rule, the old power plants would be allowed to pour much more pollution into the atmosphere and save the electric power industry $5 billion.</p>
        <p>Leaders of several environmental groups today also cited other examples of what they said was the Administration's strategy of aiding industrial companies by reducing or limiting regulations. Earlier this year, the White House Competitiveness Council, a group of Administration officials led by Vice President Dan Quayle, blocked a proposal by the Environmental Protection Agency to require municipal incinerators to establish recycling programs. The council also defeated a plan by the agency to discourage the incineration of lead batteries, a source not only of lead in the atmosphere, but also of mercury that is contaminating lakes in the Great Lakes region, New York and New England.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Deland, the chairman of the White House Council on Environmental Quality and the chairman of the new commission, said today that President Bush was not seeking to repeal or withdraw from the Government's program for regulating pollution.</p>
        <p>"The President feels very strongly that the command and control and highly prescriptive regulatory structure that we have had for the last 20 years has served us well," Mr. Deland said. "Yet we have paid a significant amount for it. The pollution control costs in 1990 alone were $115 billion which is 2.1 percent of G.N.P."</p>
        <p>During the group's first meeting today, a representative of the McDonald's Corporation described how the fast-food restaurant chain had designed new paper packaging and a model recycling program with the help of the Environmental Defense Fund, a New York-based environmental group.</p>
        <p>Another panel member is Allen F. Jacobson, chairman and chief executive officer of Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Company. Mr. Jacobson has been among the first American industrialists to embrace the idea that preventing pollution saves money, and under his guidance 3M has developed one of the world's best programs for eliminating pollution from manufacturing plants.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Members of Commission</p>
        <p>Following is the list of commission members:</p>
        <p>Michael R. Deland, chairman of White House Council on Environmental Quality, chairman. William D. Ruckelshaus, chairman and chief executive officer of Browning-Ferris Industries, vice chairman.</p>
        <p>Edwin L. Artzt, Procter &amp; Gamble; Dr. Marguerite Ross Barnett, president, University of Houston; Riley P. Bechtel, Bechtel Group Inc.; Dean L. Buntrock, Waste Management Inc.; Richard A. Clarke, Pacific Gas and Electric Company in San Francisco; Derrick Crandall, American Recreation Coalition; Kenneth T. Derr, Chevron Corporation; Robert Fri, Resources for the Future; Kathryn S. Fuller, the World Wildlife Fund and the Conservation Foundation; John A. Georges, International Paper Company; Dr. Paul Edward Gray, chairman, Corporation for Massachusetts Institute of Technology; Gilbert M. Grosvenor, National Geographic Society; Allen F. Jacobsen, Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing; Fred Krupp, Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>Kenneth L. Lay, Enron Corporation; Richard P. Mayer, Kraft General Foods North American; N. J. Nicholas Jr., Time Warner Inc.; Patrick F. Noonan, Conservation Fund; Harold A. Poling, Ford Motor Company; Frank P. Popoff, Dow Chemical; Adele Simmons, John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation; Dr. P. Roy Vagelos, Merck &amp; Company; John F. Welch Jr., General Electric.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
