<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmental Rules: How They Dictate Region's Agenda</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC WORKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPECTER, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Works</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC113AF936A15752C1A967958260" item-length="1582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmental Rules: How They Dictate Region's Agenda</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SPECTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SPECTER, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades they have been little more than fantasies: Automated people movers gliding swiftly between New York's airports, and electronic fare cards shepherding drivers effortlessly through the city's tolls.</p>
        <p>Nice ideas, it has often been said, but hopeless. Yet, for an unlikely reason, the visions have recently come alive. They are now considered essential because rigorous new air quality standards demand them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades they have been little more than fantasies: Automated people movers gliding swiftly between New York's airports, and electronic fare cards shepherding drivers effortlessly through the city's tolls.</p>
        <p>Nice ideas, it has often been said, but hopeless. Yet, for an unlikely reason, the visions have recently come alive. They are now considered essential because rigorous new air quality standards demand them.</p>
        <p>After years of indifference, the city has also embarked on a vast program to install water meters in hundreds of thousands of homes and apartment buildings. Again, the reason was indirect. Without them, punitive rationing measures would soon become inevitable. Almost by default, environmental regulations -- and the relentless advocates who use them most effectively -- have begun to dictate the physical shape and priorities of the region.</p>
        <p>From the most ambitious bridges to the smallest playground, from airports and highways to shopping malls and boat slips, legal requirements and protests rather than planning now orchestrate nearly every decision a builder or government can make.</p>
        <p>"We plan by not doing," said Robert J. Pirani, director of environmental projects for the Regional Plan Association. "The mechanism is all backward. Fear is the driving force. Instead of sitting around and saying what kind of place do we want to become, we are wondering what punishments we can avoid."</p>
        <p>While laws with brutal sanctions provide handy ammunition for opponents of growth, so has the recession, which has dimmed the vision of many of the regions most ambitious developers.  Unfinished Projects</p>
        <p>The combined results are easy to see. From Westway, which never was built, to the contested Meadowbrook Parkway on Long Island, which was, projects have been delayed, scuttled, diminished. Often those that proceed -- like the huge Metrotech office and research complex in Brooklyn or the final stretch of Interstate 287 in northern New Jersey -- do so only after years of negotiation and a stream of concessions.</p>
        <p>Except for Los Angeles, air quality does not get much worse than in the three states of the metropolitan region. Together, they have been violating the Clean Air Act for two decades. But a set of new sanctions that could ultimately force millions of drivers from their cars, has done more to promote mass transit -- and to discourage new highway construction -- than any politician possibly could.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, for example, has retreated from any serious plans to erect another bridge between New Jersey and Staten Island, even though many of its planners say traffic patterns argue for it strongly. The recession has played a role, of course. But the Clean Air Act, which gives this region 15 years to resolve some of its most intractable pollution problems, has proven far more compelling.</p>
        <p>The New York metropolitan region already has nearly twice the permissible amount of ozone in its atmosphere. The area stands to lose all highway funds if it does not begin to comply with Federal standards. In southern California, Federal officials have already begun to take away people's barbecue pits and gas-powered lawn movers. New York could face a similar fate.</p>
        <p>In addition, beginning this year, Federal law dictates that all new sources of pollution have to be more than compensated for by reductions nearby.</p>
        <p>The practical effects could be significant. For every major road that generates 1,000 new miles traveled by automobiles each day, for example, local officials must find a way to eliminate 1,200 miles traveled elsewhere. If they fail, the ratio will nearly double in the next decade.</p>
        <p>"We are all beginning to realize that we are going to have to make profound and continual adjustments to what we build and how we live," said Anthony E. Shorris, deputy executive director of the Port Authority. " It isn't just a question of whether it would be nice to alter our behavior. The regulations make it financially impossible for us to do anything else. All the incentives have changed, probably for good."</p>
        <p>Federal and local statutes are not the only deterrents. Skillful campaigns by those opposed to development have become routine, and routinely successful.  Battle Over Airport</p>
        <p>In Westchester, local officials have long envisioned an expanded county airport as a fitting anchor to development in the area. But with opponents bitterly insisting that bigger runways would bring intolerable levels of noise, water and air pollution -- in addition to unwelcome new traffic -- planners wonder if even their most modest goals may be impossible to attain.</p>
        <p>For more than a decade, the Postal Service has been trying to build a $100 million processing center in Westchester, to serve an area that the Postmaster General last year called the worst in the nation for mail service. Yet, after seeing its environmental-impact study assessing the risks to the region, New York City sued, contending the center would pollute important reservoirs. A Federal judge blocked its construction earlier this year.</p>
        <p>"If you build and you ignore the environmental consequences," said Michael Gerrard, an environmental law expert at the Manhattan law firm of Berle, Kass &amp; Case, "you do so at your own peril. We are now living with the consequence of generations of thoughtless development. It's time we learned our lesson."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerrard has interceded dozens of times, usually with success, on behalf of clients who say a project presents unacceptable environmental risks. He currently represents three towns north of Hartford that challenged Connecticut in an attempt to prevent the creation of a nuclear waste site in Ellington -- although the state will soon be unable to ship such waste to South Carolina, as it has done for years.</p>
        <p>"If it needs to be done," said Mr. Gerrard, voicing a sentiment shared widely by those who oppose such projects, "this is not the place to do it."</p>
        <p>The days of autocratic development, embodied most blatantly by Robert Moses, who sliced up neighborhoods and carpeted New York with highways, won't be back, planners, developers and environmentalists all agree. And few would argue that they should return. But people are starting to worry about what has replaced them. Without a coherent vision of where to place the roads, sewage plants, bridges and other essentials that all communities need -- those who scream the loudest have turned into those who make the rules.  Permissions the Hard Part</p>
        <p>Seeking permission to widen a road or build an incinerator has become more difficult than the actual construction.</p>
        <p>The Bronx Lebanon Hospital will be the first to use a new $20 million incinerator in an industrial section of the Bronx when it is completed next year. If local residents do not revolt. The incinerator was designed to handle medical waste, and it was placed where it would do the least harm to neighbors. Few complaints were heard until recently, as the project nears completion. Without it, New York will have to continue to export waste at great cost.</p>
        <p>To some this sort of activism is a telling achievement of the environmental movement. Yet, to others it is a disturbing combination of idealism and inflexibility. Many of those who worked hardest to guarantee that tough regulations would serve as a solid check on thoughtless expansion or greedy builders have been surprised by the speed with which opponents of development become "environmentalists."</p>
        <p>"Growth has to be driven by decent environmental protections and increasingly it has," said Thomas C. Jorling, commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation. "But we all hear the loud whine of people who use the environment to refuse to bear any responsibility for community well-being. I am just as scared by them as I am by polluters."</p>
        <p>The balance between producing sensible public works and protecting the land has never been harder to puzzle out. Eventually, critics and even some environmentalists are starting to ask, where will we find all the places to put the glamorless necessities on which most of life relies?</p>
        <p>"We need to respect the natural resources we have," said Ara K. Hovnanian, president of Hovnanian Enterprises in Red Bank, N.J., one of the nation's largest residential developers. "But if I only had a nickel for every person who opposes growth by calling themselves an environmentalist."  Real Concerns From Tirades</p>
        <p>Officials say they can have a hard time separating legitimate environmental complaints from standard no-growth tirades.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, for example, the relationship between a soaring rate of driving and dangerous levels of air pollution is easy to understand. Between 1970 and last year, Connecticut drivers increased the miles they traveled in automobiles by more than 63 percent, turning a once-quiet state into one of the most congested in the nation. Perhaps no highway in the state has become as impassable as Interstate 95.</p>
        <p>Several proposals have been put forth to widen the highway at strategic points, but engineers from the state Department of Transportation have grown understandably wary because any such action will only increase their struggle over air pollution.</p>
        <p>"All of the gains mandated by the Federal Clean Air Act would be wiped out in about six months by the increased traffic," said Donald Strait, legal director for the Connecticut Fund for the Environment. "How could you possibly do it?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
