<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>War's Hazards for Environment Are Assessed</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="417582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61F3CF937A15752C0A967958260" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>War's Hazards for Environment Are Assessed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The war in the Persian Gulf could have serious environmental consequences for the region, although most scientific opinion is that even an extensive burning of Kuwait's oilfields would not affect the global climate.</p>
        <p>Iraq is generally assumed to have mined the 360 active oil wells in Kuwait as well as refineries and storage tanks, and Iraqi leaders have threatened to destroy them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The war in the Persian Gulf could have serious environmental consequences for the region, although most scientific opinion is that even an extensive burning of Kuwait's oilfields would not affect the global climate.</p>
        <p>Iraq is generally assumed to have mined the 360 active oil wells in Kuwait as well as refineries and storage tanks, and Iraqi leaders have threatened to destroy them.</p>
        <p>In addition, there are fears that military action around the oil operations could lead to huge oil spills in the gulf, as happened in 1983 during the Iran-Iraq war. Obstacle to Troops</p>
        <p>"There are rumors of pipelines connecting wells to harbor areas," said Richard Golob, publisher of Golob's Oil Pollution Bulletin. "The idea is that the Iraqis would set it on fire as an obstacle to allied landing forces."</p>
        <p>If the wells and other operations were set on fire at the same time, some scientists say the resulting soot and smoke could cloud the skies downwind and possibly lower temperatures, thus disrupting harvests.</p>
        <p>An Iranian radio broadcast monitored by The Associated Press in Nicosia, Cyprus, yesterday reported that greasy "black rain" fell on part of Iran as a result of fires set Tuesday in the Wafara oilfield in southern Kuwait. The field is considered a small one, pumping less than 100,000 barrels a day before the Iraqi invasion on Aug 2. Total pre-invasion output in all of Kuwait was about 1.5 million barrels a day.</p>
        <p>A leading proponent of the theory that numerous oil well fires would lead to colder temperatures and other climatic change is Carl Sagan, the Cornell University astronomer and a developer of the theory that airborne debris from a nuclear war could cause a "nuclear winter."</p>
        <p>The assumption is that soot would rise into the stratosphere and linger, blocking some sunlight and lowering surface temperatures.</p>
        <p>Such an outcome in Kuwait could affect the growing season in areas like Iran, Afghanistan and northern India, which are in the path of the prevailing winds from Kuwait.  Volcanic Eruption Cited</p>
        <p>"There is real-world precedent for this," Mr. Sagan said. "In 1815 there was an eruption of the Mount Tamboro volcano in Indonesia that put large amounts of soot into the atmosphere. The following year, 1816, is known as the year without a summer."</p>
        <p>Accounts from that time report widespread snow in New England in June and crop failures in northern Europe. But Mr. Golob has calculated that even the burning of an entire year's output of Kuwaiti oil would produce only a small fraction of the material the Mount Tamboro explosion injected into the air.</p>
        <p>Other scientists say the wells in Kuwait are spaced far enough apart that there would be no cumulative effect that would cause soot to be projected higher into the atmosphere than usual. Dr. Richard D. Small, an atmospheric specialist at the Pacific Sierra Research Corporation, said "our simulations show the smoke will rise from one to three kilometers," which is low enough that it can be dispersed by normal winds.</p>
        <p>This was the same conclusion reached by researchers at the Sandia National Laboratories in a report to the Energy Department. The researchers said major global weather changes were "unlikely" because "normal phenomena in the lower atmosphere" will disperse the smoke. But it warned that there could be a measurable impact on the region.  Possible Effect on Monsoon</p>
        <p>The British Government's meteorological office similarly played down any global effect, but said soot-induced cooling could affect the monsoon rains that much of the Indian subcontinent relies on for agriculture. "Downwind of Kuwait, the obscuration of sunlight might significantly reduce the surface temperature locally," it said in a report last week. "This in turn could locally reduce rainfall over parts of Southeast Asia during periods of the summer monsoon."</p>
        <p>Mr. Small said burning of the Kuwaiti oilfields would be "a massive pollution event" even if no changes in climate occur. He estimated that 540,000 tons of soot would be injected into the air in the first month, if all the wells and refineries were set afire. Most would fall within two weeks on the countries downwind, he added.</p>
        <p>"You have to wonder what the impact will be on people breathing sooty air and livestock feeding on soot-covered grassland," he said.</p>
        <p>Others expressed concern about water pollution, which could occur if fighting erupts around oil platforms in the gulf. "In 1983 Iraqi fighters attacked the Nowruz oil facility of Iran, destroying two platforms and igniting fires which burned for nearly a year," said Brent Blackwelder, a vice president of the environmental organization Friends of the Earth.</p>
        <p>He said about 5,000 barrels of oil a day poured from the platforms, forming a slick that extended the entire length of the gulf and crippled fishing.</p>
        <p>Peter Montague of Greenpeace said, "The total amount of oil from that one spill was three times what was lost from the Exxon Valdez." Threat to Water Supplies</p>
        <p>Spilled oil could also pose a hazard to people living in the region, by endangering the seawater desalinization plants that provide much of their drinking water. "Currents in the gulf run counterclockwise, so spills in Kuwait would be carried down to Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, Qatar and the emirates," Mr. Golob said.</p>
        <p>Desalinization plants, he said, "cannot accept contaminated water" so they might have to shut down if oil slicks could not be blocked by booms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blackwelder said the plants were shut briefly during 1983 while defenses were put into place.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists also expressed concerns that air attacks on Iraq's plants that manufacture chemical and biological weapons could release long-lived toxins. "Mustard gas lasts a long time," Mr. Montague said. "There are people in France who are still being burned by mustard gas left over from World War I."</p>
        <p>Even the maneuvering of 500,000 troops in the desert will have an environmental impact, and may produce more frequent sand storms by disturbing the surface of the desert. "We know from what happened in North Africa in World War II that there is likely to be an increase in sand and dust storms," Mr. Blackwelder said. "Even today, 50 years later, the vegetation has only partly returned."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
