<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only the Wind Should Sigh in This 'Garden'</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RADIO CITY MUSIC HALL PRODUCTIONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARDS, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MINNELLI, LIZA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SECRET GARDEN, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB1631F936A35756C0A967958260" item-length="1940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only the Wind Should Sigh in This 'Garden'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Richards</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICHARDS, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All during "The Secret Garden," the new musical at the St. James Theater, I kept trying to account for my mounting sense of claustrophobia. But it wasn't until midway through the second act that an explanation occurred to me. No one was paying the slightest attention to the weather.</p>
        <p>If ever children's book celebrated the restorative virtues of fresh air, it is Frances Hodgson Burnett's classic of the same name, upon which this mysteriously beautiful, if almost unbearably morose enterprise is based. But where were the vivifying winds, blowing in off the moors, stirring dormant plants to life and putting a blush of color in sickly children's cheeks?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All during "The Secret Garden," the new musical at the St. James Theater, I kept trying to account for my mounting sense of claustrophobia. But it wasn't until midway through the second act that an explanation occurred to me. No one was paying the slightest attention to the weather.</p>
        <p>If ever children's book celebrated the restorative virtues of fresh air, it is Frances Hodgson Burnett's classic of the same name, upon which this mysteriously beautiful, if almost unbearably morose enterprise is based. But where were the vivifying winds, blowing in off the moors, stirring dormant plants to life and putting a blush of color in sickly children's cheeks?</p>
        <p>There are, I'll grant you, three thunderstorms in the course of the show, which is, frankly, two too many if you have an eye for variety. Thunderstorms, however, can be equated with the emotional turbulence in troubled souls, and the stage is certainly full of</p>
        <p>that</p>
        <p>. But there's no rain, for rain's nurturing sake. No warming sunshine. No crisp morning dew. When you come right down to it, the only climate this "Secret Garden" is really interested in is moral.</p>
        <p>I'd even be willing to argue that the playwright Marsha Norman, who is responsible for the book and lyrics, has gone and turned Burnett's novel on its head. The original tale, if you need a quick refresher, concerns a spoiled young girl, Mary Lennox, who loses her parents to a cholera epidemic in India and is shipped back to England to be raised by a cold uncle, Archibald Craven. Initially, life at Misselthwaite Manor, his 100-room domain on the edge of the Yorkshire moors, is somber. Ever since Archibald's wife, Lily, died in childbirth, her favorite garden has run wild, the locked gate discouraging any intruders. Shut away in a wing of his own, Archibald's puny son, Colin, languishes on his sickbed and throws temper tantrums.</p>
        <p>Little by little, Mary is coaxed out of her sour shell by her new companions -- a forthright chambermaid; the gruff gardener; and especially Dickon, a Yorkshire lad who communes magically with all living things. It's her discovery of the secret garden, however, that transforms her. She and Dickon will bring it back to splendor, and its greening wonders will awaken her to a life beyond her own. When the ailing Colin is introduced to the garden, he, too, experiencing its enchantment, blooms.</p>
        <p>Renewal is the obvious theme in Burnett's book. The winter gusts that greet Mary on her arrival at Misselthwaite give way to bracing spring winds, which, in turn, soften into the conciliatory breezes of summer. What seems brown and sere behind the high walls reveals itself in time to be full of sap or "wick," as Dickon's Yorkshire dialect puts it. Nature is clearly setting an example. A rose is a rose is a teacher.</p>
        <p>Ms. Norman, as odd a choice as one could imagine for this project, envisions it far differently. In the musical she has fashioned with the composer Lucy Simon, the director Susan H. Schulman and the set designer Heidi Landesman, nature has an incidental role. Ghosts are doing the instructing.</p>
        <p>The show begins in India in 1906 with the cholera epidemic, although it may take you a while to figure that out since the plague is depicted symbolically. Women in ball gowns and men in crisp military uniforms are playing drop-the-hanky. The hanky, red as blood, is death, apparently. The losers gather in the center of the circle. A mosquito net falls over them. Then a doll house -- a colonial mansion in miniature -- bursts into flame. Only Mary gets out of this muddle alive. But for the rest of the show, she will be dogged by phantoms.</p>
        <p>Adding apparition to specter, Missel thwaite also turns out to be haunted. Although his wife has been dead for 10 years, Archibald (Mandy Patinkin) hasn't forgotten her. There she is, perched above the stage in an ornate picture frame, rather as if she were a Gibson girl in a swing. From then on, she drifts in and out of the premises -- tracing lovely, lavender circles in the mustiness, looking in protectively on her bedridden son and singing love duets with her grieving husband.</p>
        <p>What seems to concern Ms. Norman more than the children's bond with nature is their relationship to the grown-ups, some living and remote, others dead and benevolent. In her harrowing drama, " 'Night, Mother," she showed us a mother unable to prevent her daughter from committing suicide. This time, among other acts of supernaturalism, she wants to show us a deceased mother urging her ailing son to embrace life. A mystical spin has been put on matters, and for anyone not familiar with Burnett's narrative, I suspect the intermingling of here and hereafter may prove confusing. Ms. Norman's is not a joyful temperament, and she ends up convoluting a simple story, without necessarily improving upon it.</p>
        <p>A large part of the book's lasting appeal is that it recognizes a child's desire for a sanctuary, safe from the prying eyes of adults. Not the musical. It takes Mary all of Act I to find the door to the garden and crack it open, letting in a flood of celestial light. At the beginning of Act II, she dreams of holding a party in its confines, attended by everyone she knows or once knew. The all-white vision -- "Sunday in the Park With George" minus the colored dots -- is eerily elegant, but still nothing you'd call a garden.</p>
        <p>Mary and Dickon don't get down to the hard, redemptive work of pruning and mulching until the second act is half over. And even then the chores are symbolically undertaken in "Come Spirit, Come Charm," a druidic-like incantation accompanied by sinuous Indian dance movements. This isn't cultivation, it's conjuration.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simon's score, when it forsakes the echoes of Ancient India, devotes itself to the sounds of Olde England -- madrigals, jigs, rounds, folk songs and the like. None of this is jarring to the ear, but it is not particularly beguiling. Its cool temperature, however, is right in keeping with the show as a whole. For fear of succumbing to mawkishness, the creators have made "The Secret Garden" nearly emotion-free.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patinkin is the most fervid of performers -- that tenor voice can quiver like a grove of aspens -- but it is his fate in "The Secret Garden" to flee all human contact. As Lily, Rebecca Luker extends comforting arms and beckons enticingly, but she's a ghost, after all, and it's her misfortune to keep melting away. Robert Westenberg, as the in-house doctor, delivers dire ultimatums sternly. While the servants could be expected to add a more playful note, only Alison Fraser, as a spunky chambermaid, evinces much earthiness.</p>
        <p>With Daisy Eagan, the show has just the right Mary -- cute, but not button-cute; knowing, but not calculating. Sitting Sunday-school straight, her mouth drawn in a tight line, she really does seem to be a willful little girl with a mind of her own and not just a Broadway trouper following a stage mother's directives. In a musical largely concerned with the secrets children keep, though, there are precious few scenes for the children themselves. The heroine's critical relationship with Dickon (the oddly elfin John Cameron Mitchell) is brushed over lightly. Mary manages at one point to put hysterical Colin (John Babcock) in his place, but that friendship is given no chance to evolve either and is simply presented as a fait accompli. I should imagine theatergoers under 12 would feel particularly shortchanged.</p>
        <p>The topsy-turviness is endemic. Whatever's dark and repressed in the fable is invariably favored over all that is bright and open. Ms. Landesman's designs, extraordinary as they are, also contribute to the feeling of dislocation. The stage of the St. James has been remade to resemble that of an ornate 19th-century toy theater, while the surrealistic sets themselves often bring to mind those boxes in which the artist Joseph Cornell tucked away butterfly wings, postage stamps, cigar bands and old photographs. A baby's face, big as a billboard, sometimes gazes down on the action, as if it were no more than a bubble in a naptime dream.</p>
        <p>For most of the evening, the garden is represented by four huge interlocking pieces of topiary -- a dove, a peacock, a swan and an owl -- that could be ice sculptures for a giant's punch bowl. The sight of trees and flowers in their full summer finery is reserved for the finale, when curtain upon curtain of lacy pastel blossoms is dropped into place. The image is as pretty as a Victorian valentine and as airless as a Portobello antiques shop. (You'd catch your breath, were there any breath around to be caught.)</p>
        <p>As a result, "The Secret Garden" is unlikely to instill in anyone a heightened awareness of the great salutary outdoors. But I wouldn't be surprised if you came away from it, as I did, with a compelling need to throw open a few windows -- which is not at all the same thing. 'Liza: Stepping Out at Radio City'</p>
        <p>I learned one lesson at "Liza: Stepping Out at Radio City," the concert-cum-stage show that Liza Minnelli is performing at Radio City Music Hall. If you're looking for a song to fill up that cavernous auditorium, one by Fred Ebb and John Kander is probably your best bet. Since Kander and Ebb are also doing quite well filling up the small Westside Theater, Off Broadway, with the retrospective revue "And the World Goes 'Round," it is possible they are a songwriting team for all halls.</p>
        <p>But back to Ms. Minnelli, who certainly appears out of her element warbling the black-and-blue chansons of Charles Aznavour or pumping up Stephen Sondheim's ballad "Losing My Mind" into a piston-driven dance number. She's on much surer ground ripping ferociously through "Some People" from "Gypsy." (The next revival really should be hers, guys.) Kander and Ebb, however, bring out the best in her -- the brass and the wide-eyed pluck. "New York, New York" needs no endorsement at this stage of the game, but even "Sara Lee," that silly tribute to the queen of calories, lends itself nicely to Ms. Minnelli's brand of strutting. Since "Stepping Out," the title number of her forthcoming film, falls squarely in the tradition of Kander and Ebb songs exhorting stay-at-homes to paint the town, it also has her name stamped all over it.</p>
        <p>"Stepping Out" actually receives two hearings -- as a first-act solo, then as a second-act production number, in which the star is joined by what she calls her "demon divas," a dozen women of assorted sizes, shapes and ages. The chorus line made up of disparate types can be good fun for a while, but the "demon divas" are wildly overused. They're fine in the medley of songs about men ("Stouthearted Men," "Some Day My Prince Will Come," "Hit the Road, Jack," etc.) that they share with Ms. Minnelli. But they don't have the bodies to do angular justice to the show's tribute to Bob Fosse -- a marriage of "Pack Up Your Troubles" and "It's a Long Way to Tipperary." And having them pound out jungle rhythms on oversize toy drums is high-precision drill work in its most rudimentary form.</p>
        <p>In a quieter vein, Ms. Minnelli recounts some memories of her father, Vincente Minnelli, who in the early 1930's was the Music Hall's art director, before going to Hollywood. "I got my drive from my mother, but I got my dreams from my father," she says. Judging from the photographs projected on the large screen behind her, she also got his expressive hands. The trip through the family album is touching. Too much of the time, however, "Liza: Stepping Out at Radio City" doesn't seem to know what direction to take and leaves its eager star, covered with bright lights, stabbing bravely in the dark.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
