<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Trek of One's Own in Nepal</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEPAL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIEBERMAN, MARCIA R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Nepal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC133AF93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="2279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Trek of One's Own in Nepal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCIA R. LIEBERMAN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIEBERMAN, MARCIA R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FASCINATED by Nepal after first trekking there several years ago, my husband and I were ready to return at once. However, most adventure travel companies offer organized, regularly scheduled treks in Nepal only in the spring or fall, the optimal trekking seasons, and we are rarely free to travel together at those times of year. Last winter, however, we were able to arrange our own private trek, supported by a Sherpa crew, and we discovered there are several advantages to this arrangement.</p>
        <p>My husband and I and an artist friend, Leslie Bostrom, requested an itinerary combining standard routes, modified for our own particular interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FASCINATED by Nepal after first trekking there several years ago, my husband and I were ready to return at once. However, most adventure travel companies offer organized, regularly scheduled treks in Nepal only in the spring or fall, the optimal trekking seasons, and we are rarely free to travel together at those times of year. Last winter, however, we were able to arrange our own private trek, supported by a Sherpa crew, and we discovered there are several advantages to this arrangement.</p>
        <p>My husband and I and an artist friend, Leslie Bostrom, requested an itinerary combining standard routes, modified for our own particular interests.</p>
        <p>We wanted to visit an area off the beaten track but we also wanted to get near the great mountains so that Leslie, who had not been to Nepal, could see them. And we wanted to visit several gompas, Buddhist temples or monasteries, and look at Buddhist art.</p>
        <p>Trekking several years ago with a group, my husband and I had arrived at Tengboche monastery, some 100 miles east of Katmandu at 12,714 feet, just at the start of Mani-Rimdu, a three-week Buddhist festival. A procession of red-robed Buddhist monks wearing golden hats wound through the temple courtyard, blowing long horns and conch shells and pounding drums -- a scene both moving and exotic. We learned that the next day the monks, in elaborate costumes, would perform ritual dance-dramas. Fascinated by this extraordinary religious and cultural event, some of us wanted to stay, but our group had to move on to keep up with our schedule.</p>
        <p>In arranging our own trek, we asked for a slightly more leisurely schedule to give us more flexibility. Regularly scheduled treks include one or two rest days, so that trekkers can relax and acclimatize to the higher altitude (above 10,000 feet). This acclimatization process is essential for safe and healthy trekking. Sometimes, however, a rest day is eliminated, to enable an organized group to keep to schedule. This happened to a friend of ours. When bad weather delayed his group's departure, their rest days were eliminated so they would not forgo the special destination billed as the climax of their trip. For our private trek, with a 23-day schedule, we included three rest days as an additional safety cushion.</p>
        <p>With the help of a good friend in Katmandu we dealt directly with a trekking agency. We could have arranged the same kind of trek, however, through an adventure travel company in the United States, which can advise you about itineraries and equipment and will provide a good, experienced crew.</p>
        <p>On a regularly scheduled trip, trekkers sleep in tents and have meals cooked specially for them. We wanted a trek in this style, but with a scaled-down crew; besides porters we had a cook with two assistants and two guides (though one would have been sufficient). One acted as sirdar, the chief sherpa, who hires and pays the porters and makes food purchases along the route. (Sherpas are an ethnic group of Tibetan origin, but the word sherpa has also come to mean a trekking guide, occasionally from one of Nepal's other ethnic groups.)</p>
        <p>Regularly scheduled groups have a trek leader, usually a Westerner, though occasionally a Nepali. Ideally, the leader knows the route well, can speak Nepali and is knowledgeable about local religions, flora and fauna. Not all trek leaders, however, match this ideal. On the eve of our first trek I was dismayed to learn that our leader had never been on the route and had trekked only once before in Nepal. (Evidently, the assigned trek leader, presumably more experienced, suddenly dropped out and a last-minute replacement had to be found.)</p>
        <p>An American I met in Katmandu, an old Nepali hand, reassured me, telling me we did not actually need the trek leader; the sirdar really runs the trek. And thanks to our sirdar, who knew the country intimately and spoke English quite well, the trek went smoothly. Reputable trekking agencies require that a sirdar speak English reasonably well; thus a trek leader is not necessary for a private party.</p>
        <p>Our trek began in Tumlingtar in eastern Nepal, visited by comparatively few trekking groups. Our route traversed the Arun River valley, through the villages of several groups: Hindus in the south, Rai in the middle hills, Sherpas in the higher country. Reaching the Dudh Kosi River, we joined a main trekking route as far as Pangboche, one of the highest permanent villages in Nepal, with views of Everest, Lhotse, Ama Dablam and other great mountains. We toured several other Sherpa villages -- Khumjung, Khunde and Thomde -- before turning south for Lukla and a flight to Katmandu. We traveled through a country of rich cultural contrast, with different landscapes and zones of climate and vegetation. The southern Arun valley, in mid-December, was warm: we saw monkeys, papayas and the purplish-carmine flowers of banana trees; in the north, we encountered snow.</p>
        <p>The small size of our group, and our control over our schedule, left us unrushed and gave us opportunities to talk to local people. In the Sherpa village of Pangkum, we lingered at the beautifully painted little gompa, where Leslie sketched many of the images on its walls. We learned that one of the villagers had a private shrine in his home, which we were allowed to visit; it was elaborately painted with Buddhist motifs. Then we were invited to join his family, who were sitting around the kitchen fire, warming themselves and drinking chang, homemade Sherpa beer.</p>
        <p>In the high country, winter evenings were spent around the kitchen fire; we were invited to join several such convivial groups. At the lodge of Mingma Tsering in Khunde (after the snowfall, we slept indoors), we listened to the old sherpa reminiscing about Sir Edmund Hillary, whom he served on the famous Everest expedition of 1953. And at the Himalayan Lodge in Lukla, we spent a delightful evening in Dawa Tsering's kitchen, sipping a concoction of rum and hot lemon juice.</p>
        <p>When we trekked with a regularly scheduled group, we liked nearly all our trekmates and became very good friends with two of them. The chance to make new and perhaps lasting friendships is one of the most pleasant aspects of joining a large group. (If you join a trek with Himalayan Travel, your group will be a mixture of Britons and Americans.) There is, besides, the comfort of carrying some of your own culture with you in a strange and primitive land. The reverse side of this is that a large group of Westerners forms a sort of cocoon, remaining more distant from the people among whom you travel.</p>
        <p>When our party of 14 Westerners stopped for a break at one of the little teahouses along the trail, the Nepalis inside became silent onlookers. A smaller party of three or four Westerners is a less formidable and more approachable group, and it is easier and more natural for Nepalis to strike up a conversation -- in English, even if haltingly, or with sherpas as interpreters.</p>
        <p>The most delightful part of our trek, however, was the friendship we developed with our crew. Trekking is an intimate form of travel: the group is a self-contained community, pretty much together from morning to night and sharing all meals. In a large group it was much easier simply to accept the quiet, unobtrusive services of the Sherpas and crew, and focus most of our attention on our trekmates. In a small, private party, we could interact to a much greater degree with the crew. The Sherpas were endlessly cheerful and pleasant, caring for us with constant courtesy and attention, and singing and whistling half the day. They taught us Nepali songs; we taught them "Old MacDonald Had a Farm," which had them rolling with laughter, and rounds (they had never heard one) like "Frere Jacques." On Christmas Eve they decorated our dining tent with balloons and served us little wrapped candies and mince pies they had obviously carried from Katmandu. We sang carols for them (they stood with crossed hands, listening with great solemnity); when we entered Buddhist temples, the Sherpas taught us how to perform the traditional prostrations. And on a moonlit field on New Year's Eve we taught them the hora, the highland fling and the bunny hop; then they danced for us, Nepali style. Some Sherpas and other Nepalis speak English quite fluently; ours spoke well enough to meet our needs. We found simple ways to express more complex ideas, and managed to talk about our families, religion and even politics. Discussing last year's pro-democracy demonstrations in Katmandu, I found myself trying to describe such concepts as democracy, due process and checks and balances. One Sherpa, concerned about Leslie, felt close enough to ask her why at her age (39) she was not married. She explained that in the Western culture, a woman can choose to remain single.</p>
        <p>What began as fun ended as a rather moving experience. When we said our farewells, several members of the crew placed katas -- ceremonial white scarfs that betoken honor and respect -- around our necks, bought with their own meager funds. Then we sang the old songs again together, with unmistakeable mutual affection.</p>
        <p>One of the drawbacks of a private trek is that you must assume more responsibility for yourself and your party, particularly about matters of health, than you would with an organized group. Although trekking companies do not hire doctors to accompany large groups, most offer them reduced rates to take part. (You cannot assume, however, that there will be a doctor along.) Some companies require trek leaders to take an emergency medical training course. A trek medical kit, whose contents will vary, is sent out with organized groups. Despite this, a trekker even with an organized group must take some individual responsibility, taking along not only any personally required medications but also a small stock of first aid material and some antibiotics.</p>
        <p>Our trekking agency sent along a first aid kit for our private trek, but we took a stock of medicine for ourselves and our crew. This consisted mainly of several courses of various kinds of antibiotics and other medications to take in case of respiratory or gastrointestinal infections. (None of us became very ill.) Several excellent trekking guidebooks include a full list of items to be included in the kit, which we prepared after consultation with our doctor.</p>
        <p>A private trek is an excellent option for a more adventurous traveler, or a party of friends who want to make some decisions for themselves and have more control over the itinerary and timetable. It is also good for people whose schedules do not permit them to join a regular organized trek. For us, the extra responsibility was more than repaid by the chance to view temples at leisure, converse with local people and form deep attachments to our crew. GUIDE TO ADVENTURE COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Trek Organizers</p>
        <p>Several reputable adventure travel companies arrange private treks. The costs listed here are approximate, depending on such factors as the party's size, the amount of support desired and the route. The flight to Katmandu, either by way of Bangkok or New Delhi, is extra. From New York the round-trip fares are $1,942 via New Delhi and $1,825 via Bangkok.</p>
        <p>Our trekking agency was Himalayan Explorers, Post Office Box 1737, Jyatha Thole, Thamel, Katmandu, Nepal; telephone (977) 1-226142. Our 23-day trek cost $1,297 per person, including internal flights, trekking permits and park fees. At a first-class Katmandu hotel, a room for two with bath costs $110.</p>
        <p>Above the Clouds, Post Office Box 398, Worcester, Mass. 01602; (800) 233-4499 or (508) 799-4499. Fourteen-day treks are $130 per person per day; for three to five people, $120. Twenty-one day treks are $120 per person per day for two people; $105 per person per day for three to five people. Flights from Katmandu to Lukla are $88 one way; $44 for the sirdar, or head guide, and cook. Katmandu hotel rooms are from $10 to $117 for two people to a room, according to the type of hotel. Most rooms, even those costing $10 a night, have a private bath. The more expensive rooms are larger and more elaborately furnished.  Reservations needed two months ahead; four months for fall treks.</p>
        <p>Himalayan Travel, Post Office Box 481, Greenwich, Conn. 06836; (800) 225-2380 or (203) 622-6777. In the Annapurna region, 14-day treks are $1,300 per person; 21-day treks $1,700. In the Everest region, 14-day treks are $1,400; 21-day treks $1,850. The prices include internal transportation, such as the flight to Lukla, four nights at a Katmandu hotel, sightseeing and airport transfers. Reservations needed three months ahead for the Everest region, one month for the Annapurna region.</p>
        <p>Mountain Travel/Sobek, 6420 Fairmount Avenue, El Cerrito, Calif. 94530; (800) 227-2384 or (415) 527-8100. Fourteen-day treks $2,170; 21-daytreks $3,268. Reservations needed four to six months ahead.</p>
        <p>Overseas Adventure Travel, 349 Broadway, Cambridge, Mass. 02139; (800) 221-0814 or (617) 876-0533.  Fourteen-day treks $2,150; 21-day treks $2,650. Prices include internal flights and hotel in Katmandu. Reservations needed two months ahead.</p>
        <p>Wilderness Travel, 801 Allston Way, Berkeley, Calif. 94710; (800) 368-2794 or (415) 548-0420. From $100 to $150 a day. Prices include internal flights, Katmandu hotel, sightseeing. Reservations four to six months. Reading</p>
        <p>Following are invaluable guides:</p>
        <p>"Trekking in the Nepal Himalaya," by Stan Armington (Lonely Planet).</p>
        <p>"A Guide to Trekking in Nepal," by Stephen Bezrushka (The Mounaineers).</p>
        <p>"Trekking in Nepal, West Tibet and Bhutan," by Hugh Seift (Sierra Club Books).  -- M. R. L.  MARCIA R. LIEBERMAN is the author of "The Outdoor Traveler's Guide to the Alps," due this fall from Stewart, Tabori &amp; Chang.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MARCIA R. LIEBERMAN is the author of "The Outdoor Traveler's Guide to the Alps," due this fall from Stewart, Tabori &amp; Chang.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
