<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patancheru Journal; 300 Factories Add Up to India's Very Sick Town</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="420758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PATANCHERU (INDIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D61030F935A35751C0A967958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patancheru Journal; 300 Factories Add Up to India's Very Sick Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>PATANCHERU, India</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last six years, Dr. Krishna Rao has watched a catastrophe unfold around him as he cares for the sick in the town where he was born 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>"More than 2,000 acres of our fertile land has been damaged by chemicals -- sulfides, sulfates, nitrites, nitrates and phosphorous," he said. "All our subsoil water is polluted down to 145 feet, but people are forced to drink from wells because there is no other source."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last six years, Dr. Krishna Rao has watched a catastrophe unfold around him as he cares for the sick in the town where he was born 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>"More than 2,000 acres of our fertile land has been damaged by chemicals -- sulfides, sulfates, nitrites, nitrates and phosphorous," he said. "All our subsoil water is polluted down to 145 feet, but people are forced to drink from wells because there is no other source."</p>
        <p>"Three boys died of leukemia last year, an unknown event here," Dr. Rao said as he shifted through papers on his desk at his small clinic. "Our cattle are dying -- and goats, thousands of goats. I have seen a calf born without skin."</p>
        <p>Within minutes, as if on cue, a thin old man passed by leading a bullock cart with a dead cow in an improvised sling. Pollution From 300 Factories</p>
        <p>Patancheru, once a farming community, is now an industrial development zone, and Indian environmental-action groups say it has quickly become one of the most polluted places on earth.</p>
        <p>More than 300 factories pollute the air, land and water. Industrial waste is dumped in public places, fouling the atmosphere. Children develop lesions from playing in the dirt, Dr. Rao said.</p>
        <p>He treats many cases of restlessness, headaches and other nonspecific illnesses, including psychological disorders, that he associates with a shortage of oxygen. In one outlying village, Sultanpur, no children are being born, as women suffer repeated miscarriages.</p>
        <p>The fate of Patancheru, 20 miles from Hyderabad, and other industrial development areas in India has come to symbolize the deadly results of an official policy of rapid industrialization without accompanying political will to control its side effects.</p>
        <p>India has laws protecting the environment -- the most recently enacted one making companies liable for damage -- but corruption among politicians and government officials and the power of industrial corporations, which often defy court orders, make any law hard to enforce. 'Not Against Industry'</p>
        <p>Because so many Indians see only this side of industrialization, they are often persuaded to turn against modernization altogether, seeing it as a sinister, Western-inspired encroachment, even though nationalized Indian industry was influenced by Soviet advisers.</p>
        <p>A 1990 "Citizens' Report" on pollution in this state, Andhra Pradesh, by the 10-year-old Academy of Gandhian Studies in Hyderabad, suggests a link between local development policies and "an international network of capitalists, capitalist governments, military power and bureaucratic steel frame."</p>
        <p>"We are not against industry," said Purushotam Reddy, a political scientist at Osmania University in Hyderabad, who was associated with the Citizens' Report. "We only want that it should be controlled." He said that some of the polluters are Indians who made money in the West and returned to open factories here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reddy, a founder of Citizens Against Pollution, says he believes that only constant pressure from residents of the area can force a change in official attitudes. Mr. Reddy's group has scored some notable successes, making it one of India's leading enviromental groups.</p>
        <p>"The secret of our success is basically that we come out with a lot of facts and figures," he said. "We build up potential accident scenarios. We work out costs of prevention." Nuclear Plant Stalled</p>
        <p>The formula was applied to a citizens' movement that has stalled government plans to build a 2,000-megawatt nuclear power plant near Hyderabad, which would have dumped effluents into an irrigation canal. Mr. Reddy and like-minded scientists went directly to the Atomic Energy Commission to put their case.</p>
        <p>Citizens Against Pollution more or less began in Mr. Reddy's brother's rose garden in 1985. After more than 10,000 rose bushes died in the family-run nursery, the brothers had the well water tested and found it polluted by a new chemical factory.</p>
        <p>With the help of a local Institute of Preventive Medicine, scientific studies were made of the neighborhood, and the Citizens Against Pollution marched on government offices and the courts.</p>
        <p>The company agreed to install a treatment plant and pipeline, and pay compensation to residents whose land had been damaged. Soon after, the pipeline was broken by local vandals.  Victories Are Cited</p>
        <p>"We are back to square one," Mr. Reddy said. But he is not dismayed. He cites victories over a starch company that was polluting the water near Osmania University's residence halls and in forcing the Nuclear Fuel Complex, a Government-run uranium enriching plant, to wall itself off from nearby residents after several children were burned with radioactive waste.</p>
        <p>But the nuclear plant still looms as a major threat to the Hyderabad region and its four million or more people. So do pesticide and fertilizer factories, despite some moves to begin building effluent treatment plants.</p>
        <p>Citizens Against Pollution is now working with a local technology college on detailed, scientific surveys of Patancheru and other industrial zones. Mr. Reddy wants to have the information necessary to give citizens a voice in the decision-making process.</p>
        <p>"When major decisions are taken in this country, there is no debate," he said. "Nobody is informed."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
