<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Morning TV: The Twist That Works</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNYW-TV (NEW YORK)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOX BROADCASTING CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIMER, SARA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GOOD DAY NEW YORK (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1E31F932A05753C1A967958260" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Morning TV: The Twist That Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA RIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIMER, SARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wednesday last week, with auto industry earnings plummeting, the morning network television shows rounded up industry analysts and auto executives for the standard interview-with-expert. But on "Good Day New York," the morning program produced by the Fox-owned station in New York, WNYW, a reporter, Gordon Elliott, showed up at a garage in Woodside, Queens. He brought along a stylist from Pierre Michel, a fancy Manhattan salon, to make over the silver-haired mechanic for a feature entitled: "From Automan to Anchorman."</p>
        <p>The mechanic makeover just happened to have been scheduled for that day. "If we could have planned it that way, we would have," said Joachim Blunck, the executive producer of "Good Day New York." The local news report included a cursory mention of the auto industry's declining earnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Wednesday last week, with auto industry earnings plummeting, the morning network television shows rounded up industry analysts and auto executives for the standard interview-with-expert. But on "Good Day New York," the morning program produced by the Fox-owned station in New York, WNYW, a reporter, Gordon Elliott, showed up at a garage in Woodside, Queens. He brought along a stylist from Pierre Michel, a fancy Manhattan salon, to make over the silver-haired mechanic for a feature entitled: "From Automan to Anchorman."</p>
        <p>The mechanic makeover just happened to have been scheduled for that day. "If we could have planned it that way, we would have," said Joachim Blunck, the executive producer of "Good Day New York." The local news report included a cursory mention of the auto industry's declining earnings.</p>
        <p>"What can we say about an auto industry in Detroit?" said Mr. Blunck, who was one of the creators of Fox's nationally syndicated news magazine, "A Current Affair."</p>
        <p>"They lose lots of money because they make lousy cars," Mr. Blunck said. "We know that. Why put people to sleep with a long discussion about it when they'd rather see Gordon Elliott? You can't have wall-to-wall cerebral reporting."  Winning Formula</p>
        <p>It is this sort of thinking, combined with an emphasis on local news and features, that has made "Good Day New York" a hit with 7 A.M. viewers. For the last 30 weeks, the low-budget show, now in its third season, has finished second only to ABC's "Good Morning America," beating NBC's "Today" and "CBS This Morning." For the period from Sept. 26 through Oct. 23, "Good Day New York," the city's only local morning show, scored a 3.3 Nielsen rating and 16 share, a 50 percent increase over its ratings in the October 1990 Nielsen survey. The rating is the percentage of all televisions tuned to the show, and the share is the percentage of televisions in use.</p>
        <p>The success of "Good Day New York" has inspired local stations around the country to start their own morning shows. WTTG, the Fox-owned station in Washington, has a two-and-a-half-hour news program starting at 6:30 A.M. WSVN, the Fox affiliate in Miami, and KTVU, the Fox affiliate in San Francisco, both have morning programs. So does KTLA in Los Angeles, which is owned by the Chicago Tribune Company.</p>
        <p>"The common essence for all these shows is that they're local," said Carolyn Wall, the vice president and general manager of WNYW, who came up with the idea for "Good Day New York."</p>
        <p>The sensibility of the local morning show varies from city to city. Mr. Elliott, a onetime radio and television talk show personality in Australia, likes to barge into the homes of ordinary New Yorkers at 7 A.M. on live television. On Tuesday last week, unannounced, he took three Hawaiian dancers and a catered Hawaiian feast, complete with a suckling pig named Freddy, to a family in Manhattan Beach, Brooklyn. On the way up the driveway, he tripped and fell on his back. For a moment, he lay there, laughing, on live television.</p>
        <p>"I'm gonna sue!" he shouted into the camera.  A Difference oin Washington</p>
        <p>Mr. Elliott's style might not wash in, say, Washington. WTTG's show is usually more serious than the New York program, though yesterday the guests on "Good Day New York" included the embattled City College professor, Leonard Jeffries, who has been reappointed chairman of the black studies department despite racially charged remarks about Jews and other whites.</p>
        <p>"WTTG is more heavily news oriented because that's appropriate to the nation's capital," Ms. Wall said.</p>
        <p>Frank Magid, a media consultant whose clients include "Good Morning America," said the popularity of shows like "Good Day New York" demonstrated the increasing fractionalization of television audiences across the country. "With the proliferation of opportunities -- cable, over-the-air TV, videotape -- individuals can have that broader choice," he said. "I don't imagine any of the three networks are doing what some of the shows try to do on a local basis. What 'Good Morning America' does is not designed for New York. It's designed for America."</p>
        <p>"Good Day New York" is not addressed to just Manhattan but to all the boroughs and the nearby sections of New Jersey and Connecticut. "If there's a water main break, we're there," Mr. Blunck said. "If there's a hostage situation in Ridgewood, we're there. If it rained for 20 straight days, we'd go out and do stories on sunlight deprivation."  The Usual Mix</p>
        <p>The program with the mechanic makeover last week included the usual mix of local news, weather, traffic and "life style" reports. A reporter, Dick Oliver, talked with teachers at P.S. 289 in Crown Heights, Brooklyn, about a recent rash of muggings near the school. He also reported on a group of Metropolitan Transit Authority workers who had filed a class-action suit over drug testing.</p>
        <p>Lynne White, the news reader, informed viewers that the City Comptroller, Elizabeth Holtzman, had declared her intention to run for United States Senate and that the city planned to crack down on speeding cyclists and roller bladers in Central Park.</p>
        <p>Cande Roth, the traffic reporter, warned motorists that construction would make the Brooklyn Bridge a nightmare over the weekend.</p>
        <p>Julie Golden, the meteorologist, predicted warm, sunny days through Friday. Jim Ryan, the anchor, usually the show's straight man, quoted an article from The Associated Press in The New York Post that suggested that "dinosaur flatulence may have helped warm the earth's climate millions of years ago." Julie Golden then predicted a warming trend for New York.</p>
        <p>Playing off the dinosaur item, Mr. Ryan suggested that Larry Hoff, one of the show's reporters, should be thanked for "our next few nice days." Mr. Hoff is known as "the first person in New York television to try bungee jumping," a Fox spokesman said. On Friday last week, he walked barefoot across a pile of hot coals in Harlem.</p>
        <p>In another segment, New Yorkers were asked at random to list their lovers' pet peeves. Some answers: leaving the toilet seat up, hair rollers, underwear strewn on the floor, no welcome-home kiss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoff interviewed Megan Gallagher, a television actress who was recently named America's sexiest woman by People magazine.</p>
        <p>Denise Richardson, the celebrity reporter who often appears with her dog, a bichon frise named Muffy, was on vacation.  Easy Show to Fix</p>
        <p>Mr. Blunck became the third executive producer of "Good Day New York" a year ago. "The show was dead last," he said. "It lacked focus. The intimation to me was to fix it or put it out of its misery." Fixing it, Mr. Blunck said, was easy. He considered the audience, which is predominantly women, many of them mothers at home. "I brought in a stack of women's magazines," he said. "I told people, 'We have to do a show directed at women.' "</p>
        <p>Helen Gurley Brown, the editor of Cosmopolitan magazine, was invited to appear. "She talked about getting a man -- how to close the deal," Mr. Blunck said.</p>
        <p>Last Monday, the show's guests included Susan Faludi, a Pulitzer Prize-winning reporter for The Wall Street Journal, who talked about her new book, "Backlash: The Undeclared War on American Women," which documents the backlash against the feminist movement.</p>
        <p>"The show is very freewheeling," Mr. Blunck said. "It's the way people's heads are in the morning. They're a little fuzzy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
