<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stolen Bikes Join War on Pollution</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="446069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="GLENDALE JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BICYCLES AND BICYCLING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GLENDALE (ARIZ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB143EF934A25756C0A967958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stolen Bikes Join War on Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>GLENDALE, Ariz.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nelson Galligan used to drive a smog-spewing pickup to work. Now he pedals a bicycle to his job. The environment is healthier for it. So is Mr. Galligan.</p>
        <p>It was all made possible by a theft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nelson Galligan used to drive a smog-spewing pickup to work. Now he pedals a bicycle to his job. The environment is healthier for it. So is Mr. Galligan.</p>
        <p>It was all made possible by a theft.</p>
        <p>In an effort to fight pollution, this Phoenix suburb of 148,000 people has taken its stable of unclaimed stolen bicycles and lent them to city employees like Mr. Galligan. The workers pledge to give up driving at least three times a week, and pedal to work instead.</p>
        <p>In Maricopa County, where polluted haze can obscure the Camelback Mountains and make breathing a burden, the Glendale project is one of several strategies aimed at reducing automobile travel.</p>
        <p>"We had all these bikes just sitting around, and no one ever claimed them," said Susan Bookspan, a transportation coordinator for the City of Glendale, which employs 1,100 workers. "This was a way we could help the environment."</p>
        <p>About 40 city workers are using the bicycles, and there is a long waiting list for more stolen two-wheelers. The employees can keep the bikes after one year if they are not claimed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Galligan, a 35-year-old graphic designer who described himself as "not the athletic sort," said his new bike-riding regimen is improving his shape.</p>
        <p>"People tell me I look like I've lost weight," he said. "But mostly, I just feel hungrier."</p>
        <p>The effort grew out of an Arizona law that requires all Maricopa County employers with 100 or more workers to reduce by 5 percent the number of people who drive to work alone.</p>
        <p>Every little bit helps. Promoters of the law like to say that 25 miles of driving creates a pound of pollution.</p>
        <p>The state law, which provides no penalties as long as employers provide a good-faith effort to comply, has led to some innovative strategies.</p>
        <p>A hotel here offers valet parking to workers who come to work in a car pool. One company struck a deal with a nearby apartment complex to offer lower rents for employees who travel to work by bus. Another business provides shaded parking spaces for those who commute in a car pool. That is no small benefit in summer months in the desert.</p>
        <p>"It was 122 degrees here last June," said Diane Adams, who coordinates the ride-sharing program in Glendale. "Of course, that was unusual. Usually it's only about 110."</p>
        <p>Such programs appear to be working. Carbon monoxide emissions have dropped significantly in the last few years here.</p>
        <p>The gains have been achieved largely through stricter tailpipe tests and the use of oxygenated gasoline, which reduce carbon monoxide emissions, said Francis Wicher, an engineer with the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>"But these driving-reduction programs do certainly make an important difference," she said. "It's really helping."</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide concentrations in Maricopa County have fallen to about .11 parts per million, down from about .18 parts per million in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>But the region still has a way to go. It remains one of the 44 regions in the nation with carbon monoxide levels higher than the Federal safe air standard of .9 parts per million.</p>
        <p>Moreover, clean air advocates say they are swimming against the tide. The rapid growth in the Phoenix area over the past decade means that driving miles have been increasing by 4 percent each year in the 80's, with no end in sight.</p>
        <p>The bike-to-work campaign might not work for all employers. After all, people arriving on the job fresh from a workout, or not so fresh, might not do wonders for the environment inside the office.</p>
        <p>For its part, the city provides shower stalls for its workers.</p>
        <p>And what if the original owner of a stolen bicycle sees it around town, and confronts the rider? Might not the original owner think the explanation, coming from someone seated on his or her bike, sounds a bit fishy?</p>
        <p>"We've never had that happen," said Ms. Bookspan. "But I'm sure we'd give the bicycle back."</p>
        <p>There has been one problem with the program, however.</p>
        <p>"It was great to have a bike," said Jim Corbett, a city worker who took part in the program, "until it was stolen."  GLENDALE JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
