<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weather to Make a Polar Bear Glad to Be Alive</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Life Style Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ZOOS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CENTRAL PARK ZOO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYONS, RICHARD D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE113AF93AA35751C0A964958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weather to Make a Polar Bear Glad to Be Alive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD D. LYONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LYONS, RICHARD D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gus was feeling good, all 800 pounds of him. He swaggered around the Polar Circle area in the Central Park Zoo with his snout in the air showing off for visitors, leaping from one rock to another. Then he nuzzled into a pas de deux with Ida, his 600-pound playmate for the morning.</p>
        <p>Winter is the best time to go to the Central Park Zoo to commune with the animals that thrive in cold climates. They are friskier, friendlier and in some cases more amorous than they are the rest of the year. Also, crowds are small in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gus was feeling good, all 800 pounds of him. He swaggered around the Polar Circle area in the Central Park Zoo with his snout in the air showing off for visitors, leaping from one rock to another. Then he nuzzled into a pas de deux with Ida, his 600-pound playmate for the morning.</p>
        <p>Winter is the best time to go to the Central Park Zoo to commune with the animals that thrive in cold climates. They are friskier, friendlier and in some cases more amorous than they are the rest of the year. Also, crowds are small in February.</p>
        <p>"Polar bears love this sort of weather," said Roy Riffe, the keeper of the bears, as Gus, Ida and Lilly, the Zoo's third polar bear, cavorted on the rocks and in the pools of the Polar Circle. The Circle is part of the Edge of the Icepack exhibit, which is on the north side of the zoo, appropriately.</p>
        <p>Warming to his chilly subject, Mr. Riffe said: "Polar bears have big heavy bodies, like sumo wrestlers. But they are burdened with heavy coats that make them lethargic in the summer, whereas in winter they feel better and really move around almost as easily as cats." The Frolicsome Ida</p>
        <p>On a chilly winter morning, Gus, on cue, hurled himself into a grand jete over a stream and chased the frolicsome Ida over a couple of rocks, evoking cheers and howls of laughter from a group of early risers.</p>
        <p>"We're moving into the breeding season for the polar bears," Mr. Riffe said. He hopes this year the bears will have some offspring.</p>
        <p>The three bears are among the 100 or so specimens at the zoo that might well be considered wintry or polar animals. These include macaques, or Japanese snow monkeys, which breed in the fall, with the females delivering their babies in May. The dozen macaques at the zoo, several of which weigh up to 30 pounds, are particular crowd pleasers.</p>
        <p>Anthony Brownie, the zoo's animal supervisor, said, "The snow monkeys interact a lot, and in cold weather they like to root around for pieces of ice and throw them at one another." The macaques inhabit a rocky island in a pond in the Temperate Territory on the west side of the zoo. Sea Lions and Red Pandas</p>
        <p>Among the other animals that enjoy the cold are North American otters and Arctic foxes. Many people think sea lions, the perpetual favorites in the sea lion pool in the Central Garden, are from the polar latitudes. But those at the zoo are from the California coast. Harbor seals, which are just to the east of the polar bears, come from the Atlantic and Pacific coasts of the United States; some may even be seen in the wild off eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>More exotic are the red pandas from the Himalayas, which are about the size of raccoons, with coats of a deep rust red and a dark mask. They thrive on bamboo shoots, and may be seen at the Panda Pavilion near the zoo's westernmost edge.</p>
        <p>The zoo, the first municipal zoo in the United States when it opened in 1864, was once operated by the city Parks Department. It was closed in 1983 and virtually rebuilt. When it reopened four years ago, the New York Zoological Society took over responsibility. The society operates the Central Park Zoo, the Bronx Zoo and the New York Aquarium at Coney Island. Admission to the Central Park Zoo is $2.50 for adults, 50 cents for children and $1.25 for people 65 years old or older.</p>
        <p>The zoo also conducts educational programs. Yesterday, for example, it sponsored a 90-minute lecture devoted to animal breeding strategies. The reproductive behavior of polar bears, penguins and leaf cutter ants were featured. Puffins and Penguins Coming Up</p>
        <p>Penguins were the subject of a children's lecture last Sunday, which will be repeated March 1 at 10 A.M. A lecture starring puffins and penguins will be given March 7 at 2 P.M. Seats are still available for both. The lectures are held either at the Zoo School building near the park entrance at Fifth Avenue and 64th Street, or at the exhibits themselves. For information or reservations, call (212) 439-6538.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riffe, a 38-year old native of Arkansas, graduated from the School of the Ozarks, a college in Missouri. He studied acting and landed his first job as a barker in a marine park in Gulfport, Miss.</p>
        <p>"I sort of drifted into training sea lions and dolphins, and got to like the handling of animals," he said. "I drifted toward New York, liked it here and decided to stay."</p>
        <p>He was walking toward the sea lion pool. "I started out thinking I was going to end up behind the footlights," he continued. "But to my own surprise I've ended up instead behind the feeding bucket."</p>
        <p>He threw a handful of fish to the sea lions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
