<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: White House; BUSH GIVES BREAK TO AUTO INDUSTRY ON GASOLINE FUMES</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BENZENE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71E31F937A25750C0A964958260" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: White House; BUSH GIVES BREAK TO AUTO INDUSTRY ON GASOLINE FUMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four days before the Michigan primary, President Bush told business executives today that the Government would not require automobile manufacturers to install pollution-control devices on new cars to capture gasoline fumes released into the atmosphere during refueling.</p>
        <p>In making the announcement just three days after the primary in Texas, Mr. Bush settled a long dispute between auto makers and oil companies over which industry would be required to invest in new equipment to clear the air of benzene and other chemical compounds that contribute to urban smog.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four days before the Michigan primary, President Bush told business executives today that the Government would not require automobile manufacturers to install pollution-control devices on new cars to capture gasoline fumes released into the atmosphere during refueling.</p>
        <p>In making the announcement just three days after the primary in Texas, Mr. Bush settled a long dispute between auto makers and oil companies over which industry would be required to invest in new equipment to clear the air of benzene and other chemical compounds that contribute to urban smog.</p>
        <p>The oil industry, which dominates the Texas economy, today lost the dispute that began 17 years ago, when the Government first considered controlling the fumes from refueling. The decision was roundly criticized by lawmakers and environmental groups as well as the oil industry.  A Tradition of Campaigns</p>
        <p>Doling out political favors has been an election-year tactic of Presidents for decades. Environmental officials asserted privately this week that Mr. Bush's strategy is driven by the belief that there is only one political gain available to him from the recession: packaging his stepped-up attack on environmental regulations as an effort to help business and preserve jobs.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency said today that it would soon issue a new regulation under the Clean Air Act of 1990 directing service station owners in about 45 cities to install rubber collars on nozzles and vapor-recovery systems on pumps.</p>
        <p>The Government said the average cost of such systems, already in use in California as well as the District of Columbia and other Northeastern cities, is about $2,200 a pump and $20,000 to $40,000 for each station. The environmental agency estimated the cost of installing fume-trapping canisters in cars at $20 to $30 for each car. Small but Vital Step</p>
        <p>Gasoline fumes contain substantial quantities of benzene, a known cancer-causing chemical, and organic chemicals that combine with nitrogen oxide and other compounds to form smog. Except in cities that require containment systems at service stations, fumes that accumulate in gasoline tanks escape into the atmosphere during refueling.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. said today that gasoline fumes account for 2 percent of the urban smog problem. The agency said that although that percentage is small, there are so many sources of smog that identifying one and reducing it sharply would be a major improvement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the E.P.A., said the decision in favor of the automobile industry was the result of new studies by the Department of Transportation. They found that installing canisters near gasoline tanks to capture the fumes would be a risk to passengers because of the increased chance the canister would catch fire or explode in a collision.</p>
        <p>In addition, William G. Rosenberg, the assistant administrator of the environmental agency for air and radiation, said that the automobile industry deserved a break from requirements of the Clean Air Act, since it is already required to reduce emissions in new cars by developing more advanced engine and tailpipe controls.</p>
        <p>"This was perceived to be the least-cost way for the consumer to pay, and a fairer distribution of the economic burden," Mr. Rosenberg said.  Under Immediate Attack</p>
        <p>The action by the Bush Administration was attacked today by lawmakers, environmentalists, independent station owners, and the Center for Auto Safety, a Washington-based consumer group.</p>
        <p>"The on-board canisters were a cheaper and better way to control volatile emissions than the vapor-recovery systems at gasoline stations, which are expensive and difficult to maintain," said Senator Max S. Baucus, Democrat of Montana who was a principal author of the Clean Air Act. "The so-called environmental President is playing politics with clean air."</p>
        <p>The Center for Auto Safety disputed the Government's contention that vapor canisters were a safety risk. The group has said that cars already have similar canisters installed to control emissions and the Government has never maintained that they were a danger.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups said the Clean Air Act, which the President vigorously supported, requires installation in cars and gasoline stations of systems to control gasoline fumes. Waiving one requirement was a purely political move that would do nothing to reduce pollution from vapors in less smoggy cities, they said. An Act 'Held Hostage'?</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council today listed 11 other regulations under the Clean Air Act that have been proposed by the environmental agency but which have been blocked by the White House. One covers emissions of toxic chemicals from factories, one of the largest sources of air pollution. "The Clean Air Act is being held hostage by the White House," said David D. Doniger, a lawyer with the group.</p>
        <p>Independent gasoline marketers also criticized the President's action, calling it expensive, unnecessary and likely to reduce competition. They said the cost of installing vapor-recovery systems could put hundreds of stations out of business and allow the big oil companies to gain a much larger share of the $130 billion retail gasoline market.</p>
        <p>The Petroleum Marketers Association of America said that although independent businessmen own two-thirds of the 175,000 stations across the country, they pump just 45 percent of the gasoline.</p>
        <p>"The big oil companies don't like this much either, but they are in much better financial position to afford the vapor-recovery systems," said Phillip R. Chisholm, executive vice president of the association. "They have the advantage of their size. They also have higher concentration of stations in the markets that are most affected by this rule, which means they can get the contractors who do this work first and at lower costs."</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush campaigns against Patrick J. Buchanan, the conservative commentator who is challenging him for the Republican nomination, he is doing what politicians at all levels do in an election year: dispensing pork.</p>
        <p>In addition to President Bush's announcement last week of a $514 million reclamation project to straighten the Kissimmee River in Florida, he has reduced some environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>In the past month, the Administration relaxed regulations on the natural gas industry in Oklahoma. It also announced its intention to seek Congressional approval to bypass the Endangered Species Act in the Northwest to allow cutting of the last stands of virgin forest. Backers say that would preserve 30,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>It was revealed this week that the Administration joined sides with the coal industry in a Federal Court lawsuit the industry hopes will weaken enforcement of the nation's strip-mining law. Earlier, the White House announced a program to remove regulation of the biotechnology industry, including making it easier for agricultural biotechnology companies to test living genetically-engineered organisms outdoors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
