<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 17 Years, NASA Prepares for a Return Trip to Mars</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="558245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLANETS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DE1E30F931A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="1686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 17 Years, NASA Prepares for a Return Trip to Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVENTEEN years after the last American flights to Mars, a spacecraft is set to depart on a $900 million mission of renewed exploration of the one other world in the solar system where humans might conceivably make a home away from Earth.</p>
        <p>"America is going back to Mars," said Dr. Wesley T. Huntress, director of solar system exploration for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, putting the simplest interpretation on the importance of the new mission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVENTEEN years after the last American flights to Mars, a spacecraft is set to depart on a $900 million mission of renewed exploration of the one other world in the solar system where humans might conceivably make a home away from Earth.</p>
        <p>"America is going back to Mars," said Dr. Wesley T. Huntress, director of solar system exploration for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, putting the simplest interpretation on the importance of the new mission.</p>
        <p>Elaborating on the mission's scientific context, Dr. Arden L. Albee of the California Institute of Technology, the chief project scientist, said: "Previous missions have dispelled much of the mystery that's surrounded Mars. Mars is alive and complex, much like Earth. We have explored it and are now going back to observe it."</p>
        <p>The agent of this new round of planetary investigation is the 5,700-pound spacecraft Mars Observer, which is to be launched Friday at Cape Canaveral, Fla., by a Titan 3 rocket with a powerful new upper-stage booster.</p>
        <p>Anxiety is running high among scientists and spacecraft engineers, who have not waited out a countdown for flights to Mars since 1975. This time there is only one craft, with no backup. And they must get it going by Oct. 13, or else face a costly delay of two years until Mars is again in proper alignment with Earth.</p>
        <p>Nine days of the launching opportunity were squandered when workers recently discovered metal flakes, paint chips and other contamination all over the spacecraft and had to haul it back to the hangar for a thorough cleaning. Some officials said this added to the vague unease that haunts the final days of any countdown and may be more worrisome this time because Mars Observer, built by the General Electric Company under the direction of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., had encountered so many development troubles.</p>
        <p>If all goes well, though, Mars Observer will embark on an 11-month voyage, then swing into an orbit of Mars. From an altitude of 242 miles, the craft will cross both poles once every 117 minutes and return more data about the red planet than were transmitted by all previous missions to Mars.</p>
        <p>Mariner 9 was the first spacecraft to orbit Mars, in 1971 and 1972, producing the first maps of another planet based on almost complete photographic coverage and demolishing forever legends of Martians who left a network of canals irrigating their dying civilization. Two Viking spacecraft, launched in 1975, reached Mars a year later for the first successful landings and automated experiments examining Martian soil for signs of biological activity -- and finding none. The most recent probes to Mars were two Russian spacecraft launched in 1988; one failed en route, the other shortly after reaching Mars.</p>
        <p>Scientists hope that at the least Mars Observer will photograph the entire planet in finer detail than ever before and will be able to report on seasonal changes through an entire Martian year, which lasts 687 Earth days. The spacecraft is equipped with cameras and remote-sensing instruments to conduct the most thorough survey yet of the planet's topography, magnetism, mineral wealth, global wind storms and generally frigid weather and of the role water played in its past and could play in its future.</p>
        <p>Even if those canals were figments of human imagination, one of the most intriguing questions about Mars -- was there ever life there? -- hinges on the matter of water in the planet's past. The question is raised because of clear evidence of widespread dry river valleys and other scars of erosion indicating global flooding on Mars in its early years. So scientists think it is possible that in those wetter times, when the climate of Mars was probably more like Earth's, life could have evolved briefly and left some fossil traces that future explorers might search for.</p>
        <p>The other question is, where did the water go? Much of it undoubtedly evaporated into space, but previous spacecraft have detected large amounts of frozen water in the polar ice caps and have hinted at the existence of even more water trapped underground as a thick layer of permafrost extending over much of the higher latitudes. These residues of water, scientists reason, are the most promising places to search for pockets of existing microbial life or fossils of extinct organisms from the Martian past. Potential for Major Discoveries</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael H. Carr, a planetary geologists with the United States Geological Survey who is a member of the Mars Observer science team, said: "We know that life started on Earth. We don't know what happened on Mars, and so we want to go back in time and look at, particularly, water-associated deposits."</p>
        <p>The spacecraft's seven scientific instruments give the mission the potential for a wide range of discoveries beyond the water question.</p>
        <p>Mineral prospecting will be conducted by the gamma ray spectrometer. High-energy gamma radiation is produced by the natural decay of radioactive elements and by cosmic rays interacting with the atmosphere and surface. By observing these gamma rays, the spectrometer should be able to determine the chemical composition of the surface.</p>
        <p>The same instrument also includes a detector for measuring neutrons created by cosmic-ray impacts on the surface. The neutron detector is especially sensitive to the presence of hydrogen and carbon in Martian soil.</p>
        <p>"With the neutron data we will be able to map out planetwide the water content in the top meter of Martian soil and search for carbonate minerals that could indicate the previous existence of life on Mars," said Dr. Bill Feldman, the physicist at the Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico who developed the neutron detector.</p>
        <p>Minerals will also be identified by the thermal emission spectrometer, designed to measure telltale infrared emissions from the Martian surface. Another instrument, the pressure modulator infrared radiometer, will monitor the atmosphere by determining temperature, water vapor and dust from near the surface to altitudes of 50 miles.</p>
        <p>A magnetometer will search for evidence of a magnetic field now or in the past. Mars is the only planet, aside from Pluto, for which a planetary magnetic field has not yet been observed.</p>
        <p>"Mars ought to have on," Dr. Albee said. "If it doesn't, did it have one in the past? If it did have one in the past, when did it quit having a magnetic field, and why?"</p>
        <p>Scientists say the Mars Observer's narrow-angle camera is expected to take the most detailed pictures ever made of the planet, discerning objects as small as 10 feet across. The two wide-angle cameras can produce a complete color image of the entire planet every day.</p>
        <p>A laser altimeter will be used to measure the distance from the spacecraft to the surface with the precision of several feet. From these measurements, scientists will produce more exact relief maps of Mars and learn something of the geologic forces shaping the planet's crust.</p>
        <p>Dr. Huntress said that Mars Observer was a prerequisite to human flights to Mars because it should "provide a global data base and map where to send humans and what it is they are to do once they get there."</p>
        <p>Although President Bush has said human flights to Mars should be the ultimate goal of the American space program, there are no such firm plans and, in the current economic climate, are not likely to be any for some years. But there are plans to accelerate and broaden robotic exploration of the planet by both the United States and Russia, and all will be depending on Mars Observer.</p>
        <p>As Mars Observer is completing its primary mission covering one Martian year, a Russian spacecraft to be launched in 1994 would be delivering two or more small landers with scientific instruments to the surface of the planet. In addition, two "penetrators" would be deployed to drill into the surface for geological studies.</p>
        <p>Russian scientists are counting on Mars Observer maps to help them select the most promising landing sites. And the American craft will also be carrying a French radio to relay transmissions from the Russian landers and penetrators to control stations on Earth. This should insure a greater return of data than could be handled by Russian transmissions alone.</p>
        <p>If Mars Observer is still active in 1997, it will be asked to perform the same relay service for a planned Russian-European mission, launched in 1996, that is to deploy a roving vehicle on the Martian surface and a French balloon in the planet's thin carbon-dioxide atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Carr, a member of a joint working group of American and Russian planetary scientists, said that despite political and economic turmoil in the former Soviet Union, the Russian Mars projects for 1994 and 1996 appeared to retain financial support, with French help, and to remain on schedule. But scientists worried that the slightest setback could derail the programs.</p>
        <p>On the drawing boards is an even more comprehensive program of exploration to follow Mars Observer. As outlined by mission planners at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, NASA's next Mars mission would be called Pathfinder, a landing craft to be sent to the planet in 1996 carrying a small roving vehicle. Scientists said they were fairly optimistic that the project would be approved.</p>
        <p>Pathfinder would be a test run for the much more ambitious Mars Environmental Survey, or Mesur, a 10-year program that would deliver 16 small automated science stations to the planet's surface, beginning in 1999. The network will concentrate on geological studies, weather measurements and seismic monitoring to learn something of the Martian crust and deep interior. Some stations will have mini-rovers for going out and collecting rock samples and making other observations.</p>
        <p>Daniel S. Goldin, the NASA administrator, is pressing for such expanded exploration of Mars. The Mesur landers, he said, "will head for some of the more interesting areas of Mars -- such as the polar regions and canyons -- seeking possible human landing sites where the potential for water and signs of life or fossils may be greatest."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
