<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Surge of Interest In Affordable Housing</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'ROURKE, ANDREW P (COUNTY EXEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D61130F937A35753C1A964958260" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Surge of Interest In Affordable Housing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SIX months ago, when County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke offered 20 county-owned sites to municipalities interested in building affordable housing, the plan drew little response from politically sensitive municipal leaders.</p>
        <p>Last week county planners reported after months of discussion and negotiation that they were now swamped with requests for assistance, advice and financing from 27 housing groups, nonprofit agencies and some communities interested in building owner-occupied and rental units.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SIX months ago, when County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke offered 20 county-owned sites to municipalities interested in building affordable housing, the plan drew little response from politically sensitive municipal leaders.</p>
        <p>Last week county planners reported after months of discussion and negotiation that they were now swamped with requests for assistance, advice and financing from 27 housing groups, nonprofit agencies and some communities interested in building owner-occupied and rental units.</p>
        <p>The proposals, mostly unrelated to Mr. O'Rourke's housing plan, came from organizations eager to test the county's new commitment to build affordable housing and from communities desperate for affordable housing for their municipal workers and elderly residents, attracted by the County Executive's promise to give preference to local residents and to respect zoning laws.</p>
        <p>Spurred by the March ruling from the State Attorney General that gave counties the power to build housing and to override local zoning if necessary, Westchester has set aside $100,000 to provide technical assistance to housing-advocacy groups. That money is in addition to money from the county's Housing Implementation Fund and two federally financed programs, the Community Development Block Grant program and the HOME program. 'Something Must Be Done'</p>
        <p>Groups advocating affordable housing have started appearing in large numbers at legislative committee meetings and, said Judith R. Shepard, a member of the Subcommittee on Community Affairs and Housing, "There's a greater awareness on the part of some board members that something must be done."</p>
        <p>David Bogdanoff, a retired builder who was chairman of the county's Citizen Advisory Committee on Housing until he was dismissed for criticizing Mr. O'Rourke's lack of attention to building affordable housing, said the political climate for such housing is warming up. "Has there been any significant amount of rental housing put in the works?" he asked. "Obviously not. But there is movement, and it is beginning to permeate all levels of government."</p>
        <p>Lynn Oliva, the County Planning Commissioner, said last week, "If all goes well, we will have 175 affordable new homes and 300 new rental units under construction within the next year." The proposed affordably priced rental units would be the first built in Westchester since Mr. Bogdanoff built a 90-unit complex in Yorktown in 1985.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Oliva concedes that her estimates are optimistic. Building affordable housing in Westchester has been an agonizing process in a county whose leaders have been reluctant to oppose residents who fear the prospect of neighbors with limited incomes and worry that their arrival will lower property values and increase crime. Legal Action Under Consideration</p>
        <p>Neighborhood opponents announced last week that they are considering legal action to stop an affordable-housing project in Harrison, the first community actively to support Mr. O'Rourke's plan.</p>
        <p>The project, consisting of 14 two-family homes on a 4.5-acre site on Main Street, has aroused strong community opposition since the announcement in June that 25 houses were proposed.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the project, including members of the Harrison Town Board and county officials, say the impending legal action will not change the course of a project they believe will be a model for the development of affordable housing in the county and around the state.</p>
        <p>"Our whole purpose was to get preference for our residents using county land and county money," said the Harrison Supervisor, Charles G. Balancia, a condition the proposal guarantees. He said he was dismayed by community opponents who continue to resist the plan, make angry phone calls to his home and threaten legal action. "Who wouldn't applaud it?" he asked. "Is there something I'm missing?"</p>
        <p>The Board of Legislators tomorrow will begin considering a proposal to transfer the county-owned site to the Village of Harrison. The proposal is believed to have the support of a majority of the Board's 17 members.</p>
        <p>The Legislators will also consider whether to include a one-third-acre section that county lawyers discovered has parkland designation. Revoking that status, which would require the approval of county and state legislators, would allow adding three more houses to the plan. The parkland issue could become the basis for a lawsuit, opponents of the housing plan say.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, municipal workers and other Harrison residents earning $28,000 to $64,000 would purchase the homes for $154,000 to $184,000 and rent units to low-income elderly residents who will receive rental assistance under the Federal Section 8 program. Legal Battle Is Seen</p>
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, son of Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the project's developer, has established Equity Homes, a nonprofit corporation, to seek Federal and state subsidies to help finance the plan and others like it in the state.</p>
        <p>The neighbors' suit, Mr. Cuomo said, was expected. "What else is new? Any project worth doing is worth suing," he said, adding that every attempt he has made to build temporary or permanent housing has led to a legal battle, although the opposition is always based on tangential issues like use of parkland or threats to wildlife.</p>
        <p>The opponents "don't trust government," Mr. Cuomo said. "They don't believe a preferential system will be enforced, and they believe they will have different people in their neighborhood than at present. They don't want that."</p>
        <p>Once county and village officials give final approval to the plan, a process expected to be completed in a month, "the project will go forward," Andrew Cuomo said. Groundbreaking is expected this fall. 'Others Will Follow'</p>
        <p>Timothy S. Carey, the county legislator who is chairman of the Subcommittee on Community Affairs and Housing, said last week that a successful Harrison project will spur other developments. "If we can just get it done, others will follow," Mr. Carey said. "All we have to do is get it up and running." His committee, Mr. Carey said, plans to insure that the Harrison project gets all necessary financing for road and sewer improvements through the County's Housing Implementation Fund.</p>
        <p>Legislative support, Mr. Carey said, has provided other money from the fund to help several projects around the county and has helped create 300 permanent units of housing in the last three years. With new attention from county officials, Mr. Carey said, numerous small grants are now available for affordable-housing groups to perform feasibility studies and to hire architects.</p>
        <p>"Affordable housing can work if each community will look at how to create a win-win situation," said Ms. Shepard, the subcommittee member. "People have to feel they will get something out of it."</p>
        <p>Part of Ms. Shepard's district is in Yorktown where a nonprofit group, the Association for the Improvement of Mohegan, presented a proposal to the Yorktown Town Board to rehabilitate two dilapidated buildings housing 11 families and to build 6 additional units of low-income housing. Part of the rehabilitation plan calls for extending county sewer lines, allowing 150 homeowners to hook in. 'Hundreds Showed Up and Cheered'</p>
        <p>Without a sewer line, many homeowners have not been able to sell their homes. At the first public hearing, "hundreds showed up, and they cheered," said the association's executive director, Hune Margulies. "This is an example of an affordable-housing project revitalizing the community."</p>
        <p>In the towns of Bedford, Cortlandt, Eastchester and Greenburgh and in the cities of Rye and New Rochelle, discussions are under way or site plans are being drawn or grant applications are being submitted for proposals to increase the amount of affordable housing in the county.</p>
        <p>"We are not trying to ram anything down anybody's throat," Commissioner Oliva said. "We are working cooperatively. We haven't said, 'We're the county and it doesn't matter what you want.' Communities are beginning to realize we are not going to dictate the process."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
