<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle in Rio: The Day After Friends and Foes Agree On a Sharper Sentinel</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE EARTH SUMMIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC113DF936A25755C0A964958260" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle in Rio: The Day After Friends and Foes Agree On a Sharper Sentinel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Earth Summit, which wound up with predictable fanfare today, has given the world its first real glimpse of the kind of global diplomacy that is becoming possible now that the the cold war is over. But the conference has also shown how difficult negotiating worldwide solutions to worldwide problems is likely to be.</p>
        <p>For decades East-West tensions made it hard to take joint approaches to challenges affecting all the world's nations, including environmental problems like threats to the atmosphere, population growth, and international migration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Earth Summit, which wound up with predictable fanfare today, has given the world its first real glimpse of the kind of global diplomacy that is becoming possible now that the the cold war is over. But the conference has also shown how difficult negotiating worldwide solutions to worldwide problems is likely to be.</p>
        <p>For decades East-West tensions made it hard to take joint approaches to challenges affecting all the world's nations, including environmental problems like threats to the atmosphere, population growth, and international migration.</p>
        <p>Yet over the last 10 days, the Earth Summit brought together the greatest number of world leaders that have ever assembled with a single aim -- in this case to seek a global agreement that shifts mankind's search for economic betterment onto a more environmentally sound plane by asking developing countries to industrialize in environmentally sustainable ways. A Time of Promise</p>
        <p>They came together at a time of extraordinary promise in world affairs, after the demise of Communism, which has reordered priorities not only in the industrialized world but also in the developing world.</p>
        <p>The summit agreement that was approved today has already been denounced by some groups as weak -- as "business as usual" and "a failure to set a new direction for life on earth," as Friends of the Earth called it today. And countries of the developing South have expressed disappointment that the industrialized North was not more generous.</p>
        <p>But for many, the accord is important mainly as the start of a process that could eventually change the way the world approaches the challenge of fostering economic growth in the Southern Hemisphere, shifting the basis of all new aid and investment toward environmental responsibility. A Watchdog Group</p>
        <p>Just as the world has set up international agencies to insure respect for human rights and to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons, so the Earth Summit created a new Sustainable Development Commission to monitor the world's compliance with the promises it made at Rio.</p>
        <p>"The Rio Conference does not end at Rio," the Brazilian President, Fernando Collor de Mello, said today.</p>
        <p>The strength of public interest in the meeting -- 10,000 private environmentalists and 8,000 journalists attended -- suggests that governments will not be allowed to forget what they have begun.</p>
        <p>But the Earth Summit also showed that tackling global challenges in today's world means forging agreement among some 180 countries that are no longer focused on the East-West divide, and who may regard the United States as no more than one player among many. Re-examining the U.N.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union's disintegration has allowed the United States to dominate the United Nations Security Council in recent years, using it to achieve its aims in many areas and arousing fears of a "unipolar" world under effective American domination.</p>
        <p>But the Earth Summit was a reminder that outside the field of peace and security, the United Nations lacks other small, powerful bodies like the Security Council that the United States, as the remaining superpower, can work through to achieve its ends.</p>
        <p>The United Nations also remains the only international framework that exists for approaching global challenges, however, and its machinery often requires what can be a slow, fumbling search for consensus among its nearly 200 members.</p>
        <p>The agreement sought by the Earth Summit participants on the environment and development, as on any other global issue, was intended to be a bargain between North and South that both halves would find in their interests.</p>
        <p>The developing countries hoped to pick up some of the economic gains they tried but failed to win in the 1970's when they called for a new world economic order. This time, they tried to persuade the North to eradicate poverty in return for cleaner growth in the South.</p>
        <p>The Northern governments, it was hoped, would agree to this because of the strength of environmentalist groups back home and because their own efforts to fight pollution would come to little in the end if the Southern countries did not follow suit.</p>
        <p>But the initial outcome fell short of Southern expectations largely because of the growing rifts within Northern and Southern camps.</p>
        <p>Opposition of countries like Malaysia and India to any binding commitment on preserving the world's forests meant that the South could not offer the one concession that might have encouraged the Bush Administration to take the Earth Summit more seriously.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the genuine fear among small island states that they will soon be flooded if temperatures rise left the developing world divided over the urgency of curbing "greenhouse" gas emissions. Ultimately it meant that the Southern countries could not hold the global-warming convention hostage to Northern concessions.</p>
        <p>In a complete change of position since the first oil-price shock of the 1970's, when Saudi Arabia and other oil exporters told the industrialized countries that they would have to reduce consumption if they wanted prices to decline, major oil exporters are now fighting the world consensus in favor of saving energy. Issues That Cross Divide</p>
        <p>Some concerns cut across the North-South divide. Efforts to promote family planning as the key to population control, higher living standards and reduced pressure on the environment ran into opposition from a curious coalition, including the Vatican, conservative Islamic nations and some feminists who argued that male-dominated governments should not interfere with women's lives.</p>
        <p>At the conference, the United States made no attempt to exercise the kind of leadership it had shown at a world environment meeting 20 years earlier in Stockholm that brought environmental concerns into sharper focus on the diplomatic agenda.</p>
        <p>Instead the Bush Administration appeared divided and paralyzed by ideology and political concerns, reinforcing the perception that in an election year it is incapable of facing up to new foreign policy challenges.</p>
        <p>Among industrialized countries, Japan alone appeared ready to offer the South meaningful new aid, but it made no attempt to lead the Northern bloc. Indeed, Prime Minister Kiichi Miyazawa, citing a legislative debate at home about whether to commit troops to international peacekeepiung forces, did not even attend the Earth Summit.</p>
        <p>As a result the United States, Britain and the Germany successfully resisted being drawn into any specific commitments on new aid, despite pressure from France and the Scandinavians to be more generous. East Bloc's Argument</p>
        <p>Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union infuriated the South by asserting that their "transitional" status as countries on the road to capitalism justified special aid.</p>
        <p>And Germany confirmed the Southern countries' worst fears by citing its commitment to helping the former Communist countries of Eastern Europe as a major reason that it could not do more for the South.</p>
        <p>The collapse of Communism, widely seen as ushering in a new era of more constructive international diplomacy, has thus ended up by pushing North and South even further apart.  THE EARTH SUMMIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
