<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Georgetown, a Speech on Education's Ills</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEGREES, ACADEMIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGETOWN UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BARD COLLEGE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT COLLEGE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD173AF937A15756C0A964958260" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Georgetown, a Speech on Education's Ills</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decline in American education can be traced to the way in which colleges and universities increasingly are run like businesses, Robert N. Bellah, a sociology professor at the University of California at Berkeley, told graduates of the College of Arts and Sciences at Georgetown University yesterday.</p>
        <p>"When education becomes merely a means to an end, it loses its integrity and fails in its own deepest vocation," Professor Bellah said at the university's 193d commencement in Washington. "Since American business is not obviously superior to other major American institutions, it is not clear why it should provide a model for education."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The decline in American education can be traced to the way in which colleges and universities increasingly are run like businesses, Robert N. Bellah, a sociology professor at the University of California at Berkeley, told graduates of the College of Arts and Sciences at Georgetown University yesterday.</p>
        <p>"When education becomes merely a means to an end, it loses its integrity and fails in its own deepest vocation," Professor Bellah said at the university's 193d commencement in Washington. "Since American business is not obviously superior to other major American institutions, it is not clear why it should provide a model for education."</p>
        <p>Professor Bellah, the author of two books about individualism and American character, received an honorary degree yesterday.</p>
        <p>Georgetown held six separate commencement ceremonies yesterday and will hold one on Monday. Each commencement speaker received an honorary degree yesterday.</p>
        <p>Edward Djerejian, assistant Secretary of State for Near East and South Asian Affairs, spoke to graduates of the School of Foreign Service.</p>
        <p>John J. Ring, president of the American Medical Association, addressed students at Georgetown's Medical School.</p>
        <p>Laurel Copp, a professor in the nursing school at the University of North Carolina, spoke to the 52 graduates of the Association of Colleges of Nursing.</p>
        <p>Shirley B. Heath, a professor of English at Stanford University, addressed graduates of the School of Language and Linguistics.</p>
        <p>Representative Amo Houghton, Republican of upstate New York, spoke to graduates of the School of Business Administration.</p>
        <p>Mayor Sharon Pratt Kelly of Washington will speak to graduates of the Law Center on Monday at 10 A.M. Bard College</p>
        <p>Bard College held its 132d commencement yesterday on the main campus lawn in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. William Julius Wilson delivered the commencement address to the school's largest graduating class, about 235 graduating seniors and 24 master's degree recipients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilson, a sociologist and a professor of race relations and public policy at the University of Chicago, received an honorary doctorate of humane letters.</p>
        <p>Honorary doctorates were also awarded to the choreographer and dancer Jean Erdman; the educator John C. Honey; the jazz musician Sonny Rollins; Dr. Oliver Sacks, the neurologist and writer, and the film director Martin Scorsese. Connecticut College</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the administrator of the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, delivered the commencement address at Connecticut College's 74th commencement, held yesterday at the school's New London campus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly spoke to the 400 undergraduates about global climate warming and next month's international Earth Summit in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Besides Mr. Reilly's honorary doctor of law degree, a doctor of science degree was awarded to Rosalyn S. Yalow, the 1977 Nobel Prize winner for medicine. David Arthur Hayes, the founder of the National Theater of the Deaf, received an honorary doctor of fine arts.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
