<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of the West, Rose Rustlers</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="565561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROSES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D7173CF936A15753C1A964958260" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of the West, Rose Rustlers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Texas rose rustler had come to Brooklyn, and the old roses around here gave him itchy fingers.</p>
        <p>"Old Blush," G. Michael Shoup said with certainty, staring at a nondescript little bush in front of an old brick town house on Prospect Park West. It didn't even have a bloom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Texas rose rustler had come to Brooklyn, and the old roses around here gave him itchy fingers.</p>
        <p>"Old Blush," G. Michael Shoup said with certainty, staring at a nondescript little bush in front of an old brick town house on Prospect Park West. It didn't even have a bloom.</p>
        <p>"Yeah," said Stephen Scanniello, the rosarian at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, who has been known to rustle in old churchyards and vacant lots. "Look at the twiggy growth, the little leaves." The two rustlers had started out in the Botanic Garden's rose garden, but it was too tame in there.</p>
        <p>Old Blush is a lovely pink China rose with a delicate fragrance, introduced to England in 1759.</p>
        <p>A tall, elegant man (the scarf, the soft leather jacket) came out from the backyard with a cool, almost irritated expression on his face. "Could I help you?" he asked. He was Dr. Gary Mulkowsky.</p>
        <p>The two rustlers explained that they were scouting out old roses that thrived in the 19th century and earlier, but may have been forgotten since hybrid teas came into vogue. The antiques are often the hardiest -- having survived years of neglect -- and their fragrance hasn't been bred right out of them. By taking cuttings and starting new plants, the rustlers are protecting roses that might otherwise be lost to the world.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mulkowsky, who teaches international finance at Baruch College, looked protectively at his little bush.</p>
        <p>"I don't know its name, but it blooms all summer," he said. "And it smells wonderful." He sized up the strangers. "I guess you can take a cutting. If it won't hurt the plant."</p>
        <p>Mr. Scanniello said not to worry, this was just sort of a dry run (though he had pruners in his pocket), a little identification game.  Even when a rose is not blooming, its name may be guessed by looking at its leaves and stems and seeing whether it has thorns or "mossy" little prickles that smell like pine if you rub your fingers along the petioles.</p>
        <p>Another clue lies at the base of the plant. If it has a large knot, where the top of one plant has been grafted onto a sturdier rootstock, you may well be looking at a modern rose. This point isn't foolproof, because sometimes nurseries graft old varieties. But no graft means you're hot on the trail of a bona fide antique.</p>
        <p>Though propagating old roses probably goes back to the world's first grandmother, rose rustling got its name about 10 years ago when Mr. Shoup and a group of other rose scholars (to put it politely, though Mr. Shoup</p>
        <p>does</p>
        <p>have a master's in horticulture) were rambling over the homesteads of Bellville, Tex., and a hardboiled resident appeared with his shotgun. After a quick retreat, the collectors realized they were</p>
        <p>rustlers.</p>
        <p>Just like those guys that rode the range.</p>
        <p>(Don't worry. These people are very polite and will always ask your permission before rustling your rose.)</p>
        <p>The attention turned to a vigorous climber on the south side of Dr. Mulkowsky's front door. It had one lone rose blooming -- half-gone, to tell the truth -- and the stems were almost thornless (a clue for any good rustler).</p>
        <p>"Maybe a climbing La France," Mr. Scanniello said. La France was the first hybrid tea, introduced in 1867; the climbing form came a bit later. But both types have fragrant, silvery pink blossoms</p>
        <p>all</p>
        <p>summer. And this beauty can stand the cold. No wonder it started the hybrid tea craze.</p>
        <p>"Maybe it's Zephirine Drouhin," Mr. Shoup said, studying the leaves of the season's new growth. "No, Zephirine has more of a bronzy-red growth."</p>
        <p>On the other hand, could it be a climbing American Beauty, they wondered. Hmmm.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mulkowsky was warming up to the gang. "It was here when I came 15 years ago," he said. "It smells wonderful."</p>
        <p>He knew a good thing when he saw it. "Would you mind coming around back for a minute?" There, among the weeds and ivy, were a number of roses: something that might be Old Blush, a modern Red Blaze, maybe a polyantha rose (no, wait, they found the buried tag; it was just a Bonica).</p>
        <p>Rose rustling is really very simple.</p>
        <p>"Down in Texas, the old-timers just stick the cuttings right in the ground," said Mr. Shoup, who began collecting old roses 10 years ago. "Under a redbud tree, or out back by the faucet." These old practices make sense: a redbud tree isn't very big, so it offers filtered light, and there's humidity and moisture by a faucet.</p>
        <p>Marc Weissbach, a friend of Dr. Mulkowsky's, shook his head in disbelief. "You mean you can just take one of these branches and make a new bush out of it?" he asked. He kept shaking his head over the miracle of getting something for nothing.</p>
        <p>Late summer and right through the fall is a perfect time to rustle roses. Gardeners around New York may be better off starting their cuttings in pots, so they can bring them into a cool, sunny place when the hard freeze hits. Long Islanders, though, or gardeners in more temperate climates might try a version of the redbud-faucet trick.</p>
        <p>The advantage of starting cuttings outdoors is that the plant, once established, doesn't have to be mollycoddled. It's had its feet in the soil and its head in wind and rainsince birth. Potted roses have to be gradually acclimated to the outdoors.</p>
        <p>To start new plants from an old rose, take a four- to five-inch cutting from the tip of a cane, making sure each cutting has at least two leaf nodes. Strip the bottom leaves, but keep the others, because these will make food for the plant while it develops new roots.</p>
        <p>For potted plants, stick each cutting into a little pot with very light potting soil that is moist but not wet, and cover it with a plastic bag to keep the miniclimate moist. Make sure you vent your makeshift greenhouses on sunny days or the cuttings will cook to death.</p>
        <p>"I've seen little peat pots hanging in Baggies from a clothesline," Mr. Scanniello said. Keep these outside until the weather turns frigid; then move them to a cool, sunny windowsill.</p>
        <p>To "stick" cuttings outside, find a well-drained spot in bright shade (such as under the mother rosebush or under a redbud tree) and keep the area moist. Some people make instant greenhouses by sticking quart jars or plastic milk jugs over these babies, with little pebbles under the rims for ventilation. Remove the covers once the plants are established, usually in about six weeks, Mr. Shoup said. If you live in a mild climate, just give them a few days to get used to the open air, then transplant to a permanent spot. Northerners may want to mulch them right where they are after the ground freezes and to transplant them in the early spring.</p>
        <p>An even easier way to propagate old roses is to bend a long, flexible cane, nick it about one-third through (see drawing) and bury the nicked area about six inches deep, leaving about two inches of the tip above ground. Place a rock over the bent cane to hold it in place and retain soil moisture. Once the plant is established just dig it up and move it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoup and another rose lover named Liz Druitt tell all about such tricks, as well as the art of rose rustling, in "Landscaping With Antique Roses," just published by Taunton Books ($34.95). Mr. Shoup's running with the gang in Texas also led to his business, the Antique Rose Emporium in Brenham, Tex., which offers more than 250 kinds of roses.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
