<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Redefining National Security</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CARNEGIE ENDOWMENT FOR INTERNATIONAL PEACE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GELB, LESLIE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LORD, WINSTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDD1F3EF931A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Redefining National Security</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE H. GELB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GELB, LESLIE H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We all know that the world has undergone a revolution. Equally evident, U.S. foreign policy has hardly adapted. But no one has added up the new facts, or clearly demonstrated the gap between the new realities and American responses or pointed to eminently doable ways of bridging that gap and restoring American strength and leadership -- until now.</p>
        <p>The job was done by a bipartisan commission of government veterans headed by Winston Lord, former U.S. Ambassador to China and State Department planning chief. The Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (of which I am a trustee) sponsored the enterprise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We all know that the world has undergone a revolution. Equally evident, U.S. foreign policy has hardly adapted. But no one has added up the new facts, or clearly demonstrated the gap between the new realities and American responses or pointed to eminently doable ways of bridging that gap and restoring American strength and leadership -- until now.</p>
        <p>The job was done by a bipartisan commission of government veterans headed by Winston Lord, former U.S. Ambassador to China and State Department planning chief. The Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (of which I am a trustee) sponsored the enterprise.</p>
        <p>The commission report is an anthology of hard facts and good sense. It lays out where the U.S. and others must spend more money to avoid disasters. It also shows how to pay the new bills.</p>
        <p>Based on the new realities, the commission recommends these spending priorities:</p>
        <p>Population.</p>
        <p>The crowded earth already peopled by about 5.5 billion will groan under about 8.5 billion by 2025. This growth will overwhelm governments, resources and the environment. The cures are economic growth and education. But the Reagan and Bush Administrations have not helped. They stopped contributions to family planning efforts abroad because of false fears about promoting abortion.</p>
        <p>Refugees.</p>
        <p>The international homeless total reached 18 million in 1991, and grows faster each year. The main causes are war and poverty. Costs are staggering: $7 billion yearly just for those seeking political asylum.</p>
        <p>Peacekeeping and Peacemaking.</p>
        <p>The flood of refugees will grow and so will threats to peace unless collective security is strengthened, and quickly. U.N. forces now stand guard in a dozen places at an annual cost approaching $3 billion. That figure will have to be at least doubled and a standing U.N. force established to prevent what could become rampant anarchy.</p>
        <p>Economic Development.</p>
        <p>Aid to and trade with poor nations are matters of self-interest to rich ones. U.S. trade with developing nations has been increasing faster than with any other group of nations and already is 35 percent of all U.S. exports. Trade as a percentage of U.S. gross national product has doubled to 25 percent since 1970. Making the poor richer is the best way to prevent refugees and create new exports and wealth for Americans.</p>
        <p>The Environment.</p>
        <p>The tab for making good environmental practices affordable for poor countries (and for wealthy ones as well) will be in the billions yearly. But the costs of doing little to control greenhouse warming gases and deforestation would be unimaginably higher. And dealing with environmental problems will create jobs and growth.</p>
        <p>Also with attention to hard facts, here is how the commission proposes to raise the necessary money -- and plenty more to cover domestic priorities and budget-deficit reduction:</p>
        <p>Promoting Economic Growth Through Freer Trade.</p>
        <p>This is the surest and cheapest means to pump up economies. For the U.S., every additional $1 billion in exports produces 20,000 jobs. The leaders of the industrial world have become so mesmerized by economic gimmicks and so mired in domestic politics that they have failed for years to press ahead on the freer-trade front.</p>
        <p>Cutting Military Expenditures.</p>
        <p>Worldwide spending for arms and armed forces reached $1.2 trillion in 1988, and if promises are kept, will decline to about $800 billion by 1996. The commission wants to bring this down by an additional $200 billion, which seems reasonable given the decline of transnational threats. For the U.S. alone, this could generate savings of $90 billion annually after five years.</p>
        <p>Raising Energy Taxes.</p>
        <p>U.S. energy efficiency is about half that of Western Europe and Japan. Inefficiency here adds to the trade deficit and undermines competitiveness and security. Higher prices are central to efficiency, and U.S. gas taxes are one-eighth Western Europe's and one-fourth Japan's. The commission calls for increases of up to $1 per gallon, over time and with help for the needy.</p>
        <p>This package of proposals profoundly redefines U.S. national security -- away from military concerns and toward a new agenda. And yet it is manageable and affordable. It does not call for a political or governmental revolution, only for leadership.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
