<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Point Reyes: Paradise Retouched</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL PARKS, MONUMENTS AND SEASHORES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MARIN COUNTY (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">POINT REYES NATIONAL SEASHORE (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, DANIEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Point Reyes National Seashore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE1E31F93AA15752C1A964958260" item-length="2952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Point Reyes: Paradise Retouched</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL LEWIS;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, DANIEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE trail up to Mount Wittenberg rises steep but short, so if you pace yourself you can reach the top with enough breath left to cheer the view.</p>
        <p>From this 1,400-foot lookout in the middle of the Point Reyes National Seashore in California, green-black forests and golden meadows roll down to a coastline that the eye can follow for miles without spotting a living soul. In the middle distance two estuaries, named Drakes Estero and Limantour Estero, cut inland like the last blank spaces in a topographic puzzle. To the left the long sandy finger of Limantour Spit points outward along the great arc of Drakes Beach toward Chimney Rock and blue infinity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE trail up to Mount Wittenberg rises steep but short, so if you pace yourself you can reach the top with enough breath left to cheer the view.</p>
        <p>From this 1,400-foot lookout in the middle of the Point Reyes National Seashore in California, green-black forests and golden meadows roll down to a coastline that the eye can follow for miles without spotting a living soul. In the middle distance two estuaries, named Drakes Estero and Limantour Estero, cut inland like the last blank spaces in a topographic puzzle. To the left the long sandy finger of Limantour Spit points outward along the great arc of Drakes Beach toward Chimney Rock and blue infinity.</p>
        <p>My wife, Katy, and I have caught the fog in an idle moment, just barely. As we make the summit a dense white blot, suspended like an emulsion between the sky and the water, has already started ashore, swallowing the horizon, outrunning itself here and there to leave momentary holes pierced through by cones of sunlight.</p>
        <p>It is one of the great views of the California coast -- and one of the nicer illusions of our time. An easy drive from San Francisco, the Point Reyes peninsula is not an untouched paradise, of course, but a retouched facsimile: an outpost where they have tried to turn back the clock against the overgrazing, extermination and speculation that once seemed sure to transform an ecological marvel into a Marin County suburb.</p>
        <p>The story of this experiment wasn't on our minds at all when we decided to steal an extended weekend this September, find a cozy inn and spend a few days hiking the 65,000-square-mile seashore park. But by coincidence we got there at a time for recollection. September was the 30th anniversary of the law establishing Point Reyes as the first of a new kind of Federal preserve, where the idea was to freeze things and try to reclaim a lost natural order, rather than conserve a pristine one.</p>
        <p>No doubt there are many people who believe the reversal didn't go far enough, and others who still curse the time when the Government broke up the roads for foot trails and squashed a housing venture inevitably named Drakes Beach Estates. But on balance the compromise that Point Reyes became -- less than a wilderness, more than an outdoor museum -- may be the best that could be hoped for in a unique place accessible to so many.</p>
        <p>The peninsula has undeniably regained much of its natural diversity through the years, sometimes by being left alone and sometimes helped by importation of species that had disappeared. In less than three full days of easy hiking, Katy and I saw a greater range of landscapes, weathers, plant life and wildlife than can be found in any comparable area of the country that I know of. We came across tule elk, pronghorn antelope and gray fox; damp Douglas fir forests and dry sage country; squadrons of brown pelicans patrolling the shallow waters where occasional sightings now foreshadow the gray-whale migration that reaches its peak around the Christmas season.</p>
        <p>Add the comforts of friendly inns and good California cooking in the little towns of Inverness and Point Reyes Station, and it's no mystery why Point Reyes attracted more than 2.4 million people in 1991. It is one of the most-visited places in the national park system. Yet, if you can arrange to be there in midweek, you may walk the trails for half a day and find no human company but your own.</p>
        <p>We drove up on a Sunday after breakfast in San Francisco, checked into our room at 10 Inverness Way, a bed-and-breakfast in Inverness, and less than an hour later we were oriented and setting off on our first walk.</p>
        <p>"Efficient" may be a funny word for such a place, but figuring out Point Reyes seems less bother than finding your way around a department store. It has been so thoroughly observed and described that there's a name, a map, a marker, a story for everything. Then too, the peninsula is easy to visualize in distinct sections -- geographic zones and bands with characteristics determined by elevation, soil type, distance from the ocean and the like.</p>
        <p>AT the northernmost end, where we began, the main hiking route is the Tomales Point Trail, a nearly nine-mile round trip through grasslands, manzanita, thistle and other low growth along an ever-narrowing spine of land. The seashore's tule elk live in this section, and in due time we came upon dozens of them grazing a few hundred feet from picnicking hikers. There had been a lot of antler-banging lately, according to the innkeeper, as the males fought out the protocol of the annual rut. But things had evidently been sorted out for now. A humorless bull was calling in the herd with that unearthly nasal bugling sound the elk make, and there was no backtalk.</p>
        <p>Another reward of the Tomales trail is the double-barreled sight of the Pacific below the cliffs on one side, and the long expanse of Tomales Bay on the other. As you walk farther out toward land's end, with the packed gravel trail fading into a footpath over high grassy dunes, the panorama stops you in your tracks time and again.</p>
        <p>Or so they say. On this afternoon we soon crossed a ragged line of fog that cut us off completely from the warm sunny day in Inverness, just a few miles behind us, and entered a world that grew clammier and smaller the more we walked.</p>
        <p>It is no use hoping that the weather will cooperate at Point Reyes. You end up fitting your expectations to the conditions. You may even find that this is a key to the relaxing influence of the place; it flexes a different set of mental muscles than those needed for the everyday antler-banging of city life.</p>
        <p>At first, gaps would open to show a tantalizing sliver of beach and surf, or a slab of cliff the size of a Gothic cathedral. By the time we reached the end of land at Tomales Point in late afternoon we couldn't see much past a congregation of cormorants sitting off duty on the rocks less than 100 feet below.</p>
        <p>On the return trip, all gloom broke loose. No self-respecting film director would dare call for such dreary light, keening wind and thickness of fog as now goaded us back toward the trailhead. Nature was reduced to the particular and the eerie. Nearby mule deer were keeping track of us, and their skinny necks and huge ears would pop up unexpectedly like cutouts against a dim screen. Hundreds of busy things hopped and skittered in the brush all around -- a little bird called the Townsend's warbler, we later determined. An occasional tiny yellow flower, looking out of season and out of place, was the only evidence that the universe had not turned monochrome.</p>
        <p>Night fell during the drive back to the inn. And when we had finished getting the fine brown sand out of everything and recovering from fog-induced disorientation, we saw it was already past closing time at Manka's, a restaurant up the road in Inverness that friends had advised us not to miss. We had dinner instead at a nondescript place in another town, and little to complain about. It would take a weird talent to find bad produce, bad wine or bad coffee in that part of California, and Point Reyes has its own famous specialty besides: fresh oysters. They were delicious pan-fried.</p>
        <p>We nevertheless made a resolution to leave more time the next day for after-hours pleasures. And stuck to it.</p>
        <p>The first day's walk had shown that despite some knowledge of California country -- Katy grew up in the northern Cascades, and we have hiked a good many places from the Trinity Alps to Big Sur -- we would need help sorting out the profusion, and unusual variants, of plant and animal life of Point Reyes.</p>
        <p>The Park Service's free maps and brochures are adequate guides for general hiking, sightseeing and wildlife spotting. For a more detailed sense of the strange geology, climate, flora and fauna, we got good use from "The Natural History of the Point Reyes Peninsula" by the local naturalist Jules G. Evens (published by Point Reyes National Seashore Association, Point Reyes, Calif. 94956; $14.95).</p>
        <p>This is a readable distillation of countless papers, scientific studies and anecdotes from 1579, when Sir Francis Drake put ashore for repairs (thus Drakes Beach), through the Spanish ranching period, the profitable frenzy of seal-hunting and whale-hunting, and on through the late 80's. It's conveniently organized and it explains, among other phenomena, how earth-plate activity must have moved the peninsula to its current location from many miles away; why the average temperature stays much the same year round (in the 50's), and why the birds, mammals and fish migrate as they do. But a dedicated birder or botanizer would also need detailed field guides, because the Evens book is not profusely illustrated. (Though it quotes a finding, for example, that 61 plants on the Point Reyes peninsula do not appear elsewhere in Marin County, it includes few drawings of plants.)</p>
        <p>Privately published nature books and trail guides of less ambitious scope can be bought at information centers like the one at Point Reyes Light and the Park Service's main visitors headquarters at Bear Valley. Both places were on our itinerary for Day 2, which covered central parts of the seashore.</p>
        <p>The lighthouse stands on the severe western tip of the peninsula, which means driving a half-hour or so through ranch country neither more nor less interesting than ranch country elsewhere in the West. Beef and dairy products were long synonymous with Point Reyes and the herds are still a significant factor, though they are fewer now and the government has a hand in managing them.</p>
        <p>The lighthouse was built far down on a cliff, so that its beacon can be seen under the fog. Along the 300-odd steps leading down to it are platforms that become prime whale-watching points in season, and welcome rest stops for the upward bound at any time of year. There's not much in the way of hiking at this end of the point, but the headlands are impressive and there is the added attraction of Sea Lion Overlook, which is exactly what it says it is. Toward the east-central part of the peninsula, at Bear Valley, the well-organized Park Service headquarters would be a logical first stop for visitors. It is also the trailhead for several walks, including the Bear Valley Trail, the most popular of the lot.</p>
        <p>I have mixed feelings about the Bear Valley Trail. In a little more than four miles (one way) it takes you through a cross-section of damp forest, dry hills and coast, and ultimately to the imposing ocean outcropping called Arch Rock. It helps you understand how Point Reyes is divided and affected by Inverness Ridge, which runs up through the peninsula like a spine.</p>
        <p>And it is alive with animals, many of which seem to have developed an offhand attitude toward humans that stops short of tameness. On one stretch a beautiful little gray fox hunted the edges of the trail ahead, keeping a distance of about 40 yards and glancing back at us almost playfully. At another spot we were delayed a few minutes by a skunk who would neither be shooed away nor let us come very close without menacingly raising his tail. We finally gambled that he was bluffing, and we were right.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the Bear Valley Trail is so easy and well-worn as to be a little tedious after a while. Either on the way out to Arch Rock or the way back, it's a good idea to explore one or more of the paths that branch off from it into somewhat more challenging terrain. We tried the Sky Trail (about 2.5 miles), and the spur from the top of it that leads to the bald height of Mount Wittenberg and its spectacular view; and the Meadow Trail, an alternative, less-steep route to Wittenberg from a different angle. It leads not only through meadows but also through fragrant Douglas fir forest with very old trees that somehow escaped cutting in the days when these hills fed the sawmills.</p>
        <p>That evening we had dinner at the Station House Cafe in Point Reyes Station, a wonderful restaurant to linger in. Nineteen years after it helped to redefine California cuisine, it remains a fresh and warming place, open morning to night and serving everything from hamburgers to the latest inventions for purple-potato-eating people. Our dishes included salmon with mint pasta and mint hollandaise, and a hearty combination of fettuccine and lamb shanks. And the next day we returned for a late lunch of souffle-light polenta with two cheeses, and a salad from heaven.</p>
        <p>Our last day of hiking -- spent mindlessly tramping around deserted Limantour Beach and the estuary trails behind it, the Muddy Hollow and Estero Trails -- was the least eventful and in some ways the most enjoyable. We don't pretend to be serious birders -- it is a hard thing to pretend to be -- but we had no trouble identifying more than a dozen birds on a day when the area was not exactly teeming with activity.</p>
        <p>All in all, I prefer nature a bit less managed than the version Point Reyes offers, so I had imagined that our three days there would be plenty. But we ran out of hours before we ran out of inviting destinations, including the entire southern section of the peninsula.</p>
        <p>I suspect we will find a reason to go back some day. A national seashore is not the worst use of Federal tax dollars I can think of. And a citizen ought to get out and inspect his property from time to time. SAMPLING A WELL-GROOMED PARK Information</p>
        <p>The 65,403-acre Point Reyes National Seashore has programs and exhibits throughout the year. The Bear Valley headquarters, (415) 663-1092, is open 8 A.M. to 5 P.M. weekends and holidays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. weekdays. The lighthouse visitor center, (415) 669-1534, open Thursday to Monday 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., is a good, but sometimes crowded spot for watching the winter migration of the gray whale.</p>
        <p>It's always smart to check the park's weather, which varies from beach to ridge to valley; (415) 663-9029.  Inns and Cottages</p>
        <p>There is no real off season in Point Reyes. Weekends are crowded year round, especially holidays, and the many small inns and individual cottages can fill up even during the week, so call far ahead for reservations. Some inns don't allow children, some don't allow smoking. For information on a number of accommodations, call Inns of Point Reyes, (415) 485-2649, or the West Marin Network, (415) 663-9543. The Cottages of Point Reyes, (415) 663-9445, handles some cottages, with rates from $75 to $135 a night.</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of inns and cottages. Rates are for two people.</p>
        <p>Ten Inverness Way, 10 Inverness Way, Inverness; (415) 669-1648. Post Office Box 63, Inverness, Calif. 94937.  Well-tended four-room redwood inn known for its breakfasts. Quiet, with lovely garden and hot tub. Rates: $110 to $160.</p>
        <p>Blackthorne Inn, 266 Vallejo, Inverness; (415) 663-8621. Post Office Box 712, Inverness, Calif. 94937. This treehouse-style inn has five rooms, including the octagonal Eagle's Nest. It also has a fire pole, hot tub and buffet breakfast. Rates: $105 to $175.</p>
        <p>Holly Tree Inn, 3 Silverhills Road, Inverness Park; (415) 663-1554. Post Office Box 642, Point Reyes Station, Calif. 94956. Bed and breakfast in serene setting. Four rooms and a cottage ($100 to $125); nearby Sea Star Cottage on Tomales Bay ($175).</p>
        <p>Knob Hill, 40 Knob Hill Road, Point Reyes Station; (415) 663-1784. Post Office Box 1108, Point Reyes Station, Calif. 94956. Small but comfortable cottage ($95, with breakfast in refrigerator) and small room off the main house ($50, no food). Riding stable next door.</p>
        <p>Marsh Cottage, 12642 Sir Francis Drake Boulevard, south of Inverness; (415) 669-7168. Post Office Box 1121, Point Reyes Station, Calif. 94956.  Clapboard cottage with kitchen on Tomales Bay. $95 on weekdays; $110 weekends. Camping</p>
        <p>Overnight camping in the National Seashore is for those willing to backpack two to six miles to the sites. Space is scarce on weekends. Call the Seashore office, (415) 663-1092, for reservations up to two months ahead. Other camping sites in the area: Samuel P. Taylor State Park, (415)488-9897, and the 32-acre Olema Lake Campground, (415) 663-8001. Food</p>
        <p>The Station House Cafe, downtown Point Reyes Station; (415) 663-1515.  This great American country restaurant has been around for almost 20 years. The menu changes often, but staples include Hog Island oysters ($12 a dozen), double-cheese polenta with garlic-grilled potatoes and spinach plus salad ($8) and a hamburger and fries ($5.25). Recent specials included salmon with shallot vinaigrette ($15) and chicken with quince and onion relish ($13). Open 8 A.M. to 10 P.M. Sunday to Thursday, 8 A.M. to 11 P.M. Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>Manka's Inverness Lodge, Argyle and Callander Streets, off Sir Francis Drake Boulevard, north of Inverness; (415) 669-1034. Menu changes daily; recent offerings included scallops with artichoke hearts and shiitake mushrooms ($16), and venison with yams and zucchini in currant thyme jus ($22). Special holiday menu. Open for dinner, Thursday through Monday. Reservations recommended.</p>
        <p>Gray Whale, Sir Francis Drake Boulevard in Inverness; (415) 669-1244. Pizza, salads, light fare, to eat in or take out. The teen-agers behind the counter know their mozzarella. Open daily 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>Bovine Bakery, downtown Point Reyes Station; (415) 663-9420. Chile cheddar cheese scones and other snacks to take on a hike. Open 7 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday to Friday; 8 A.M. to 5 P.M. Saturday and Sunday.  Bicycle Rental</p>
        <p>Trailhead Rentals, Highway 1 and Bear Valley Road, Olema; (415) 663-1958. Near the Seashore entrance. A good variety of trails are open to bicycles. Mountain bikes rent for $20 a day on weekends; $17 a day weekdays. Half-day rates. Call ahead. Open daily 10 to 6.</p>
        <p>DANIEL LEWIS, the editor of The Week in Review, frequently hikes in the West.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">DANIEL LEWIS, the editor of The Week in Review, frequently hikes in the West.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
