<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carpentras Journal; Counterfeit Truffles Scandalize Southern France</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUFFLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUNTERFEITING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PROVENCE (FRANCE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Provence and the French Riviera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Truffles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED91F3AF93AA15751C0A964958260" item-length="1112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carpentras Journal; Counterfeit Truffles Scandalize Southern France</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>CARPENTRAS, France</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the towns and villages of medieval Provence, the ancient battle between good and evil has taken on the form of a fungus that for centuries has been uprooted by pigs and eaten by noblemen.</p>
        <p>At issue is the reputation of the black truffle, an underground mushroom known for its penetrating scent, its role in fine cooking and its exorbitant prices. In the south of France, truffles are serious business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the towns and villages of medieval Provence, the ancient battle between good and evil has taken on the form of a fungus that for centuries has been uprooted by pigs and eaten by noblemen.</p>
        <p>At issue is the reputation of the black truffle, an underground mushroom known for its penetrating scent, its role in fine cooking and its exorbitant prices. In the south of France, truffles are serious business.</p>
        <p>Yet some local merchants, long thought of as reputable, have been accused of dyeing lowly white truffles and passing them off as black truffles of the Perigord variety. The white kind, found only in summer and considered much inferior in taste, fetches only one-tenth the price of its black winter cousin.</p>
        <p>The alchemists have reportedly inserted their fakes into pates and foie gras, and canned others for sale at home and abroad. Paul Bonnet, whose family has dealt in black truffles for 120 years, said recently that chefs in the village of Bedoin were sneaking the chopped impostors into omelets.  A Metaphor for Decadence</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonnet and other defenders of the moist and pungent black truffle have denounced the supposed frauds to Government inspectors. Now the accused are countersuing, charging defamation.</p>
        <p>A skirmish over a subterranean mushroom may not carry much weight in a world that worries about dismantling underground nuclear warheads. But it deeply disturbs the French, who see such acts as metaphors for the corruption and decadence of modern life.</p>
        <p>The costly truffle -- sold here recently at $230 a pound -- cannot be found on every kitchen shelf. But in the French psyche, it ranks high with symbols like the fine grape and the palace of Versailles, which reassure the nation that despite the sputtering economy and the mood of ennui, there are still firm pillars of pleasure and quality.</p>
        <p>In this region, the truffle is treated almost with reverence. Consider the Truffle Mass held every January at the church of Richerenche, with full attendance of the Truffle Fraternity in ceremonial robes. On this occasion, parishioners put some of their finest samples in the collection basket to raise money for the 12th-century church. At the end of the service the offerings are weighed and sold. Everyone was pleased this year when the collection basket held a record 10 pounds, worth $2,300.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Pierre Gleize contributed a homily dedicated to truffles and love. "Today our church is impregnated with the perfume of truffles, the way love must impregnate each one of us," he told his flock. "Love transforms everything. Isn't that what a good truffle does to an omelet, pate or poultry dish?"</p>
        <p>But the truffle world also knows pitfalls and sin. The police have received complaints about hunters who have been rooting around on a neighbor's land at dawn. And at the height of the current harvest, Jean Panza's car was intercepted by armed men on a lonely road near Malemort. Mr. Panza, a licensed dealer who had just finished his rounds of the farms, was ordered to surrender the 77 pounds he had on board.</p>
        <p>Uneasiness about the sale of fraudulent truffles is compounded by periodic reports that biologists in Japan and the United States have succeeded in taming the wild fungus and cultivating it in nurseries. More disturbing still have been claims from French biologists that they have unlocked the secret of the truffle's haunting aroma. After identifying its chemical compounds, they say they are making a bottled synthetic imitation, soon to be marketed.</p>
        <p>Connoisseurs in the south of France say they will not believe it until they smell it. Nobody, they say, could possibly imitate "the mesmerizing odor of a pig in rut," a smell that explains why pigs are traditionally used to find the truffle growing a few inches below the ground.</p>
        <p>The pig, as it happens, is fast losing its status as the prime hunter of the treasure. In Provence at least, Mayor Jean Piguet of Richerence said, almost everyone has switched to specially trained dogs.</p>
        <p>"The pig is heavy and often crushes the truffle," Mr. Piguet said. "Besides, it's unscrupulous. You look away for a second and it will eat the truffle."  Production Down Sharply</p>
        <p>Even the environment is posing problems. An association based in Carpentras offers charts to show how the warming climate and the drop in rainfall in southern France are responsible for the dramatic drop in production. Early this century, France produced about 1,000 tons a year. This year, the third dry year in a row, it could be less than 10 tons.</p>
        <p>Wine is also said to be a culprit. Because vines are more predictable than truffles, farmers have been cutting down the old oak trees under which truffles grow to make room for vineyards.</p>
        <p>Some old-timers prefer to blame the strangers who buy the old farms as weekend homes and are almost agricultural illiterates.</p>
        <p>"You have to know how to prune the oak trees, air the soil, keep the right degree of moisture," said Andre Charensol, who has his own stand of "truffle trees." But then, he conceded, "the truffle is always a mystery."</p>
        <p>"You can plant 10 cuttings from the same oak, and 10 years later only one of them gives truffles," he said. "No one knows why."</p>
        <p>Recognizing the economic potential of the truffle, even the Government has become involved and is subsidizing the planting of oak trees. It says that beside protecting France's gastronomic tradition, truffle farming also motivates people to stay on relatively poor land.  A Processor Is Fined</p>
        <p>All these matters are topics of intense debate in the cafes of Richerenche and Carpentras after the weekly truffle markets. The trading itself, though, is practically a cloak and dagger affair. The truffles are not on display, but are covered in plastic or linen, lest their precious aroma escape. Buyers peer into bags and sniff and squeeze the little tubers, and everyone talks in whispers. Just as quietly, wads of money change hands. The taxman has no grip on this.</p>
        <p>Government inspectors did intervene a year ago when they fined a truffle processor $22,000 for dyeing white fungus black, using it in his pates and misrepresenting the ingredients on the containers. Four others are being tried for similar fraud in the Carpentras region. Unlike the celebrated white truffle of Alba, Italy, the pale French fungus has little flavor or aroma.</p>
        <p>"Fraud gives the truffle a bad name," said Mr. Bonnet, who heads the truffle association. "And it threatens the price of our real black diamond." Asked how the innocent buyer could guard against fraudulent truffles, Mr. Bonnet said sadly: "You cannot. You only find out when you open the jar, and then it's too late."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
