<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Versatile Citrus, Thorns and All</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="550737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DRUSE, KEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D81430F935A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Versatile Citrus, Thorns and All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ken Druse</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DRUSE, KEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is an exquisite cousin to lemons and limes that is quite at home in my backyard garden in Brooklyn. Some people around here, however, aren't attracted to it for its citrus lineage; they like it for its relationship to razor ribbon.</p>
        <p>The plant, known as Poncirus trifoliata, or trifoliate orange, is theft-proof. Would-be urban bush-rustlers might end up slashed by one-inch long, needle-sharp thorns that lie in wait just beneath a shroud of shiny green leaflets. Planted beneath windows, it might be equally discouraging to a housebreaker. Several trifoliate orange shrubs were planted in the 1960's inside the fence at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden in a successful effort to discourage trespassers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is an exquisite cousin to lemons and limes that is quite at home in my backyard garden in Brooklyn. Some people around here, however, aren't attracted to it for its citrus lineage; they like it for its relationship to razor ribbon.</p>
        <p>The plant, known as Poncirus trifoliata, or trifoliate orange, is theft-proof. Would-be urban bush-rustlers might end up slashed by one-inch long, needle-sharp thorns that lie in wait just beneath a shroud of shiny green leaflets. Planted beneath windows, it might be equally discouraging to a housebreaker. Several trifoliate orange shrubs were planted in the 1960's inside the fence at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden in a successful effort to discourage trespassers.</p>
        <p>This versatile shrub or small tree from northern China was popular until the post-war building boom, when house after house settled for mirror-image plantings of standard hemlocks and yews. For a while, it served as the under-stock for grafting commercial citrus varieties. But to me, its charm is purely esthetic.</p>
        <p>In spring, one- to two-inch star-shaped fragrant flowers cover the branches. After the petals drop, little mossy marblelike fruits form. The three-part leaves start out grass-green and deepen in color to a park-bench green as the round fruits swell through the summer, ultimately reaching two inches in diameter.</p>
        <p>Unlike the subtropical evergreen citrus varieties, the hardy trifoliate orange is deciduous. Its leaves and fruits turn yellow in autumn, but after the leaves fall, the pretty fruits remain to deck the branches like Christmas tree ornaments. Sadly, the aromatic fruits are merely a decorative bonus. They are not tasty -- too sour to eat off the bush -- but can be harvested for marmalade or to garnish beverages.</p>
        <p>Older plants take on a wonderful winding form with sinewy trunks and striped green and light brown bark. "They get muscular as they get older," said Edmond Moulin, director of horticulture at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden. The oldest Poncirus there, planted in 1914, grows at the base of a hill west of the Steinhardt Conservatory. There are a number of examples at the garden, including several that form one spoke of the "hedge wheel," a demonstration planting of shrubs for home gardens.</p>
        <p>The trifoliate orange takes well to pruning and training. At Meadowbrook Farm near Philadelphia, Liddon Pennock has created a border of Poncirus trained and trimmed into five-foot-tall standards: topiaries in a lollipop shape. At the noted Wave Hill estate in the Bronx, a seedling planted to be espaliered against a wall has grown into a solid column of foliage that has to be sheared in spring and occasionally through the season; otherwise it would be a hazard to workers and visitors. In spite of this treatment, it manages to flower and fruit.</p>
        <p>Since Poncirus plants are rarely sold at garden centers these days, the fruits present an easy way to get these plants. Like many citrus, it is easy to propagate from seeds; the fruits are filled with them. If you know where one grows, get permission from the owner to pick a ripe fruit, or collect one off the ground from late fall to early spring. Fallen fruits collected after winter will be ready to germinate. I have collected fruits with seeds already sprouted inside. But success is guaranteed with "stratified" ripe seeds.</p>
        <p>Stratification, often necessary for seeds of cold-climate plants, is a process by which seeds are exposed to chilling and warming to fool them into thinking they've been through a winter. Carefully cut open the ripe yellow fruit, then remove the seeds and wash them thoroughly. Sow them on their sides about one-half inch deep in a three- or four-inch plastic flower pot filled with moist commercial starting mix (made from peat moss, vermiculite and perlite). Place the pot in a plastic bag in the refrigerator for two or three months. Then move the planted container to a sunny window, and keep the mix moist but not soggy. Within a few weeks, the seeds should sprout.</p>
        <p>"Seed" leaves appear first, followed by the distinctive three-parted "true" leaves. If you have several seedlings growing in one pot, carefully separate them after the leaves unfurl. The young specimens make beautiful house plants and will grow well on a sunny windowsill through the winter, providing the temperature is cool -- below 60 degrees Fahrenheit at night.</p>
        <p>Outdoors, the trifoliate orange appreciates an acidic, well-drained soil, similar to the type enjoyed by rhododendrons. It dislikes cultivation close to its shallow roots. It will do well with six hours or more of direct sunlight a day, and it tolerates dry or moist conditions.</p>
        <p>"It really isn't all that fussy, and has no pest problems," Mr. Moulin said.</p>
        <p>The plants can grow up to 35 feet tall, but rarely do, making them a good choice for small properties. Eight feet tall and nearly as wide is more the norm within the plant's preferred hardiness range of United States Department of Agriculture zones 5 to 9; that could be outdoors in New York City as well as in a warm-temperate garden in Berkeley, Calif., or a protected spot against a sunny wall in Boston.</p>
        <p>A few mail-order suppliers carry Poncirus, and some growers say they have noticed a renewed interest in the plant. There is even a new grafted variety called Flying Dragon, which has twisted, contorted stems. For now, you'll have to ask your garden center to try to order one, or seek small plants from one of these sources: Logee's Greenhouses, 141 North Street, Danielson, Conn. 06239 (catalogue $3); or Forest Farm, 990 Tetherow Road, Williams, Ore. 97544-9599 (catalogue $2). You could always grow your own from seeds. It is worth the effort, for the plants are vigorous once established.</p>
        <p>To paraphrase the song: this "lemon" tree "very pretty," and the flowers do smell sweet, but the fruits of this bold citrus are impossible to eat. And the thorns can be lethal, although they may have other uses than deterring intruders.</p>
        <p>Judith Zuk, the president of the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, remembers that when she was a student, her professor used to cut off a branch in December and stick gumdrops on all the thorns.</p>
        <p>"It was the most unorthodox Christmas tree I ever saw," she said. "We all loved it."  CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
