<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Times Adds Pollution Index And Expands Local Forecast</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK TIMES</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D6113FF931A25756C0A964958260" item-length="394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Times Adds Pollution Index And Expands Local Forecast</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting today, The New York Times's weather page will include an air quality index and an expanded extended forecast for the New York region.</p>
        <p>The air quality index, which will appear as part of the Metropolitan Almanac Tuesday through Saturday, compares the previous day's air quality in selected areas with standards for pollutants set by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency. Information for the index is collected by state agencies from locations around the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Starting today, The New York Times's weather page will include an air quality index and an expanded extended forecast for the New York region.</p>
        <p>The air quality index, which will appear as part of the Metropolitan Almanac Tuesday through Saturday, compares the previous day's air quality in selected areas with standards for pollutants set by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency. Information for the index is collected by state agencies from locations around the region.</p>
        <p>The index tracks five pollutants: carbon monoxide, nitrogen dioxide, ozone, particulates and sulfur dioxide. Index numbers below 100 indicate pollution is at levels below those known by the E.P.A. to cause adverse health effects; an index below 50 is considered good.</p>
        <p>Air with an index number above 100 is considered unhealthy, and people with heart or respiratory problems are cautioned to reduce physical exertion and outdoor activities on those days. A reading of 200 carries further warnings about reducing outdoor activities.</p>
        <p>The extended forecast is being expanded to include more details. At the same time, some individual forecasts for areas around the region that are similar are being condensed, and more accurate temperature information, gathered from airport weather stations, will be listed in a tabular form.</p>
        <p>Tom Allen, an official with the state's Environmental Conservation Department who is responsible for monitoring air quality in New York, said that generally the leading pollutant in the summer was ozone, and in the winter, sulfur dioxide.</p>
        <p>Last summer, there were 19 days when ozone levels exceeded 100 in New York State, Mr. Allen said. On Aug. 30, Babylon, L.I., recorded the worst index reading, above 200.</p>
        <p>Because the index levels on the weather page will cover the previous day, readers can use the numbers as a guide, along with weather forecasts, to gauge the air quality around them, Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>"On a warm summer day, when the temperature is approaching 90 and the sun is bright, you are going to have an ozone problem," Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>The effects of pollution are no longer confined to more congested urban areas, Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>"We used to think of air quality as an urban problem, but we are finding that some of the pollutants, like ozone or the particulates that make up haze, are transported around the state," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
