<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawn Mower Is New Target In War Against Air Pollution</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920807T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWN MOWERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESIGN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGINES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D61238F935A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="1580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawn Mower Is New Target In War Against Air Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To most people, it is a lawn mower, but to the Environmental Protection Agency it is an "uncontrolled mobile source" that becomes part of the suburban swarm adding measurably to smog on a summer's day. And the time has come, the agency says, to clean it up, along with weed eaters, leaf blowers, chain saws and a lot of other off-road gas-powered machinery.</p>
        <p>A lawn mower can easily spew as much smog-causing hydrocarbon into the air in an hour as a modern car, experts on pollution say, even though the car has 30 times as much horsepower. Chain saws are worse: the California Air Resources Board says a chain saw operated for two hours emits as many hydrocarbons as a new car driven 3,000 miles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To most people, it is a lawn mower, but to the Environmental Protection Agency it is an "uncontrolled mobile source" that becomes part of the suburban swarm adding measurably to smog on a summer's day. And the time has come, the agency says, to clean it up, along with weed eaters, leaf blowers, chain saws and a lot of other off-road gas-powered machinery.</p>
        <p>A lawn mower can easily spew as much smog-causing hydrocarbon into the air in an hour as a modern car, experts on pollution say, even though the car has 30 times as much horsepower. Chain saws are worse: the California Air Resources Board says a chain saw operated for two hours emits as many hydrocarbons as a new car driven 3,000 miles.</p>
        <p>That is because modern cars have microprocessors that can precisely control an engine's mix of fuel and air; injectors to break the fuel into droplets of optimal size, and catalytic converters to catch anything that passes through the engine unburned.</p>
        <p>Lawn mowers and other outdoor machines have none of these. In fact, they have all the pollution control equipment of a '57 Chevy -- without a muffler. Electronic Yard Work</p>
        <p>Tomorrow, William K. Reilly, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and an organization of electric utilities plan to announce the start of a program to clean up America's lawn mowers. The effort on lawn mowers will be part of a plan that will eventually cover all kinds of engines, small and large, used off the highway. That would include construction equipment, farm tractors and even the service vehicles on airport aprons.</p>
        <p>Nine utilities around the country will each give away 100 newly designed battery-powered mowers, taking their customers' old gasoline models in trade and asking them to test the new mowers in the field -- or, more precisely, on the lawn -- and report back on their performance. Meanwhile, the E.P.A. will haul the old mowers into its labs to study their emissions, in preparation for issuing new air-quality regulations similar to the rules now in place for cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>In its new get-tough approach, the E.P.A. plans to make an example of the lawn mower. "We joke around and call it the last frontier for mobile sources," said Gay McGregor, an air-pollution specialist in the E.P.A.'s mobile-source laboratory in Ann Arbor, Mich.</p>
        <p>The lawn-mower-engine industry, after initial resistance, is acknowledging the mighty little machine's role in air pollution. At the Outdoor Power Equipment Institute, formerly the Lawn Mower Institute, Dennis C. Dix, the executive director, conceded, "We certainly could do better." His industry, which never worried much about exhaust, is being forced by California to abide by new regulations that are to take effect in 1994 and 1999 and may be extended to other states as well.</p>
        <p>Ann McClure, the executive vice president of the Professional Lawn Care Association of America, said: "There's an irony in this. Turf actually helps to cleanse the air, taking what emissions there are in the air, removing them, and replacing them with oxygen."</p>
        <p>At Caterpillar Inc. in Peoria, Ill., a big maker of the type of agricultural and heavy construction equipment that is likely to be regulated soon, Rita L. Castle, said that the trend was "not unexpected." She added, "They've gone after most of the large emissions sources, and off-road vehicles certainly deserve a close look." A Snow-Blower Exemption?</p>
        <p>At the Toro Company, Karl C. Kaukis, the director of marketing for the Lawn Boy line, said lawn mowers could be cleaned up, but consumers would find them more costly. He added that he hoped for "a common sense approach."</p>
        <p>Specifically, he said that he hoped that the cleanup would not extend to snow blowers, of which Toro is a major producer.</p>
        <p>"The utilization is so low, and the summer utilization is zero," he said.</p>
        <p>Smog is a summer hazard, though carbon monoxide, which small engines also emit, is a particular problem in some cities in winter.</p>
        <p>Nobody is certain how many lawn mowers are in use or what their emission levels are after a few years without being tuned up, but an E.P.A. study late last year suggested that in areas that are already in violation of smog rules, nearly 20 percent of volatile organic compounds and nearly 30 percent of nitrogen oxides come from "nonroad sources." Mixed with sunlight, those two chemicals make smog.</p>
        <p>The population of "nonroad sources" varies now from place to place; in the metropolitan New York area, for example, outboard motors on pleasure boats are numerous, but in Colorado they are not.</p>
        <p>Most manufacturers will try to lower emissions from gasoline engines by redesigning the combustion chambers, in many cases switching to overhead valves instead of side valves, a change made by the auto industry 40 years ago. They also plan to make engines that run on a leaner fuel-air mixture.</p>
        <p>California has adopted rules to begin in 1994 for improvements that the state says can be achieved with existing technology, and stricter rules for 1999 that will require new approaches.</p>
        <p>Meeting the 1999 standards may mean installing catalytic converters. That development would not delight the makers and users of gasoline-powered mowers, because the super-hot converters could set fire to grass clippings. It should pose "an interesting packaging problem," said Thomas Bingham, a product engineer at the American Honda Motor Company.</p>
        <p>The dirtiest of the outdoor machines are those that burn a mixture of gasoline and lubricating oil and run on a rich fuel-air ratio, like chain saws and weed eaters. Producing such engines is easier for the manufacturer, and their lack of fuel economy is not a concern; it is the rare customer who asks if the chain saw gets six trees to the gallon or seven.</p>
        <p>Moreover, chain saws, mowers and the like have always escaped notice because they are outnumbered by cars. But collectively these and other outdoor engines are a big source of pollutants. The California Air Resources Board estimated that in its state, the annual hydrocarbon emissions of such devices equaled the output of 3.5 million 1991-model cars, each driving 16,000 miles.</p>
        <p>One reason for the lawn-mower problem is that cars must, by law, be maintained and periodically inspected for their emission levels, but lawn mowers, typically, need not.</p>
        <p>"What is tuning?" said A. Joseph Vandenberg, director of technical services at the Edison Electric Institute, in a reaction that pollution-control officials fear is typical of lawn-mower owners. Mr. Vandenberg is helping to organize the swap program.</p>
        <p>"I've got a spark plug I've left in it for 12 years," Mr. Vandenberg said. "As long as the thing cranks, you run it. If it doesn't, go out and buy a new one." Cruising Range: a Quarter- Acre</p>
        <p>One result of the new focus on lawn mowers is that before the much-ballyhooed zero-pollution electric car makes it into the typical suburban garage, the rechargeable electric mower may arrive there first.</p>
        <p>The new electric mowers being distributed in the test program, made by Black &amp; Decker, will be able to mow about a quarter of an acre without recharging. A full charge takes 20 hours; an 80 percent charge 4 hours.  The mower, which will sell for about $500, will use about 6 cents' worth of electricity per charge. Producing that electricity will result in some air pollution, but studies show that power plant smokestacks are cleaner than auto tailpipes, per unit of energy, and far, far cleaner than lawn mower exhaust. Disposing of dead batteries also poses a pollution problem, but, again, a lesser one.</p>
        <p>This is not the debut of a new concept in mowing. Mr. Kaukis said Lawn Boy sold battery-powered mowers a decade ago, but found consumer interest very low. The company still sells plug-in mowers that require a heavy-duty, and very long, extension cord.</p>
        <p>The electric mowers to be distributed to consumers for testing are being provided by Baltimore Gas and Electric, Boston Edison, Indianapolis Power and Light, the New England Electric System, New York State Electric and Gas, Oklahoma Gas and Electric, Potomac Electric Power, Southern California Edison and Tampa Electric.</p>
        <p>The utitilies are still deciding how to choose who will receive the new mowers, though they will be seeking a representative cross section of old mowers. The consumers chosen for the test group will get to keep the electric mowers, in exchange for donating their gas-powered machines to science.</p>
        <p>Switching to electric mowers would eliminate several other categories of pollution, advocates say. For example, the E.P.A. estimates that about 7.5 percent of the contribution to hydrocarbon emissions of lawn and garden equipment comes from spilling gasoline while refueling.</p>
        <p>Mark P. Mills, an energy consultant, estimates that the United States has 18 million walk-behind lawn mowers, and that if all of them were converted to electricity, oil consumption would fall 2.2 million barrels a year. Consumption of coal and natural gas to run power plants would rise somewhat, but total energy use would still decline because the electric system is more efficient than a small internal-combustion engine, he said.</p>
        <p>Converting all of this equipment is doubtful, however, since, for one thing, not all lawns are less than a quarter-acre, and not everyone will want to prolong the job of mowing the lawn by stopping to recharge the mower. Others, on the other hand, may seize the opportunity for such a respite.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS  Correction:  August 7, 1992, Friday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about a program to reduce air pollution from lawn mowers included one utility erroneously in some editions among those participating in a test program and rendered its name incorrectly. Arizona Public Service, not Arizona Power System, has decided against taking part.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 7, 1992, Friday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about a program to reduce air pollution from lawn mowers included one utility erroneously in some editions among those participating in a test program and rendered its name incorrectly. Arizona Public Service, not Arizona Power System, has decided against taking part.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
