<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Producer-Friendly Oil Conservation</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE113FF930A35755C0A964958260" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Producer-Friendly Oil Conservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that Saddam Hussein has been shoved back within his own borders and the pragmatists in Teheran are oozing moderation, is Saudi Arabia once again summoning the courage to flex its formidable energy muscles?</p>
        <p>That was certainly the spin the kingdom's leaders wished to put on their decision last week to side with the price hawks in OPEC. And while there is widespread feeling that the Saudis are bluffing, it raises anew the question of how far oil-importing nations should go along to get along.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that Saddam Hussein has been shoved back within his own borders and the pragmatists in Teheran are oozing moderation, is Saudi Arabia once again summoning the courage to flex its formidable energy muscles?</p>
        <p>That was certainly the spin the kingdom's leaders wished to put on their decision last week to side with the price hawks in OPEC. And while there is widespread feeling that the Saudis are bluffing, it raises anew the question of how far oil-importing nations should go along to get along.</p>
        <p>To Morris Adelman, professor emeritus of economics at M.I.T., the Saudis' reported motive, pique at the prospect of an anti-greenhouse tax on carbon fuels, is just a frustrating reminder that OPEC's efforts to raise oil prices have always been vulnerable to strategic countermeasures. Philip Verleger, an oil specialist at the Institute of International Economics in Washington, is more cautious: The Saudi tilt, he suggests, is a warning that the West would be well advised to curb carbon in ways less likely to provoke confrontation.</p>
        <p>According to news reports last week, Saudi Arabia had planned to raise output this summer in order to keep oil prices near the current $18-$21 a barrel benchmark at a time of rising demand. But the Saudis changed their mind, serving notice that they would no longer champion price moderation if the industrialized nations went along with a European Community proposal to tax carbon emissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Verleger doubts the Saudis are showing all their cards. The carbon-tax proposal, he notes, was already dead on arrival at the Rio environmental summit since the Bush Administration is not buying it, and the Europeans will not go it alone.</p>
        <p>The real story, Mr. Verleger speculates, goes something like this. Oil prices spiked a bit before the OPEC meeting, perhaps on rumors of an assassination attempt on the King of Saudi Arabia. The Saudis then quietly decided to allow prices to stay up for a few months as a gift to the financially pressed (and politically unstable) governments of Venezuela and Nigeria -- but chose to use the occasion to register their protest over carbon taxes.</p>
        <p>This fits with the near-consensus view that Saudi Arabia's strategy for long-term survival -- an image of moderation built around stable oil prices -- has not really changed. It also meshes with the view that the Saudis no longer believe they could keep prices much above the current level without racheting down the flow of oil below the rate that keeps them in Rolexes and Range Rovers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adelman, who has long believed that the importers were foolish to concede any price-setting power to OPEC, says the Saudis have done us a favor. The right course, he argues, is full speed ahead on conservation.</p>
        <p>He says the Saudis are right to worry about carbon taxes. For while the money would initially come out of the pockets of consumers, the ultimate incidence of carbon tax, like any other excise tax, would turn on how buyers and sellers responded. And since energy consumers have substantial capacity to shift to energy-conserving technologies, the tax would almost certainly reduce the price of oil at the wellhead.</p>
        <p>While other energy analysts do not disagree with the thrust of Mr. Adelman's analysis, many still fear there is risk to playing hardball. Jack Riggs, the staff director of the House Subcommittee on Energy and Power, guesses that the Saudis do perceive some flexibility in long-term pricing -- surely not the $10 or $15 a barrel assumed by OPEC hawks in the 1970's, but perhaps a few dollars. And it hardly seems wise to provoke them to try for a higher price if importing countries can find producer-friendlier ways to meet policy objectives.</p>
        <p>That, of course, leaves open the question of how to put meat on these worthy bones. One way, suggests Mr. Verleger, would be to use free markets -- but not taxes -- to limit carbon emissions.</p>
        <p>The model is the trading system now in place for sulfur. An overall national limit on sulfur emissions was set in the 1990 Clean Air Act, with each polluting electric utility assigned a quota according to past rates of emissions. The utilities are now free to clean up their own mess, or to buy emissions rights from others who can trap sulfur at lower cost.</p>
        <p>The design and enforcement of a trading system for carbon would be far more problematic because there are so many sources of emissions. But economists at the Environmental Defense Fund say it could be done. And the ends, least-cost adjustment to fossil fuel conservation, would be identical to that achievable through a carbon tax.</p>
        <p>The one big difference is that the Government would not collect a giant pot of money. That might be seen as a big disadvantage by people who would use the tax to fund the budget. But it could prove a big advantage in dealing with Saudi Arabia, which apparently sees itself in competition with governments for the oil consumer's dollar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
