<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Didn't Feel Like May; Quest for Cool on Record-Setting Day</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="608350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D8173BF931A25756C0A965958260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Didn't Feel Like May; Quest for Cool on Record-Setting Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time it was a near scorcher on May 11, a broken engagement was front-page news. The former fiance had been arrested for stealing $200 from the woman who still loved him. This time, the front-page news is a 16-year-old who took the A train on a joy ride.</p>
        <p>But a hot day is still a hot day. Which is why the next time the thermometers hit 92 on May 11, people will remember yesterday, the day that displaced May 11, 1896, in the record books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time it was a near scorcher on May 11, a broken engagement was front-page news. The former fiance had been arrested for stealing $200 from the woman who still loved him. This time, the front-page news is a 16-year-old who took the A train on a joy ride.</p>
        <p>But a hot day is still a hot day. Which is why the next time the thermometers hit 92 on May 11, people will remember yesterday, the day that displaced May 11, 1896, in the record books.</p>
        <p>They will remember the magical click of an air-conditioner being switched on, or the frustration of the landlord saying it can't be done until May 28 (read the lease).  Charting the Climb</p>
        <p>They will remember lying down for a few minutes in the midmorning sun, dozing off for nearly an hour and waking up lobster-red -- on only the left side. (Maybe by this morning, the tan will have evened out.)</p>
        <p>They will remember hearing radio announcers charting the temperature's climb from clock-radio dawn right through that two-minute thunderstorm over Central Park. (That cloudburst sent people scurrying for umbrellas at 3 P.M. and left others huddled under the marquees of buildings on West 72d Street, but it did not send the mercury into a nose dive.)</p>
        <p>And if they were among the thousands who headed for Jones Beach or Coney Island -- never mind where their bosses thought they were -- they will remember dipping a toe in the still-chilly ocean.</p>
        <p>"It didn't feel like 90 degrees at all," said Isabelle Kellogg, who spent a couple of hours at Jones Beach. "The sand hadn't heated up yet. By June, it will be hot after the sun has beaten down day after day after day."</p>
        <p>Never mind the meteorological gobbledygook. Yesterday was like the Irving Berlin song "Heat Wave": the temperature was rising and it wasn't surprising. After all, Berlin was 8 years old when the old record for May 11 was set. As for yesterday, George Klein, a forecaster for the National Weather Service at Rockefeller Center in Manhattan, said, "Basically what was going on, there was a high pressure dominating the region and we had a westerly flow. On Monday, we had winds from the ocean. Overnight, they swung around the other way. That's all we needed to pump in the warm air from the Midwest."</p>
        <p>And it was all that was needed to make the air quality poorer in some places. One monitoring station, in Winslow Township, N.J., recorded an unhealthful reading of ground-level ozone of 0.129 parts per million, just over the state standard of 0.125 parts per million. High levels of ozone were also reported in Camden, Gloucester and Mercer Counties, but the readings did not exceed the limit, state environmental officials said.</p>
        <p>Unhealthy air has more ground-level ozone, a compound formed by gases like the emissions from car exhausts that is trapped and heated by sunlight in the lower atmosphere. When air-quality readings fall, environmental officials advise elderly people, young children and those with respiratory problems to stay indoors.</p>
        <p>But thousands were out anyway yesterday, splashing on the suntan lotion and trying to remember whether SPF 4 offered more or less protection than SPF 6 (less). Outdoor grocers had to hose down the vegetables from time to time to protect them from withering in the uncompromising sun. And fire hydrants were opened here and there, sometimes to offer a sip of water to thirsty pedestrians trudging by, sometimes to give children on the sidewalk a chance to choreograph the first water ballet of the year. Buying Fans and Ice Cream</p>
        <p>Suddenly, from sweaty city offices to the hushed lounges of midtown university clubs, there was an obsession with air-conditioning, or the lack of it. At a Post Office near Fordham Road in the Bronx, customers fanned themselves with their letters before they mailed them -- sorry, no air conditioning -- and the quest for cool had nothing to do with making a fashion statement.</p>
        <p>"We've gone in and out of every air-conditioned store on Fordham Road to escape the heat," said Lissette Dehoyos, a 25-year-old housewife who had just bought two fans.</p>
        <p>But by late afternoon, she and dozens of others in search for anything cool were streaming into the Carvel ice cream shop at 189th Street and Webster Avenue, entranced by the swirls of ice cream in cone after cone.</p>
        <p>What some people will remember about yesterday is that it was not 1992. "We had 16 weekends of rain," said Marie D'Ercole of D'Ercole Farms and Garden Center in Norwood, N.J. And yesterday? "People were buying annuals and vegetables to get their gardens started," she said. "Even though the frost-free date in this area is May 15, they didn't seem to care."</p>
        <p>What Connie Comberg, a retired school teacher in Eatontown, N.J., will remember is that it was the day she decided her half-acre lawn needed to be mowed. But she didn't want to rush things. She said she would wait until at least Saturday to put in the tomato plants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
