<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Dr. George A. Clark Jr.; Lessons to Be Learned From the Birds</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARK, GEORGE A JR (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD173BF93AA2575AC0A965958260" item-length="1681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Dr. George A. Clark Jr.; Lessons to Be Learned From the Birds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DR. GEORGE A. CLARK JR. was recently awarded the Mabel Osgood Wright Award by the Connecticut Ornithological Association for "outstanding contributions to the study of birds in Connecticut." He has been the state ornithologist since 1981 and is editing for publication an "Atlas of Breeding Birds of Connecticut."</p>
        <p>A professor of ecology and evolutionary biology at the University of Connecticut since 1965, Dr. Clark has studied birds throughout North and South America, Africa and Australia. He earned his bachelor's degree from Amherst College in 1957 and his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1964.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DR. GEORGE A. CLARK JR. was recently awarded the Mabel Osgood Wright Award by the Connecticut Ornithological Association for "outstanding contributions to the study of birds in Connecticut." He has been the state ornithologist since 1981 and is editing for publication an "Atlas of Breeding Birds of Connecticut."</p>
        <p>A professor of ecology and evolutionary biology at the University of Connecticut since 1965, Dr. Clark has studied birds throughout North and South America, Africa and Australia. He earned his bachelor's degree from Amherst College in 1957 and his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1964.</p>
        <p>The Wright award, named for a Fairfield resident who was prominent in the early days of the Audubon Society, was given to recognize Dr. Clark's work coordinating surveys on the status of Connecticut birds. Dr. Clark talked about birding at his office in the biology building at UConn recently. Here are some excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. : Is birding becoming more popular?</p>
        <p>A. There are a lot more casual birders, and this is reflected in the number of people going to meetings. On a national scale, even a meeting on a topic as specialized as raptors, say -- hawks and owls -- we'll get 1,000 people sometimes. Then we have things like the American Birding Association, which has a large membership. At a state-level meeting, we might see upward of 200 people. Twenty years ago, we didn't even have such meetings, there wasn't such a thing as a Connecticut Ornithological Association.</p>
        <p>Q. Why is the interest increasing?</p>
        <p>A. In birding, there's the excitement of something new all the time. It gets you away from the things you have to deal with all the time -- if you're sick of hearing about the economy, go out and watch birds, because you don't have to think about the economy. You find people from all professions getting into this, highly trained physicians and lawyers to people washing dishes in restaurants. It gets people out of their daily routine, gets them close to nature, gets them a little exercise. I don't think most of them get into it because they're environmental activists, but they get interested in the environment once they start birding.</p>
        <p>Q. What have your studies shown about the status of some of the migratory songbirds that summer here and winter in the tropics?</p>
        <p>A. You have to look at population trends over a period of decades to see any changes, but certainly we're not seeing some of the migration flights that we saw in the 1950's or 60's, or even into the 70's. Things like radar studies of birds crossing the Gulf of Mexico show about half as many nights with large number of targets, which indicates a decline. Now maybe these declines can be explained away. Perhaps the birds are moving in some other way, or they've relocated, but it looks like there's an overall decline. We have other kinds of data to show that. We do roadside surveys during June. You stop every half-mile and listen for three minutes, mark down how many birds you hear, and those kinds of assays also show the numbers of birds are declining. We have several possibilities, and a lot of uncertainty about the exact cause, but certainly tropical deforestation is causing a loss of habitat on their wintering ground. And up here as well, we have more urbanization and suburbanization. A lot of them are woodland species, so the number of neotropical migrants that you're going to get is going to be down along roads that have been built up.</p>
        <p>Q. : But many areas of the state are still pretty rural. Will a house every few hundred feet really affect the birds?</p>
        <p>A. A lot of the neotropical birds are forest birds, and if you put a house in your habitat, even if you leave trees in position, they're not going to nest near it. And typically what happens is, you have house cats associated with human dwellings, and raccoons are attracted. Nest predation goes up, and so does nest parasitism because of things like the brown-headed cowbird. On the other hand, if you go into the woodland tracts that are less disturbed, there's been no decline in the neotropical migrants -- we have some really good studies from the Litchfield area, where they have actually gone up a little bit.</p>
        <p>Q. What are some of the predicted climactic changes going to mean?</p>
        <p>A. Some of the projections show us undergoing a dramatic warming. The problem is, our knowledge of global climate is still pretty limited. One doesn't want to get too alarmist, but there are warning signs, and we should be very cautious about what we do globally, because if we have an abrupt increase in temperatures we're going to lose a lot of plants, and we're going to lose a lot of animal species that rely on the plants, including birds. They won't be able to change their migration and nesting patterns quickly enough to keep up with the change in temperatures. Over millennia temperatures have moved up and down naturally, and animals have moved as the temperatures have changed, but we've not been exposed to extremely rapid kinds of changes.</p>
        <p>Q. What species are of most concern in Connecticut?</p>
        <p>A. One species that's getting a lot of attention right now is the worm-eating warbler, in terms of research. It's sort of a greenish bird with a light crown, and it winters down in the Caribbean. It's considered to be especially sensitive to the kind of disturbances you have when there's development going on in wooded areas.</p>
        <p>The Federally endangered species right now are the roseate tern and the piping plover, so they're getting as much attention as anything. One of the problems is when the numbers get really low, you don't have enough to study. Grasshopper sparrows, for instance: About the only major nesting ground now is Bradley International Airport.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there any quantifiable change taking place in the mix of Connecticut birds?</p>
        <p>A. Certainly grassland species like the brown thrasher are on the decline, and birds that live in shrubby areas seem to be somewhat on the decline. Things like the yellow-breasted chat used to be pretty much all over the place, particularly in the coastal areas, and this year I don't know of a single nesting taking place. It's not due to development, it's because agriculture is on the wane in Connecticut, so the grasslands and shrubland have been allowed to return to forest. Around the turn of the century about 70 percent of the land in Connecticut was farm fields, but today about 60 percent is forest. And the agriculture that is left is very neat, often weed free, so the natural foods for birds are just not there.</p>
        <p>Q. Are there many species that have entirely disappeared recently?</p>
        <p>A. There are some birds that have pretty much disappeared in terms of being reported, or they have disappeared as breeders, but they still are sighted as migrants -- something like the sedge wren, which once in a while still breeds in the state, but it's certainly down.</p>
        <p>Q. How much diversity is there remaining in Connecticut?</p>
        <p>A. Our species list for one individual in a day is as high as 170. That takes about 24 hours. You start at night, picking off the things you hear calling, even if you don't see them very well. It's fairly easy to do over 100 a day, without any particular strain. Our state list is pushing upward of 400. There's a lot of diversity, and we're continually getting new species for the state, most of them birds of the Southwest or the South that get blown in. We just had a tropical kingbird come up, which is normally in the Southwest and down into Latin America.</p>
        <p>Q. What makes some species so much more successful than others?</p>
        <p>A. A lot of the birds doing real well now are human-associated birds, such as the starling. They were introduced from Europe, and have spread all over the country. They nest in holes, often man provided, whether birdhouses or buildings. And it feeds very well in association with domestic livestock. It's a bird that has millennia of association with people in the Old World, comes over here and finds people living in pretty much the same way, and did very well.</p>
        <p>The Canada goose has done tremendously well, but if you go back to 1960 they weren't here at all. We had Canada geese, but they were migrating through Connecticut, maybe wintering with us a little bit. The Canada goose has become a bit of a plague on golf courses and playing fields.</p>
        <p>Q. : Why should we care what happens to birds?</p>
        <p>A. From a bird lover's point of view, and it could be a very selfish point of view, they just want to keep seeing these things. From a human standpoint, if we lose a single species, such as the Cape May warbler, it probably won't impact us directly, but it's a bad sign, because it's indicative of environmental degradation in general.</p>
        <p>Birds have been useful as indices of environmental conditions for a long time. Think back to the episode that we went through when we used chlorinated hydrocarbon pesticides like DDT, where birds were a good indicator that this was having a major environmental impact. There's still some problems associated with lawn care, where we've had some bird mortality. In general, as we lose birds, we're probably contaminating the environment.</p>
        <p>Q. What's your favorite bird?</p>
        <p>A. That's a tough one. I guess the one I'm looking at at the moment is often my favorite, a black-capped chickadee, or the ruby-throated hummingbird, which is migrating through the area now, and they're just great. I think one of the things that really attracts me is if I see something I haven't seen in a while, or if I see a bird doing something that I didn't know they did, I get excited.</p>
        <p>Q. What's the most exciting sighting that you've had?</p>
        <p>A. One of the most spectacular things I've seen is at Cape May, N.J. Back some decades ago when the flights were really spectacular you'd have thousands of warblers at once flying over you. You can't begin to identify them all, and they're just pouring past you. In the time it takes you to figure out what one is, hundreds of others have gone by you. You're looking at maybe 20, 25 different species flying by at one time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
