<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Creating Parks In a Crowded Metropolis</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="600023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RIVERBANK STATE PARK (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HARLEM (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB143CF937A35757C0A965958260" item-length="2726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Creating Parks In a Crowded Metropolis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERVYN ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN their effort to create new parks and playgrounds in sections of New York City that do not have enough of them, government agencies and nonprofit organizations are understanding more and more that, as Kermit the Frog would say, it's not that easy being green.</p>
        <p>Seeking to establish open spaces, Lilliputian or Brobdignagian, in underserved communities throughout the five boroughs, they are devising new strategies to cope with diminishing budgets and are increasingly turning to the unexpected: vacant lots, abandoned buildings and the top of a huge sewage-treatment plant on the Hudson River in West Harlem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN their effort to create new parks and playgrounds in sections of New York City that do not have enough of them, government agencies and nonprofit organizations are understanding more and more that, as Kermit the Frog would say, it's not that easy being green.</p>
        <p>Seeking to establish open spaces, Lilliputian or Brobdignagian, in underserved communities throughout the five boroughs, they are devising new strategies to cope with diminishing budgets and are increasingly turning to the unexpected: vacant lots, abandoned buildings and the top of a huge sewage-treatment plant on the Hudson River in West Harlem.</p>
        <p>"Looking for parkland in a city as densely populated as this one is a matter of taking advantage of opportunities wherever you find them," said Elizabeth Goldstein, New York City regional director of the state's Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation.</p>
        <p>As she spoke, Ms. Goldstein was standing atop one of those opportunities: the concrete roof of the euphemistically named North River Water Pollution Control Plant, the home of the new $129 million, 28-acre Riverbank State Park, which is the only state park in Manhattan and is to open May 27.</p>
        <p>"Building a park on top of any other kind of structure is a very urban concept," Ms. Goldstein said. "In the entire world there are 11 parks atop waste-treatment plants, and the other 10 are in Japan. And that may well be for the reasons that this was a logical option. When you've got this kind of density of population and very little land, this is one of the things you do -- you go up."</p>
        <p>Built with Federal, state and city funds, the park, on the Hudson between 137th and 145th Streets, includes indoor and outdoor swimming pools, an 834-seat auditorium for cultural events, a 1,270-seat gym with facilities for basketball, volleyball, gymnastics and martial arts; locker rooms for more than 1,000 people; a 200-foot-long rink for ice skating and roller skating; a softball field; a 400 meter running track around a football/soccer field; outdoor courts for basketball, handball, paddleball and tennis; a restaurant; an amphitheater; children's play areas; a carousel, and a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldstein anticipates that the park will draw about 10,000 people a day on weekends in nice weather, and a total of 2 million to 3 million people a year.</p>
        <p>The park is a direct result of the plant, which processes 170 million gallons of raw sewage a day. When government officials selected the site in the 60's against the strong objections of the Harlem community and its elected officials, Ms. Goldstein said, residents soon began pressing for a recreational facility on the roof. The park, she added, "is what was finally negotiated between the community and the State of New York."</p>
        <p>ONE reason the community so vehemently demanded a recreational facility, of course, was that West Harlem was like many sections of the city: There was no sizable one in the neighborhood or in the immediate area. Now West Harlem finds itself among the park-privileged.</p>
        <p>"Indeed, this facility is quite unique in the City of New York," Ms. Goldstein said. "There are city-run recreation centers in a number of places, but there's nowhere that has the concentration of this level of indoor and outdoor activity in such a small space. And there's nothing else like this that's so close to a residential neighborhood. Many city parks that have a lot of these kinds of facilities are very far from public transportation and much less easily accessible."</p>
        <p>The park will be open 18 hours a day, from 6 or 7 A.M. to midnight or 1 A.M. Bridges at 138th and 145th Streets link it to Riverside Drive. An elevator-stairway tower in the northeast corner provides a direct entrance from Riverside Park below. Buses on Riverside Drive and along 145th Street, the 145th Street stop on the No. 9 line, which is a block away, and other lines connecting to the 145th Street bus will also provide easy access.</p>
        <p>As far as getting there by car, though, forget it.</p>
        <p>"There is practically no public parking here at all," Ms. Goldstein said. "The community felt very strongly in the original planning for the park that it did not want to encourage people to come by car."</p>
        <p>Riverbank is the fifth state park in New York City. The first, Roberto Clemente State Park in the Morris Heights section of the West Bronx, a full-service recreational park like Riverbank, opened in 1973. The others are Empire-Fulton Ferry State Park next to the Brooklyn Bridge in Brooklyn, which contains the Empire Stores historic warehouses and is a strolling area rather than a recreation park; Clay Pit Ponds State Park Preserve, a 250-acre wildlife refuge on Staten Island, and Bayswater Point State Park Preserve, in Far Rockaway, Queens, which is run by the Audubon Society.</p>
        <p>There is, naturally, one inherent disadvantage in building a park atop a sewage-treatment plant: odors. There have been complaints for years about the odors from the plant. Ms. Goldstein, however, said that the problem was infrequent and that the park's planners were working to resolve the difficulty.</p>
        <p>"Time will tell," she said. "Once people start using the park, the issue may fall away."</p>
        <p>Not every underserved section of the city, of course, gets the opportunity to have such a waste-treatment plant dropped in its lap, and to get such a large park in recompense. So when New York City's Department of Parks and Recreation seeks to add dabs of green to neighborhoods that do not have enough of them, ways have to devised that take into account the financial squeeze that has reduced the department's budget and work force by 20 percent in the last three years. Those ways usually involve work on a small scale and the use of city-owned land.</p>
        <p>City-owned vacant land is a key, said Jack T. Linn, assistant commissioner for government relations. "There's no cash cost to the city in transferring property from another city agency to ours," Mr. Linn said. And, he added, less is very definitely more.</p>
        <p>"In the inner city, the built-up sections of the city, what you have the opportunity to get your hands on tends to be a small parcel anyway," he said. "And the marginal difference in our operating budget to maintain an extra acre or two is not significant."</p>
        <p>Jane P. Cleaver, the department's director of park lands, said the department had "made a conscious decision a few years ago to create one new active recreational community park per borough, in neighborhoods that do not have a neighborhood or community park."</p>
        <p>"We started out with a list of five," she said, "and we're a third of the way through the list."</p>
        <p>THE first two sites are at the northwest corner of 177th Street and Walton Avenue in the Mount Hope section of the Bronx, the Mount Hope-St. Edmund's Community Park, and on a block bounded by Prospect Avenue, Clyde Place, Harvard Avenue and Arnold Street in the West New Brighton section of Staten Island, in what will be the Cottages Hill Playground.</p>
        <p>The 2.8-acre Staten Island playground, combining two existing empty park lands with the former site of Public School 17, will include two tennis courts and a preschool playground and will cost almost $1.5 million. The 1.7-acre Bronx site is to include two basketball courts, play equipment and a spray shower and is to cost $680,000. Construction on both is to begin this spring, Ms. Cleaver said, and take from a year to 18 months.</p>
        <p>Finding ways to make existing small parks and playgrounds bigger is a major department technique, Ms. Cleaver said. "Looking for adjacent land and adding it to the park is a big strategy," she said. "It doesn't always make a huge difference, but it means that a rehabilitated park comes back a little bit bigger. Probably a third of the additions we have made since 1989 have been in this add-a-lot program."</p>
        <p>Very often, she said, city-owned land turns up adjacent to existing parks that are being redesigned. "A good example," she said, "is Joseph C. Sauer Playground, on East 12th Street between Avenues A and B. It has had two small additions since 1989, one lot .07 percent of an acre and the other .02 percent of an acre. So it only gave us a tenth of an acre more. But it allowed us to go from a midblock park to the corner."</p>
        <p>And, she added, it helped improve the quality of the neighborhood. "The first addition," she said, "was a vacant lot, where addicts in a crack house next door used to throw their used needles. And the second lot was the crack house itself."</p>
        <p>Still another technique, Ms. Cleaver said, is linking park land. The Environmental Quality Bond Act of 1986 let the city use the value of certain city-owned land as a match for state cash. Using this law, the city has received a $2 million redevelopment grant to take city-owned land between West 155th Street and West 158th Street near the Hudson River to connect Riverside Park with Fort Washington Park.</p>
        <p>One of the best methods to create or redevelop open spaces, said Marilyn Gelber, executive assistant to Brooklyn Borough President Howard Golden, is to do so in conjunction with new or rehabilitated housing. She said that the Nehemiah houses at Belmont and Sutter Avenues and Livonia Avenue and Mother Gaston Boulevard, both in Brownsville, and Ten Eyck Plaza, at Ten Eyck Street and Lorimer Street in Williamsburg, were notable examples of this process at work.</p>
        <p>"It's critical if we create open space in so-called underserved, or badly developed, or poor areas to do it in a smart way, to have a community built around it that will help maintain it," Ms. Gelber said. "If you plan things in conjunction with new housing development, then it's a win-win situation."</p>
        <p>The city's Department of Housing Preservation and Development runs an Open Spaces Program to complement urban-renewal sites or projects or other city housing developments. Valerie Jo Bradley, a department spokeswoman, said that budget cuts had eliminated city financing for the program but that the Brooklyn, Bronx and Manhattan Borough President's Offices had donated $1.5 million to continue it in the current fiscal year.</p>
        <p>Projects completed last year, she said, included the $130,500 Pearl Street Park, a triangular area at Water and Fulton Streets in Manhattan near Southbridge Towers, a Mitchell-Lama co-o housing complex, and the $284,000 David F. Feingold Park, next to a housing development for the elderly built with Federal funds on Himrod Street, near Myrtle and Central Avenues, in the Bushwick section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Because there is less public money to go around, the private sector -- businesses, foundations, nonprofit lobbying groups and the communities themselves -- are getting more involved in creating, restoring and maintaining parks. The $8.9 million renovation of Bryant Park in midtown Manhattan was supervised by the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, a private nonprofit group, using money from sources that included the city, private donors and the property owners and businesses around the park.</p>
        <p>Other public agencies are also into green. The Battery Park City Authority is responsible for the new Hudson River Park and the planned South Park on the Lower Manhattan waterfront. The city's Operation GreenThumb, which is part of the Department of General Services and gets its money from the Federal Government, has for 15 years leased vacant city lots to community groups for use as gardens. Jane Weissman, its director, said that its more than 700 community groups and more than 1,000 gardens produced $1 million worth of fruits and vegetables each year.</p>
        <p>BETSY GOTBAUM, the city's Parks Commissioner, said that in some neighborhoods the communities themselves maintained new or renovated small parks. "In Greenwich Village, for example, at the intersection of Eighth Avenue, Greenwich Avenue and West 13th Street, there's a little park called Jackson Square Park," Ms. Gotbaum said. "We've lost more than 1,000 people, so how are we going to get there to keep it up? But the community locks it and opens it up and cleans it and sweeps it. There's a community organization that keeps it beautifully."</p>
        <p>The Parks Council, a nonprofit group that works with the Parks Department and other organizations to preserve open spaces, is very much involved in helping to arrange public-private partnerships to build parks, playgrounds and gardens in the city's underserved areas. The council is strongly urging that as much as possible of the thousands of acres of city-owned vacant land be set aside for park use.</p>
        <p>"It's primarily the low-income communities that are deprived of adequate open spaces," said Linda Davidoff, the council's executive director. "Whole stretches of Queens and Brooklyn and the South Bronx, where most of the poorer people live, are distant from where most of the parks are."</p>
        <p>As an example for the city, the council points to Success Garden, on 134th Street between Lenox Avenue and Adam Clayton Powell Boulevard. Working with Public School 175 and Community School District 5, the council turned a series of debris-filled, city-owned lots into a flowering playground, garden and environmental learning center. Conceived by Joseph Pupello, a council official, the project cost about $80,000 and was built using government grants and funds from foundations, corporations and individuals.</p>
        <p>"This block was honeycombed with vacant lots," Ms. Davidoff said. "The school's main entrance was on this block, but there was so much drug and crime activity the school locked it and told the students to come in through the asphalt playground. Once the site was cleared and fenced, other people on the block got the idea of setting up gardens on their adjacent properties. And the block improved in appearance so much that the school gate could be reopened."</p>
        <p>NOW the council is involved in a second such garden, to be known officially as the School District 7 Center for Horticulture and the Urban Environment at P.S. 30, in the Mott Haven section of the South Bronx. It involves a double-block site, including a vacant lot owned by the Board of Education and a yard owned by St. Ann's Church, between St. Ann's and Brook Avenues and 139th and 141st Streets. It is scheduled to be completed next year and it is to include a meditation area, a rock garden, community gardens, an aviary, a pond and a gazebo.</p>
        <p>The council is also working with residents of SoHo, TriBeCa, Little Italy and Chinatown in open-space-deprived downtown Manhattan on plans for a park on vacant land by Canal, Grand and Wooster Streets and the Avenue of the Americas.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gotbaum, the Parks Commissioner, said that she understood the Parks Council's concern about the need for new park space but cautioned that things were not all that simple.</p>
        <p>"If a piece of open space becomes available," she said, "we make an attempt to take a very good look at it to see if in fact it's really desirable, if it's feasible to fix it. And it's also very important to find out what the community really wants."</p>
        <p>Mr. Linn, the assistant commissioner, said there was always competition for the use of a piece of real estate. "People want housing," he said. "They want jobs. They want parks. The collision of public purposes is sort of normal, and you try to sort that out with some rational planning for the whole of the neighborhood."</p>
        <p>Crime, he said, is another concern -- trying to discern whether the city can reasonably control the open space, keep out drug addicts and make the neighborhood residents feel that they and their children can use the park or the playground without fear.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldstein, the state park regional director, said that when it came to dealing with the potential for crime "we have a very serious advantage that city parks unfortunately do not -- a separate state parks police force."</p>
        <p>The police presence at Riverbank State Park, she said, will consist of 40 patrol officers in addition to supervisory staff. "We want this to be a place where parents will be comfortable sending their young children by themselves," she said, "because the parents are comfortable that the youngsters will be safe here."</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldstein added that she had "heard rumors that there are large discussions going on in the illegal segments of this society about whose turf this park will be as far as drug sales."</p>
        <p>"Well," she said, "they've got a big surprise coming."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
