<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Gun Takes Aim at Tailpipe Pollution</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="636238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASER (LIGHT AMPLIFICATION BY STIMULATED EMISSION OF RADIATION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF133DF930A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Gun Takes Aim at Tailpipe Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like something out of "Star Wars," it will prowl the streets of New York City taking the measure of cars as they pass by unaware and taking pictures, too, that could be used to summon the drivers to make amends.</p>
        <p>The enemy: tailpipe pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like something out of "Star Wars," it will prowl the streets of New York City taking the measure of cars as they pass by unaware and taking pictures, too, that could be used to summon the drivers to make amends.</p>
        <p>The enemy: tailpipe pollution.</p>
        <p>The enforcer: a van arrayed with sensors and computers that is the latest weapon in the city's war on pollution.</p>
        <p>The experiment begins with a $200,000 grant from Washington. City officials hope the program will begin within six months.</p>
        <p>The money will let the city get a van with a gun that shoots a beam of infrared light across a single lane of traffic a few inches above the pavement. Of several designs,the one that the city has looked at most carefully uses a reflector that bounces the beam back to the van, where a sensor analyzes it to determine what parts of the light were absorbed. From that data a computer determines how much carbon monoxide and hydrocarbons are emitted.  Working at High Speeds</p>
        <p>A video camera in the van will capture the car's license plate number, allowing another computer to generate a letter to the owner.</p>
        <p>"They don't even have to slow down," said Antonia Bryson, deputy commissioner of environmental protection for the city. One equipment manufacturer boasts, probably with some other city in mind, that the instruments work with cars passing at speeds up to 100 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>The results could be used to target individual vehicles, or to find patterns involving certain models and years of car, or vehicles used certain ways, like taxis. With a little more computer work, the system might find patterns showing that cars inspected by a certain gas station tended to fail the test often.</p>
        <p>The system actually begins a war of dueling computers, because on newer cars the emissions controls are run by a computer under the dashboard. If that computer fails, Ms. Bryson pointed out, emissions can increase rapidly, but the computer running the infrared system cancatch those cars.</p>
        <p>Remote Sensing Technologies, of Columbia, Md., offers the RSD 1000 van, with a little hatch that swings open for the infrared beam and a video camera on a boom on the back. The Hughes Corporation, of Santa Barbara, sells the Smog Dog, with components that are transportable by van but designed to be operated from outside the vehicle. New York has not put the project out for bid, but city officials said that the plan was to lease the equipment, which they could do from Remote Sensing Technologies for $129,000 for a year.</p>
        <p>The equipment has been tried out in Los Angeles and Provo, Utah, and the two manufacturers are now competing for additional business.</p>
        <p>Nationally, air pollution experts are divided over whether to try to make all cars a little bit cleaner, by enforcing stricter requirements on the auto manufacturers and on cars brought in for inspection, or whether to target "super-polluters" with spot checks from roadside monitors.</p>
        <p>The city, Ms. Bryson said, did not believe in roadside monitoring as a substitute for cleaner new cars, but she added, "We subscribe to the theory you do have to have at a minimum some kind of audit program." She said the infrared program would do that, as a real-world check on the effects of stricter standards on manufacturing and inspection.</p>
        <p>Not everyone likes the idea. Simulating Conditions</p>
        <p>"It's double jeopardy," said William Berman, a lobbyist for the American Automobile Association in Washington. "You've already put that motorist through a periodic inspection, which he's already passed."</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Berman said, the testing equipment is often set up on highway entrance ramps or exit ramps, which is unfair, because auto makers design cars to meet a treadmill test designed by the Environmental Protection Agency. That test simulates many conditions but not rapid acceleration and deceleration.</p>
        <p>Mark Simon, a vehicle specialist at the city's Department of Environmental Protection, said this second objection may be valid, although by comparing data from many cars in the same condition -- for instance, driving up a ramp to the Queensboro Bridge, which is one location the city is considering -- useful data could still be gained.</p>
        <p>The money will come to the city under a Federal program called Congestion Mitigation and Air Quality. Other grants, announced by Mayor David N. Dinkins last week, will be used to convert 375 taxis to natural gas, and to extend bicycle lanes and bicycle paths.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
