<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capitol Stirs To Mr. Green, Ne Gorbachev</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="602390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL GREEN CROSS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDA1639F935A25757C0A965958260" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capitol Stirs To Mr. Green, Ne Gorbachev</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just in from a whirlwind speechmaking tour through Virginia and minutes away from jetting to the Coast for his San Francisco opening -- en route to his Japan appearance -- Mikhail S. Gorbachev dropped in on the Capitol today, promoting that favorite cause of celebrities everywhere, the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev, until 16 months ago the President of the Soviet Union and General Secretary of its Communist Party, is now president of the International Green Cross and Green Crescent, a new environmental organization that will formally spring to life in Kyoto, Japan, on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just in from a whirlwind speechmaking tour through Virginia and minutes away from jetting to the Coast for his San Francisco opening -- en route to his Japan appearance -- Mikhail S. Gorbachev dropped in on the Capitol today, promoting that favorite cause of celebrities everywhere, the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev, until 16 months ago the President of the Soviet Union and General Secretary of its Communist Party, is now president of the International Green Cross and Green Crescent, a new environmental organization that will formally spring to life in Kyoto, Japan, on Saturday.</p>
        <p>A score of lawmakers, a hundred or more of their youthful aides, and scores of other Administration and environmentalist guests sat in an ornate House of Representatives meeting room, at least partly to hear Mr. Gorbachev speak on the Green Cross and the pollution threat.</p>
        <p>Unofficially, they came to mob him and his wife, Raisa -- to pump hands, obtain autographs, try out their old college Russian, and just take a close-up gander at the famous bald head, precisely trimmed fringe of gray hair and wine-colored birthmark that made the former Soviet leader a darling of editorial cartoonists. For Environmental Crises</p>
        <p>"The poor man can't eat," said Elaine Wicker, director of the Congressional Clearinghouse on the Future, as she watched Mr. Gorbachev try to gulp down bites of catered London broil, grilled chicken, Caesar salad, new potatoes and rolls between interruptions by the star-struck.</p>
        <p>"We do a lot of international celebrities," Tony Staffieri said. "We do Liz Taylor. He draws a lot of the same crowd." Mr. Staffieri is with Savvy Management, the New York public-relations firm hired to promote Mr. Gorbachev and the Green Cross.</p>
        <p>The Green Cross aspires to be for environmental crises what the Red Cross and Red Crescent already is for disaster relief. Today, Mr. Gorbachev spoke fervently and at length about it, saying the group would seek to standardize antipollution laws worldwide, integrate the diverse efforts of environmental groups and press rich countries and corporations to start assuming their share of the global cleanup task.</p>
        <p>Reversing the degradation of the planet, Mr. Gorbachev said, is harder but no less important than reversing the course of the nuclear arms race, which he cited as his last major accomplishment.</p>
        <p>"It was probably risky" to accept the Green Cross presidency, he said. "But I agreed, because I am convinced, because I believe saving the environment is the No. 1 priority for all countries. I regard it as a privilege to offer my experience and knowledge."</p>
        <p>At first blush, perhaps, Mr. Gorbachev might seem an odd choice to head a top-rank global environmental organization.</p>
        <p>The earth's worst nuclear accident, the explosion of the Chernobyl nuclear reactor, occurred on his watch, shortly after he came to power in the old Soviet Union. In recent months, as the disintegration of the Communist empire has faded into memory, harrowing tales have emerged about Soviet environmental practices, from the dumping of nuclear wastes at sea to public-works projects that have drained and rendered lifeless vast inland oceans.</p>
        <p>Some environmental experts nevertheless say Mr. Gorbachev is the exception to the Soviet rule. "I think his credentials are very good," said Gareth Porter, international program director for the Environmental and Energy Study Institute, a research organization based in Washington. "He deserves recognition for having been the first major country leader to elevate what he calls 'environmental security' to the same level as national security."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev did that in 1988, when he suggested that environmental problems should be accorded the same international diplomatic importance as military problems like arms control.  Gorbachev's Own Concept</p>
        <p>The concept of an International Green Cross also is Mr. Gorbachev's, Mr. Staffieri said. The group is being sponsored by an assemblage of high-profile political and spiritual leaders, including Mr. Gorbachev, Mother Teresa and Javier Perez de Cuellar, the former Secretary General of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The swift and seamless nature of Mr. Gorbachev's life-change from Communist strongman to environmental star was epitomized by Senator John F. Kerry. Mr. Kerry, the Massachusetts Democrat and the Senate's most outspoken environmentalist, introduced Mr. Gorbachev today with a remark aimed at both his guest and his onetime adversary at the negotiating table, George Bush.</p>
        <p>"I think it fair to say that you might have called him the environmental President," Mr. Kerry said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
