<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Counting the Cost of Cleaning Up the Storm</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOCAL GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRENNER, ELSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB1F3AF93BA15750C0A965958260" item-length="1623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Counting the Cost of Cleaning Up the Storm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRENNER, ELSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE remains of the Blizzard of 1993 may finally be melting away, but now comes the hard part for officials left trying to reconcile their municipalities' already strained finances with the huge costs incurred by the snowfall.</p>
        <p>"Like the landscape, our budget was blown out with the storm," said James Madaffari, Peekskill's assistant city manager. "And now we are left with a deficit, because we were in a tenuous position to begin with."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE remains of the Blizzard of 1993 may finally be melting away, but now comes the hard part for officials left trying to reconcile their municipalities' already strained finances with the huge costs incurred by the snowfall.</p>
        <p>"Like the landscape, our budget was blown out with the storm," said James Madaffari, Peekskill's assistant city manager. "And now we are left with a deficit, because we were in a tenuous position to begin with."</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, too, are tallying the damage from the blizzard earlier this month and worrying about flooding this spring and the impact of salt on wells and other water supplies.</p>
        <p>The fallout from this year's cold and wet winter -- 61.9 inches of snow was recorded in Yorktown when 40 to 45 inches is the normal snowfall -- will be felt in Westchester for many months to come, both the municipal officials and those assessing the environmental impact said. And mopping up afterward, they agreed, will be a long-term project.</p>
        <p>"The actual weather is long gone," Mr. Madaffari said, "but the work goes on."</p>
        <p>He said that Peekskill, which budgeted $80,000 for snow removal for the entire year and spent more than $60,000 cleaning up during and after the blizzard, may be forced to float a bond issue to meet the costs of the storm "if worse comes to worse."</p>
        <p>In Yonkers, Jay B. Green, who was worrying about budget concerns and fielding complaints from some residents who didn't think the city had cleared the snow quickly enough, said he had taken to calling himself the "beleaguered with a capital 'B' commissioner of public works." Federal Aid, Again</p>
        <p>"I'm still trying to tabulate the fallout," he said. "Not only the blizzard but this whole winter has been a very, very expensive proposition for us, in a lot of ways."</p>
        <p>Mr. Green said that the cost of cleaning up 300 miles of roadway in the county's largest city during and after the storm came to $461,416 -- slightly below the $527,500 that Yonkers had budgeted for the entire year. With the costs of cleaning up from earlier storms, the city was in the red, he said.</p>
        <p>But the good news for Peekskill, Yonkers and other cities and towns in the county -- whose road crews battled heavy snow, rain and leftover mounds of intractable ice -- is that there is Federal aid available to help defray some of the initial cleanup expenses associated with the blizzard.</p>
        <p>"We are hopeful that the Federal Government's program bears some nice green fruit on the money tree for Yonkers," said Mr. Green.</p>
        <p>As it did following the violent Northeaster on Dec. 11, when storm damage to public and private property in the county totaled $68 million, the Federal Emergency Management Agency announced that it will help out once again.</p>
        <p>While there were few reports of property damage during the recent blizzard, County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke estimated that snow removal costs for Westchester communities -- whose budgets, he said, were already "pared to the bone" -- exceeded $15 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Rourke is also seeking special disaster aid from the Federal Government in addition to snow-removal monies.</p>
        <p>Under the latest aid program, the Federal Government will pay a municipality 75 percent of its costs for snow removal on main roads and arteries. The remaining 25 percent will be shared by the state and local governments. Not covered by Federal aid are related costs for sanding and salting and for collecting, hauling and disposing of snow.</p>
        <p>For New Rochelle, the Federal aid may make the difference between going in the hole financially and "just about breaking even this year," City Manager James C. Smith said. "This was an expensive little storm for us, something we're going to have to live with for a long, long time to come."</p>
        <p>Because of fiscal constraints, New Rochelle's snow removal budget this year was slashed to $160,000 -- almost two-thirds less than it was in 1992, Mr. Smith said. With minimum funds available, and money already spent in that category, the blizzard put the public works department way over budget, he said, "leaving the city in a pretty difficult position."</p>
        <p>While White Plains had $518,000 budgeted for snow removal this year, $400,000 of that had been spent on cleaning up after smaller snowstorms and icy conditions before the blizzard moved in on March 13, Joseph J. Nicoletti, Commissioner of Public Works, said.</p>
        <p>Now, with most of the snow removal money gone, Mr. Nicoletti said last week that "only if it really has stopped snowing for the year, will we be O.K." Borrowing From Peter to Pay Paul</p>
        <p>In Mount Vernon, "lots of overtime and lots of sand and salt wiped out what was left in our budget," George L. Preston, commissioner of public works, said. The city had already spent more than half of its $120,000 snow removal budget on smaller storms before the big one hit.</p>
        <p>But it was not just the big cities that felt the financial crunch. Smaller towns and villages, also strained their budgets while battling the effects of the blizzard. And they, too, will have to borrow from Peter to pay Paul to cover the costs, officials said.</p>
        <p>"We will have to do some juggling," Christopher E. Martino, Rye City's comptroller, said. "This El Nino thing hasn't been fun. It has been a tough winter for everyone."</p>
        <p>In Hastings-on-Hudson, the village manager, Neil P. Hess, said that officials may have to dip into a contigency fund to pay for the cleanup.</p>
        <p>As officials labored over their budgets, environmentalists worried about what the coming weeks might bring as melting proceeded, and meteorologists studied new weather patterns to determine what might be ahead. Salt Reported in Drinking Water</p>
        <p>Cesare J. Manfredi, regional water engineer for the State Department of Environmental Conservation in Tarrytown, said that after receiving complaints from county residents, his department was "going after salt piles," to make sure runoff from them was contained.</p>
        <p>"Private citizens say they taste it in their drinking water," said Mr. Manfredi, whose department is encouraging municipalities to shield their salt storage sheds against leakage and is urging citizens to make sure their wells are sealed against the invasion of contaminants like sodium chloride, which is used to melt snow and ice from roadways.</p>
        <p>He said that White Plains and Yorktown had already taken measures to prevent leakage of salt from storage bins and that North Salem, Lewisboro and Carmel were completing similar projects.</p>
        <p>Sand, also used on roads during storms, runs off into rivers and streams, and unlike salt, Mr. Manfredi said, it does not dissipate. Rather, it settles to the bottom of streams and rivers, sometimes sealing off breeding grounds for fish. Potential Hazard for Vegetation</p>
        <p>At the Rye Nature Center, the director, Tracy R. Kay, said that the sand and salt have begun to settle into catch basins and storm drains on the east side of the county and were potential contaminants that could enter Long Island Sound through freshwater tributaries.</p>
        <p>Also, the road treatment materials posed a problem for vegetation like sugar maple trees and white pines, which are sensitive to abrasive materials, he said.</p>
        <p>"The contaminants are just another urban stress that adds insult to injury," Mr. Kay said.</p>
        <p>The nature center director also said that the thaw would reveal whether animals like rodents, reptiles and racoons, which take refuge underground during the winter, survived the blizzard and the hard freeze that followed.</p>
        <p>At the County Environmental Management Council, the director, Laura E. Tessier, said that the slow thaw so far would probably minimize the likelihood of severe flooding later this spring, although officials would continue to monitor the situation.</p>
        <p>Both officials and environmentalists agreed that the landscape and the county's municipal budgets were strained to the limit -- and that neither could take much more buffeting.</p>
        <p>"The weather played havoc with all of us," Mr. Martino in Rye City said. Cold but Dry Spring Forecast</p>
        <p>What is in store for the future? Anthony F. Gigi, a Yorktown resident and a meteorologist with the National Weather Service who tracks weather patterns in the metropolitan area, said his agency is predicting a colder than normal spring -- but also a drier than normal one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gigi said that El Nino, the phenomenon that occurs when there is abnormal warming of water in the eastern part of the Pacific Ocean near the Equator, "tends to make for wetter weather patterns in the United States, and that's what happened this year." It is called El Nino for the baby Jesus, because typically it forms in December, although this year the event occurred in January.</p>
        <p>But also, cold air from Canada and milder air from the Gulf of Mexico and the Atlantic Ocean gathered in a trough that had formed in the atmosphere over the eastern half of the country. "Anytime we have that in winter, we are going to get a lot of intense storm systems," Mr. Gigi said. A Different Opinion</p>
        <p>In Hastings last week, Vincent George, an engineer from Yonkers who was shopping at the local A.&amp;P., disputed meteorological explanations of the winter of 1992-93.</p>
        <p>"They say El Nino is the cause of it all, but I say it's all these things we're sending up in space," Mr. George said. "They should stop it, and the weather will get better."</p>
        <p>Whatever the explanations for the weather, Mr. Gigi suggested that in drawing up snow-removal budgets for the future, municipalities would be wise to take a 30-year climatological average.</p>
        <p>"You can't predict based on the last five years, because they have been unseasonably warm and unseasonably snowless," he said. "When you get a year like this one, you realize that you have to look at longer-term patterns."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
