<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meteor Shower Obscured By Uncooperative Clouds</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METEORS AND METEORITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA173FF931A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meteor Shower Obscured By Uncooperative Clouds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The preparations began weeks ago. John Marshall and his band of urban astronomers planned beach-chair gatherings at Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn and the marshes of Staten Island. The Parks Department decided to assemble skywatchers at sites around New York City. Across the region, people had vowed to wake after midnight, throw open their windows and look up.</p>
        <p>Overnight, the annual Perseid meteor shower was supposed to have made such a forceful appearance that even in a city of domineering architecture swathed in artificial light, residents would finally be able to sample the heavens. The usually pallid sky should have been flecked with color, giving it more pizazz than the skyline to which it has long been subservient.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The preparations began weeks ago. John Marshall and his band of urban astronomers planned beach-chair gatherings at Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn and the marshes of Staten Island. The Parks Department decided to assemble skywatchers at sites around New York City. Across the region, people had vowed to wake after midnight, throw open their windows and look up.</p>
        <p>Overnight, the annual Perseid meteor shower was supposed to have made such a forceful appearance that even in a city of domineering architecture swathed in artificial light, residents would finally be able to sample the heavens. The usually pallid sky should have been flecked with color, giving it more pizazz than the skyline to which it has long been subservient.</p>
        <p>But Mother Nature had other ideas. A cloudy, dreary afternoon turned into an even drearier night, crushing the hopes of thousands of skywatchers, from Ph.D's at Columbia University to a retired medical librarian in Flatbush, Brooklyn, who had readied her bird-watching binoculars for a little alternative service. The meteors did their dance, but many in the New York area could not see them.</p>
        <p>"It's too cloudy and a lot of people have just given up," Mr. Marshall, 74, executive director of the Amateur Astronomers Association of New York, said last night as he peered out his window on the Upper East Side. "But in my strange occupation as an amateur astronomer in New York City, we must be stoic. We're used to the suffering." Celestial Party Time</p>
        <p>The sky hosts the Perseid meteors every August, but this year, the shower has returned with unusual vigor because a passing comet recently recharged the stream of debris, which the Earth crosses annually. The shower, which has fascinated skywatchers for thousands of years, is so named because it seems to radiate from a point near the constellation Perseus (the son of Zeus in Greek mythology).</p>
        <p>Most years, the shower produces only about a flash a minute and is usually not visible from urban areas, said Suzanne Chippindale, an astronomer at the Hayden Planetarium at the American Museum of Natural History. But overnight, it broke up the sky with hundreds of flashes a minute in a show that was visible in some areas of the Northeastern United States, Europe and Asia.</p>
        <p>The peak of the shower was overnight, but some astronomers believe that it will be as strong tonight and early tomorrow morning.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Chippindale said the planetarium received hundreds of phone calls yesterday from New Yorkers who wanted to know how and where to view the shower. Staff members told them that they should go to an isolated area away from buildings and artificial light, which washes out the night sky.</p>
        <p>"It's primarily an event that amateurs get excited about because it's one of the easiest things to observe," she said. "You don't need technical equipment or a $3,000 telescope. All you need is a lounge chair, a thermos of something to keep you warm, a blanket and a dark site. It's more an excuse to have a party than an event that has scientific interest."</p>
        <p>About 100 people turned out at 9 P.M. last night for a viewing at South Beach on Staten Island conducted by Keith Rowan, a supervisor of the Urban Park Rangers. But visibility there and around the city was poor, so park officials said they might schedule more viewings for tonight.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, John Pazmino, a 46-year-old computer specialist in Brooklyn, resolved to view the shower by escaping the city for a visit to friends in Red Bank, N.J., where the air is cleaner and the buildings don't swallow the sky. Haley's Comet Veteran</p>
        <p>Like other veteran amateur astronomers, he collected the necessary paraphernalia for the expedition: star charts, binoculars, portable telescope, tripod, camera with high-speed film, lawn chair, beach blanket, two pillows, crackers and cookies (chocolate chip or Oreos), juice and a radio.</p>
        <p>"You might be able to see something from Manhattan, but it would be a very patient person who would want to do that," he said, adding that he hoped the weather would clear by tonight so he could catch the vestiges of the shower.</p>
        <p>Other outings had been organized at parks, golf courses and various open spaces around the region. Before it was canceled, more than 300 people had been expected on the shore of Lake Sebago at Harriman State Park in Rockland County. The Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection had opened four parks, including Dennis Hill State Park in New Britain, Conn., for viewing.</p>
        <p>In Brooklyn, Arlene Freedman, a retired medical librarian who is in her 70's, kept her binoculars on the shelf last night after she concluded that it was too cloudy to venture into Prospect Park for the shower.</p>
        <p>"I've missed meteor showers before this, so I miss them again," she said. "It's not such a great place to watch anyway. I know when I watched Haley's Comet there, you had to use a great deal of imagination, because there was a lot of light pollution. So I'm taking it in stride. What can I say? You learn to take disappointment after a while."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
