<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health; Protecting your body during winter exercise.</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD6123DF931A15751C1A965958260" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health; Protecting your body during winter exercise.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"OH, the weather outside is frightful." But before you decide to venture out anyway for your daily constitutional, think about how to protect your body. Or, if you decide to stay in, think about how to give it the workout it deserves.</p>
        <p>Too many people use winter's inclement weather and short days as an excuse to follow the advice of the old pop tune and stay in front of the fire that's "so delightful" -- until spring. And too many who pursue their regular outdoor activities despite freezing temperatures, biting winds and icy precipitation are careless about protecting themselves properly against winter's hazards. But if you follow the sage advice of cold-weather experts, you need not turn to flab or risk weather-related discomfort or injury. Dress Properly</p>
        <p>This is the key to safe and comfortable winter exercise. The trick is to protect your body, especially your extremities, against the cold, wind and precipitation and to avoid becoming overheated. If the fabric next to your skin gets wet, you are likely to get chilled when you slow down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"OH, the weather outside is frightful." But before you decide to venture out anyway for your daily constitutional, think about how to protect your body. Or, if you decide to stay in, think about how to give it the workout it deserves.</p>
        <p>Too many people use winter's inclement weather and short days as an excuse to follow the advice of the old pop tune and stay in front of the fire that's "so delightful" -- until spring. And too many who pursue their regular outdoor activities despite freezing temperatures, biting winds and icy precipitation are careless about protecting themselves properly against winter's hazards. But if you follow the sage advice of cold-weather experts, you need not turn to flab or risk weather-related discomfort or injury. Dress Properly</p>
        <p>This is the key to safe and comfortable winter exercise. The trick is to protect your body, especially your extremities, against the cold, wind and precipitation and to avoid becoming overheated. If the fabric next to your skin gets wet, you are likely to get chilled when you slow down.</p>
        <p>Layering is the secret: a nonirritating layer like polypropylene or some other synthetic fabric that wicks away moisture next to your skin; a midlayer of wool or fleece for insulation, and an outer layer that is wind and water resistant and, ideally, "breathes" -- that is, allows perspiration and excess heat to escape. If the outer layer zips open, you will have more flexibility if you begin to get too warm.</p>
        <p>Hands and feet need particular attention, since when it gets cold, blood is shunted to the core of the body to keep vital organs at a normal temperature. Consider wearing a thin pair of gloves under heavier gloves lined with wool or fleece. When it is very cold or if your hands are especially sensitive to cold, make that outer layer mittens that have a wind-resistant shell.</p>
        <p>Buy exercise shoes that are a size larger than you usually wear, to accommodate heavy thermal socks or an extra pair of regular socks. As an outdoor ice skater and winter cyclist, I have found that putting an insulating layer on my legs helps to keep my feet warm. Cyclists can also buy neoprene booties to fit over their shoes, and skaters and cross-country skiers can get insulated skate covers to help keep their feet warm.</p>
        <p>Consider, too, that surfaces may be slippery and that you will need soles with treads that retain their grip on ice and snow. My personal preference for winter walking is fleece-lined high-top shoes with treaded soles (for example, so-called after-ski boots) or hiking boots.</p>
        <p>Head, face and ears need protection, too. One outer blood route that the body does not divert in the cold is the supply to the brain, which unfortunately means that a lot of body heat can be lost through a bare head. At the least, cover your ears to protect them against frostbite. For your face, a ski mask, scarf or bandanna can protect your skin and nose in the wind and cold and at the same time help to warm the air you inhale. To keep glasses from fogging, try wearing a ventilated neoprene mask over the nose and mouth.</p>
        <p>Knees deserve special attention, since the cold can thicken the lubricating fluid in this exposed joint and it can impair the function of a nerve along the outside of the knee that enables you to lift your toes and foot; this in turn increases the risk of tripping. And men must not forget that their genital organs may need an extra layer to prevent frostbite.</p>
        <p>If your schedule does not permit a daytime workout and you will be walking, running, cycling or blading in semidarkness, be sure to wear a reflective vest or at least have reflective stripes on your jacket and shoes. You might also consider holding a flashlight. Cyclists should have a light in front and reflectors on the rear of the bike, the wheels and the pedals. Prepare Yourself</p>
        <p>It may be wise to have company during your winter workout, especially if you will be doing some activity, like downhill or cross-country skiing, that has a greater than usual risk of injury. A companion is a good idea for any activity, even walking, when conditions are icy.</p>
        <p>Adequately warming up is especially important before a cold-weather workout. Cold muscles and joints not only compromise your performance but are much more likely to be injured should you misstep or slip. Warm up indoors, perhaps by running in place, jumping rope or riding a stationary bicycle, or do an extra-long warmup outdoors. And do nt forget to stretch once your muscles are warm, both before and after your main activity.</p>
        <p>Do not expect to maintain the same pace you exercise at in warm weather. The cold, wind and extra clothing necessarily will slow you down. But you can get just as good a workout, since your body has to work harder (that is, use more calories) to stay warm.</p>
        <p>Protect your exposed skin and eyes from the sun's damaging rays, especially when skiing or skating. Ice and snow are excellent reflectors of the sun's ultraviolet rays. Wear sunscreen and sunglasses, even on overcast days. Many an unschooled skier has suffered painful and unsightly corneal burns from skiing without sunglasses. Chronic exposure to the sun can cause cataracts and skin cancer.</p>
        <p>Be sure to drink lots of plain fluids. Many people, especially those who do not work up a noticeable sweat during their exercise routine, fail to realize how much water the body loses, even in winter. Water is lost through inapparent as well as obvious sweating and through the process of warming and moistening the air you breathe. Not only is dehydration bad for muscle function, it also increases the risk of hypothermia, a dangerous drop in the body's core temperature. Liquids that are hydrating include plain water, seltzer, mineral water, diluted fruit juices and caffeine-free coffee, tea and herbal teas.</p>
        <p>As you plan your workout, keep the weather uppermost in mind. Start out by going against the wind, if there is one, so that it will be at your back and less likely to cause a chill on your way home when you are sweaty and tired. If it is raining or snowing, wear water-resistant clothing from head to foot. Once your clothing gets wet, you will lose body heat rapidly. If You Can't Go Out</p>
        <p>If weather makes outdoor exercise unappealing, impossible or unduly hazardous, skip it. Instead consider these options:</p>
        <p>*Work out on indoor exercise equipment like a stationary bicycle, ski machine or rowing machine, either at home or at a nearby gym or Y.</p>
        <p>*Swim laps in an indoor pool.</p>
        <p>*Skate -- ice or roller -- in an indoor rink.</p>
        <p>*Walk or jog at an indoor shopping mall or, when traveling, in the halls of a hotel or motel.</p>
        <p>*Run, or walk, up and down a staircase for 20 minutes or so.</p>
        <p>*If you are physically fit and free of heart disease, shovel the walk and perhaps the neighbor's walk as well.</p>
        <p>Or forget about exercise for a day or two, as long as you resume working out as soon as the weather eases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
