<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Snooty Dame at the Block Party</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="113" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC103FF937A15753C1A965958260" item-length="15334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Snooty Dame at the Block Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerri Hirshey;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We are Where America Shops -- at Sears, in Glendale, Calif. And Americans -- college students, Hispanic moms with toddlers, old people -- are gawking at a striking apparition poised on the stairway to the women's fitting room. Cindy Crawford, supermodel, Hollywood wife and hostess of MTV's fashion program "House of Style," is calling out her bra size -- off camera -- above the racks of industrial-gauge corsets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We are Where America Shops -- at Sears, in Glendale, Calif. And Americans -- college students, Hispanic moms with toddlers, old people -- are gawking at a striking apparition poised on the stairway to the women's fitting room. Cindy Crawford, supermodel, Hollywood wife and hostess of MTV's fashion program "House of Style," is calling out her bra size -- off camera -- above the racks of industrial-gauge corsets.</p>
        <p>Standing by, catalogue in hand, is Simon LeBon of the British rock group Duran Duran. He's pointing to a saucy black lace push-up bra. He mugs for the MTV camera and speaks loudly into the courtesy phone.</p>
        <p>"Do you have that in a buxom 34-B?"</p>
        <p>LeBon is wearing men's pajamas, his initial selection in a made-for-MTV shopping spree with the "House of Style" crew. Style chameleon David Bowie had been slated to lead the expedition; he bought himself a boxy stage suit at Sears before he was able to trade up to Versace and Savile Row. Alas, scheduling problems kept the soigne Mr. B elsewhere with his wife, the fashion model Iman. Rock and style have been keeping close company for years; more and more, they're making it legal.</p>
        <p>LeBon, also married to a model, seems pleased, almost giddy to be at play in these fields of polyblend and rayon. Duran Duran began as one of the so-called haircut bands that surfaced in the fashion-mad 80's. Before Madonna hooked her first video bustier, these boys knew the business end of an eyeliner pencil. It was a mode of grooming uber alles. Dandies and ersatz pirates, french cuffs and bondage trousers -- the London club look sold whole cloth on MTV. For some bands, fashion stylists became as de rigueur as Jack Daniel's and roadies.</p>
        <p>LeBon says he's still possessed of deep closet; here amid the garish racks he's a right puckish juxtaposeur, helping bandmate Nick Rhodes accessorize a pair of Dickies overalls with about two dozen polyester clip-on ties. LeBon's own clothes lie in a pile back in the Nintendo section: jaggedly cutoff white jeans, work boots, high white crew socks and a pricey ruffled shirt in flowered red silk by Vivienne Westwood, fashion consigliere to the Sex Pistols -- and to the kinkier Kensington debs.</p>
        <p>"Rock-and-roll sportswear," LeBon explains in Robin Leach hypetones. "For the life style of utterly relentless chic!"</p>
        <p>The black bra arrives; Crawford takes it into a dressing room and reappears in a moment wearing it beneath a little boy's black, see-through mesh T-shirt that LeBon chose for her. The shirt ends about six inches above the waistband of her jeans. There is scattered applause from smitten shoppers.</p>
        <p>It's a Look -- probably best suited to a Duran Duran concert -- and attainable on a baby sitter's budget. This is the show given to featuring cheap chic -- Chanel knockoffs on a shoestring and so on. For style-struck vidkids, it's another object lesson in 90's found fashion.</p>
        <p>"Fabooo, Cin, Madonna would have needed Gaultier to pull this off," snorts a wag in the crowd, referring to that pop diva's high-fashion corsetier. His friend seconds that emotion with the ultimate street endorsement:</p>
        <p>"Yo, Cin-daaaay! Girl, you are large!"</p>
        <p>LeBon is fingering a pair of baby doll pj's. He turns to a pair of stricken-looking boys.</p>
        <p>"Understand something," cautions LeBon, mock serious. "When it comes to today's fashion, lads -- there are no rules!"</p>
        <p>THIS WAS BURLESQUE. BUT AMERICA IS serious about its style dispatches. More than a million people watched this segment each time it was broadcast this summer. Since the show began four years ago, advertisers have fallen over themselves to sell home perms and surfer duds between interviews with Lucie de la Falaise, the Saint Laurent model, and thrift shop decorating tips from the designer Todd Oldham.</p>
        <p>As I took cover from the Cindy clamor in the relative calm of Sears' purple Barney display, questions bristled from our style safari: How is it that an L.A. street kid knows the name of one of Madonna's Paris designers? How has it come to pass that the most successful new feature on this now-global cable network is about fashion, that couturiers like Karl Lagerfeld are willing, even eager, to share a spot on the dial with Humpty-Hump and Naughty by Nature? And what's happened to make our Cindy so large? Naomi. Christy. Kate. Please, how is it that subteens know the names of more models than of former Presidents?</p>
        <p>Call it the preening of America. Style's the ascendant supernova, spinning off a new galaxy of celebrities for the ever-hungry infotainment maw. Designers, models, photographers, hairdressers and makeup artists make the people pages as often as actresses and politicians. Even the President risked approval rating points for a Hollywood hedgeclip by one of those boldface barbers.</p>
        <p>The wide, blue skies are not safe from the style commandos. On a hot day in July, I thought my sun block had failed me when I looked up to see a 30-foot banner bearing the colossal grinning likeness of Calvin Klein's underwear poster boy. As it was towed through the skies above the Fire Island shoreline, the cotton-clad Bulge that has dominated thousands of bus stops threw a huge shadow over some toddlers making sand castles.</p>
        <p>"Look, Mommy!" one bellowed. "It's Marky Mark in heaven!"</p>
        <p>From Seventh Avenue to the mouths of babes, the transverse is complete. Fashion has rolled its pipe racks into the mass consciousness as never before. Ours is a style-savvy culture where Giorgio Armani shows up on "Saturday Night Live," where Roseanne dallies backstage at an Isaac Mizrahi show and Madonna begs a piggy nine seats for one of Gianni Versace's runway lollapaloozas in Milan. These are days when Bloomingdale's advertises Mizrahi's fall collection -- and his movie debut, with Michael J. Fox. It's a time when designers like Arnold Scaasi can sell $410,000 in outfits in just 45 minutes of air time on the home shopping channel QVC, pet project of the entertainment mogul Barry Diller.</p>
        <p>Folksy, not frosty, is the QVC designer ethos. Diane Von Furstenberg, former princess, talks tacos with a call-in viewer who's just bought her palazzo pants in size extra-large. ("Well, black is perfect then.") D.V.F., who long ago closed her jewel-box boutique on Fifth Avenue, sold 3,000 pairs of her silk pants in less than two minutes for a tidy gross of $150,000. For two hours' work, the take was $1.2 million. The production values may be a hoot, all crackling fireplaces and tufted sofas forklifted into the hangarlike studios in a Pennsylvania industrial park. But retailers aren't laughing. Saks Fifth Avenue grossed $570,000 in orders on the debut of its Real Clothes Collection QVC spot. Other department stores are taking meetings; Calvin Klein does not rule it out.</p>
        <p>On Saturday mornings, as those credit cards cool, one can sober up with a bracing half hour of Elsa Klensch, a real journalist who works the fashion beat for CNN. For the first half of her 13 years on air, she was a voice in the video wilderness, covering the collections, interviewing the likes of Blass, Kawakubo and Mugler with quiet authority. Now she is "Elsa" and no designer evades her inquiring mike. If Klensch is the Cronkite of the rag trade, Crawford is a game, albeit hipper, Kathie Lee, talking zits with fellow model Naomi Campbell, singing along with an ossified Don Ho during a Hawaiian segment.</p>
        <p>"I don't present myself as a serious journalist," Crawford told me. Instead, she sees her role as fashion Demystifier. "We talk about how I've got to hold my stomach in when I'm shooting," she says. "That I don't walk around looking like a Cosmo cover. They see me in rollers, shlumping around after the shoot. I think that's part of the reason people do relate to me. I'm not afraid of showing that side."</p>
        <p>The best from Bill Blass -- or Cindy in Sears deshabille -- you can conjure both sides with your Sony remote.</p>
        <p>THIS NEW ACCESSIBLITY IS A PATENTLY populist trend, putting designers in the same service-oriented chatstream as the Frugal Gourmet and those Sheetrock gurus of "This Old House." Fashion -- that once-snooty uptown dame -- has been coaxed from the atelier down into the block party. The poor dear has been polka-ed around the malls, frightened a bit by the rough trade of leveraged buyouts and Chapter 11, has been a bit bouleversee as the big department stores fell like so many top-heavy politburos. No one will tell you that the fashion industry is robust, assailed as it's been by retail failures, general economic downturns and the artistic and personal devastation wrought by AIDS. But anyone working in it today will agree: Never has so much been available to so many -- with so few rules.</p>
        <p>View it as a kind of democratization, if you will, a movement as inevitable as the end of the cold war and the revival of all-cotton sheets. Given today's climate -- economic and ecological -- it all just made sense.</p>
        <p>The underclasses have always had clothes; they just never have had so much design. They have long had style, but until recently street fashion had never made it to the runway with such a swagger. If Coco Chanel's revolution was to translate easy, sensible street dressing to couture chic, Gloria Vanderbilt's was to fill the streets with denimed female rumps bearing the designer imprimatur. Two decades ago, the very term "designer jeans" would have been a laughable misfit. Now it's just a timely lambada of the practical and the privileged. And at a swell price.</p>
        <p>How did the haughty crinoline crumple? In the half century that this magazine has regularly devoted pages to Fashions of The Times, successive style insurrections have loosened corsets and attitudes. It's happened in degrees, but overall the changes are vast. If in 1943 a Mainbocher-draped Wallis Simpson defined elegance, in 1993 it can be drag diva RuPaul in a snippet of to-die-for Alaia. Male fashions, traditionally conservative, have now embraced elements of "outsider" black and gay styles; even Joey Buttafuoco wears an earring. Today, muses come in all income brackets -- and cup sizes. "You can learn from Dolly Parton," insists Gianni Versace. "And from Marella Agnelli."</p>
        <p>How does it translate on the racks? Toppled hierarchies, madly scrambled in a satellite dish, make for fashion over easy. Fussy ensemble dressing has given way to witty, comfortable juxtaposition: Calvins with cashmere, kente cloth with pin stripes, Gap T's beneath $2,000 suits. Foundations are worn on the outside, if at all. Classics have gone far beyond the little black dress as upscale outlaw togs lurch down the runways, making the formerly outre instant ooh-la-la. (How else could Chanel sell out its $1,000 biker boots?) The newest perennials are often the naughty made nice.</p>
        <p>As Jean-Paul Gaultier has explained: "The motorcycle jacket that I always have in my collections, that is Marlon Brando in 'The Wild One.' Now a whole society of youth wears it, and it has become as much a classic for me as the navy blazer."</p>
        <p>DOES ALL THIS MEAN THE COUTURE HAS been tossed into the tumbrels and hauled down that cobblestone path to oblivion? To be sure, some once-proud heads have rolled. But most have learned to look beyond the salon trade. Houses like Dior, Cardin and Givenchy have retrenched and reached out, pumping up revenues by licensing their names to fragrances, to T-shirts, to cookware. Of necessity, they're designing lower-priced lines of ready-to-wear, from expensive "bridge" clothes down to jeanswear. "Second lines" have given new life to flagging design houses. If fashion once depended on the kindness of the in-crowd, now its most stalwart support comes from those strangers below.</p>
        <p>It all comes down to this: Few people live for fashion anymore. Fashion must survive by taking its cues from real life. Listen to that Wizard of Wearable, Calvin Klein, who made a fortune by understanding that the modern woman hasn't the time or the inclination to study fashion magazines like a breviary. He says his own revolution began in a dowdy wasteland of fussy frocks and "old lady coats." It was the late 60's, and he found the options unacceptable.</p>
        <p>"Even at nonexpensive prices,  [ coats and dresses ]  tended to be influenced by couture," he says. "It was all coming from the top. That seemed like nonsense to me. It was just old."</p>
        <p>So was the clubby fashion pack mind-set.</p>
        <p>"It was lunch at La Grenouille," he says. "You just knew what fashion was supposed to be about. And I would think, This has nothing to do with life. I've always been looking at the way people live. Pieces and mixing and adding and subtracting just seemed to make sense. People call it sportswear. But to me, it's a jacket and pants and a blouse and a sweater and a skirt. And you take those pieces and wear them different ways."</p>
        <p>Ask him the key to his astonishing success and he will tell you, simply, that he reaches America. All of America. He sells $10,000 dresses . . . and $5 briefs.</p>
        <p>Did this make Calvin king? Certainly not. The major American designers claim to feel no competition from one another, each content with his or her band of loyalists. In fact, no one rules this sprawling new marketplace. Now that you can buy DKNY in Jidda, Versace in Kyoto, is Paris burning? Pas du tout. European, American and Japanese designers all know the score. Recalling a European vacation with his family, Ralph Lauren says his then-17-year-old daughter asked him what she might wear to a disco so as not to look so . . . well, American. "Wear a Polo shirt," he told her seriously. "You'll look Italian. Or French."</p>
        <p>How best to take the measure of this half-century of fashion ferment? By its nature, fashion is a restless business. Borrowing often from eras past, jerking ahead with nanosecond technology and exuberance, the style history of the last 50 years constitutes a jumpy dialogue between what is and what's gone before. As Cyndi Lauper once said, "We all dress in versions now." THE BONDAGE YEARS</p>
        <p>"If there is a war, fashion will be different. But it doesn't mean that there will be no fashion. The most exciting fashion periods are often the years after a war -- 1947, the 20's. It's very interesting, how futility can make you survive in a difficult moment." -- Karl Lagerfeld</p>
        <p>During World War II, the worst fashion faux pas was to be too fashionable. Ingenuity was chic and sometimes silly. Once rationing deprived them of silk stockings, women painted their legs. By 1943, as leather became scarcer, they tottered on wedged heels made of cork. L-85, an order designed to save 15 percent of the domestic fabric production, prohibited a host of fripperies: no cuffs, no double yokes, no patch pockets, no coat hoods.</p>
        <p>"Buy American!" Forty years before that rallying cry was used to fend off the advances of Toyotas and Hondas, American department stores were campaigning for home-grown designers. The Germans rolled into Paris in 1940; fashion houses that stayed open were suspected of collaborating with the Occupation Government. Coco Chanel, living at the Ritz with a Nazi officer, had shuttered No. 31 rue Cambon a year before the war reached France.</p>
        <p>In New York, the established designers shone brighter: Claire McCardell, Charles James, Norman Norell. Mainbocher worked on military uniforms for the United States Navy; Norell took wartime restrictions seriously and turned out waistless jersey shifts that used 50 percent less fabric.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, there were no startling innovations during the war years and the look remained static: skirts below the knee, shoulders wide and padded, waist narrow, shoes clunky. World War II's most lasting fashion legacy may well be the T-shirt, developed when the Navy came up with specs for a "T-type" undershirt in white knitted cotton.</p>
        <p>The fashion press was ever cautionary. If loose lips could sink ships, the truly full skirt was tantamount to treason. Reporting in 1945, this magazine predicted that once L-85 was lifted there would be "no violent change in fashion."</p>
        <p>How wrong that was. Shortly after, fashion would impose a tyranny unknown since the days when a Scarlett O'Hara was trussed like a turkey for the sake of a 17-inch waist. It happened, as Lagerfeld said, in 1947, and for nearly a decade afterward, one female silhouette dominated millions of body shapes.</p>
        <p>If there is a single defining example of fashion despotism -- and the complicated psychological pas de deux between woman and designer -- it was Christian Dior's New Look, unveiled in February of 1947. Dior himself announced it as "the corolla," or flower, for the way his skirts bloomed so fully from tightly corseted bodices -- up to 80 mad yards of fabric in the most extravagant ball gown. But the Harper's Bazaar editor Carmel Snow renamed it when she gushed in the post-show hysteria: "It's quite a revolution, dear Christian. Your dresses have such a new look."</p>
        <p>Even Bugs Bunny lampooned it in cartoons. Photos depicting the fashion underpinnings of the day look like some S &amp; M seraglio: Reed-thin models knee one another in the back for leverage as they lace up the requisite corsets. These come-hither foundation garments featured chunky shoulder pads hung from bra straps and triple-stitched, warheadlike bra cups.</p>
        <p>Dior's "revolution" made for a willowy-looking figure -- and, judging from the hundreds of scary foundation ads that ran in this magazine alone, he cavalierly sentenced his devotees to nearly 10 years in bondage.</p>
        <p>How did Dior's grand vision trickle down to the working class? For the first time, inexpensive knockoffs of Parisian fashions were widely available, thanks to wartime advances in mass production techniques. The proliferation of the New Look, which would be reflected even in June Cleaver's crisp sitcom shirtwaists, prefigured the rise of a la mode ready-to-wear. Soon, fast, cheap knockoff houses would have spies poised at the couture collections; stores like Ohrbach's in Manhattan would draw East Side matrons on the prowl for a Givenchy look at Herald Square prices. In France, as well, the ready-to-wear industry was tooling up.</p>
        <p>Couture may have been contemptuous of these gauche imitators, but it was hardly threatened. The Europeans established a firm beachhead in New York. Dior opened his Fifth Avenue establishment in 1948; soon he was followed by Jacques Fath. By 1952, Pierre Balmain and the formidable Elsa Schiaparelli had steamed across the ocean with trunks full of silken pronouncements.</p>
        <p>As the couture enjoyed its strongest decade, there was additional ferment below. A new fashion force arose that had been historically unheard from. Those eternal sans-culottes -- the kids -- were on the march in greater numbers, and with more spending power. In 1957, Newsweek reported that teen-agers had an estimated $9 billion in disposable income. And all that loose change jangled with a restless impulse that said "later" to the dorky versions of Mom's wardrobe that dominated teen fashion up to that point.</p>
        <p>Shortly after Richard Nixon bragged of Pat's respectable Republican cloth coat in his Checkers speech, there was a new sound that brought with it a new new look. The song titles spelled it out: "High-Heeled Sneakers," "Blue Suede Shoes," "Venus in Bluejeans." Rock-and-roll kids had no use for those icky organdy confections called "date dresses." The Peter Pan collar was their yoke of oppression. As bobby soxers graduated into high heels, the next wave of girls and boys fell in thrall to fashion's bad boys, subversive dressers like Elvis and James Dean. Dungarees and sloppy shirts ruled these wild ones. And slightly sexy dressing began to keep subdivision Dads pacing nervously on date night. Off went Sweet Little Sixteen in tight calf-length capris, new "training bra" straining under a cloud of touchable angora.</p>
        <p>The closet rebellion wasn't exclusively American. Young Britons began to wear their restive feelings on black leather sleeves. "Teddy Boys" slapped on a dollop of Murray's pommade and a lot more attitude as they scootered and slouched about. And the less adventuresome wanted to look different from Mum and Dad as well.</p>
        <p>In 1955, the British designer Mary Quant had the foresight to address this new market. She opened her boutique, Bazaar, on King's Road in London, the first to offer stylish clothes affordable to the thousands of young women with low-paying jobs, bed-sitter lodgings and great yearnings for just a tiny bit of glamour.</p>
        <p>Thirty years past her revolution, I had occasion to visit with Quant in her Chelsea headquarters. She explained that it all had to do with the war, with the fact things wouldn't, couldn't, ever return to the way they were. The Englishwoman who had helped in the war effort, or at the very least endured its hardships, had seen a good deal of life beyond the hearth. And for her daughter, the horizon was wider still.</p>
        <p>"I was designing for me," Quant said, "for girls with a career or with a job. Until that stage, either women would be their father's little daughter, their clothes paid for by their father, or they were the wife of the doctor. This was probably the first time women had their own careers -- and therefore dressed for themselves."</p>
        <p>At this point, little of this social change was touching the couture. Apart from Chanel, Schiaparelli and the American sportswear seer Claire McCardell, men were the arbiters of female style. In 1954, Chanel had reopened her house. Though privately it was hoped she could goose perfume revenues with a soupcon of fashion, Chanel announced that she had returned to save women from the "50's horrors" perpetrated by men.</p>
        <p>From everywhere they came to Paris, young men arriving at the Gare du Nord with taffeta fancies and steely ambition. In 1953, a pale neurasthenic youth from French Algeria won the coveted International Wool Secretariat contest for dress design with a cocktail gown. Yves Saint Laurent was just 17. The same year, the son of a wealthy German industrialist won the coat division. Karl Lagerfeld and Saint Laurent were friends when they apprenticed, the German at Balmain, the other at Dior.</p>
        <p>In 1961, another impatient young man took the train from Madrid to Paris with a portfolio of sketches under his arm. He, too, wanted to be a designer, to totally change his fate. THE CONCORDE COUTURIER</p>
        <p>Look at Oscar de la Renta now and you do not see the insurance adjuster his father had hoped for. Tall, elegant, his balding head tanned the color of toasted almonds by decades of resort sun, the designer stills his phones and settles in for a chat. The hustle and honk of Seventh Avenue does not invade his minimalist white and cream office. He works -- hard -- eight collections a year now: two each (spring and fall) for his own couture and ready-to-wear lines and the same in his new role as head designer for the old house of Balmain.</p>
        <p>But he prefers this mad regime to hauling actuarial tables around the steamy tropic neighborhoods of his native Santo Domingo. Entering the family business was expected for the only son out of seven children. Somehow, his softhearted mother secured permission for him to go to art school in Spain, and his sketches landed him a job in Madrid at the house of Balenciaga. When the great man would not let him work in his Paris house, young Oscar went there on his two-week vacation and was hired by Lanvin on the basis of his portfolio. It was a dizzying pace. Press, clients, designers -- everyone relied on the talents of the sketch artist then.</p>
        <p>Shuttered with clients who made him doodle at alterations and variations, he says he was not a courtly presence in the fitting room, a character flaw that persists today. These women can be very needy, terribly demanding. They are paying -- handsomely -- for fealty. Better, he says today, to sell to friends on that level. This past spring, a flock of Oscar loyalists Concorded to Paris for his first Balmain show and behaved as though those dreaded letters "S &amp; L" meant "spend -- and lavishly." The names read like the lunch reservation book at Mortimer's: Nan Kempner, Mica Ertegun, Barbara Walters. . . .</p>
        <p>He concedes that his reviews are sometimes tepid, even faintly dismissive. The terms revolutionary or innovative do not pepper his notices. He takes it with the equanimity of a very successful man. But recently the critics sniped at his ladies, which really got his ruffles up.</p>
        <p>"This year, Bill Blass, myself and somebody else were in Women's Wear Daily," he says. "They criticized our collections by saying we were designing clothes for the forgotten woman."</p>
        <p>Understand, these loyalists, these forgotten types, the ladies who lunch and underwrite foundling hospitals, have long relied on the quiet, sporty elegance of Blass, the ruffled dramatics of Scaasi, the safe little Adolfo suits. De la Renta, along with these others, is still a darling of the carriage set. Fashion may well be more democratic these days, but not everyone is comfy on the black-clad, see-through, bell-bottomed Edge. Doubtless, you would not see Nan Kempner clomping into Le Cirque in a pair of Lagerfeld's giant white mukluks with Chanel in huge leather lettering. Even the cerebral seaming and innovative textiles of that established American artist Geoffrey Beene can be a bit too avant-garde for this crowd. Attention must be paid to the less-adventurous constituency, which is why de la Renta lectured editor Anna Wintour that her coverage in Vogue has been "too downtown."</p>
        <p>He is warming up now to the subject of his far-out competitors, the almond forehead burnished by a flush of indignation: "I should perhaps take a double page in The New York Times. Make a list of every woman I know who dresses beautifully, who works, who is a contributor to society and say, 'This is the forgotten woman!' " He smiles. "This is what I call the real world. I think what we are seeing today is clothes for freaks."</p>
        <p>Quietly, Oscar de la Renta does a huge business, up to half a billion a year by his own estimation. Grafting spreadsheet savvy onto couture tradition, De la Renta's is an operation that has its heart in the 50's and its business plan looking at the 21st century. Ladies and licensing: it's a combination that has weathered the recent economic storms.</p>
        <p>The high-end business is probably, at retail, about $25 million, he says pleasantly. "And we are doing about $500 million of Oscar de la Renta products around the world. About $150 would be in fragrances. Over $100 million in Japan."</p>
        <p>Japan bears some watching as its economy continues its downturn and status-mad consumers curb their Gucci habits. And currently de la Renta is re-evaluating his entire licensing program. He is acknowledged as one of the most successful players in this high-stakes game. In 1991, licensing sales, of items from Dior to the Chicago Bulls to Teen-age Mutant Ninja Turtles, totaled a robust $63.5 billion. Nearly a third of that was apparel and accessory related. But if the future of licensing seems assured in this celebrity-mad world, the track record of designer licensing has been somewhat spotty of late.</p>
        <p>"Designers: Endangered or Extinct?" asked WWD, noting that "Armani's doing basics and the Gap is on the cover of Vogue." Are they being "democratized" out of the marketplace? Or do they take the blame for diluting the product? Worried about lack of control over quality and distribution, many designers have pulled back in recent years, rewriting contracts as safer joint ventures, imposing stricter quality control methods.</p>
        <p>Since designers began licensing voraciously in the 70's, there have been several cautionary tales. The once grand name of Cardin was devalued by being stamped on everything from chocolate to sausage machines. As of last year, Cardin had sold 840 licenses. Halston, blithely declaring that a licensing agreement with J. C. Penney would allow him to "dress America," watched his business disintegrate as horrified high-end stores like Bergdorf's dropped his line. Corporate takeovers of the business he had sold to Norton Simon further divided his empire. By 1987, Halston's name became the property of the Revlon Group -- the sixth company to hold his trademark in just four years. At the time of death from AIDS in 1990, he was virtually prohibited from selling fashion items of his own design under his own name.</p>
        <p>This will not do for Oscar de la Renta. He says he is shoring up his defenses, setting up a cozy but serious international licensing seminar. Over coffee and brioches, he'll be talking quality to his licensees. Servicing! He'll be talking global.</p>
        <p>Even discussing his plans for publication can be touchy, he says. It costs so much to protect a name these days. Potential licensees must be investigated; product quality policed. He's already being sued. The lawsuits are inevitable when you must divorce yourself from a sleazy licensee. But the name is such currency, such a huge part of the franchise. It's a lot different from when he first came to America and it had been Halston for Bergdorf's, Bill Blass for Maurice Rentner -- so clearly employees. Now, fashion designers may be "owned" by huge companies like Murjani, Dunhill, Gruppo GFT and Revlon. But corporate logos do not appear on the lapels, the pockets, the sunglass frames. Designers' signatures do.</p>
        <p>Oscar de la Renta says he will take no foolish chances, will do everything he can to protect that loopy bit of longhand with the big fat "O." Yes, he wants . . . insurance. "I am very conscious that you cannot take a name and divide it into hundreds of different particles," he says. "Because by the end, there is no name." EAUTIES AND BEASTIE BOYS</p>
        <p>In 1965, this magazine carried a kicky two-page ad for Mary Quant clothes:</p>
        <p>"How do you dress for a Happening, a frug jamboree, an opening of a drugstore, a six-hour movie, a daytime drive-in, a water pistol duel? These London designers know. They're in charge of the Youthquake."</p>
        <p>The couture men didn't know what even young girls understood: Fun was creeping into fashion. And it sold: miniskirts and tights, short vinyl slickers, ribbed poor-boy sweaters, pale lipstick and eyelashes sold by the yard. Much of the hullabaloo came from across the Atlantic, where the Beatles' call to "Shake it up, baby!" echoed well beyond the dance floor.</p>
        <p>"Stop! The English HAVE ARRIVED!" Vogue editor Diana Vreeland shrieked to her staff when Cockney photographer David Bailey motioned model and then-girlfriend Jean Shrimpton onto Vreeland's faux leopard-skin rug one rainy day in 1965. Vreeland was also mad for Bailey's photos of his 22-year-old friend Mick Jagger. Shrimpton was what English kids were calling a dolly bird: huge eyes, porcelain complexion, hemlines way above the knees, Shirley Temple style. The first "waifs," big sisters to today's crop, began to make it out of Seventeen and into Vogue. Twiggy became a bony, knock-kneed caricature of this glorious gamine.</p>
        <p>The youth movement, so irrelevant to the pressed-linen world of couture ladies, had begun to infect one very influential atelier. Yves Saint Laurent had been only 21 in 1958 when he set the fashion press buzzing about his "childishly pretty" high-waisted dresses and the "look of extreme youth and femininity" embodied in his famous figure-skimming trapeze dresses. Within a few years, he was chafing at Dior's fusty imperatives. He understood that high fashion could benefit from the noise and bustle coming out of the new little shops.</p>
        <p>In 1960, he left Dior and started his own house. And in contrast to his reclusive habits today, Saint Laurent often left that house, to check the pulse in the streets. He was a habitue of the King's Road shops, where Biba, with its sensible $:7 price limit on dresses, had joined Mary Quant's boutique revolution. And far above this ready-to-wear "youthquake," Saint Laurent decided to create an outlet for his more youthful, less expensive designs. He opened his Rive Gauche boutique chain in 1966 and soon had 160 branches around the world.</p>
        <p>By then, Vogue was regularly slumming with the young and the vestless. That same year, Town &amp; Country's debutante issue featured one Miss Alexandra Chace on its cover in the scruffy company of the Rolling Stones. She wore ostrich plumes; Brian Jones, ignoring the Girl of the Moment, was deep in conversation with his bandmates -- and holding a cigarette. Bad boys, bad manners: quel kick! Ask Mick Jagger how he and his paisleyed ilk got invited to Fashion's garden party and he'll tell you it was just good business. The photographers were the brokers.</p>
        <p>It was not as though they were shooting a bunch of naifs. Many of the British rockers had art school backgrounds. And they had been studying style, Jagger noted, since Buddy Holly made nerd glasses cool. "Rock-and-roll is not only about music, it's about style," Jagger said. "It's all about what clothes and hair you have and what makeup. When we were growing up, we perceived the Everly Brothers as a sound. And look at that hair, you know? That was really important."</p>
        <p>Dating models sealed the deal. The 60's rock mannequins performed an essential function; they made fashion hip. Prancing through editorial pages normally reserved for horsy-set philanthropists and debs, they would create a new, alternative aristocracy. The era of beauties and beastie boys had begun. Chrissie Shrimpton and Mick Jagger, Pattie Boyd and George Harrison, Jane Asher and Paul McCartney were the precursors of the rock-runway stairway to heaven: Mick Jagger and Jerry Hall, David Bowie and Iman, Billy Joel and Christie Brinkley, Rod Stewart and Rachel Hunter, Simon LeBon and Yasmin, Keith Richards and Patti Hansen, Naomi Campbell and (U2's) Adam Clayton, Madonna and John Enos.</p>
        <p>As style-setters, rockers soon had the clout of film stars and socialites. And from the beginning, clothing merchants knew the value of hanging their wares on solid-gold idols. The kids would follow them anywhere -- especially to the shops. It could be luvlier still, should the dolly birds agree to a spot of shilling. Chrissie Shrimpton had her own gossip column in the American fanzine Tiger Beat. It was called "From London With Luv," and it was often about clothes -- like this fab report on the Who drummer, Keith Moon:</p>
        <p>"Keith wore a beautiful red shirt that evening. It was all sort of silky with red roses on it. He said it had been made for him at a boutique called 'Granny Takes A Trip.' This is hidden away in the depths of darkest Chelsea. But it's worth looking for." 'IT'S LIKE A COSTUME PARTY'</p>
        <p>Manhattan, SoHo, summer of '93.</p>
        <p>A Lincoln Town Car idles on Prince Street outside Phat Farm, a clothing emporium conceived and bankrolled by the rap impresario Russell Simmons. Inside, the decor is homeboy-meets-Polo: rough wood fencing, pitchforks, conservative, well-made shirts. One shirt, a soft cotton plaid, looks like something you'd find on Woody Allen, not Dr. Dre. Cutting-edge street stuff has gone conservative; Timberland boots and parkas, classic ball caps. Ralph Lauren says he is amazed by news clippings reporting that some urban street gangs are now boosting his Polo knit shirts.</p>
        <p>While the Lincoln's occupants -- two young Japanese tourists in 555 Soul ski caps -- browse at Phat Farm, a chauffeur rearranges bags in the trunk. I've seen young women like this before: in Paris, poking about the small shops in the Marais district; in London, negotiating the tilted floor of Vivienne Westwood's tiny shop on King's Road. They are a tribe that dates back to the siren call of Chrissie Shrimpton's breathless style dispatches.</p>
        <p>They're energetic, and deep into the hunt, but they're thrilled when stores like Union on Spring Street pull it all together: the right knit cap, hip-hugging bell-bottoms, a gold and white Ban-Lon shirt that fairly bellows Troy Donahue! They buy a look, whole cloth, even if it does look like pan-generational flea marketing.</p>
        <p>On a Saturday afternoon in SoHo, the shops are full of these prospectors. Wandering among them is the retail equivalent of channel surfing. "There used to be one trend that ran and another to replace it," notes the editor of Details, James Truman. "But now you see 10 subcultures walking down lower Broadway side by side. Punks, skinheads, new romantics, hip-hop kids. Everything's going on at once -- it's like a costume party out there."</p>
        <p>Get your Mary Quant hosiery and Doc Martens boots at Na Na; your reggae-striped knit T's at Stussy. Here at Phat Farm, the Japanese women are giving some baggy shorts intense study. Few shoppers have the global savvy or the budgets of this pair from Osaka. They decline to give names, citing their wealthy parents' fears of ostentation -- and kidnapping. But they are voluble about their prizes, especially a boxy polyblend work jacket by Dickies, a line of work clothes sold at Sears. The zip-in lining is missing, but for the $78 price one gets a glowing orange patch bearing the design company's logo, a cutesy obscene pun.</p>
        <p>Whose joke is it, selling industrial chic and retread Ban-Lon -- recycling Sears at boutique prices? It's the logical, rather cynical end game of the Adidas Esthetic that in the late 80's prompted young black men to shave that shoe manufacturer's "a" logo into their hair, to wear its satiny warm-up suits with the easy aplomb of Astaire in tails. The ultimate antifashion may not be in some Martin Margiela "deconstructionist" frock artfully flung at the press in a vacant lot -- but in the creative co-opting of the corporate and tame.</p>
        <p>As a fashion force, this street style is certainly less elitist, less precious than designer shredded waistcoats. Customizing mass-produced fashion may have been the only avenue open to hip-hop kids on a budget. But thanks in large part to the global reach of "Yo! MTV Raps," the lure of "outlaw," or outsider, fashion has reached beyond the street corners and clubs. Already, sympatico Oradell moms are cruising Prince Street in their Taurus station wagons, armed with wish lists from the sons of suburbia.</p>
        <p>This new youthquake was not announced in mainstream ads, but its influence has certainly reached Madison Avenue. Why else would Ralph Lauren run ads with a dreadlocked young black girl in a boy's funky-mixed Polo? How perfect for Calvin Klein that the street penchant for baggy pants worn below the underwear waistband showcases the designer's stitched name. Use a white rapper (Marky Mark) who's long relied on a black style consultant (Boston-based Patrick Petty). Add a topless babe (model waif Kate Moss) -- Whoa, just like a rap video! -- and you pull in some def demographics. The reach is surprising: This summer, Details was in the streets shooting a story on preppie hip-hop -- private-school princes wearing their ball caps backward and their Bermudas B-I-G.</p>
        <p>"We like the things of the black people," one of the Japanese women tells me at Phat Farm. And while that's long been true, while Japanese kids were torturing their heads with Afros back in the 70's, never before has black street style gotten its propers, with entrepreneurs like Simmons and Spike Lee making and selling the stuff of the nabe.</p>
        <p>Long before Elvis took his pink-jacketed cues from black Memphis street dandies, black elegance, especially in male dressing, was a deep-rooted source of community pride. This belies the tendencies of the media and Hollywood to showcase only the more extreme examples, from zoot suits to those 70's Superfly threads with more vents than a fast-food fry station. The appreciation for quality, both conservative and cutting edge, goes way back -- just listen closely to the Coasters' hilarious 1960 passion play, "Shoppin' for Clothes." And think about it: For every cartoony Mr. T, there is a soigne Duke Ellington, a preternaturally stylish Miles Davis.</p>
        <p>"Is very fresh, I think."</p>
        <p>After much deliberation, one of the Osaka Two has decided on that standout plaid shirt. She fondles it as the clerk rings it up. Another customer, a young black man in an Orlando Magic shirt, leans over. "Got the same one myself," he says. "So soft it hugs you like your mamma." DRESS YOUR HEART, NOT YOUR TAX BRACKET</p>
        <p>Uptown, Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>"Let me take you to another world," says Ralph Lauren. And he is off, clicking down the corridor of his mahogany-paneled headquarters in small, round-toed pumps with grosgrain bows -- worn sockless. "This is what I love," he tosses over his shoulder. Startingly tan against his snowy linen suit, he shoots ahead like a pinball off the spring -- at a salesman's pace. All week long, Lauren lieutenants have been leading store buyers down this long paneled hallway to show them retail's bright future with Ralph.</p>
        <p>"It's just behind this door. . . ."</p>
        <p>Leapin' lamb's wool! It even smells like another world, another time! The scent is a potpourri of old Shetland and laundered cotton, woodsy cabin and a sharp note or two of -- Churchill Downs? Lauren's essence elves have created another breathtaking stage set to sell his newest Double RL line, this time a countrified unthrift shop. Planked floor, old display cases, jeans, utility pants, bulky sweaters, unconstructed tweed jackets. The hook: new clothes, distressed with more detail than the Paramount prop closet.</p>
        <p>"We call this one 'Dances With Wolves,' " Lauren says, pointing to a blue cavalry vest on a headless dummy. He is smiling broadly, seems a genuinely content man in here, patting folded flannel shirts, smoothing lapels, offering up a pair of new jeans with the command, "Just feel."</p>
        <p>"Amazing," I must tell him. "You've even got that y--"</p>
        <p>"Yellow color around the worn seams, right?"</p>
        <p>Right. It's an impressive piece of distress-tech, far beyond the ersatz verite of most stone-washed fare. He says he's patented the process. These jeans are soft as a baby's bottom, worn in contours that conjure long hard rides on a Harley -- or on a 16-hand hunter. Nineties activewear -- it's already lived a fuller life than you have.</p>
        <p>"But brand new," Lauren keeps saying. How does he know when artfully worn gets too close to Salvation Army?</p>
        <p>"It's all a secret. But I'm the one who decides."</p>
        <p>He is the undisputed master of instant patina, and as such he has suffered the slings and arrows of press types who would call him snippy names like "life style purveyor" and "the Wee Haberdasher." He admits it's made him cranky. Before we tour his other "worlds" -- the recreated St. Tropez beach club displaying resort wear, the chintz-and-tartan hives where the vast Home collection is conceived -- Lauren says that he wants it made clear that he sells aspirations, yes. But not to the regatta-and-lawn croquet echelons.</p>
        <p>"In the last few years, I get this, 'Well, Ralph represents the WASP life,' " he says. "That's not what it's about. It's never been that."</p>
        <p>It's upscale, sure. His own promotional copy suggests that his new Active Trainer clothes are "for the gym or a cappuccino on the way home." And he doesn't mean a go-cup from Dunkin' Donuts. Still, it's not all rich people who have pumped the worldwide revenues of Polo/Ralph Lauren Products, a privately held company, to $3.7 billion in retail volume. He has 140 stores worldwide, from Palm Beach to Kuala Lumpur.</p>
        <p>Despite a few profitability problems in the women's division, Lauren is still opening stores, most notably Polo Sport, across from his flagship store-cum-gallery in the Rhinelander Mansion at Madison and 72d Street. And Laurenization, from khaki pants to all-cotton turtlenecks, has spread beyond and below his price points, of course. The Gap, Banana Republic and J. Crew, to name a few, have successfully marketed his look at a lower price. It's a kind of piggyback populism, this rush to things basic and essentially conservative, worn, in Gap ad campaigns, by the unassailably edgy and hip. They are photographed in minimalist black and white: actors, painters, musicians.</p>
        <p>This is, in its way, a rebirth of the Whitmanesque longing that caused the jeaning of America in the late 60's and went so wonky. On the ramparts and on campus, we looked earnest, but so sloppy -- so very Goodwill. Ralph knew how to do it right. What he dragged back into the American marketplace was the thing that Time and Technology forgot. Good stuff, with roots deeper than a 60-second spot on the "Sonny and Cher Show."</p>
        <p>Over and over, he says it's about quality, and he means it. He says that he is tired of being misunderstood, weary of barbed profiles that paint him as some pretender to the Windsor line by way of the Lifshitz branch from the Bronx. Sure, he was a hustling tie salesman in the late 60's. But that's the beauty of it. Humping along with his sample cases, he refused to muffle himself in some Willy Loman quitter's suit; he wore a leather jacket and drove a cream-colored Morgan with a leather strap across the hood. Lauren is one of those dyed-in-the-diaper dandies, like Tom Wolfe or Gay Talese, who found himself a good tailor before he worried about his first girlfriend. Dress your heart, not your ZIP code or tax bracket, he has long believed. He's as moony, as cinematic about clothes as Woody Allen is about Manhattan.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes you can't explain clothes unless you put it in the environment that sets it up the right way," Lauren is saying. "It doesn't mean that you're trying to give them the good life or the status life. It means that people do have aspirations, to have a good life, to have a home with an extra bedroom, decorate it the right way. They want the best school for their kids. They want to go on vacation."</p>
        <p>Lauren's naturally soft voice lowers still, to the soothing interrogative of a $125-an-hour Freudian: "Why do you go on vacation? Why do you buy this dress? Who do you think you are when you're putting it on? What does it make you feel like?"</p>
        <p>He holds this truth to be self-evident: That all men -- and women -- are created with shoulders equal to what the Coasters called "pure, pure herrin'bone." After all, historically, we are a nation of upstarts, ever eager to clamber off that barren polyester hardscrabble. Why else would American department stores entice customers with sections that read "Better Sportswear?"</p>
        <p>Get into some classy tweeds, that riding look, Lauren says, and it just gives you "a spirit of that country look. Sort of sets you up with a world that's nice." So you're not out in Bridgehampton waiting to jump the final round of Working Hunter. Maybe you're just driving the twins to the orthodondist. But Lauren says you get his Feeling:</p>
        <p>"Hey, that's nice. I didn't know I could do that."</p>
        <p>Feelings. Nothing more than feelings. It's no accident that designers do so well in fragrance. Pheromones and longings are all of a piece. And feelings, longings, are what Ralph Lauren says his clothes are all about. Feelings that are primarily his own. All his companies, he says, "are a part of my life. My designing comes from what I do. I live it, I wear it, I love it. I don't sit there and say, 'I think we should do big sleeves this year.' "</p>
        <p>He says that all of his divisions started off with these words:</p>
        <p>Why can't I have . . . ?</p>
        <p>Just fill in the blanks. Men's wear (Why can't I have a pair of khakis like my dad's in the 50's?). Women's wear (Why can't I have a jacket cut and tailored as well as my husband's?). Ralph Lauren Home (Why can't I have a towel that will dry all of me?).</p>
        <p>He's given them 400-count all-cotton sheets. Real wool tweed. Potpourri that doesn't smell like a melted Mars bar.</p>
        <p>Why can't I have . . . ?</p>
        <p>It is a class question, born of a very basic itch. "Why is it," the late designer Willi Smith once roared at me over chicken salad, "that if someone without a lot of money wants a shower curtain, it has to have huge yellow flowers all over it?"</p>
        <p>Why can't I have . . . ? Hear Lauren's tweedy cri de coeur as the mantra of the upwardly mobile, or just those seeking equality in design. Giving middle-class people what was formerly available only to their lawyers, undertakers and heart surgeons has made Ralph Lauren a very wealthy man. But he wants you to understand this one thing: When he started out, it was weird. You may think of Ralph Lauren as silver loving cups and hacking jackets and more tradition than the Queen's Regiment, but he insists he started off as the Alternative Guy. Please, he says, remember the times.</p>
        <p>"America was very traditional, somewhat preppy," Lauren says. "The Carnaby Street revolution came out of England and that faded out. Pierre Cardin was just moving. You'd hear something about a designer name. But there was no such thing as designers in the United States."</p>
        <p>In 1969, hair was a helmet by Kenneth or a fop crop by Vidal Sassoon. Fashion designers were at play in fields of paisley, granny prints and gauze.  The Europeans were off on their own flights of fancy. Courreges had turned to rocket suits, Cardin to Op Art. Karl Lagerfeld, designing for Chloe, indulged his obsession for collecting Art Deco. Balenciaga retired, declaring that the age of couture was over.</p>
        <p>Amid this classless hodgepodge, the time was absolutely right for a gentleman of consistency, a man with a slow hand. It was a fortuitous moment for the salesman to quit hauling around sample cases of boring rep ties "to go with I.B.M. suits" and start cutting his own wide flashy affairs out of suiting fabric, gabardine, Indian prints. Lauren's ties were big, beefy things that made a knot the size of a plum tomato. Ralph Lauren started doing it because he couldn't find a decent tie for himself.</p>
        <p>Why can't I have . . . ?</p>
        <p>"Whered'ya get it?" they kept asking about his ties. He quit his job and hawked them around to department stores. They sold out.</p>
        <p>He went from men's wear to a women's collection that started just with simple, man-tailored shirts cut slim and sold in the narrow boutiques of Bloomingdale's and Bendel's. They were selling, but not to the plaid-and-chino masses who buy them today. "I had a cult following," he says. "It was the hippest customers, young models, thin, antifashion girls."</p>
        <p>As Lauren explained back then to an inquiring press, "I think it looks chic now to look straight." He kept adding to the collection: flannel slacks, man-tailored blazers, tuxedos, tuxedo vests. Some people, he says, called it "dykey" -- it was that off-center. In fact, Ralph Lauren was about a decade and a half ahead of the back-to-basics mania that's still with us. Slowly, it grew, until hordes of tiny polo players thundered across the oxford cloth plains.</p>
        <p>As with many things, the cultish became the commonplace. And the niche marketer widened his sliver to engulf the world. Today, his is a vision so broad, so larger than life that insiders in his mahogany warren call it "the Movie." Indeed, no print profile of Lauren has neglected to emphasize the cinematic aspects of his world, the movie references in his speech, the trend-setting costumes Diane Keaton wore in Woody Allen's "Annie Hall." Fashion and fantasy have long been a compatible double bill. And in this costume drama, anyone can be a star.</p>
        <p>To dismiss Ralph Lauren as simply faux elitist, then, is to miss the point. A vision that appeals to the Prince of Wales and his estranged wife, to hip-hop kids in Flatbush, to purdah ladies in Bombay reaches far beyond wannabe WASPism. Unless you posit some international movement to restore the Raj, Ralph Lauren has to be right: They just want quiet, somewhat better, less disposable stuff. It's a global longing now. A MULTICULT MYSTERY TOUR</p>
        <p>As September school bells tolled, Ralph Lauren fitted out a special tractor-trailer and hauled his Double RL retail crypt downtown to the campus of N.Y.U. for a little "point of sale" education. Uptown, another, less commercial institution was mounting its next show, encapsulating the way we were.</p>
        <p>Below the mummies and sarcophagi of the Metropolitan Museum's Egyptian Wing, thousands of garments lie in storage or restoration, in drawer after drawer of epochal chic. On a table, a seated mannequin is being eased into the tweedy comforts of an early 70's Anne Klein suit for the current exhibit of the museum's Costume Institute, "Versailles 1973." It is centered around a famous French show two decades ago that featured five American designers: Anne Klein, Bill Blass, Stephen Burrows, Halston and Oscar de la Renta.</p>
        <p>"It's the signal event when American designers were taken seriously by the Europeans," explains Richard Martin, curator of the institute. "It's really the triumph of American sportswear."</p>
        <p>Casting about for traits distinctive to American fashion, Martin and his co-curator, Harold Koda, are strong on pragmatism -- the American hankering for comfort, wearability, durability. And sportswear -- the abandonment of the total look for a mix-and-match mutability. By the early 70's, the fussy chapeau-to-shoe ensemble look was all but spaded under, along with big-finned cars and Jackie O.  pageboys.</p>
        <p>Extravagant display felt unseemly, much as it does in these recession-bound times. One dressed down for sweaty hours on the gas lines. As the 70's wore on, mortgage rates rose to unprecedented double figures. America's inner cities still bore the sooty scars of the 60's riots. For many depressed and defeated activists, the fatigues went into the attic and "work clothes" now meant leaving the thrift stores for Hickey-Freeman and Anne Klein.</p>
        <p>Fashion was not immune to the times. Soothing, quality classics flowed from ready-to-wear designers like Sonia Rykiel, Jean Muir and Karl Lagerfeld for Chloe. Diane Von Furstenberg had an instant hit with her short, go-anywhere wrap dress, which had a touch of Dido -- with a car-pooler's comforts.</p>
        <p>But predictably, there were those who prefered not to stay at home. In an age still itchy with spiritual quests, from the Beatles' pilgrimages to India to Carlos Castaneda's "Teachings of Don Juan," fashion set off on its own beads-and-burnoose odysseys. As a word, multiculturalism was hardly in use yet, but fashion designers, like questing rock stars and suburban swami followers, were having their passports stamped at more and more exotic ports of call. Yves Saint Laurent was seen scouting in Denver and Albuquerque in 1976, poking in the same cafes and trading posts that had sparked Ralph Lauren's blanket jackets and prairie skirts.</p>
        <p>"In the mid- to late-70's, fashion was really wandering," Richard Martin says. "It was looking at the world for inspiration. That's one of the reasons Japanese fashion became important."</p>
        <p>Hailing the asymmetrical hemlines of Yohji Yamamoto, the fluid draping genius of Issey Miyake, the dark, minimalist lines of Rei Kawakubo for Comme des Garcons or the amusing forays of the peripatetic Kenzo, the fashion world, Martin says, "was realizing that the monolithic Western tradition was breaking apart."</p>
        <p>Multiculturalism arrived on the runway in another form. It first made waves at that Versailles show in 1973, when the American designers brought over a number of black models, blessedly unbowed by Parisian traditions. Once the music started, the clothes began to come alive as they never had before. Europeans, used to a very static, pivot-and-pose kind of show, cheered the loudest.</p>
        <p>Even on the New York runways of that time, "the black models steal the shows," Eli Evans reported in this magazine. "At the shows of the major black designers -- Scott Barrie, Stephen Burrows and Willi Smith -- the models are unrestrained enough to skip down the runways and occasionally toss off an all-out, high-stepping, syncopated wipe-out step, turning an ordinary jersey dress into two hound dogs in a burlap bag."</p>
        <p>The black models reminded people that clothes were meant to be worn, that the body was in fact the key accessory. Customers were easily convinced. On Saks' seventh floor, Kal Ruttenstein, then a merchandise manager, watched the dresses fly out the door when the models Bethann Hardison, Billie Blair and Norma Jean Darden did it to death during store promotions for designers like Clovis Ruffin.</p>
        <p>"The audience went nuts," Ruttenstein recalls. "And the minute the show was over, they were trying clothes on and buying them like wildfire."</p>
        <p>There have been waves of standout black models since then: Beverly Johnson and Iman, Naomi Campbell, Beverly Peele, Veronica Webb. Visit a few European ateliers and you now see many stunning women of color among the house models, rustling about in muslin tailles.</p>
        <p>It's an achievement burlesqued -- but reverently -- in those late 80's vogue-ing balls so popular with gay black and Hispanic men who organized themselves into fashion "houses" and walked it, talked it, wore it with an esprit that could make you holler and weep.</p>
        <p>Long before Madonna mined her platinum CD's from that Shake 'n' Bake subculture, a friend took me to a vogue-ing ball the night he was being inducted into the House of Africa. We stood by apprehensively as one of the judges, the towering transvestite Pepper Labeija, set down the prescriptives for the "Fem Realness" competition. A skinny boy in lame platforms and very tacky shirred Qiana had the misfortune to catch the regal eye.</p>
        <p>"Lord, girl," Her Spiciness scolded through the mike. "You look like some 'Brady Bunch' car wreck. I'd say about 1975!" THE GROOVINESS HANGOVER</p>
        <p>Pepper had a point. Things did get ugly for a while there. Despite the cooled-down classicism at the higher price points -- the zipless, buttonless minimalism of a Halston, the simple linens and cashmeres of Calvin Klein -- there was a good deal of unsightliness in Junior and Misses Sportswear. Even in men's wear, our collective grooviness hangover collided with disco, punk, you name it -- and the knockoff men hauled the whole mess to Bloomingdale's second floor.</p>
        <p>In a decade that had embraced the dashiki, hot pants, the denim jacket and the leisure suit, more than a few closets developed multiple personalities. Cinema offered style-setters from "The Rocky Horror Picture Show" to "Annie Hall." As a Presidency fell and ugly things skittered from beneath the Oval Office rug, as China opened and the Shah was closed down, the floodgates to bad taste were flung wide.</p>
        <p>If you have any doubts that "mainstream" 70's fashions could be truly bizarre, just watch a "Brady Bunch" rerun, a riot of light-blue polyester, kicky icky bell-bottoms, gaudy ties, platform oxfords -- and much of this perpetrated on children. Despite the gas shortages, there seemed to be no dearth of petroleum-based fashion. In 1974, three years before they celebrated the Queen's Silver Jubilee by selling T-shirts with a safety pin stuck through the royal face, British style tricksters Vivienne Westwood and Malcolm McLaren turned out a swell line of bondage wear in sweaty, snappy rubber.</p>
        <p>Into this valley of gaucherie and misshapen Corfam shoes rode Giorgio Armani, the quiet tailor. In men's wear, and in men's-styled women's wear, he put the European designers' imprimatur on the casual revolution the Americans had begun. Quietly, insistently, he would banish the crass imperatives of Fashion for the classy impulses of Style.</p>
        <p>Always a person of particular tastes -- he says he probably styled his sandbox -- Armani confessed that he had been chafing against the unnecessarily ugly in fashion since he designed window displays in the Italian department store La Rinascente in the mid-60's. Things weren't much prettier in 1975 when Armani started his own label with less than $10,000 and a belief that the antifashion of the late 60's needed a firm hand to get it back on track. The Italian felt that modernity should go beyond the faddish, toward the timeless. He tilted his scissors, spurred his fledgling work force and drove hard at the suit jacket, that ages-old coat of mail that had recently been discoed, denimed, tortured with Naugahyde elbow patches, yoked and topstitched in Ultrasuede -- or worse, left stiff and unbending in that tired old box, the business suit. Armani cut his new shape, bold as the mark of Zorro.</p>
        <p>"Though it was the spirit of casualness, it was the spirit of the new era of the 70's," he says. The thing he loosed would be "a little used, not absolutely perfect." It would have some classic lines, but feel modern and comfy as a running shoe. It was the Armani Jacket.</p>
        <p>Armani had taken the suit jacket and torn its guts out; though he kept some classic lines, he deep-sixed the glued-on, stiffening lining, risking rumple for the sake of ease. He dropped the lapels and moved the top button down to a level that was cardiovascular friendly. Shoulders were dropped and extended. And when he was done with this handsome sedition, one that would change men's wear so profoundly, Armani extended his tailoring in a softer version to women.</p>
        <p>There were, of course, widely divergent interpretations of Haberdashery for Her, from Armani's suave suits to the funkier newsboy "garconne" looks bouncing out of European houses. Even male terrorist chic hit the Paris runways in 1978 as Daniel Hechter's I.R.A.-tweed look jackbooted along. Black beret, leather jacket, man's shirt and tie, shades, crepe-soled brogues and rolled-down ankle socks. All that was missing was the ultimate accessory, an AK-47 -- in basic black.</p>
        <p>By the late 70's, the names of American designers were firmly stitched in the American consciousness -- and on countless products: Bill Blass. Geoffrey Beene. Calvin Klein. Halston. Ralph Lauren. Perry Ellis opened his firm in 1978 and would make the grade in record time. Thanks in large part to frequent profiles and party coverage in Women's Wear Daily, the designer loomed larger as a personality. No consortium of P.R. wizards could have done what the WWD publisher, John Fairchild, did to glamorize the job.</p>
        <p>Given the growth of these names, licensing boomed in the shaky 70's. Industry experts have long believed that licensed products do well in downturned economies because the customer believes a licensed product has a higher value than a generic item. A perfect example: designer jeans. 'YOU OUGHT TO DO JEANS'</p>
        <p>Fashion moment, 1978.</p>
        <p>Calvin Klein is at the bar in Studio 54, the very spot where his good friend Steve Rubell had informed him, one mad Halston/Calvin/Liza night, that fashion designers had become celebrities. How strange, he thinks. He's just having fun. It's 4 A.M and he's decided to stay up all night and cruise straight to the airport for a business trip to Frankfurt in the morning. It's that time in his life when he's not thinking marriage and evenings by a crackling mesquite hearth -- feelings that would inspire his Eternity fragrance a decade later. No, he's having an Obsession kind of sensation, a heady frisson he'd eventually communicate to the chemists who helped him develop his signature fragrances. Recalling all-nighters like this, he'd talk to the scientists as though they were a team of shrinks:</p>
        <p>"You know, I'm feeling really strong, very sexy. Like life is wild and I'm up all night and you just don't have sex with one person, you have sex with a group. . . ."</p>
        <p>They'd suggest musk notes -- the kind that assailed you at 54 when uptown girls brushed up against Christopher Street on the dance floor.</p>
        <p>So here he is, having one of those nothing-is-beyond-you nights, when suddenly a man walks up and introduces himself to Klein.</p>
        <p>"You ought to do jeans," the stranger tells him. His name is Peter King, he's got a company, could do the licensing. . . .</p>
        <p>Oh, what an idea, what a damned fine idea! "What Levis does is fantastic," Klein is thinking. "But I'm a designer. I can do things with cut, silhouette, shape that they can't. To create attitude. An image. . . . It could be really fun."</p>
        <p>After dawn, the notion is still with him. It has Calvin Klein, well, obsessed. On the way to the airport, he picks up his car phone and directs his business partner, Barry Schwartz, to look into this guy, have an agreement ready when he gets back.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years later, there is thunderous applause in the Hollywood Bowl as Brooke Shields smiles from a huge video screen and says that nothing comes between her and her Calvins. After the seven-minute montage of Klein's most arresting ads over the years, they are all on their feet: 350 models, Barry Diller, Tina Turner, David Geffen, Warren Beatty, Jeffrey Katzenberg, the whole fashion/Hollywood arc -- here to celebrate the World of Calvin Klein and benefit AIDS Project Los Angeles. It's normally a tough crowd, but there is plenty of oozing mascara.</p>
        <p>Bloomingdale's fashion czar, Kal Ruttenstein, who remembers a young Calvin pushing pipe racks of his coats down Seventh Avenue, is nearly overcome. Here is Calvin, reclaimed -- from substance abuse, from financial uncertainty -- so strong now. Out in the crowd, a much younger man is surprised at his own, rather emotional reaction. Details editor James Truman is a tough-minded Brit, a man who has just banned the word style from his fashion magazine, despising its "tyranny." But Calvin's montage hits square between his oh-so-slim lapels. "It brought a lump to your throat," Truman recalls. "It had such power to the heart. It was like seeing Greta Garbo. I think advertising appropriated the emotional style that the movies had before. And I think that anyone who's grown up with that cannot help but think this is so emotional. And so important -- that they have to be a part of it. With clothes."</p>
        <p>Calvins, instead of that Proustian madeleine. Amazing, the impact of a topstitched pair of pants.</p>
        <p>Remembering the moment himself, Klein smiles. "This is about the democratization of fashion," he says. "It used to come from Babe Paley. Now it comes from stone-washing denim to make it look like you've owned it a long time."</p>
        <p>Within a year after Klein indulged his denim dreams, there were more than 30 brands of designer jeans on the market, signaling a slide toward casual that now suits airplane travelers in jogging outfits and dentists in Birkenstocks. Tourists who once wore their Sunday best to visit big cities now dress as though they're headed for a Kiwanis barbecue -- all tube socks and fanny packs.</p>
        <p>On the designer level, the 80's found Lauren, Ellis, Armani and Klein solidifying their market positions with assured understatement. What the fashion copy called "easy elegance." Smooth, casual lines that don't change drastically from season to season, a quiet confidence that eschews haggling over hemlines and the color of the season. All their palettes were natural, muted, heavily anchored by navy, gray and black. They offered clothes that were safe but not snore-inducing. They were cut well and closer to the Edge. Designers were getting out more. Shopping. Spying. And having a little fun.</p>
        <p>Even the monk of Milan went to check out Madonna; Armani's nephew took him to a concert in Turin. Often Calvin Klein calls his daughter, Marci, a talent coordinator at "Saturday Night Live." "Honey, what's goin' on?" he needs to know. Retailers order buyers to stay out late and look at club kids. Kal Ruttenstein says that in his late 50's he would rather be home watering the roses on his terrace. But he is out almost every night getting to know disk jockey Johnny Dynell, transvestite diva RuPaul.</p>
        <p>"I want to see what Ru is wearing," Ruttenstein says. "I watch MTV constantly. I have to know what's going on everywhere. . . ." THE UNDERWEAR THING</p>
        <p>Calvin Klein is excited.</p>
        <p>"Wait'll you see, guys. You've gotta check this out."</p>
        <p>Klein is barefoot, in a stunning Italian summer-weight suit, a soft white T-shirt (Calvin, of course) underneath. As the design team for his women's Collection line waits around the conference table, the boss rummages through a shopping bag full of shoes: woven leather slip-ons, huarache-type weaves, plain slippers. He bought them all from street vendors in Rio last week, shopping with his wife, Kelly. And he has an idea.</p>
        <p>"So? Huh? What? Is it cool?"</p>
        <p>He's slipped on a pair of the woven shoes and there is no doubt, even if you ignore his beaming face -- almost goofy in its enthusiasm -- that the look is very cool. The fine double-breasted tailoring against the soft cotton T, the long, narrow street shoes, plainly made, but with an elegant tapered shape. He wants to make the shoes for next year. Summer, resort, whatever. Men, women.</p>
        <p>"Chic," says the Collection head, Susan Sokol. "Really chic."</p>
        <p>"They're not primitive," someone else ventures. "I think they're chic as hell."</p>
        <p>Klein grins. They're getting it. "We're thinking refined," he says. "We're tired of how tough and street everything looks. All those big boots. Every kid is wearing them."</p>
        <p>Never mind that as he says this Vogue's August cover is proclaiming this "The Year of the Boot," that his own fall collection is being shown with more clodhoppers than Dogpatch, with knee-high black leather combat boots for $325.</p>
        <p>Boom. He's over big feet. Time to move. And if Calvin says so, you bet his loyalists will. He will tell them, not in so many words, but in attitude, in clothes that just look right with the shoes, in carefully styled ads. It doesn't mean they'll have to kick those clunkers to the back of the closet; Calvin will simply give them options. He says he's never been about planned obsolesence. Take these fabric swatches he's been poring over for next spring. Some look almost antique, others stretchy and now, but none of them is wear-dated.</p>
        <p>"Amazing. Hell of a job. I'm stunned."</p>
        <p>He is congratulating his design team, many of whom have been wrangling with fabric houses for months to produce the tiny swatches taped and pinned to sketches: soft damasks and georgettes, silks and linens in gray, white, "souris" and bone. As he fingers a gorgeous damask, custom-made in an Italian mill, a sudden grimace passes across his face. "Oh God, I'm thinking about the economy," he says. But then he grins. "I mean, I could get really aggressive about this stuff, it's so beautiful."</p>
        <p>Klein says he's learning to rein himself in, on many fronts. He is out of the musks now and into the florals and woodsy tones of "more traditional values." After the 1991 restructuring of his business with the help of his best friend, David Geffen, who bought up $55 million in long-term debt notes, he says he learned "one hell of a lesson." He finds himself more introspective -- and receptive.</p>
        <p>"I listen to people and I watch people," he says. "What I love about fashion is that it's so tied into psychology and sociology."</p>
        <p>He says he's had the privilege of assisting in a quiet but profound revolution. "Women have really evolved about clothes," he says. "So have men, incidentally. It's about confidence. It's about asking for help and advice, having someone (close to you) say these things are for you or aren't -- regardless of what Bazaar says. No one really needs fashion. The point is, clothes are supposed to make you feel good. For not a lot of money you can find something that makes you feel sexy, sporty, sophisticated, hip."</p>
        <p>Of his ultrastylized ads, all that face slapping in the name of Obsession, those Bruce Weber-photographed friezes of naked boys and girls together, of those crotch-grabbing Marky Mark ads -- the ones that talk about safe sex -- he says: "People will say that I'll do something just to get attention. But that's not what I try to do. I try to take risks. Sometimes it's boring, sometimes you go too far. But at least it makes you think."</p>
        <p>Take this "underwear thing." Klein gulps some cold coffee and says that he and Kelly made it up together. Men's-inspired briefs and shirts for women. Underwear as loungewear for men. He says it gets you where you live.</p>
        <p>"It's sexy. It's fun. A man takes off his suit and shirt and he's just watching TV, reading. In all kinds of shorts. They're clothing. And they're not expensive."</p>
        <p>No, they're prole -- but designed. When Marlon Brando bellowed "Ayyyy, Stellaaaaa" and tossed a chunk of meat up to Kim Hunter, no one ran out and bought sleeveless undershirts. Now, when a former Boston gangbanger named Marky Mark snaps his waistband, consumers snap to.</p>
        <p>Ask Klein about those spots, or spawts, as this charming son of the Bronx calls them, and he says that while he hires the best photographers and talent, "It's all in my imagination. It's all me. And that's what people are paying for."</p>
        <p>Sure, he's learned plenty of lessons, sobered up in every way since the days of musk and Stoli. But there is an element of the 70's, the decade that so launched him, that remains his driving wheel.</p>
        <p>"I like to live in the moment. There were designers that were so rarefied in their ateliers. Come on. How could you be modern and know what's going on in the world unless you're out there?" LA GRANDE BOUFFE</p>
        <p>In January 1988, Giorgio Armani stood in a gale of air kisses and photo flashes, wondering if he had just made a business blunder. He was about to open one of his minimalist stores in Beverly Hills. At a party in his honor, le tout Hollywood embraced the man who had dressed Richard Gere in "American Gigolo" and Robert De Niro in "The Untouchables." That night, Armani was in their hearts and on their backs as the mighty tucked into a Spago-catered meal. Michael Eisner, Steven Spielberg, David Hockney, Martin Scorsese.</p>
        <p>It was the women who frightened the quiet tailor that night. So many of them were strapped and bustiered into those 80's excess outfits, clothes that screamed more about one's credit line than about good taste. It was the brief but splashy moment of Christian Lacroix's glorious immoderations, of bustles the size of beer kegs, killer crinolines. These clothes bellowed "FASHION!" Armani's whispered "style." Here was a man who made clothes as noiseless as the rustle of old bank notes. Would these people buy what he called his "nothing" elegance?</p>
        <p>"I always had certain ideas about Los Angeles," Armani recalled when we spoke shortly afterward. "And when I was at the party, I continued to be worried. Here I was, looking at these people, overdressed, with these big dresses. . . ."</p>
        <p>Big hair. Big junk bond portfolios. In the 80's, fashion, like finance, went to extremes. At one end were the platoons marching forth to the workplace in those ghastly women's power suits worn with faux bow ties and commuter Reeboks. It was the 70's men's-wear trend taken to numbing uniformity. Horrified, Vivienne Westwood parried with her "mini-crini's" -- short, feminine and fanciful. Lacroix unloosed les poufs -- fat, floaty confections that belled and bunched when madame tried to sit down to her blinis.</p>
        <p>The forces in many women's lives seemed to be duking it out on the runway and in the closet. Just who was she, the veep or the vamp? And what was "feminine"? If those boxy gray suits camouflaged the figure, 80's body-conscious fashion required a high tolerance for Soloflex reps. In the early 80's, Lagerfeld revived the mini; Norma Kamali did a "sweats" collection; Azzedine Alaia trussed fannies in tight leather and stretch fabrics; Thierry Mugler's hourglass shapes could be positively Valkyrian. Claude Montana shoulders were the envy of the N.F.L., his leathers masterworks of snug engineering. Gaultier burlesqued it all with his conical, nuclear warhead bra tops and his outside-in corsets, an inspiration from his childhood, he declared, watching his grandmother sip vinegar to shrink her stomach -- the better to lace up her corset.</p>
        <p>Fashion's dichotomy did reflect the growing gap in Reagan-era economic groups. Those who pouffed also had reservations at la grande bouffe, as restaurant madness seized the nation and the sun-dried tomato rose high over the land. But with the Subaru set, staying at home acquired its own media-certified cachet. Trendmeisters like Faith Popcorn announced that Americans were "cocooning," snuggling in with upscale takeout and a video. Food and shelter magazines boomed. Conran's and Ikea megastores sprouted along interstates. The aisles were crammed with determined life-stylers, paint chips clicking merrily in the pockets of their matching khakis from Lands' End. Or from Ralph Lauren.</p>
        <p>This is not to say there was no comfortable, witty middle ground. Perry Ellis had arrived by 1980 and, as the decade went on, refined his lively two-step of the classic and the quirky. Until his death in 1986, Ellis was the least conservative of the American consortium that solidified its base in the 80's -- Calvin Klein, Ralph Lauren and Donna Karan.</p>
        <p>Despite his worries, Armani continued to sell -- from Beverly Hills to Bangkok. The well-cut Armani jacket or suit became an anchor in power wardrobes for both sexes. Milan emerged as a greater force (Gianfranco Ferre, the Fendi sisters, Gianni Versace, Romeo Gigli). Japan was still well represented, with Miyake and with the dark, edgy silhouettes of Kawakubo's Comme des Garcons.</p>
        <p>Wherever a woman found herself in the 80's -- dancing at Nell's or prowling Home Depot -- at least she had options. She could wear jeans to the ball or browse produce in sequins without raising an eyebrow. Despite the sometimes cartoony aspects wrought by this freedom of choice, she had come a long way from Dior's unilateral imperatives. THE MAN WHO LOVED WOMEN</p>
        <p>What do women want now? Designers are asking Freud's hoary question -- and listening to the answers -- as never before. It's the most rudimentary form of market research. But applying it assiduously has helped create two of the last decade's biggest, most high-tech fashion successes.</p>
        <p>"I am very comfortable working in this age," Gianni Versace says. "The women today are so spectacular. They are modern, they work and they relate."</p>
        <p>He is sitting down to breakfast in his St. Regis suite at the outset of a short vacation. He says he takes quite a few these days -- most permissible for a man whose family-held business is doing about $800 million a year in men's and women's wear, with 130 stores worldwide.</p>
        <p>With robust appetite, he breaks the yolks on a pair of fried eggs. A fax machine beeps discreetly; on the desk in the living room, there is a sheaf of late-night sketches made for this fall's couture. Back in Milan, the men's-wear show is just weeks away. He says this is all light years from the way they did things in the Calabrian fitting rooms overseen by his dressmaker mother in the 50's and 60's. The phone trills and the designer picks up.</p>
        <p>"Bruce. Dahhhrling. How you make me suffer with these pictures. They are TOO BEAUTIFUL."</p>
        <p>The photographer Bruce Weber is calling for input on his latest campaign for Versace's fall men's wear. They had agreed on all but one point: the maestro would not make a kilt for the male models as Weber had requested.</p>
        <p>"Not me. No the skirt."</p>
        <p>You do not appropriate women's things, make jokes. Have rispetto. The media can say what they like, call some of his work vulgar, vampish. He says they only show his "crazy" things, the men's studmuffin leatherware, the "bondage" dresses with more straps than the harness on a Budweiser Clydesdale. Never mind that he also makes cashmere separates and suits quiet enough for the Princess of Wales.</p>
        <p>"Never mind. I know who I am, I promise you."</p>
        <p>He says he is a man who loves women. And, from Jane Fonda to Michelle Pfeiffer, they seem to embrace his visions of Woman. When he signed copies of his coffee-table book, "South Beach Stories," this spring at Bloomingdale's, a woman had herself wheeled up to him in a hospital bed.</p>
        <p>"Women!" he says. "I live my life in an atelier and there were 45 girls working all the time there. I can be the Truman Capote of the atelier."</p>
        <p>He laughs, remembering the seamstresses' love affairs, wayward husbands, fat, gorgeous babies. The working women talked to him. And the wealthy women trusted him; by the time he was 15, the clients were telling his mother, "Let Gianni choose the fabric."</p>
        <p>"The universe of women around me was so . . . so beautiful," he says. "Then, today, you relate with the women who are stronger than men. I try to understand what they want. When I'm in the fitting, I'm surrounded by five or six women. I never do a dress just by myself. I say, 'Will you wear that?' "</p>
        <p>He says that he still sees the old stereotypes sometimes, the designers who lose themselves too deeply in the world of women. "There are some designers who transfer their personality into women. Not me."</p>
        <p>It's not that simple anymore; her personality is too strong, too resistant. Instead, he says, he makes clothes for different tastes and needs, clothes for the contemporary Faces of Eve:</p>
        <p>"She's mother, she's lover, she's madonna, she's beetch. . . . "</p>
        <p>To all of them he listens. And should he ever forget how to listen to Woman?</p>
        <p>"She keek my behind." SEVEN EASY PIECES</p>
        <p>Before she can say hello over the speakerphone from her New York office, Donna Karan must issue some last-minute orders on this lingerie thing. O.K. No. HOLD THAT ONE! Oh, come on!</p>
        <p>"Since I've been designing," she begins, "it always has been for me. As a woman. I know that some designers, mostly men, have models who -- what do they call it? Their muse?"</p>
        <p>Right. Saint Laurent is now using the niece of his longtime inspiration, LouLou de la Falaise. Lagerfeld had Italian Vogue's Anna Piaggi. Donna Karan says she had a good relationship with her former employer, the late Anne Klein. But though they worked well together, she says they argued a lot. Klein designed for herself and Karan couldn't wear the stuff she herself was making. Armholes too small, pants didn't fit right. Comfort level not quite there for the working woman. When she started her own company in 1984, she knew what to do.</p>
        <p>"I was living that life," she says. "Not only was I designing it, I was wearing it."</p>
        <p>She is known best for her body-friendly wrap dressing, seven easy pieces to take you from the board room to catching Bobby at the Carlyle. Many of her own innovations -- the bodysuit beneath skirts and pants, the sophisticated but kind draping -- came out of black moments in front of her own mirror. Just moments before our talk, she is staring at prototypes, thinking:</p>
        <p>What is the ultimate bra for me?</p>
        <p>Karan is a big-boned woman, in good shape, but never skinny. Desiging for herself has its own set of imperatives. "It has a lot to do with body type," she says, laughing. "What I want to cover and what I don't!"</p>
        <p>Karan has now covered the market, with 14 companies, from children's wear to accessories, and men's wear, with price points "from caviar to pizza." When it was announced that her firm would go public, one industry analyst predicted, "This will be another Snapple." All of the companies, she says, came from her life.</p>
        <p>"I see myself as, No. 1, a mother," she says. "So this mother thinks about her children, what my daughter wants to wear. I think about what my son, my husband wants to wear. I basically have taken this mother role" -- she is laughing -- "and expanded it into a business!"</p>
        <p>They're buying it in a big way, the sons and daughters and moms and dads. And when she meets her constituency, as she does often in store appearances, she says she loves it, even relishes the haggling when she pushes little changes at them and they balk a bit. Always, they speak their minds:</p>
        <p>"Please, give us more of these, more colors."</p>
        <p>"Donna, please, accessories. With this -- WHAT?"</p>
        <p>"You expect me to wear that?" 'CAN I PUT My PANTS ON?'</p>
        <p>"Drop your pants, please. Just -- boom -- right there on the ground."</p>
        <p>Leslie Navajas stands knock-kneed on the photographer's no-seam, wondering if she has heard right. The model's pretty mouth has formed an inquiring "O" as she stares at Brana Wolf, a stylist hired to vamp the product of Club Monaco, an up-and-coming Canadian company that produces clothes at Gap prices -- with a lot more panache.</p>
        <p>"Trust me," Wolf says. "Let 'em go."</p>
        <p>Navajas drops the navy wool pants and stands there, unspeakably lovely, in just the suit jacket, handsome indeed in its new solitude. Photographer Mario Sorrenti goes to work. Standing by is Joe Mimran, Club Monaco president, nodding approval. He has come to New York with a small team -- just a designer and ad director. Apart from shoots like this, he says, everything -- design, press, packaging, store design -- is done in-house, in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Club Monaco is a young, lean, 90's fashion company. It's small enough to move quickly, independent enough to cut its "basics" on the edgy side for that sizable clientele ready to move on past the turtleneck-and-pocket-T mode. Begun in 1985, Club Monaco has 60 stores in Canada, six in Japan and four in California. Philosophy: "approachable design." Volume: $55 million.</p>
        <p>As with most fashion shoots, this one is a team effort. But ad director Christine Ralphs says she relies especially heavily on the eye and input of two people: Lloyd Douglas, the art director, and Wolf, who suggested the photographer, the pieces to highlight, the accessories. A good stylist is plugged in, can give you a Look and deep Rolodex -- the best makeup, hair, antique car rental. She knows which model wilts fastest, which is allergic to dogs.</p>
        <p>Wolf, an Australian who lived and worked in Europe before she came to New York, is wearing the usual stylist gear: black pants; big white shirt stuck with straight and safety pins; rubber bands around her wrists; cigarettes in her pocket; worn, scuffed leather sneaks. No makeup, hair pulled back, all business.</p>
        <p>As a fashion stylist, Wolf is part of a growing corps of style interpreters -- people who can translate a look, evoke a feeling with the turn of a cuff, a maribou mule, an empty McDonald's wrapper tossed beside a couture redingote. A contributing editor to Vogue, she has a client list that takes in editorial and advertising -- at many price levels. She's worked with the film director David Lynch to style Armani's TV ad for his fragrance, Gio, and has styled for Valentino, Dolce &amp; Gabbana, Perry Ellis, Gianfranco Ferre, Hermes, as well as for Esprit and the Gap. Jobs are so different, she says, "even my own mother doesn't know what I do."</p>
        <p>Unlike some top stylists who stick with couture or expensive ready-to-wear, she says she's best known for her rescue operations at the lower level. "I don't think I'm a trend-setter as much as" -- she laughs -- "as a fixer-upper of things."</p>
        <p>The clothes for this shoot are nice enough -- no limping bunnies here. But the budget and the minimalism constitute a challenge. "This is very market researched," Wolf says of the Club Monaco line. "The customer is 18 to 35, style conscious, a little bit more so than someone who'd go to the Gap."</p>
        <p>They have decided to keep it simple, she says -- a sign of the times. The pieces are pared down; the feeling needs to be the same. "All of this," she says, "is still a reaction to the 80's when everything was so overdone, so overaccessorized."</p>
        <p>From the kitchen area, Navajas calls out, a tad plaintively: "Uh, Brana? Can I put these pants on now?"</p>
        <p>Wolf is scrutinizing the rack for the next idea. "It's about choices," she says of her work. "If you can just choose the right things and put them together properly, then you can help the woman out there who can't afford one look or isn't interested in those top lines. It's spreading the style down the line -- and teaching people how to do it."</p>
        <p>Navajas is asked to don a long, straight jersey dress. She comes out with suede clogs on beneath it and Wolf shakes her head. The stylist ducks behind the pipe rack and comes up with a huge pair of basketball shoes. Grinning, Navajas slips them on, unlaced like the downest homeboy's, and clomps back to her place before the lens.</p>
        <p>"Yeaaah, we got it." Sorrenti is clicking. The clients say they love the look. And here is the message: Minimal is maxi. But darling -- have fun.</p>
        <p>'YOU DON'T SUFFER FOR DRESSES'</p>
        <p>"Want a hot dog?"</p>
        <p>Four floors above the rue Cambon, Karl Lagerfeld holds up a fat, flesh-colored saucisson, plucked from a plate of what look like Nathan's finest. He plunges it into a mound of mustard and makes short work of it, with a Diet Coke chaser. Urbane, saturnine in his trademark baggy black suit and dark glasses, he's chatting like a multilingual magpie from behind his huge desk. It's 7:30 P.M. and he's just begun supervising fittings for 25 suits, dresses and evening gowns -- part of the Chanel winter collection -- due to be shown in just a month's time.</p>
        <p>Lagerfeld is easily the busiest designer on the planet with his own KL line, Chanel's couture and ready-to-wear and his fur designs for the Fendi sisters. And two collections for Chloe. "This work allows no time to be civilized, you know?" Lagerfeld says, reaching for another hot dog. "This must be dinner. Eat. We will be here all night."</p>
        <p>As a bare-torsoed model is fitted for a bra top to go with her floaty evening skirt, the couturier is discussing "Achy Breaky Heart." That country hit was made popular by one Billy Ray Cyrus, a smug, mall-cut galoot now given to wearing $1,500 Versace shirts with his blue jeans. The song has been recommended, a bit behind the curve, by a good friend and couture client sitting atLagerfeld's right hand. Tonight she is dressed, toe to earlobe, in sea-green Chanel.</p>
        <p>"Oh, Karl, 'Achy Breaky's' kinda cute," says Susan Gutfreund, the high-profile wife of the deposed Salomon Brothers chief, John Gutfreund.</p>
        <p>"It is," Lagerfeld snaps, "a HORRIBLE thing. Surely you know this."</p>
        <p>He turns to his left and asks me, smiling: "You were expecting maybe Mozart up here? Mahler?"</p>
        <p>Not at all. Guns 'n' Roses, maybe, from the looks of things. Tattoos have invaded the atelier -- a bold heart on the bicep of the black-clad assistant rushing about with fabric bolts. Those four-figure biker boots clunk beneath the models' half-finished velveteen gowns. Like the other dark princes of fashion -- Mugler, Gaultier, Versace -- Lagerfeld has not been loath to loose scurrying bits of gutter chic on Chanel's exalted runways. He admits to being a bit perverse -- and egotistical. But to call him aristocratic is to invite a burning Nosferatu gaze through those oversized smoked lenses. He insists he's a tradesman.</p>
        <p>When, at age 16, he informed his wealthy mother of his career choice, she said, "You are not snobbish, my son."</p>
        <p>The signature ponytail shakes. "Some designers tell you how much they suffer, and then you have every six months the same dress. Please, no! This bull -- we've heard before. I don't have to give you names, you know what I'm talking about. But no, no, no, no. You don't suffer for dresses!"</p>
        <p>While Saint Laurent has periodic nervous breakdowns and rereads Proust obsessively, Lagerfeld will settle in with an Italian design magazine, a Sotheby's catalogue and plan a dinner party. This is a designer who does jokes -- albeit pricey ones. Velvet Mickey Mouse ears on the runway; precious purses in the shape of baguettes; hundred-dollar Chanel T-shirts. By having a hoot, he made the moribund relics of Mademoiselle's House hip again.</p>
        <p>"For me, the atelier is not a temple," he says, as he polishes off another hot dog. "It is my playroom."</p>
        <p>A model pirouettes in a muslin taille that will soon be a ball gown. It has been penciled in for black velveteen. The fabric bolt is rolled out against her hip but Lagerfeld is frowning.</p>
        <p>"Nah, NEIN, pas le noir, all WRONG," snorts the couturier.</p>
        <p>"Tweed!" he yells, and a bolt of tweedy wool gauze, light and soft as a cobweb, is wrapped around the muslin.</p>
        <p>"Sexy, extremely sexy, the tweed on bare skin," he says in French. "We do it."</p>
        <p>"Oh, ravissante, Karl," Gutfreund is murmuring. "Just ravissante."</p>
        <p>Lagerfeld does not seem to hear her. "The most important thing is to give the mood of the moment," he is saying. "It's part of the expression of our times. Chanel, from the beginning, took ideas from the street and put it on the runway and made it fashionable. But Chanel was fated to outlive her revolution and grew cliched in the end.</p>
        <p>"Designers are only as good as the next collection," he continues. "You can have the biggest name in the world, but nobody will wait for you. Classic? What is classic? Forget it."$  Gerri Hirshey writes a column about popular culture for GQ.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gerri Hirshey writes a column about popular culture for GQ.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
