<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Victims in Mass Deaths Linked to Magical Sects</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUICIDES AND SUICIDE ATTEMPTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGIOUS CULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SWITZERLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORDER OF THE SOLAR TEMPLE (RELIGIOUS SECT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOURET, LUC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEBUHR, GUSTAV</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E7D9123DF935A35753C1A962958260" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Victims in Mass Deaths Linked to Magical Sects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEBUHR, GUSTAV</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 50 people who died in simultaneous suicides or killings in Switzerland and Canada yesterday appeared to have been members of an occult, ritualistic organization led by Luc Jouret, a dark-haired, charismatic Belgian remembered in Europe for lectures that combined spiritual ideas with warnings about coming environmental catastrophes.</p>
        <p>The Swiss police said they did not know whether Mr. Jouret, 46, was among the total of 48 people found dead in two places in Switzerland -- a burned farmhouse in the village of Cheiry, northeast of Geneva, and at three chalets in a ski area at Granges-sur-Salvan, near the Italian border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 50 people who died in simultaneous suicides or killings in Switzerland and Canada yesterday appeared to have been members of an occult, ritualistic organization led by Luc Jouret, a dark-haired, charismatic Belgian remembered in Europe for lectures that combined spiritual ideas with warnings about coming environmental catastrophes.</p>
        <p>The Swiss police said they did not know whether Mr. Jouret, 46, was among the total of 48 people found dead in two places in Switzerland -- a burned farmhouse in the village of Cheiry, northeast of Geneva, and at three chalets in a ski area at Granges-sur-Salvan, near the Italian border.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jouret was also said to be the founder of the Order of the Solar Temple, outside Montreal, and was believed to have fled to Switzerland a year ago after having been charged in Canada with weapons possession and conspiracy.</p>
        <p>Little is known about Mr. Jouret, but according to cult-watchers, he has been lecturing in Europe and Switzerland for several years on spiritual themes. According to Jean-Francois Maier, a well-known Swiss authority on small sects, Mr. Jouret had lectured about several subjects.</p>
        <p>"He created an atmosphere of an impending catastrophe around him," Mr. Maier told Swiss television, Reuters reported. "He spoke of the death of forests, galloping pollution and a loss of values."</p>
        <p>According to the Canadian Press news agency, Mr. Jouret received a medical degree in 1974 from the Free University of Brussels and studied acupuncture in Belgium and homeopathic medicine in Mexico and Argentina.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jouret was also reported by the Canadian Press to have worked as a surgeon and general practitioner in obstetrics in Europe, Africa and Asia, but the agency said that Quebec Corps of Physicians did not recognize him as a doctor.</p>
        <p>Several of the dead in Switzerland were found in an underground, mirror-lined chapel. They were dressed in ceremonial robes of red, black, gold or beige, and their bodies were near an altar. Nearby were a rose, a cross and a picture of Mr. Jouret.</p>
        <p>An authority on cults said that some of the evidence connected to the deaths, including the fact that some of the victims were wearing robes, suggested that their belief systems placed them within those modern groups that secretly practice ceremonial magic in an effort gain personal power.</p>
        <p>"The mystery religions, the secret societies were the norm, rather than the exception in the ancient pagan world," said Carl Raschke, a professor of religious studies at the University of Denver. "So what we're dealing with is the persistence of ancient pagan magic into the present day."</p>
        <p>Both the Order of the Solar Temple and the Cross and the Rose, a group in Switzerland associated with Mr. Jouret "were two branch names with the same trunk," Johannes Aagaard, head of a Danish cult-monitoring group, told The Associated Press. He said he believed Mr. Jouret was behind both organizations and had founded several occult groups in Canada and Europe.</p>
        <p>In interviews, people who track new religious sects in the United States, Canada and Europe said they had little knowledge of either the Canadian or the Swiss groups.</p>
        <p>The Canadian group, the Order of the Solar Temple, came to public attention in that country in March 1993, when two men with ties to it were arrested and charged with plotting to buy three silencer-equipped firearms, according to news reports at the time. They were later sentenced to six months' probation after pleading guilty.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, police in Canada were investigating whether a fire that burned a house in Morin Heights, Quebec, killing two people, was linked with the Swiss deaths. The house was adjacent to one owned by Mr. Jouret.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jouret's organizations were apparently small, according to estimates in Canada and Europe.</p>
        <p>Eighteen months ago, a member of the Order of the Solar Temple told a Canadian reporter that the organization had between 70 and 80 members in Quebec. Yesterday, Reuters, citing European researchers, said Mr. Jouret had attracted between 150 and 200 followers in Switzerland by the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>It was not clear whether Mr. Jouret's sects had any connection to the several groups that go under the name of Rosicrucians.</p>
        <p>Dr. Raschke said the intellectual tradition behind occult groups like Mr. Jouret's can be traced to the Aleister Crowley, an early 20th century English writer, magician and founder of secret societies, most notably the Ordo Templi Orientis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
