<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rare Butterfly Consigned to Extinction</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940427T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="683303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUTTERFLIES AND MOTHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLECTORS AND COLLECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLORADO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Butterflies and Moths</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DB1F31F935A15757C0A962958260" item-length="1728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rare Butterfly Consigned to Extinction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS say the country's most recently discovered species of butterfly is about to become extinct. But rather than taking what they call "heroic measures" to save it, they are advocating a more hands-off policy that they predict will soon have biologists counting one less species among North America's butterflies.</p>
        <p>Like concerned family members gathered around a loved one's death bed, the biologists who studied this small alpine insect, the Uncompahgre fritillary butterfly, have begun the mourning process, already sadly shaking their heads. They say there is no clear way to save the butterfly, so rather than spending precious conservation dollars to try to resuscitate the species, they suggest letting it go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS say the country's most recently discovered species of butterfly is about to become extinct. But rather than taking what they call "heroic measures" to save it, they are advocating a more hands-off policy that they predict will soon have biologists counting one less species among North America's butterflies.</p>
        <p>Like concerned family members gathered around a loved one's death bed, the biologists who studied this small alpine insect, the Uncompahgre fritillary butterfly, have begun the mourning process, already sadly shaking their heads. They say there is no clear way to save the butterfly, so rather than spending precious conservation dollars to try to resuscitate the species, they suggest letting it go.</p>
        <p>"This is probably a fairly heretical stance to some people," said Dr. Hugh Britten, a conservation biologist at the Nevada Biodiversity Research Center in Reno who is an author of a paper about the species. "It's not very easy for me to say I am presiding over the extinction of this species. But in the world of science, so what? Your personal feelings are not relevant and they shouldn't be."</p>
        <p>While Dr. Britten and his co-authors, Dr. Peter Brussard, president of the Society for Conservation Biology, and Dr. Dennis Murphy, a conservation biologist at Stanford University, recommend continued monitoring and guarding of the survivors, their ominously titled study, "The Pending Extinction of the Uncompahgre Fritillary Butterfly," makes clear their vision of the future.</p>
        <p>"Remember that the whole funding for endangered species is one pie," Dr. Britten said. "We're saying there's not much we can do that's sure to work and we ought to leave those funds in there to be applied somewhere else where they can work."</p>
        <p>Among conservationists, the recommendation on this butterfly, which measures barely an inch across its wings, has already elicited everything from hearty approval to anger. Some say the researchers are making exactly the kind of hard decision they need to make and have been promising to make, forgoing expensive last-ditch efforts to conserve doomed single species.</p>
        <p>"I think they're right on target with no heroic measures," said Dr. Paul R. Ehrlich, the Bing Professor of Population Studies and president of the Center for Conservation Biology at Stanford. "I can't get excited about captive breeding of an alpine arctic ecosystem species that may go extinct on its own. It'd be much better to work much harder to save the species of the Northwest -- to save whole huge habitats."</p>
        <p>But others warn that the recommendation may be typical of many examples to come in which biologists subscribe to a triage mentality, too quickly writing off one species in favor of others in the name of economic prudence.</p>
        <p>"Personally, I find the triage idea ethically repugnant," said Dr. Reed Noss, editor of Conservation Biology, the journal in which the butterfly report was published. "We too readily assign species to the category of hopeless. It's too easy for political reasons to say we can't do anything about that species, that it would put too much of a burden on our economy. I probably wouldn't have concluded the same thing."</p>
        <p>Dr. Jeffrey Glassberg, president of the North American Butterfly Association, which has its headquarters in Morristown, N.J., suggested that the constraints of the triage mentality may in some ways be self-imposed. "I think these are self-fulfilling prophecies: 'I have limited resources and we're not going to do anything.' I don't know that I'd want to give up so easily." Always a Rare Sight</p>
        <p>Named after the site in the San Juan Mountains of Colorado where the species was discovered in 1978, the Uncompahgre (pronounced un-kum-PAH-gray) fritillary -- an unremarkable-looking black and brown mottled butterfly -- has always been rare, often numbering in the hundreds at each of its two known locations. But more recently, the species, seemed in precipitous decline, virtually disappearing from Uncompahgre Peak and declining at its other known site, Red Cloud Peak.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging that the exact reasons for the populations' year-to-year ups and downs remain mysterious, the researchers blame the general decline of the species on grazing that once was allowed in the butterfly's alpine meadows, on overzealous collecting by those anxious to have this newest and very rare species, and -- most important -- on a warming climate.</p>
        <p>Thought to be a relictual arctic species left behind on Colorado's mountaintops when the last glaciers retreated some 10,000 years ago, the species, Boloria acrocnema, has been trapped in what these scientists say has been more than a decade of uncomfortably warming weather.</p>
        <p>"As far as management implications go, there's essentially nothing we can do about it," said Dr. Britten, who is a member of a team appointed by the Government to write a recovery plan for this endangered species. "When you turn the heat up, it causes problems and the butterfly has to move upslope, and there is no more upslope. It's being ecologically squeezed off the top."</p>
        <p>All the experts seem to agree that if the species is naturally doomed, then the only responsible action is to let it go and allocate limited resources elsewhere. The problem comes in deciding when to say when.</p>
        <p>Many expressed concern that the researchers may have been a bit too hasty in tolling the death knell for this species. Knowing the butterfly is indeed doomed, they say, is not as simple as it might appear to be. Researchers point out that just last month in Southern California, the Palos Verdes blue butterfly, long presumed extinct, turned up very much alive.</p>
        <p>Amy Seidl, a graduate student at Colorado State University who is the only researcher now studying the Uncompahgre fritillary, said her recent work indicated that the situation was not as dismal as the researchers suggested. Since the downward trend observed until 1991, Ms. Seidl said she had witnessed a stabilization and even an increase in the butterfly's numbers.</p>
        <p>The butterfly's population numbered nearly 2,000 last year at Uncompahgre Peak, according to Ms. Seidl's study, up from estimates of roughly zero in 1990 and 1991. She also estimated a population of 1,300 at Red Cloud Peak, up from 400 in 1990 and 400 to 1,000 in 1991. These are considerable increases for a butterfly thought to be on its way out.</p>
        <p>Given the butterfly's apparent comeback, some researchers suggested that attempts at the heroic measures of captive breeding and introduction to additional mountain meadows were in order.</p>
        <p>"Nobody can see into the future that far," Dr. Larry Gall, a curatorial affiliate at the Peabody Museum at Yale University, said of the predictions of pending extinction. "I think it would be useful for them to attempt an introduction."</p>
        <p>Dr. Gall and Dr. Felix Sperling of the University of Ottawa discovered the Uncompahgre fritillary, the only new butterfly species found in the United States in the last three decades.</p>
        <p>Dr. Britten and his colleagues, however, said they were not hopeful about captive breeding or introductions of wild butterflies to new areas, citing poor success rates in the past.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gall responded: "Sometimes it's awful but sometimes it's good. It's not unreasonable to try."  Annual Cost Put at $5,000</p>
        <p>Despite arguments against the costliness of such ventures, Terry Ireland, a Fish and Wildlife Department biologist who is a member of the butterfly recovery team, said that for this species, even the most heroic of measures -- captive breeding -- is estimated to cost no more than $5,000 a year. According to a Fish and Wildlife Survey, in 1991 Federal and state agencies spent an estimated $177 million on the recovery of federally listed endangered species alone.</p>
        <p>But so far, the recovery plan closely follows the hands-off recommendations of the researchers, a proposal of simple monitoring of the population, modest attempts to search for new populations and studies to learn more about the biology of the insect.</p>
        <p>Even if funds were available and researchers willing, heroic measures can have their risks. Dr. Britten, well aware of Ms. Seidl's findings of increased numbers, remains wary of disrupting the butterflies with removals for breeding or introduction elsewhere. He cautioned that insect populations often fluctuate greatly, with apparently healthy populations quickly dropping back to low numbers for no apparent reason. The problem is that when butterfly numbers drop down now and again, bad weather or other harsh conditions can keep the vulnerable populations from bouncing back.</p>
        <p>While the more pessimistic researchers argue that such fluctuations make it easy for the Uncompahgre fritillary to be permanently knocked out, others counter that it also makes it more difficult to predict extinction.</p>
        <p>Adding more uncertainty to the status of the butterfly is the specter of yet undiscovered colonies. Ms. Seidl is optimistic that there are still unknown populations of the butterfly. As part of her continuing study, she plans to scale the wet, northeast slopes of the San Juans, the sort the butterfly would most likely favor. Limited Sighting Period</p>
        <p>Even Dr. Britten, who has made numerous searches, admits it is impossible to be sure whether or not there are hidden colonies in the wilderness of the San Juans. It is particularly difficult because the butterflies are visible and in flight for only about three weeks a year, in July.</p>
        <p>"All this means we can't be very confident that we've looked everywhere at the right times," he said. "There have been reports of additional colonies by one other lepidopterist, who is refusing to reveal where they are. You get reports like that and you think, maybe this person's right."</p>
        <p>Amid the difficulty of assessing the health status of an endangered species, conservationists continue to struggle with making what may be life-or-death decisions for the animals and plants they study.</p>
        <p>Ann Swengel, international co-editor for the annual July 4 butterfly count run by the Xerces Society and the North American Butterfly Association, said: "When is it O.K. not to try to save a species? I think conservationists are groping with this now.</p>
        <p>"In the end, it's an opinion, a judgment call just like everything in conservation. You never know what would have happened if you'd done something else."</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 27, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Science Times yesterday about Amy Seidl, who studies a rare butterfly species, referred incorrectly in some copies to the university where she is a graduate student. It is Colorado State, not the University of Colorado.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 27, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Science Times yesterday about Amy Seidl, who studies a rare butterfly species, referred incorrectly in some copies to the university where she is a graduate student. It is Colorado State, not the University of Colorado.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
