<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Issues of Race and Pollution Trouble L.I. Town</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="724897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH-SPEAKING GROUPS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW CASSEL (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NASSAU COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK PUBLIC INTEREST RESEARCH GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service"></person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKS, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D91631F931A25752C1A962958260" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Issues of Race and Pollution Trouble L.I. Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKS, PETER;</byline>
      <dateline>NEW CASSEL, L.I.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, residents of this predominantly black and Hispanic working-class community have held their noses, shut their windows and tried hard not to dwell on the smells and the unsightliness of the 170-acre industrial site just across the railroad tracks.</p>
        <p>The putrid odors from the chemical plants and garbage-transfer stations and fish processing factories make some people sick. But they are so taken for granted in New Cassel, directly downwind of the plants, that few residents lodge complaints. In fact, Nassau County health officials say, a vast majority of complaints have come from wealthier, primarily white communities upwind of the plants like Salisbury and South Westbury, where the smells are not nearly so intense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, residents of this predominantly black and Hispanic working-class community have held their noses, shut their windows and tried hard not to dwell on the smells and the unsightliness of the 170-acre industrial site just across the railroad tracks.</p>
        <p>The putrid odors from the chemical plants and garbage-transfer stations and fish processing factories make some people sick. But they are so taken for granted in New Cassel, directly downwind of the plants, that few residents lodge complaints. In fact, Nassau County health officials say, a vast majority of complaints have come from wealthier, primarily white communities upwind of the plants like Salisbury and South Westbury, where the smells are not nearly so intense.</p>
        <p>But now, the people of New Cassel are suddenly transfixed by the sources of the odors. A recent report by a public-interest research group detailed several environmental hazards, from air pollution to toxic waste to groundwater contamination, in the industrial area, and revealed what many residents say they had not known: Since 1988 their suburb's industrial zone has been on the state's Superfund list, awaiting cleanup.</p>
        <p>John Addison, president of a New Cassell citizens group, the Progressive Civic Association, said the information in the report, gleaned from the state's own documents, stunned him. "I was awestruck by the literature," he said. "We never as a community acknowledged with any understanding how serious the issue could be. We've been in the dark for years."</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the New York Public Interest Research Group, criticized state environmental officials for failing to inform residents of the potential hazards at their doorsteps and for not taking quick action against the polluters. This has angered the community's civic leaders, who think that the slowness of the cleanup reflects New Cassel's second-class status in a predominantly white, suburban county. But the report has also inspired introspection among the community's leaders, who have begun to wonder if the apathy of New Cassel's residents also contributed to the state's slow response.</p>
        <p>"I have to say, I feel that it's because we're African-Americans here," Mildred Little said, explaining why she thinks there has been no cleanup. But Ms. Little, who has lived in New Cassel since 1957 and serves on the Town of North Hempstead's zoning board, also said it is difficult to get residents to protest, because many feel so disenfranchised. "A lot of people do not speak up," she said.</p>
        <p>A growing number of minority groups across the country have been arguing that when it comes to living in areas contaminated with industrial pollution, black, Hispanic and American Indian communities bear a disproportionate share of the burden. Last year, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency reported that higher percentages of blacks and Hispanics than whites lived in areas polluted by dust, soot, carbon monoxide, ozone and emissions from hazardous waste dumps.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups say some studies have shown hazardous waste sites in white and wealthier communities are attended to more quickly by the Government than those in minority and poorer communities. Patricia Williams, counsel on solid and hazardous wastes for the National Wildlife Federation, said low-income and minority communities lack the political and economic influence to get swift action.</p>
        <p>"You have poor communities that are not necessarily focused upon," Ms. Williams said. "They aren't the fund raisers, they aren't the people with the PAC's. They're not on the front lines of attention."</p>
        <p>State environmental officials deny that they have dragged their feet on the New Cassel site. Although the state first designated it as a Class 2 hazardous waste site -- meaning that it presented a "significant threat to the public health and environment" -- in 1988, officials say the complexity of finding the source of the contamination has prolonged the investigation of the New Cassel industrial area, one of 570 Class 2 sites in the state.</p>
        <p>Chemicals found underground at the site have been identified as trichloroethane and tetrachloroethane, degreasers used by many of the dozens of companies in the industrial zone. The problem, officials say, is trying to determine which of the 129 properties in the zone is the source.</p>
        <p>"This is not a typical site where you have one industry and one owner," said Michael O'Toole, director of the Division of Hazardous Waste Remediation for the State Department of Environmental Conservation. "Under the state's Superfund law, we can't use Superfund money unless we make efforts to identify the responsible parties."</p>
        <p>Last year, the department hired an environmental consultant to determine the origins of the underground concentrations of pollution. A draft report identifying several of the concentrations is to be submitted by the consultant this month and released to the public in December, Mr. O'Toole said.</p>
        <p>So far, the state has spent $250,000 on the New Cassel investigation, he added.</p>
        <p>But what troubles residents like Mr. Addison, a mortgage banker who was raised in New Cassel and moved back here with his family a decade ago, is that until the report by the New York Public Interest Research Group, he knew nothing about the extent of the problem. He is not sure who is at fault: the state for not doing a better job of spreading the news, or the community, for not doing a better job of looking after itself.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Addison said, New Cassel is at a severe disadvantage in trying to protect its interests. According to the 1990 Census, the per-capita income in the hamlet, where 66 percent of the 10,200 residents are black and 20 percent are Hispanic, is $12,918. That is about half the Nassau County average and about one-third less than the state average.</p>
        <p>The economic and social pressures of daily life in New Cassel leave its residents little time to consider the long-terms health effects of what might be produced in the industrial area, Mr. Addison said: "We've always been the community that is last to know. It's almost like being punched in the arm too much. You come to accept the pain."</p>
        <p>Ludovic Blain, who prepared the 54-page report for the New York research group, said New Cassel's experience fits a pattern for several minority communities around the state that are near industrial and hazardous waste sites, including Wyandanch on the Island and a black neighborhood in Albany. Whether the phenomenon -- and the Government's response to it -- is evidence of racism or lack of influence is a matter of conjecture, he said.</p>
        <p>"It's difficult to prove," Mr. Blain said. "But just like when a car hits you, the intent is secondary as far as you are concerned. The issue here is whether these communities can control the character of their neighborhood, and get the resources to make that happen."</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, meetings organized by Ms. Little and the public interest group in New Cassel's community center have drawn dozens of residents as well as the area's representatives in Albany. What residents would like, Ms. Little said, is for the state to hire a local ombudsman, someone from the community who could insure that residents are apprised of what is happening in the industrial area, and keep the pressure on environmental officials to pursue the cleanup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Addison said he was skeptical that the state's indifference to New Cassel would change. The only time he ever sees politicians, he said, is before Election Day. "The political atmosphere is, 'Here in September, gone in November,' " he said with a sigh.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
