<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mother Nature Never Intended This; Pollution and Not Enough Care Afflict City's Street Trees</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="690617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARKS AND RECREATION DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D9123BF933A05756C0A962958260" item-length="1437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mother Nature Never Intended This; Pollution and Not Enough Care Afflict City's Street Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS MARTIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a rectilinear and pushy city, New York's street trees offer a green canopy of healing and hope. But many are dying, others will die sooner than they should, and all are in a state of grim siege.</p>
        <p>The trees, a city responsibility, are simply not being taken care of. Maintenance has been reduced mainly to removing dead trees, a process itself running more than five years behind schedule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a rectilinear and pushy city, New York's street trees offer a green canopy of healing and hope. But many are dying, others will die sooner than they should, and all are in a state of grim siege.</p>
        <p>The trees, a city responsibility, are simply not being taken care of. Maintenance has been reduced mainly to removing dead trees, a process itself running more than five years behind schedule.</p>
        <p>"We are an ambulance service that can't keep up with the dead bodies," said Keith Kriet, Director of Forestry for the Parks Department, the agency in charge of New York's trees. Tree Population Decline</p>
        <p>Bad or nonexistent care comes on top of insults Mother Nature never intended for any tree. Soil in tree pits is often compacted, rooting spaces are tight and water is sporadic, while pollution, vandalism, dog urine and a whole battery of urban affronts are the order of the day. Trees are banged by cars and buses, doused with water laden with chemical cleansers, festooned with hot lights.</p>
        <p>"Trees get beat up in New York City," said Larry Elman, special projects director for the Green Guerillas, a community environmental group that plants trees. "Together, these trees are worth hundreds of millions of dollars and the level of care is abysmal."</p>
        <p>They are worth more than dollars. Dennis M. Walcott, president of the New York Urban League, said his organization's effort to bring to a life the dreary block it deems the worst in Harlem, at 140th Street between Adam Clayton Powell Jr. Boulevard and Frederick Douglass Boulevard, began with persuading the city to plant trees. "Trees give a sense of calmness," he said. "They are the first step in the block's rebirth."</p>
        <p>Exact numbers have not been kept, but since the mid-1980's, Mr. Kriet calculates the city's street tree population has declined from around 700,000 to 500,000. In recent years, he says, some 15,000 to 20,000 trees die each year, while perhaps 9,000 are planted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kriet said Norway maples, the most prevalent of more than 50 street species, face a major decline over the next decade because of leaf wilt and other stresses. Callery pear trees, a very popular species in recent years, are having problems with weakness in their branches because of inadequate pruning as saplings. London plane trees, the most popular tree in Brooklyn, are fighting a battle with a fungal disease called anthracnose.</p>
        <p>The prognosis is that the young and the old are most at risk. From Manhattan, where nearly half of the newly planted trees die in the first five years, to Queens, where as many as 30,000 towering maples are in imminent danger of toppling in a storm, Mr. Kriet projects a possible loss of a fifth or more of the city's trees in the next decade, mainly older ones.</p>
        <p>The shakiest of the big trees are in Queens, home of nearly half of the city's trees, and a source of mounting worries about potential city liabilities. "If the tree hasn't fallen on someone's car or a garage, they don't consider it an emergency anymore," said Sally Martino-Fisher, district manager of Community Board 13.  Affected by the Cold</p>
        <p>A bad storm could almost instantly topple as many as 3,000 trees, Mr. Kreit said, adding that unexpected bad weather is always a threat to such a frail population. He calculates that some 2,000 of Manhattan's 37,500 street trees surely died as the result of root damage from last winter's cold, and that the health of an additional 4,500 is highly questionable.</p>
        <p>Henry Stern, the Parks Commissioner, characterizes the trees' plight as "the silent death," saying the depths of the crisis will not be fully apparent until today's failing trees actually die, a decline he and others fear could be precipitous.</p>
        <p>"Urban forestry management is subtle," said Joseph Bernardo, director of urban forestry for Trees New York, a tree advocacy group, after being laid off after three years as a city forester. "You really don't notice the blight until the trees fall." A National Trend</p>
        <p>The city Health Department first proposed planting street trees in the 1880's to help cool the city in the summer, something it thought would reduce epidemics. In 1902, state legislation made the Parks Department responsible for planting street trees.</p>
        <p>The decline of New York's trees is part of a national trend. Gary Moll, vice president of urban forestry of American Forests, a Washington-based lobbying group, said surveys indicated more trees die than are planted in most of the nation's 20 largest cities, 70 percent of which have cut back money for tree maintenance programs.</p>
        <p>"But the larger the city, the bigger the problem," he said. "New York seems to be the worst."</p>
        <p>Indeed, a report being prepared by the Environmental Action Coalition, an advocacy group, shows the New York City budget allocating just 82 cents for each New Yorker to trees, compared with $4.06 per resident in Chicago, $11.34 in St. Louis, $15.65 in Minneapolis and $15 in Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>"New York's budgeteers regard trees as the lowest of the low," said Nancy Wolf, who with Erik Wohlgemuth, is writing the report. "Trees aren't important, period."</p>
        <p>A 23 percent cut in Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's budget proposal for tree planting and maintenance to $4 million would tend to confirm her point, following as it does a steady decline from $13.1 million in 1986.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kreit said professional forestry standards would call for a budget of $25 million just for maintenance, compared with $2.6 million in the Mayor's proposal. Mr. Stern said that to redress the damage and to plant sufficent trees to reverse the downward population trend, as much as $50 million should be spent annually.</p>
        <p>To illustrate the effect of the cuts, Mr. Stern points to the long gnawing away at the agency's pruning staff, who are the key to establishing healthy patterns in a tree's growth, particularly early on. Three decades ago, the department employed 237 pruners, compared with 125 in the mid-1980's and 61 now. Finding New Ammunition</p>
        <p>But so far the commissioner has not been able to win the argument. He has argued that trees are a civilizing influence in a city sorely needing such, that they boost real-estate values and that they are simply pretty. Famous for his almost Druidic devotion to things arboreal, Mr. Stern is not above resorting to empathy.</p>
        <p>"Trees can't speak," he said. "They just rustle."</p>
        <p>Though almost nobody comes out against trees, both Mr. Stern and Mr. Kriet suggest there is less of a natural constituency for them here than in cities where private homeowners predominate. In New York, some two-thirds of households are renters.</p>
        <p>Another potential problem is that the decades of neglect have left trees in such a state of disrepair that people will begin to think of them as nuisances. "If branches are falling on cars, people start losing enthusiasm for trees," said Dorothy Morehead, president of the Sunnyside Foundation for Community Planning and Preservation, a group that has been active in tree planting and preservation in its Queens neighborhood.</p>
        <p>But tree advocates have new ammunition, evidence that trees save quantifiable amounts of money by reducing air pollution by removing carbon from the air and cooling streets enough with their shade to cut down on air conditioning. A recent study of 95,000 trees in Chicago conducted by United States Forest Service researchers suggested that together the trees would save $38 million over 30 years.</p>
        <p>Particularly with Federal air pollution attainment deadlines threatening this and other cities, tree advocates thus think their case is gaining dollars-and-cents plausibility.</p>
        <p>If it would mean existing trees were properly maintained, Mr. Kriet said that he would sacrifice planting.  Walking down any street, he will point out trees that have been vandalized, draped with wires, gone unwatered. They are dying. "Why not plant fewer better?" he asked.</p>
        <p>If there is hope, it exists in the community groups from Washington Heights to the Upper East Side to Bedford-Stuyvesant that are learning to prune trees, as well as to press public officials to do more. One such effort is that of Joe Ferris, a teacher and former state senator who mobilized the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn to plant trees along barren streets a generation ago. Neighborhood teen-agers did the work.</p>
        <p>He has now received $1,000 each from the Park Slope Civic Council and the Park Slope Chamber of Commerce to mobilize another band of youths to venture forth to give some care to the trees their parents might have planted.</p>
        <p>They will wear T-shirts declaring, "Eternal Vigilance is the Price of Treedom."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
