<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlantic City Seeks to Lure Non-Gamblers</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAMBLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CASINOS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC CITY (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB153EF933A25757C0A962958260" item-length="1457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlantic City Seeks to Lure Non-Gamblers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON NORDHEIMER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY, April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As campaigns for casino gambling gather momentum in neighboring states and elsewhere in New Jersey, Atlantic City is betting that it can reinvent itself as a convention center and seaside tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>That is brave talk for a city that has 12 mammoth casino hotels and parking garages but not a single golf course, movie house or even a supermarket. Even the best natural attraction, the ocean beach, shuts down for most of the year for swimming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As campaigns for casino gambling gather momentum in neighboring states and elsewhere in New Jersey, Atlantic City is betting that it can reinvent itself as a convention center and seaside tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>That is brave talk for a city that has 12 mammoth casino hotels and parking garages but not a single golf course, movie house or even a supermarket. Even the best natural attraction, the ocean beach, shuts down for most of the year for swimming.</p>
        <p>The chief reason people are willing to travel long distances to get here -- there were 30.2 million visits last year -- is gambling and gambling alone, industry leaders acknowledge.</p>
        <p>"Casino operators are running scared right now, there's no question about it," said Peter G. Boynton, president and chief operating officer of Caesars Atlantic City, one of the 12 casino hotels. "There is a tremendous sense of urgency to make Atlantic City work as a tourist destination instead of just a gambling destination." Fewer Visitors</p>
        <p>The number of visitors to the city has been declining since 1988, from 33.1 million to 30.2 million last year. The recession is mainly to blame, but analysts also say that competition from other gambling centers is beginning to take its toll. Further, a breakdown of market research reveals that the 30 million figure actually represents 7 million people who visit Atlantic City an average of 4.5 times a year, spending seven hours here on each trip.</p>
        <p>"Day-trippers represent most of Atlantic City's business, and the casinos made so much money from them for so long that they never readied themselves for competition in the region," said State Senator Richard J. Codey, Democrat of Essex County, who helped write the bill that allowed casino gambling in Atlantic City to begin in 1978.</p>
        <p>He said the possible introduction in the next few years of forms of casino gambling in Pennsylvania, New York and Florida could deal a serious blow not only to the resort, but also to the $230 million or so the state collects every year from an 8 percent tax on gross gambling revenue to pay for programs for the elderly and the disabled. New York and Connecticut already have casino gambling on Indian reservations.</p>
        <p>"Up to this year the threat of competition has not been a priority in Trenton," Senator Codey said. But the proposal last month by the financier Robert E. Brennan to buy the Meadowlands Sports Complex from the state for $1 billion on the condition that casino gambling be permitted there as well as at Garden State Park, the race track his company already owns outside Camden, has brought the issue "to the front burner," he added.</p>
        <p>There is rising sentiment in some quarters that if casinos sprout like mushrooms in neighboring states, New Jersey would be forced to expand casino gambling to the densely populated northern New Jersey and Camden areas to compete. A bill recently introduced in New Jersey calls for a state referendum on riverboat gambling if Pennsylvania or New York approve riverboat gambling.</p>
        <p>Riverboat casinos are given an increased chance for Philadelphia after the term of Pennsylvania's Governor, Robert P. Casey, a foe of casino gambling, expires this year.  Casino Bill in New York</p>
        <p>In New York, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo remains opposed to additional gambling in the state, but the Legislature is warming up to a bill that would allow a vote on a constitutional amendment on casino gambling by November 1995 at the earliest. Opposition was softened by the opening of a casino last year near Rome, N.Y., by the Oneida Indians under a Federal provision that allows gambling on reservations, and the St. Regis Mohawk tribe near the Canadian border is moving toward its own casino.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo appeared to concede last week that the political climate was shifting in favor of some form of casino gambling in New York, though he continued to oppose it.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City's official response to this rising competition is to point to the building of a $234 million convention center, scheduled for completion in late 1996, and the tentative approval of plans for a $500 million central corridor redevelopment that would include an entertainment complex, shops, restaurants and other attractions to draw tourists.</p>
        <p>Whether those projects will change the city's ragged image to draw another three million convention visitors and tourists a year, as architects of the plans claim, is uncertain. Outside the Casinos</p>
        <p>Cathy Burke hopes the city is finally on the right course to expand its allure beyond the bright lights and whimsical architecture of the mammoth casino structures. She and her husband, Dick, own and operate the Irish Pub and Inn on St. James Place, just 100 yards from the boardwalk and, beyond that, the ocean.</p>
        <p>The Burkes opened their establishment in 1973, five years before the first casino opened. After gambling was legalized, they discovered how formidable the casinos were in not letting patrons stray far from the excitement of the gambling tables. Free drinks, meals and hotel rooms kept a short leash on visitors lest they stray off a property and end up playing at a casino a block away. Day-trippers on a budget were induced to remain on a casino property with cut-rate "all-you-can-eat" buffets and discount coupons for shows in theaters adjoining the casino floors.</p>
        <p>Even the perception that city streets were not safe to walk, a feeling bolstered by vacant lots, crumbling housing, high crime rates and drug abuse, worked to keep patrons and their wallets inside the high-security casinos. As a result restaurants, shops and nominal tourist-related activities more than one or two blocks from the casinos either died from lack of patronage or never got started in a city that is only six blocks wide for most of its 40-block length. 'Have to Sell Atlantic City'</p>
        <p>"I'm very pro-casino, but the reality is that they don't bring people to Atlantic City as much as they bring them into the casinos," said Mrs. Burke, whose popular restaurant and bar draws heavily from the 50,000-member casino-hotel work force, the great majority of whom live outside the city of 37,000. "They haven't had to face the reality before that they have to sell Atlantic City as a seaside resort."</p>
        <p>Mack Latz, owner of the Knife and Fork, a restaurant that has been in his family since 1927, said the city long ago fumbled a chance to develop as a convention destination because the casinos preferred keeping many of their best hotel rooms free for high rollers to tying them up far in advance for conventioneers.</p>
        <p>"After Atlantic City got gambling, Las Vegas recognized it had to change and it became a convention center and a family tourist destination," said Mr. Latz, 77. "If they could do that in the middle of the desert, imagine what could be done here with the boardwalk and the ocean." Private Investors Are Needed</p>
        <p>Nicholas R. Amato, executive director of the Casino Reinvestment Development Authority, says that Atlantic City is already well along the road to rebirth with the corridor project and 500,000 square feet of exhibit space in the new convention hall. So far, however, the project is dependent on financing by the casinos and the state and has not yet received commitments from private investors critical to its success, other than signing up Doubletree Hotels Corporation to operate a new 600-room hotel and a few additional private vendors.</p>
        <p>The casinos must pay Mr. Amato's agency about $40 million a year in a special tax on gambling revenue, with the money going largely for cosmetic changes and landscaping along a three-block wide gateway. But beyond that obligation it is unclear how far casinos will be willing to invest in the rest of Atlantic City as their corporate boards dig deep into their pockets to get in on the ground floor of lucrative venues opening up around the nation.</p>
        <p>"Gambling is the business they're in," said Thomas Ballezzi, acting director of the Casino Association of New Jersey, a lobbying and promotion arm of the industry. "From that standpoint they take every opportunity to expand, just like Wal-Mart or Kmart would."</p>
        <p>But casino operators in Atlantic City will be competing with themselves by opening new ventures in the region, torn between the allure of profitable new markets and protecting their heavily mortgaged properties here.</p>
        <p>"It's much cheaper to invest in a riverboat somewhere than rebuild Atlantic City," said Steven P. Perskie, the chairman of the Casino Control Commission, the state casino regulatory board, who recently announced he was stepping down. "But if they do substantially broaden tourist attractions here it is my opinion Atlantic City will flourish against any expansion of riverboat gambling in the region."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
