<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Italian Film That Pits North Against South</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WERTMULLER, LINA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CIAO, PROFESSORE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6D81E3CF933A25754C0A962958260" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Italian Film That Pits North Against South</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>ROME</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE A teutonic-sounding Swiss name, Lina Wertmuller has an unquenchable passion for the irrepressible south of Italy. So it is not surprising that her latest film to reach American shores would probe the differences between Italy's somewhat disciplined north and the fervently other south.</p>
        <p>Called "Ciao, Professore," the film is the tale of a dozen Neapolitan children reclaimed from lives as truants: little waiters, barbers, cigarette smugglers and drug runners. They are hauled back to school by a proper northern Italian schoolteacher, whom they in turn loosen up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE A teutonic-sounding Swiss name, Lina Wertmuller has an unquenchable passion for the irrepressible south of Italy. So it is not surprising that her latest film to reach American shores would probe the differences between Italy's somewhat disciplined north and the fervently other south.</p>
        <p>Called "Ciao, Professore," the film is the tale of a dozen Neapolitan children reclaimed from lives as truants: little waiters, barbers, cigarette smugglers and drug runners. They are hauled back to school by a proper northern Italian schoolteacher, whom they in turn loosen up.</p>
        <p>What does surprise is a name on the list of producers. Alongside Ciro Ippolito, the upstart Neapolitan producer mainly responsible for the film, and Vittorio Cecchi Gori, who brought in Paolo Villaggio, the comic actor who plays the teacher, is that of Silvio Berlusconi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlusconi is the media tycoon turned politician who became Italy's Prime Minister in April. His election was greeted in some parts of the West as a return to Italian Fascism, since he had included in his Government ministers whose political roots went back to Mussolini's Black Shirts. How did this conservative businessman become interested in spotlighting, in a quietly humorous way, the crime, disorder and neglected youth of southern Italy?</p>
        <p>Although her forebears lived in the southern cities of Naples and Puglia, Ms. Wertmuller, 65, has lived in Rome for years. High above the streets, in the narrow room that serves as her workplace, she laughed disarmingly at the notion that Mr. Berlusconi, who helped finance the film, might have chosen her -- a noted leftist -- as the director. "It's not as though he looked into this film personally," she said, noting that through an agreement to form Penta Films with Mr. Cecchi Gori, Mr. Berlusconi has helped finance about 85 percent of all Italian films since 1989. Before starting Penta, Mr. Berlusconi made a fortune in publishing and television stations.</p>
        <p>Warming to the topic, she said:"He presents himself as a new kind of politician, a businessman who wants to try to be a politician, and if they let him work, maybe he'll give us proof of what he's able to do. We'll see."</p>
        <p>If Mr. Berlusconi did not foster the making of "Ciao, Professore," the film clearly grew out of the political climate that led to his election.</p>
        <p>The collapse of Italy's previous political class was partly caused by kickback scandals, and partly by the revolt of the separatist Northern League, which supports Mr. Berlusconi's Government. The league rallied northern Italian voters with the cry that high taxes paid by the north went for handouts to the lazy south.</p>
        <p>IN THE FILM, A COMPUTER glitch lands Sperelli, an elementary teacher from the north, in a gracefully decaying suburb of Naples. While awaiting reassignment, he boards with a dotty Neapolitan family, clashes with his colleagues at school and with the children themselves. The story takes an ironic turn when straitlaced Sperelli starts bending society's rules to help the children. He roughs up a nun, hijacks a van and learns coarse Neapolitan phrases. By the time of his reassignment, both he and the children have changed.</p>
        <p>Alessandro Bencivenni, a Roman writer who worked on the screenplay, said the film grew out of a collection of school compositions, by children from Naples, that became a best seller when it was published in 1990.</p>
        <p>The film made from these gleanings opened in Italy last fall as "Me, Let's Hope I Make It," and while the film was a box office success, some critics complained of its sentimental strain.</p>
        <p>Ietta Tornabuoni, of the Turin daily newspaper La Stampa, said the movie was "divided between pathos and enjoyment." David Rooney, writing in Variety, chided its "disarming sentimentality."</p>
        <p>Tullio Kezich, a leading Italian film critic and longtime friend of Ms. Wertmuller, agrees. "It's part of the game of supply and demand," he said dismissively. "It's not really a project of Lina's. Though of course she's a southerner at heart, and Naples is her capital city.</p>
        <p>"Lina is a woman who always sailed against the wind," he said, noting that she was the sole female director in an Italian world dominated by Federico Fellini, Bernardo Bertolucci and Michelangelo Antonioni. "People expected a women to make films with sensibility, love stories, but Lina can be aggressive, independent, decisive."</p>
        <p>Ms. Wertmuller is accustomed to controversy. After the release of "The Seduction of Mimi" (for which she won the best director award at the Cannes festival in 1972), "Swept Away" (her 1975 film, which was nominated for four Oscars), and "Seven Beauties" (1976), some critics hailed her as exciting and brilliant, while others found her overrated and perverse. Interest subsided, however, as she produced several critical and commercial flops, including "Summer Night" and "Crystal or Ash, Fire or Wind, as Long as It's Love," both in the late 80's.</p>
        <p>Speaking in her gravelly alto voice and wearing her signature white eyeglasses, Ms. Wertmuller defends "Ciao, Professore," recounting the tale of a young Neapolitan boy who worked with her on an earlier film. "He didn't go to school, could hardly read or write, spoke nothing but heavy Neapolitan dialect," she said. "He worked with us with such passion that in the end I was convinced we had saved him from the million seductions of the street."</p>
        <p>Then, several months ago, she read in the newspapers that the boy, now in his 20's, had been murdered over drugs. So "Ciao, Professore," she says, is really about violence, a fact of life whether you're living in Naples, Washington or Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>She refuses to apologize for what some see as the film's sentimentality. "Then that means that I'm sentimental," she snaps, adding with a grin: "I've never been it before, but I guess I'm supposed to have become it in this case."  FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
