<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Do Tobacco Executives Live With Themselves?</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="675375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOKING AND TOBACCO</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILIP MORRIS COMPANIES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBLATT, ROGER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5DA153DF933A15750C0A962958260" item-length="9838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Do Tobacco Executives Live With Themselves?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Roger Rosenblatt;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBLATT, ROGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEOPLE WHO WONDER how tobacco company executives can live with themselves conclude that they must be in denial. That would explain how they deal with their responsibility for a product that kills more than 420,000 Americans a year -- surpassing the combined deaths from homicide, suicide, AIDS, automobile accidents, alcohol and drug abuse. But to be in denial implies that one may not be held accountable, in psychological terms, for one's actions. Tobacco people squarely face the accusation of accountability, and reject it.</p>
        <p>They reject the overwhelming epidemiological evidence in the Surgeon General's Report of 1989, connecting smoking with lung and throat cancers, emphysema and heart disease, insisting that direct causation has not been proved. They dismiss the Federal Drug Administration's suggestion that cigarettes could be banned as an addictive drug, calling smoking merely a habit that has already been broken by tens of millions. They ridicule people who say they are pushing a drug, noting that their product is legal, that the same Government that posts health warnings on cigarette packs subsidizes tobacco farmers and that what they are really promoting is freedom of choice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEOPLE WHO WONDER how tobacco company executives can live with themselves conclude that they must be in denial. That would explain how they deal with their responsibility for a product that kills more than 420,000 Americans a year -- surpassing the combined deaths from homicide, suicide, AIDS, automobile accidents, alcohol and drug abuse. But to be in denial implies that one may not be held accountable, in psychological terms, for one's actions. Tobacco people squarely face the accusation of accountability, and reject it.</p>
        <p>They reject the overwhelming epidemiological evidence in the Surgeon General's Report of 1989, connecting smoking with lung and throat cancers, emphysema and heart disease, insisting that direct causation has not been proved. They dismiss the Federal Drug Administration's suggestion that cigarettes could be banned as an addictive drug, calling smoking merely a habit that has already been broken by tens of millions. They ridicule people who say they are pushing a drug, noting that their product is legal, that the same Government that posts health warnings on cigarette packs subsidizes tobacco farmers and that what they are really promoting is freedom of choice.</p>
        <p>In other words, if they experience denial as a psychological response, they also use denial as an aggressive tactic. This mirrors the way they live with themselves in general. Individually, they remove themselves from most of the rest of the country and create their own moral universe of explanations and justifications. Collectively, they embrace the country directly, involving as much of America as possible in their enormous success.</p>
        <p>My case in point is Philip Morris, the largest tobacco company in America and the largest consumer-products company in the world, owner of Kraft General Foods, Jacobs Suchard and Miller beer and maker of Marlboro, the best-selling cigarette in America and the best-selling packaged product in the world. The connection of the company to the American economy is so deep and secure that if one were to remove Philip Morris without first finding something equally valuable to fill the hole, much of the country would cave in.</p>
        <p>The company paid $4.5 billion in taxes in 1992 (on revenues of $59 billion) and billions more in employees' and excise taxes -- making it the largest taxpayer in the country and, outside of government, the largest tax collector. Also in 1992 it contributed $4 billion toward the balance of payments. It directly employs 161,000 people worldwide (92,000 of them in this country), not including those who sell the product or make the paper and the filters or who lobby in Washington or who advertise the product.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris is also a mainstay of American farming. In Blackstone, Va., about 50 miles southwest of Richmond, I met with John Bledsoe, a tobacco farmer in his early 30's. Bledsoe believes there is a health risk in smoking, but he has to earn a living. "There's nothing that will ever replace tobacco as a cash crop," he said. "And the farther south you go from here, the more impact tobacco has. The local car store, the clothing store . . . people don't realize. And Philip Morris has always been on our side. They've sent us on trips to places like Canada and Brazil to meet other tobacco farmers. They've helped us to stand up for what they represent."</p>
        <p>The company has a presence in 50 states and the District of Columbia. In 1992 it contributed more than $50 million to tax-exempt organizations. A company lawyer wryly remarked that, thanks to the number of lawsuits it generates, Philip Morris also contributes generously to the legal profession. By that logic, one might add that it contributes to the medical and mortician professions as well.</p>
        <p>Health care companies benefit from the industry in general and from Philip Morris in particular. Pfizer manufactures flavor enhancers, which are used in cigarettes; Ciba-Geigy makes nicotine skin patches for people seeking to quit smoking, along with fungicides for tobacco growers. Kimberly-Clark is a leading supplier of paper for cigarettes and filters.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris contends with Procter &amp; Gamble for the title of the largest advertiser in the world, supporting advertising agencies and the mass media. The introduction of Marlboro Medium in 1991 cost $60 million, the most ever spent by the company on a single new product. The company has not only advertised itself, it has advertised against its attackers. In 1988 it spent $5 million on a campaign to emphasize the economic power of smokers. One newspaper ad read: "Today, 21 million American smokers will go out to eat. That's a market you can sink your teeth into."</p>
        <p>Recently, the Surgeon General, Joycelyn Elders, stated that she would like to see cigarette advertising reduced further, especially that aimed at younger people. In fact, tobacco companies have already cut back on advertising and are pursuing other ways to reach smokers. Philip Morris's Marlboro Adventure Team -- people send in the U.P.C.'s on Marlboro packs to get free outdoor gear and the chance to join an excursion to "Marlboro country" -- has been the most successful promotional campaign in Marlboro's history.</p>
        <p>Cigarette advertising has been a mainstay of the magazine business since 1971, when Congress prohibited tobacco advertising on radio and television. This prohibition did not hurt Philip Morris, since Marlboro ads were more effective as still pictures of the Marlboro cowboy (the most widely recognized advertising image in the world), either on billboards or in magazine pages. In 1992 the company spent over $2 billion on media advertising -- of food, beer and tobacco products -- including nearly $18 million in daily newspapers and over $215 million in magazines. Many publishers and editors who welcome cigarette advertising also run health-hazard articles that omit or minimize the dangers of smoking.</p>
        <p>The company's connection to journalistic enterprises is widening. Philip Morris has recently made an agreement with the Time magazine group to test a system for sending magazines with tobacco ads only to subscribers who smoke. Philip Morris has also used its own data base to enlist smokers in campaigns against increased cigarette taxes. The company places a great deal of advertising with Time Inc., as it does with The New York Times Company, The Washington Post Company, Hearst Publications and Conde Nast. One member of the Philip Morris board of directors is Rupert Murdoch, owner of such publications as TV Guide, The New York Post and The Times of London.</p>
        <p>The composition of the board of directors itself suggests the extent of the company's connections to American business, banking, arts, education, Government, intellectual and health institutions, including hospitals and even cancer research centers. Besides Murdoch, outside members of the board, who are paid about $40,000 a year, include Harold Brown, the former Defense Secretary and a director of I.B.M., Mattel and CBS; William H. Donaldson, chairman of the New York Stock Exchange, former dean of the Graduate School of Management at Yale and a director of Aetna Life and Casualty and the Carnegie Endowment for World Peace; Richard D. Parsons, chief executive of the Dime Savings Bank, a director of Time Warner, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and a trustee of Howard University; Roger S. Penske, head of the Penske Truck Leasing Company in Detroit and a director of American Express; John S. Reed, chairman of Citicorp and a trustee of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, the Rand Corporation and the Russell Sage Foundation and a member of the board of the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center.</p>
        <p>The mutually useful relationship between the company and the Government may be illustrated by the Clinton Administration's proposed excise tax on cigarettes. The tax is said to pose a menace to the tobacco industry by pricing the product off the market. Philip Morris and the other companies will, naturally, fight the tax. Yet does it matter if they lose? "You know, I don't really care about the excise tax at all," a company vice president told me. "I wouldn't mind making the Government a little more dependent on the habit."</p>
        <p>While the President works to pass his excise tax, others in his White House have had relationships with the company that might affect their enthusiasm. When he was a lawyer in California, Mickey Kantor, the Administration's trade representative, assisted restaurant owners who were fighting anti-smoking ordinances. His law firm also represented Philip Morris. Such relationships with the White House are common. After he left the Reagan Administration, Michael Deaver represented Philip Morris in its efforts to penetrate the rich South Korean market. After he left the Bush Administration, Craig L. Fuller joined the company as senior vice president for corporate affairs.</p>
        <p>Encouraged by Michael A. Miles, the corporate chief executive officer, Fuller helped the Clinton Administration promote the North American Free Trade Agreement. Free trade is in the company's interests, but "this is because we care about the issue," Fuller says. "Mike is willing to give time to public policies that matter." A corporate senior vice president, Murray H. Bring, a former partner in the Washington law firm of Arnold &amp; Porter, alludes to the White House connection when he says, only half-jokingly: "To ban a product that is used so widely by so many people doesn't make any sense . . . certainly not from a political point of view. There are more smokers in the United States than there are people who voted for Clinton."</p>
        <p>In 1991-92 (the most recent figures available) the tobacco industry contributed $2.39 million to Congress, including PAC money and donations from executives. Of that, Philip Morris gave about one-quarter, or $640,000. Connections to individuals include Representatives like Charlie Rose, Democrat of North Carolina, known as Mr. Tobacco, and Scotty Baesler, Democrat of Kentucky, who represent tobacco-growing states, and Charles Rangel, a New York Democrat whose campaigns and communities have benefited from Philip Morris donations. Rangel has been under fire for his opposition to the excise tax, especially since he has crusaded against drugs and because blacks have been found to suffer from smoking-related diseases at a higher rate than other groups.</p>
        <p>I visited Rangel, who seems to be in something of a turmoil about the smoking issue. Before I could get out a question, he exploded that his opposition to the excise tax was perfectly consistent with his opposition to all regressive taxes. Then he complained that poor people in his Harlem community would suffer nervous breakdowns because they would not be able to afford cigarettes. Finally he said that he was likely to change his mind on the tax to help pass the Clinton health package.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris's involvement with social projects and the arts ranges from donations to a variety of organizations and communities to efforts toward minority employment and civil liberties within the company. Under the former leadership of Joseph F. Cullman 3d and George Weissman, Philip Morris became the first tobacco company to hire blacks in high positions. For that the company was boycotted in the South. The white supremacist publication White Sentinel wrote that Philip Morris had the "worst race mixing record" of any large company in the nation. The company was among the first to advertise in black and Hispanic newspapers and magazines. It has been vigorous in its employment of women.</p>
        <p>Philip Morris makes large and frequent contributions to the National Urban League, the N.A.A.C.P., the United Negro College Fund, Goodwill Industries, the National Puerto Rican Forum, the Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium, the Boy Scouts, Girl Scouts, United Way, Y.M.C.A., hospitals all over America, the Legal Aid Society, the National Multiple Sclerosis Society, the Salk Institute, the National Association on Drug Abuse. In 1990-91 it sponsored a 200th anniversary national tour of the original document of the Bill of Rights.</p>
        <p>The company has supported teacher education and adult literacy, backed reform in elementary and secondary schools and helped minority students go to college. In 1993 it donated more than $1.3 million to hunger relief organizations and over $1 million to AIDS. When I asked Stephanie French, vice president for corporate contributions and cultural affairs, whether any of the gift recipients ever expressed reservations or unhappiness about taking tobacco money, she pointed out that grantees apply to the company, not the other way around.</p>
        <p>As for the arts, Philip Morris is not only the largest tobacco company contributor but one of the largest corporate contributors of any kind. Nor does it give its money only to the "safer" arts projects; it has long supported the Next Wave Festival at the Brooklyn Academy of Music and as early as 1965 it supported the well-received exhibition of "Pop and Op" art. A report on 35 years of its arts contributions runs to 130 pages and lists grants to the Joffrey Ballet, Morgan Library, Jewish Museum, the Guggenheim, the Yaddo artists' colony, the Whitney (a branch of which is located in its corporate headquarters building in New York), the American Museum of Natural History and the National Gallery of Art in Washington.</p>
        <p>George Weissman, the chief executive after Joe Cullman and before Hamish Maxwell, has been chairman of Lincoln Center since 1986. French serves on the board of the Joffrey. William Campbell, president of Philip Morris U.S.A., the domestic tobacco company, is a member of the board of the Brooklyn Academy of Music and the MacDowell Colony.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the company's single most-publicized arts donation was a $3 million-plus grant for the Vatican art treasures exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1983. When Terence Cardinal Cooke, then the Roman Catholic Archbishop of New York, offered a benediction at a banquet celebrating the exhibition, Frank Saunders, a Philip Morris vice president, remarked: "We are probably the only cigarette company on this earth to be blessed by a Cardinal."</p>
        <p>The company enjoys its association with art and artists on philosophical as well as esthetic grounds. French believes that art fosters creative risk-taking within the company. Philip Morris may also like to relate the independent thinking of artists with its promotion of freedom of choice for smokers. The freedom to choose to smoke is the company's main philosophical, and legal, position, one which it links to other American freedoms. Usually, however, it does not advertise this linkage. In a pamphlet available to the public, the company announces: "We seek to lift the human spirit." In a set of in-house guidelines, it sounds more pragmatic: "We believe that business activities must make social sense, and social activities must make business sense. . . . Alexis de Tocqueville gave a name to this concept . . . 'the principle of self-interest rightly understood.' "</p>
        <p>Every time one raises a spoonful of Jell-O or Post Raisin Bran or Breyers ice cream or pours Log Cabin maple syrup or squirts Miracle Whip or spreads Parkay Margarine or Philadelphia Cream Cheese or Cheez Whiz or takes a bite of an Oscar Mayer weiner or an Entenmann's cookie or a Toblerone chocolate or sips Maxwell House coffee or Kool-Aid or Miller Beer -- whether or not one also lights up a Marlboro, Benson &amp; Hedges, Parliament, Merit, Alpine, Chesterfield or a Virginia Slims -- he or she is proving the principle of self-interest rightly understood.</p>
        <p>ALL OF PHILIP MORRIS'S CONNECTIONS TO THE country have produced, and are sustained by, a corporate culture that gives company executives immense, if guarded, self-confidence and helps them do battle with opponents. The culture is nurtured in their New York City corporate headquarters, a tall gray stone-and-steel building largely unnoticeable where it stands on Park Avenue between 41st and 42nd Streets because that is where the Grand Central Terminal auto ramp dominates the avenue. After the World Trade Center bombing, many New York office buildings had to make protective structural alterations; this had already been done at Philip Morris.</p>
        <p>The building is clean, quiet and decorated in the not-tasteless taste of most office buildings -- grays, off-whites and tans; egg-box light fixtures; plants in the offices, fabric on the walls. Large works of contemporary art are on display. Except for the blown-up photos of cigarette brands and omnipresent ashtrays, 120 Park might be taken for any prosperous business tower. Well-dressed women and men in shirt sleeves make self-conscious chatter on the elevators and small, quick jokes in the halls, which are not smoke-filled.</p>
        <p>Not long ago I visited the Philip Morris headquarters on several occasions and spoke with upper-level executives. Leery of journalists, they were nonetheless forthcoming in describing what they do and how they feel about it, though, to be sure, they are shrewd and, in terms of legal jeopardy, know what they can and cannot say. All of them are intelligent and companionable; most are family-oriented and community-minded. All feel beleaguered by portions of society (one vice president complained of being accosted at a cocktail party in his hometown by someone calling him a "mass murderer") and by the news media and the "antis," whom they alternately call "Nazis" or "smoking police." All are well paid, but not much more than executives at other large companies. Every one of them expresses enormous affection and respect for the company.</p>
        <p>Steven C. Parrish, who turns 44 in April, grew up in Moberly, Mo., a town of 13,000 once known as the home of Banquet Foods TV dinners. His father was a railroad cop; his great-uncle a lawyer involved in state Democratic politics. Originally, Parrish thought he would go into politics himself. But after graduating from the University of Missouri, where he made Phi Beta Kappa, and from the University of Missouri Law School, where he was an editor of the law review, he joined the Kansas City law firm of Shook, Hardy &amp; Bacon. Five years later, he was made a partner. He represented Philip Morris and Lorillard in the noted Cipollone case, in which the Liggett Group, Philip Morris and other companies were sued for contributing to the death by lung cancer of Rose Cipollone, who had smoked from an early age. An initial judgment of $400,000 against Liggett was eventually overturned and the case was never retried.</p>
        <p>Parrish, who smokes, is a small, neat, compact man, young in manner and appearance in spite of graying hair. In a blue shirt with a white collar, he looks slightly overfashionable. His voice rises and falls like a boy's in the process of changing. Everything about him suggests that he had to struggle his way through the likable country boy demeanor to assert ability, sophistication and authority. He is general counsel and senior vice president for external affairs, Philip Morris U.S.A. He and his wife live in Westport, Conn., with their daughter, 11, and son, almost 4:</p>
        <p>"The Cipollone trial took several months. As soon as it was over, I took a sabbatical, and when I came back, Philip Morris approached me about working for them exclusively. I took the job because I liked being a trial lawyer. I enjoy the ego rush you get when you're up and performing in court. And there's something about being an in-house lawyer that had always intrigued me. Philip Morris is a great company in terms of its business success, its reputation and all that sort of thing. The people really impressed me. And I really like representing the tobacco workers, who run the machinery and make the cigarettes. Really good people -- the kind I thought I'd represent when I was growing up. I also had always wanted to live on the East Coast. My friends in Kansas City think I'm nuts.</p>
        <p>"I didn't have any qualms about joining a tobacco company, partly because I had dealt with the issue already in the Cipollone case. We got nasty letters and a lot of confrontational things. My biggest qualm was: 'Gee, I have a very successful practice here in the Midwest. My wife is from the Midwest. I've always been very happy here. You never know. I may go to Philip Morris and they might think I'm terrible and then what am I gonna do.' That's what I thought. But I didn't have other qualms. I'd worked it out.</p>
        <p>"And I certainly didn't divide my job and my feelings in the Cipollone case. I didn't attempt to keep myself from feeling bad for Mrs. Cipollone, who was a really neat lady. I met her a couple of times before she died. She was sort of spunky, you know. And Mr. Cipollone was a very nice man. So I didn't try not to feel bad for Antonio Cipollone, because No. 1, I didn't think I could do it, and No. 2, what would that say about me? But I really did feel strongly that he was not entitled to get money because his wife chose to smoke. I mean, she was very clear about that. That she liked it. How it made her feel glamorous. That she enjoyed the taste of it. And never made a serious attempt to quit until she was told she had a problem. So when I met Mr. Cipollone, when he told about how his wife died, it was a very moving thing. It was a terrible thing. But she chose to smoke.</p>
        <p>"But I wouldn't be honest with you if I didn't tell you that when I see Sam Donaldson, for example, on 'This Week With David Brinkley,' as he did a few months ago, say 'I don't see how an executive with a tobacco company can look himself in the mirror in the morning.' . . . It troubles me. The day that happened I was sitting on a couch with my wife and my kids. We'd just gotten home from church. I love that show, so as soon as we get home I flip it on, and there's Sam Donaldson saying that. And it was upsetting.</p>
        <p>"Obviously, one way to deal with that is to say: 'O.K., I'm not going to work for a cigarette company.  Then they wouldn't be saying those things about me.' But I feel good about what I do, both in how I go about my job and what my role in the company is, so I try not to let it bother me. But anybody would feel hurt if somebody says you are a merchant of death and you shouldn't be able to look yourself in the mirror in the morning. I wish they wouldn't say things like that.</p>
        <p>"During the trial, I got to be pretty good friends with the plaintiff's lawyer. We used to get together every once in a while after the case was over, and he told me once . . . he and I were screaming at each other in front of the judge about something and he was calling me every name in the book and the company every name in the book and then I got up to do my response. And as he walked by, he said: 'You take this too seriously. You take this too personally.' And he was right.</p>
        <p>"My philosophy about everyday life is that you really have to constantly re-examine everything. Your convictions, I mean, your religious beliefs or whatever. And if you don't, you're not doing the right thing. And I ask myself the question: 'Are you one of these people that just says, I make a nice salary. I have a job. There are a lot of people that don't have jobs at all. And so have you rationalized your way into saying, yeah, this is what I ought to be doing?' I ask myself that a lot, along with a lot of other questions that don't have anything to do with Philip Morris. And I don't think I do. I don't think I do.</p>
        <p>"A year or two ago, my daughter came home from school, and said: 'I have a homework assignment I need you to help me with. Tomorrow we're going to talk about drugs like marijuana, cocaine and alcohol. We're also going to talk about cigarettes and whether they're addictive. I want to know what you think about cigarettes.' And I told her that a lot of people believe that cigarette smoking is addictive but I don't believe it. And I told her the Surgeon General says some 40 million people have quit smoking on their own. But if she asked me about the health consequences, I would tell her that I certainly don't think it's safe to smoke. It's a risk factor for lung cancer. For heart disease. But it's a choice. We're confronted with choices all the time. Still, I'd have to tell her that it might be a bad idea. I don't know. But it might be.</p>
        <p>"Is the affection that people have for one another in this company based partly on the fact that we're all in the bunker together? I don't think so, and I'll tell you why. The atmosphere here is not really different than it was at my law firm in Kansas City. There is stress, there's pressure . . . but that was true there as well. I notice more people locking arms and getting together behind a business strategy than I see worrying about the externalities of charges about tobacco and health and things like that.</p>
        <p>"But that other lawyer was right about me. I do take things personally. My wife constantly tells me: 'You worry too much about what other people think. You're doing fine.' So, while in some ways the worst thing about me is that I take things personally, part of the reason that I think I do a good job or see things through is also because I take things personally. And I say to myself: 'If I could just sit down with Sam Donaldson, he's not going to change his attitudes about smoking, but doggone, he'd probably realize that this guy's not a bad guy. He's got two little kids. He worries about all the issues that a parent worries about with their kinds -- drugs, AIDS, violence, all that stuff.'</p>
        <p>"You might say that we ought to do everything we can do reasonably to make sure that nobody ever smokes another cigarette. But you wouldn't say that people who work for tobacco companies can't look at themselves in the mirror because they're somehow lesser human beings than people who work for a drug company or a steel company."</p>
        <p>DAVID E. R. DANGOOR, 44, WAS appointed executive vice president for Philip Morris International in 1992. He has spent virtually his entire working life with Philip Morris, having served the company in Switzerland, Germany, England and Canada. Reared and educated in Sweden, he has the easy, gracious manner and unidentifiable accent of the fictional character known as "the Continental" -- wire-rimmed glasses, iron-gray hair combed straight back, a blue-and-red striped tie over a blue-and-white striped shirt and a gray double-breasted suit with a white handkerchief peeking up from the jacket pocket. Slightly jowly and soft-looking, he nonetheless has one of those faces that says, "I will beat you with sheer brainpower, and I will do it so deftly and politely that you will love every minute of it."</p>
        <p>He was married for the first time almost two years ago, and he and his wife expect their first child imminently. They live in the city. Dangoor, a smoker, oversees worldwide marketing, finance, strategic planning and personnel:</p>
        <p>"It's so different working in international from Philip Morris U.S.A. In the United States, you have a company that's under siege. Everybody's watching every move you're making. In the international division, it's the opposite. We are growing gangbusters, and as much as people are writing about how we are corrupting the world, in truth we only have 12.5 percent of the world market of cigarettes. So what you have, in the international division, is a company and a group of people who are entrepreneurs, and who are really focused on growing the business, rather than defending the business. In a way, international is much more like the old Philip Morris.</p>
        <p>"Do you know that story? I'm surprised that business magazines don't look at the genius of the origins of Philip Morris. The reason we're the powerhouse we are is because of a couple of guys in the 50's and 60's. They rolled the dice four times and always came up double sixes. The Cullmans. With the Cullman family coming in, the Jewish mind entered the tobacco industry, which had been traditionally, 'clinically' free of Jewish executives and Jewish interests. I should tell you that I am Jewish myself -- a Jewish Swede.</p>
        <p>"The industry, till then, was run by Southern Protestants. What happened was that Jewish executives took over. I don't want to name all the executives, because, you know, some Jews don't like to be remembered as Jews and others do. So I'm not going to get into trouble here. But there were five extremely senior executives who would sit down at meals in the 1950's and remind themselves that there were six competitors in the market and they were ranked No. 8. That's how they would begin every meeting.</p>
        <p>"So they decided to look at their brand portfolio and reposition their brands and stock. And the brand they started with was Marlboro. And you know the rest. They made a macho campaign for men out of a woman's cigarette. The point is, the whole attitude of the company changed. These guys never agreed on anything and they would argue about everything, and they would kill each other and involve everyone high and low, talented people. But when they had to make a decision, the decision would emerge. This made Philip Morris.</p>
        <p>"Joe Cullman really did it. And more. He also created this incredible family feeling, by taking a personal interest in everybody. He would go to weddings and christenings or whatever, and he was one of the first to decide to implement a profit-sharing system in the company. Joe has never got the recognition he's deserved, but he's in his 80's today. I'm sure God's rewarding him because he's blessed with health. If you got to know all the people in that group, you would find each one of them -- they are still alive -- remarkable. All Democrats, all a little bit socialistic. And you ask: 'How could these people all be in the cigarette business?' If you knew them, you would understand that there must be much more to the issue than what comes to mind.</p>
        <p>"Imagine me, growing up in Sweden in 1976, extremely frustrated by a country where socialism was really going too far, where equality was everything but equality meaning everything should be average, rather than quality at a high end. And then I got an opportunity to get interviewed by Philip Morris, in Switzerland. I had no interest in working for them. I had an antipathy toward smoking. I must tell you, I met five executives and after that I walked out and the only thing on my mind was how am I going to land a job in this company. I had met people that spoke to me about the business, life, family, in a way that I had never been exposed to in school. I realized that I wasn't talking to a rigid company, where everybody had to toe the party line. It was a company were one could remain an individualist.</p>
        <p>"I don't believe I would do anything that would benefit me if I thought at the same time that I was cheating society, that I was lying to society, that I was doing something truly immoral. Everybody knows that smoking must be a terrible idea. I mean, it's not a secret. In actual fact, we live in a perfect world. We are allowed to conduct our business, and the press and the antis are allowed to rip us apart and kill us. The debate is in the forefront. And this is a shocking statement to make, but I'm sure that people think smoking is even more dangerous than it ever could be. Yet they do it. Why? Is it an addiction issue? I don't believe it. People do all sorts of things to express their individuality and to protest against society. And smoking is one of them, and not the worst.</p>
        <p>"When you are in the business, and when you're confronted with all the issues, I promise you, you come out of it saying, 'I don't feel that bad about doing this.'</p>
        <p>"Is this denial? My wife says I'm a specialist in denial, and so does my doctor. Let me try to answer you in the following way. If people are staying with the company because of denial, they must be incredibly resilient. I had a tremendous amount of job offers; a lot of our people did. I could have gone into the cereal business, the cosmetics business. I must tell you, the people you have around you every day, and the kind of environment that you live in every day, become an incredibly important part of the quality of your life. The issues that you refer to become less important, not because you deny the problems but because as a whole it's not the question of making more money. It's the question of being very happy at doing what you're doing.</p>
        <p>"You know, actually, it sounds crude and simplistic, but ultimately it's not up to the tobacco industry to deal with the cigarette issue. The final solution to the cigarette issue, that's up to society. If they want to ban cigarettes, you know, we live in a democracy, it should be done in a democratic way and discussed how the hell to deal with the economic consequences, and that's not meant as a threat. It's just a fact.</p>
        <p>"I'll tell you what I like about the business. First, there are no surprises. There is nothing more to be said or discovered about the cigarette business or the industry. And there's no way to write an article that could do us any more harm than what has already been written. Second, no new company wants to get into the tobacco business. That's great. Third, we have the best partners in the world: the governments. In a lot of countries, it's incredibly important to the whole welfare state that we sell our products to collect taxes. When you sit with a finance minister or deputy of any government to discuss taxation, he's much cruder about the financial analysis of that taxing than we are. He asks, 'How much can I put up the tax, to make sure that the demand is not going to go down so much so that my net intake goes down?' Amazing. So no matter how you look at the cigarette business, it's incredibly predictable, it's extremely secure as an investment vehicle and, therefore, it's a great business to be in -- if you can deal with the fact that some people are not going to like you."</p>
        <p>AS SENIOR VICE PRESIDENT FOR Corporate affairs, Craig L. Fuller, 43, helps to shape and superintend the company's definition and image. Fuller came to the company in January 1992, after having served as assistant for Cabinet affairs for President Ronald Reagan from 1981 to 1985, chief of staff for then-Vice President George Bush from 1985 to 1988 and chief executive of Hill &amp; Knowlton U.S.A., the public relations firm. He has spent most of his career moving between public relations and politics. His first full-time job was as manager of public affairs for the Pacific Mutual Life Insurance Company; his second, with Michael Deaver's firm, Deaver &amp; Hannaford. He grew up in the late 1960's in Walnut Creek, Calif., and went to U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>Fuller and his wife, Karen, still keep their house in Virginia from their Washington days. He is about six feet tall, has a large belly, an open merry face and is slightly bucktoothed. His dark brown hair is slick and neatly cut, like a teen-ager's of the 1950's.</p>
        <p>"My wife, Karen, has -- had -- more concerns about joining a tobacco company than I did. I smoke cigars. She's a nonsmoker. But Mike Miles  [ the corporate chief executive ]  was the first to tell me, 'Think it through.' I was very interested in understanding what the company's point of view was. I was impressed with programs that existed before I came here, about 'accommodation.' We think smokers and nonsmokers alike have rights. And that they ought to be accommodated. So I was concerned to take time to understand what the company's point of view was, and it was consistent with my own. I think that it's important to have a match with respect to some basic values.</p>
        <p>"The link between working for George Bush and working for Philip Morris is that not only must you believe, you have to make the others believe in themselves. My job with Bush was telling him, in effect, 'This is who you are and this is what you believe.' I've always thought of myself as a good listener and a good communicator between and among groups. I'd like to have people better understand what we're about. I don't know if I ever said to myself, 'What I really want to go do is represent people who might not be able to represent themselves as well,' but I sort of have done it.</p>
        <p>"My corporate job is a little different -- and I'm not sliding away from the tobacco issue. But my job is to help the company work through how you can have a great deal of pride and respect, and care a lot, and nurture a very, very successful tobacco business, while recognizing that you are a global leader in the food business. If you analyze constituencies or audiences, you find out that the general public, the media, opinion leaders, business leaders, investors really don't understand this company very well. And regardless of how they feel about tobacco, I'd like them to judge us for what we actually are -- a company of some of the world's best brands. Among our strongest brands is Marlboro; that, I think, is going to be the case for a long time to come. It gives us a chance to do a lot of other things and it gives us a strength that other companies don't enjoy. It gives us cash flow, a financial base to invest in food businesses and expand the beer businesses. And so I'm for a strong tobacco identity.</p>
        <p>"People under attack here sometimes say, 'Why don't we change our name to Kraft?' I think that would be wrong, because that would be stepping away from the world's largest tobacco company and a business that succeeds because people know that folks on this floor, and shareholders and others, have a great deal of respect for what it is is that they do. And they are a wonderful group of people. Again, I have to help people figure out who they are.</p>
        <p>"You know, there's been a deep reluctance here about talking to the press. We almost never do it. I say we should. My thinking is: If there's one more negative story, so what? I mean, if we can't describe what we think and feel and how we go about our business and we're not willing to share some of the challenges and some of the human dimensions to it and the pride, well what are we doing? Once you know what you're doing, you've got to believe in it.</p>
        <p>"When I first came here, Fortune magazine did a story on us, and it's funny because, at the time, people thought it was a terrible story. I told them, I think it's a terrific story. If you open the magazine, you see a big full page picture of Mike Miles. He looks terrific, like Clint Eastwood. Next to it is this bar chart that shows our cash flow. Just looking at it, within 10 seconds, you know that our cash flow is greater than the next 10 companies combined. I said, I'll take it. We now use that article to recruit people."</p>
        <p>ELLEN MERLO, A self-described social smoker, has worked for Philip Morris for 25 years. Born in 1940 in the Bronx, she grew up in West New York, N.J., a town on the Palisades cliffs that overlooks the Hudson. Her parents were in the embroidery business. "I hated New Jersey and I hated West New York," she says matter-of-factly. "I used to look at Manhattan across the river and say to myself, 'I'm a New Yorker.' " After high school, she spent two years studying at Katharine Gibbs, then found employment first with Young &amp; Rubicam, then at Revlon, Ziff Davis and Petersen Publishing. Starting out as a secretary at Young &amp; Rubicam, she rose at Petersen to be managing editor of Motor Trend magazine, though she had little interest in cars.</p>
        <p>Joining Philip Morris in Canada in 1969, she later transferred to New York where she was brand manager successively for Parliament, Virginia Slims and Benson &amp; Hedges. She moved up further in various executive marketing positions and today is vice president for corporate affairs for Philip Morris U.S.A. Her work focuses on government relations and supervising lobbying interests.</p>
        <p>Merlo dresses business-stylishly, has dark brown hair and dark brown eyes and carries herself with the self-assurance of someone who has worked long and hard to get where she is. She is steadfastly loyal to her colleagues, though she speaks wistfully of the days when Joe Cullman wheeled a wagon of Champagne around what were then the four floors of the corporate building at Christmas and everyone knew most everyone else. "Now we have a Christmas party for 2,000 people at the Metropolitan Museum." A lifelong liberal Democrat, her fondest memory is of shaking hands with Eleanor Roosevelt. She lives in the heart of Manhattan:</p>
        <p>"Dealing with government, state or national, the first thing you have to think about is what are the company objectives, overall. Secondly, what legislation is out there that is either positive or negative for the company. Then you put a strategy together to deal with various legislators or issues.</p>
        <p>"The way you win the most battles is to have information. Contrary to what people think, it's not having influence. Yes, it's knowing who the legislators are and having a good relationship and having access. But once you have access, you have to be able to deliver a message that makes sense. If it's a tax that we're against, then we have to be able to prove that there are going to be job losses, that it's not going to produce the revenue that is being projected, that if a state raises its taxes so high and it's next to another state that has low taxes, there are going to be cross-border sales and those sales will not only be a loss in tobacco revenue, but once someone goes over a border to buy their tobacco or their liquor or something else, they're probably making a lot of other purchases.</p>
        <p>"You ask, 'What if Rangel changes his position and supports on the excise tax?' If he does change his mind, we will show him the facts and figures -- that an excise tax will not produce the revenue. Philip Morris supports health care reform. I don't know anybody who's against health care reform. But it's a matter of how extensive it is, how quickly it's implemented and how it's paid for. What we're saying is that an excise tax is an unreliable way of paying for health care. No. 1, it will not produce the revenue to pay for the plan, so there's going to have to be other taxation, and No. 2, it's going to play economic havoc, because it probably will cost the country 275,000 jobs. So we will talk to Charlie Rangel, not to dissuade him from supporting health care reform but to get him and others to think about alternative ways of funding and reducing costs.</p>
        <p>"We really don't care how people feel about smoking; we're not asking anyone to endorse our product. It's not a smoking issue. We say: 'This is what an excise tax will do to this city, state, to people in your district. This is what a smoking ban will do to restaurants, the impact it'll have on revenue.' It's not about the tobacco.</p>
        <p>"Of course, the economic and the smoking issue are related. I'll tell you an interesting story about a Philip Morris employee. This was in California. He was taking a group of business associates to a restaurant, and when they got there -- there were six or seven of them -- he said we'd like a table in the smoking section.  They said, 'Sorry, but this is a no-smoking restaurant. We don't allow smoking anywhere in the restaurant.'</p>
        <p>"He turned to his guests and said: 'I'd just as soon not stay here. Do you mind if we go to another restaurant?' After all, it was Philip Morris money. So his guests said no problem, and they went down the block and they had a lovely time and he paid the bill, which was about $500 for everybody. And he got a copy of the bill and sent it to the first restaurant with a note: 'Just thought you should know. Here is the receipt of the funds that I spent that night, that could have gone to you. Multiply it by all of the other people who might want to come in and have a cigarette.'</p>
        <p>"Two days later, he gets a phone call -- and he never put his phone number in the letter. 'We just want you to know that we received your letter and we thought about it, and we decided that we are going to employ an accommodation in our restaurant from now on, so we hope that the next time you go out to dinner, you and your smoking friends will think about us again.' "</p>
        <p>WILLIAM I. CAMPBELL WAS born in Regina, Saskatchewan, and grew up in the oil boom town of Edmonton, Alberta. His father's family goes back several generations in Canada; his mother came over from Scotland. Campbell's grandfather had been a small-town grocer but got wiped out in the Depression. Neither of his parents went to college. They invested their hopes in their one son -- they also had two older daughters -- and were pleased when he studied economics at the University of Alberta and considered pursuing a Ph.D., with the idea of becoming a college professor.</p>
        <p>But a mentor saw in Campbell a flair for business, and Campbell felt that was right. He had, he says, an ability to "see through the data." He went east to get an M.B.A. from the University of Western Ontario ("that was my rebellion"). He went directly to work for Philip Morris, first in the marketing division of Benson &amp; Hedges, Canada, then in a number of increasingly higher marketing and sales positions. In September 1990 he was appointed president and chief executive officer of Philip Morris U.S.A., placing him in charge of everything in the tobacco company.</p>
        <p>The conference room beside his office displays photos with dignitaries, awards, a souvenir medal from President Clinton and a mug from the Clinton Continued on page 73 inauguration. Like Steve Parrish, Campbell is thin, smallish and young-looking. He turns 50 in May. He has sharp blue eyes, wavy silver hair and a face that looks both rugged and malleable. He has a ready, explosive laugh and he frequently talks with his hands. Campbell is divorced. His two young daughters live with their mother:</p>
        <p>"You know, even today I go out with the sales reps. There are things that you can learn at that level of contact that you just can't learn any other way.  You can't read it off the computer or in the reports. Especially at the early stages of a launch. Sales reps are a continuous source of real, hands-on information. And of how you're really being perceived. They react a lot like consumers. So you can get a sense of where you are, what kind of adjustments you should make and so on.</p>
        <p>"So I still go out with the sales force. Because any good leader has to be able to see the data as something else. If the skills are purely objective, at some point they'll tend to falter. And if the skills are purely subjective, where they'll falter typically is in the people area. The principal responsibilities are people-related. In a decision like Marlboro Friday, you have a tremendous obligation to your employees, your customers, your shareholders.  [ On April 2, 1993, called "Marlboro Friday," Philip Morris rattled the stock market when it cut the retail price of a pack of Marlboros by 40 cents to compete with the cheaper generic cigarettes, which had cut its market share to 22 percent. The move cost the company an instant $2 billion, but now, not a year later, the stock is up and the market share, at almost 27 percent, is at its highest point ever. ]</p>
        <p>"You know, you just can't take the responsibility lightly. And people did feel good about that. And particularly my ex-boss, Hamish Maxwell. Early in my career, I was describing to Hamish my new plan for the Canadian sales organization. And I was going on blah-blah-blah. And I said, 'You know, the morale will be much better,' et cetera, et cetera. And he said: 'Bill, you go ahead with that. I'm sure you're right. But all in all, through the years, I've found that there's nothing better for morale than a sales curve going up.'</p>
        <p>"I'm a smoker. Not a heavy smoker. I like it. Smoking slows me down, gives me a pause. I'm very active and I tend to sometimes jump. A cigarette will sort of slow me down to that level of not jumping around quite so much. My girls ask why I smoke. And I can only answer that I enjoy it, and I think I'm informed about it. And I tell them, 'You'll be facing decisions like this one, when you're an adult.' It requires thought. I think that people do have to take a step back and say, 'Isn't individual freedom and individual choice an important characteristic of our society?' And that's more philosophical than 'Don't.'</p>
        <p>"But the attacks on the company are hard on the people. I feel deeply for our sales people across the country. They go into some very hostile environments, and because they're sales people, without any escape, they basically have to take what's given to them. And, you know, some people can be downright rude if they think that right is on their side. And we always have to try to be as well-mannered as we can be, because it only makes us look bad when we're not. And yet nobody in this company I know, including the time that I've been president, and before, has ever come and said: 'I don't believe this any more. I want out.' Never. In 27 years. That's a lot of people we're talking about. All over the world.</p>
        <p>"This company is a town, and a city, a large town. It has shared values. It's a centrist town, but it's surprisingly liberal. If you added the town up, you would still statistically be on the right side of center, but the liberal attitude is significant. It's not sophisticated enough to be real Northeast. And it's not Southern, like its roots. But it's an interesting combination of South and North and probably more East than West. It's not New York, although there are some very New York elements about it. Cultural stuff and so forth. Something different. It's an American town. Yeah. An American town."</p>
        <p>IF I HAD ASKED ANY OF THE Philip Morris executives directly, "How do you live with yourself?" each would have taken the question personally. None of these executives think of themselves as morally bankrupt, and I do not think of them individually in that way, either. What often happens to people who work for a large, immensely successful company, however, is that they tend to adopt the values of the company, regardless of its product. Loyalty supersedes objectivity.</p>
        <p>How good, smart, decent individuals manage to contribute to a wicked enterprise is a question that has been applied to murderous governments as well as to industries. The best answer, which isn't particularly satisfying, is that people in groups behave differently, and usually worse, than they do singly. In speaking with these Philip Morris executives, I felt the presence of the company within the person. In the end, I felt that I was speaking with more company than person, or perhaps to a person who could no longer distinguish between the two. In this situation, in which the company has effectively absorbed its employees in its moral universe, the more responsible employees are the company and thus are to blame.</p>
        <p>What the company feels, then, is what its people feel. And these days Philip Morris is on top of the world. Like all tobacco companies, it operates under monopoly conditions, raising and lowering prices at will and using billions in monopoly profits to buy up other businesses. While functioning as a monopoly, it cannot be touched by the Government because, as Dangoor said, other companies could get in the business if they wanted to, but, given the risk of liability, they don't.</p>
        <p>Also, recent polls suggest that more young people -- women and teen-agers especially -- are smoking cigarettes these days. The number of blacks who smoke is on the rise. Articles are beginning to appear on the pure pleasure of smoking -- how a cigarette eases tension, aids thought, delineates the best moments of a day. Several executives mentioned the idea of "pleasure revenge" -- a term coined by Faith Popcorn, a specialist in identifying pop business trends. They relate an upsurge in smoking to a rebellion against what they perceive as the country's neo-puritanical attitude toward health. Several executives see in such cultural phenomena as the return of cigarette smoking in movies the signs of such a revival.</p>
        <p>The company takes the position that it does not seek to make smokers of nonsmokers. But when I asked Bill Campbell and Ellen Merlo, "Why not?" -- that is, if they believe in free choice, why shouldn't nonsmokers be free to choose and why shouldn't the company, like any other, seek new customers? -- they responded simply that it is not industry policy. In a climate where smoking appears to be growing more attractive, that may change. But, as many of them point out, even if the total domestic market shrinks to nothing, there is still the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>The company plant in Cabarrus County, N.C., is undergoing a $400 million expansion to increase production by 25 percent. The 1.6-million- square-foot plant in Richmond, which I visited, houses a network of tubes, pipes and rollers, resembling a vast model train exhibit, which is being geared up to produce between 580 million and 600 million cigarettes a day.</p>
        <p>In short, the company is feeling as robust and secure as it ever has. It continues to face attacks, like a recent $5 billion lawsuit brought by Stanley M. Rosenblatt (no relation) on behalf of flight attendants who claim to have been afflicted by secondary smoke. Yet increasingly it is taking the offensive. Last June, the company sued the Environmental Protection Agency for citing secondary smoke as a carcinogen. Last month, it sued the city of San Francisco to overturn its anti-smoking ordinance, one of the strictest in the country. On March 9, it helped organize a tobacco workers march on Washington against the proposal to raise the cigarette tax.</p>
        <p>These executives think of themselves as the best company, and with much of the country acting on their side, they are also in the best company. Of course, there is also the evidence of illness and death that result from their product, but they do not accept that and, so far, neither does the country, formally. If it did, tobacco companies would be illegal. One might say that this absolves the company of special responsibility, since the responsibility is so widespread. But a tobacco company is where the entire process begins. It often ends elsewhere.</p>
        <p>On an icy Wednesday afternoon, Victor L. Crawford sits in the conference room of his law office in a colonial house in Rockville, Md. The cold sun shoots bright light into the room without warming it. Photographs of Crawford, who was once a Maryland State Senator, hang on the walls. The house, said to be the oldest in Rockville, dates from the 1780's. "See these?" Crawford points to the stone fireplace and the white chips in its mortar. "They're oyster shells," he says. "That's what they used to fill the holes." His voice sounds raspy like Sinatra's.</p>
        <p>He is 61 years old, about six feet in height, gaunt, and he wears a three-piece sharkskin suit; the vest hangs loose. He also wears a light gray wig -- noticeable but well-made and by no means comical. A trial lawyer today, he served five years as a lobbyist for the Tobacco Institute and was instrumental in defeating major anti-smoking bills in Maryland:</p>
        <p>"At that point, I had no particular feelings about smoking. I had stopped smoking cigarettes about 15, 18 years earlier. I was 52 then. So I'd stopped smoking in my mid-30's. But I still smoked pipes and cigars. I inhaled a little bit on the pipe, unfortunately. Not on the cigars. I smoked pipes and cigars right up until the time that I was diagnosed. And, of course, I'd smoked cigarettes all those years, since I was 13.</p>
        <p>"One day I was sitting in one of the smoke-filled rooms in the Tobacco Institute -- they all smoked -- and thinking, 'My God, maybe we're on the wrong side of this issue, because I can hardly breathe.' But I was very impressed with the institute -- their expertise in P.R. and lobbying. The fees were great, and I was useful to them. I knew everybody in Maryland politics. So I served them well, from the mid-80's till 1991.</p>
        <p>"And '91 is when I started getting the problems. Pains in the head, pains in the eustachean tube. My biopsy was in right before Christmas '91. And Jan. 3 of '92 I got the diagnosis of throat cancer. Originally, I stopped cigarettes because I was having trouble breathing. Too late, maybe. It's the most insidious habit, an addiction. I was an addictive personality. I'd stop six or eight weeks. Then I'd have one cigarette and the next day I was back up to two packs and the next day I was back up to three. It is highly addictive.</p>
        <p>"I am undergoing chemotherapy. You can tell by the wig. I started off with radiation first, because they wanted to reduce the tumor before they operated. And they operated on me in the first week in April of 1992. They took away everything there in my lower neck and left shoulder, all of the muscles. You can't see the scar. They did a magnificent job.</p>
        <p>"I've aged 10 years in six months. This chemotherapy has really just torn the hell out of me, worse than the operation. . . . There's no cure, of course. There is a chance -- a good chance, since I've had such a tremendous response lately -- that they can put it in remission. It might give me anywhere up to five years. When you're 61, five years looks pretty good.</p>
        <p>"I have no animosity, though. I've got nobody to blame but myself. I knew what it was. But the tobacco companies were culpable, too. I had some twinges when I was lobbying for them. Why don't they have a feeling of responsibility? Maybe it's the corporate mentality. I defend criminals. And the biggest charge of criminal law is to get a hopeless case and win. The reason it's hopeless is because the son of a bitch is guilty. Because he did it. And by putting him out on the street, I might help him do it again.</p>
        <p>"For 33 years, I've been doing this. Just like these hard-nosed tobacco execs say that they have a perfect right to do what they do. But they must know. They have to know. Because they're brilliant people. And they're tough, hard businessmen. They know. But they're able to sublimate it, I'm convinced, because of the similar mentality that we lawyers have. 'Freedom of choice is more important than anything!' Well, that's not necessarily true. But it offers a way that you can live with yourself.</p>
        <p>"I'm not proud of having lobbied for them. I think it's ironic. And in a way, I think I got my just deserts, because, in my heart, I knew better. But I rationalized and denied, because the money was so good and because I could always rationalize it. That's how you make a living, by rationalizing that black is not black; it's white, it's green, it's yellow. But I knew, in my heart, that what the Surgeon General said was right. I think these people know that.</p>
        <p>"Do I feel guilty about what I did? Yeah. Would I do it again, knowing what I know now? No. Would I do it again not knowing what I know now? Yes. Why? Because it might be unhealthy, but it will never happen to me. And after all, there's freedom of choice. And it's a free country. And if you want to make an ass out of yourself, you have the right. It sounds good. But the fact of the matter is that it's a killer."  Roger Rosenblatt, a contributing writer for this magazine, is the author most recently of "The Man in the Water," a collection of essays and stories.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Roger Rosenblatt, a contributing writer for this magazine, is the author most recently of "The Man in the Water," a collection of essays and stories.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
