<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For U.S. Miners, the Rush Is On to Latin America</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="681037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METALS AND MINERALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOLIVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHILE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2DA1F3EF934A25757C0A962958260" item-length="1858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For U.S. Miners, the Rush Is On to Latin America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Leonard Harris, a craggy veteran of mining battles in the American West, Peru offers an investment climate to warm a rock lover's heart.</p>
        <p>"We got all our mining permits in one year here," said Mr. Harris, general manager of a new Andean gold mine operated by the Newmont Mining Corporation of Denver. "One year and 15 days after approval, we poured gold."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Leonard Harris, a craggy veteran of mining battles in the American West, Peru offers an investment climate to warm a rock lover's heart.</p>
        <p>"We got all our mining permits in one year here," said Mr. Harris, general manager of a new Andean gold mine operated by the Newmont Mining Corporation of Denver. "One year and 15 days after approval, we poured gold."</p>
        <p>Warming the hearts of Newmont stockholders, their 10-month-old Peruvian operation is producing gold bars for as little as $120 an ounce -- roughly a third the world gold price.</p>
        <p>Up and down South America, mining companies from the United States -- as well as from Australia, Canada and South Africa -- are stampeding into the mineral-rich Andes mountains in a copper, silver and gold rush.</p>
        <p>"Latin America is fast becoming the world's largest mining economy," said Eul-Soo Pang, director of the Colorado School of Mines International Institute in Golden, Colo. "By the end of the decade, Latin America's export of metallic minerals could double from $25 billion to $50 billion."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pang estimated that Latin America drew more than half the exploration dollars of United States mining companies.</p>
        <p>Discarding decades of prickly nationalism, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile and Peru have rewritten their mining codes to encourage foreign investment. The new codes establish clear tax rules, easy repatriation of profits, protection against nationalization and low tariffs on machinery.</p>
        <p>At the same time, North American and Australian mining companies complain of increasing "barbed wire" at home: environmental hearings and native Indian land-ownership disputes that either block new projects outright or stretch out approval times for years on end.</p>
        <p>"It's a push-pull thing," said Gary Livingstone, president of the Mining Association of British Columbia. "These South American countries are actively seeking North American investors, while in North America there is a punitive regime against mining that is almost a repelling force."</p>
        <p>From Colorado, Mr. Pang said: "Suppose you acquire one land position in Colorado. It takes five years to acquire the exploration license. In Latin America, it takes 45 days or even less."</p>
        <p>Today's mining rush is wildest here in Peru. In 1965, there were 12 foreign mining companies operating in Peru. By 1990, 25 years of socialist policies and guerrilla violence had reduced that number to two.</p>
        <p>A new, probusiness mining code, a radical privatization program and Government successes against the guerrillas have dramatically turned around the mining picture here.</p>
        <p>In an unprecedented boom, 2,200 new mining claims were registered with the Ministry of Mines and Energy in the first nine months of 1993. New foreign investment projects totaled $2 billion.</p>
        <p>In a cascade of foreign investment the last 18 months, a Chinese company, the Shougang Corporation, bought the state iron company for $270 million in cash and investment commitments; the Cyprus Amax Minerals Company of Englewood, Colo., bought a copper mine for $522 million in cash and investment commitments, and Mantos Blancos, the Chilean subsidiary of the Anglo American Corporation of South Africa, paid $12 million for another copper deposit and announced a $500 million investment program. In all, about 20 foreign mining companies are operating in the country.</p>
        <p>With guerrilla violence waning, the mining stampede into Peru continues unabated. To sell all the state mining assets, the Government plans to privatize in the next six months a copper refinery, a zinc refinery, a gold mine and two copper mines.</p>
        <p>On May 10, in a huge sale, Peru is set to privatize Centromin, a sprawling Andean complex that is Peru's largest producer of silver, zinc and lead. The minimum bid is $340 million, with an investment commitment of $240 million.</p>
        <p>"I have a better chance of running into mining people I know at Lima airport than on the streets of downtown Vancouver," said Mr. Livingstone, whose group represents Western Canadian mining companies.</p>
        <p>From Colorado, Mr. Pang said: "We used to say that you needed a geology master's in order to get a job waiting on tables in Denver. Now my graduates are learning Spanish," and are going to Latin America.</p>
        <p>INDEED, foreign mining investors are finding welcome mats across the Andes.</p>
        <p>After centuries of mining, geologists believe that miners have extracted only 10 percent of Bolivia's minerals -- tin, gold, silver, zinc, lead, platinum, copper and diamonds.</p>
        <p>In 1991, a free-market mining code was adopted. In 1992, new private mining investment, overwhelmingly foreign, reached $134 million -- three times the level of two years earlier. In 1993, Bolivians elected as their new President Gonzalo Sanchez de Lozada, a mine owner who was raised in the United States and speaks Spanish with an American accent. Today, 15 foreign mining companies are prospecting in Bolivia.</p>
        <p>With Bolivia expected to triple its mineral exports by the end of the 1990's, Alvaro Ugalde, general manager of Inti Raymi, a gold mining venture in which Battle Mountain Gold of Houston has a big stake, predicted: "In 5 to 10 years, Bolivia will have a boom like that in Chile."</p>
        <p>Chile, the Andean pioneer in free-market mining policies, continues to be the leader in new foreign investment. Despite occasional warnings by mining analysts that Chile is "saturated," $7 billion of mining investments are planned through 1997.</p>
        <p>Last year, mining received half the $1.6 billion in new foreign investment in Chile. In one huge deal, Cyprus Amax Minerals and Lac Minerals of Canada are negotiating a joint $1.2 billion development of a copper and gold deposit at El Abra.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the Andes, Argentina is quickly waking up to its long-dormant mining potential.</p>
        <p>Attracted by a new mining code that sets uniform tax rates and allows duty-free imports of mining equipment, 30 foreign mining companies are exploring in Argentina. Of the $1 billion in private mining investment planned through the end of the decade, one of the largest projects is a $100 million development of a lithium mine by the FMC Corporation's lithium division, based in Gastonia, N.C.</p>
        <p>Large deals are on the horizon in still another Andean country, Colombia, which has long been off the maps of most international prospectors because of security problems in the countryside.</p>
        <p>The Colombian Government plans this year to sell its 50 percent interest in El Cerrejon, the world's largest open-pit coal mine. The Exxon Corporation owns the other half of the mine, which is near the Caribbean coast. Since 1981, Exxon has pumped $3 billion into the operation.</p>
        <p>Nearby, the Drummond Company of Birmingham, Ala., is investing $50 million this year to develop a private port for another coal mine.</p>
        <p>In Colombia's rough world of guerrilla armies and bandits, only big companies can afford the high security costs.</p>
        <p>WITH so much investment flowing south, environmentalists in the United States have taken issue with the view that red tape and pollution restrictions have contributed to the exodus.</p>
        <p>"The environmental excuse is bogus," said James S. Lyon, director of government affairs for the Mineral Policy Center, a nonprofit environmental organization based in Washington. "It is more a creaming process -- the international companies are going after the most efficient ore," he said.</p>
        <p>Noting that in several large Latin American countries, a majority of respondents to opinion surveys values environmental protection more than economic development, Philip M. Hocker, president of the center, warned: "We may be inviting a new wave of nationalizations if the conduct of our industry conveys to these folks that they are now the victims of environmental colonialism.</p>
        <p>"It would be a wonderful thing if the U.S. mining industry were to adopt a policy position collectively that it would operate to top environmental protection standards anywhere on the globe," he continued in a speech last February to American mining representatives in Albuquerque, N.M.</p>
        <p>For their part, mining companies deny charges that they are using sloppy, 1960's practices to dig minerals south of the border.</p>
        <p>"All the companies that I know of are putting in the same environmental equipment that they would in Canada," Mr. Livingstone said of investment in Latin America, noting that the Canadian rules are among the strictest in the world. "It is only a short time before these standards will be worldwide. It is better to put in the right technology at the start than to have to retrofit."</p>
        <p>And South American countries are putting teeth in their environmental laws. Last November, for example, Exxon temporarily closed its copper smelter in Chile for fear of exceeding its annual average limit for sulfur dioxide emissions. The six-week shutdown at Chagres meant the plant passed up producing 700,000 tons of copper -- about 10 percent of its annual production.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the diverse international structures of mining operations require compliance with international standards. For example, Newmont's $37 million gold mining and refining operations in the Peruvian Andes follow United States standards, in part because the World Bank is a minority investor.</p>
        <p>"If people think that you can come down here and avoid pollution controls, they are wrong," Mr. Harris of Newmont said. ELSEWHERE IN THE REGION</p>
        <p>IN a measure of the ideological distance traveled in Latin America, Cuba last year signed its first mining contract with Western countries since the Communist takeover in 1959. In two Canadian joint ventures with Geominera S.A., a Cuban state company, Miramar Mining of Vancouver, British Columbia, is to exploit an open-pit copper mine in eastern Cuba and Joutel Resources of Toronto is to prospect for gold, lead, silver and zinc in central and eastern Cuba.</p>
        <p>But nationalist inertia is blocking increased foreign mining investment in two of South America's richest countries, Venezuela and Brazil.</p>
        <p>Venezuela has not changed its mining laws since 1945 and little action is expected under its new President, Rafael Caldera.</p>
        <p>In Brazil, Latin America's largest country, delegates at a 1988 constitutional convention decided to restrict foreign mining capital to minority partnerships with Brazilian-controlled companies.</p>
        <p>Since then, foreign investment in mining exploration has plummeted to $9 million in 1992, from $57 million. The overall investment in developing existing mining concessions has dropped by more than half, to $500 million in 1992, from $1.1 billion.</p>
        <p>"There is almost no new American mining activity going on here," an American mining expert in Rio de Janeiro said.</p>
        <p>Last week, Brazil's Congress abandoned a six-month effort to amend the Constitution. Although surveys of congressional representatives showed that the majority wants to reopen mining to foreign investment, the Congress, divided among 19 political parties, failed to take any action.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Brazilian mining companies and engineers are scrambling to modernize after the country recently abandoned longstanding policies of restricting imports of computers and mining machinery.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
