<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Wild Things Are, Winter's a Life-and-Death Contest</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940306T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="669861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREENBURGH NATURE CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAWYER, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD8173BF933A15751C0A962958260" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Wild Things Are, Winter's a Life-and-Death Contest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR those concerned about the fate of wildlife this winter, the news is mixed. Naturalists say that while most animals and non-migrating birds can manage in extremely cold and snowy weather, some species, especially those that forage, are under stress. By March, wildlife experts predict, many animals -- especially deer -- will die of starvation.</p>
        <p>"Last winter, we had a big die-off of deer in March and April," said Beth Herr, curator of the Trailside Museum at the Ward Pound Ridge Reservation in Cross River. "We examined them and found they had starved to death. They had only 1.5 percent body fat."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR those concerned about the fate of wildlife this winter, the news is mixed. Naturalists say that while most animals and non-migrating birds can manage in extremely cold and snowy weather, some species, especially those that forage, are under stress. By March, wildlife experts predict, many animals -- especially deer -- will die of starvation.</p>
        <p>"Last winter, we had a big die-off of deer in March and April," said Beth Herr, curator of the Trailside Museum at the Ward Pound Ridge Reservation in Cross River. "We examined them and found they had starved to death. They had only 1.5 percent body fat."</p>
        <p>While deep snow makes foraging difficult for deer, ice storms help by bending branches down low enough for the deer to chew on, Ms. Herr said, as some county property owners may know only too well.</p>
        <p>Snow is a boon to rodents, however, who are having a wonderful winter, Ms. Herr said. They tunnel under the snow and stay hidden from predators like the red-tailed hawk, which is consequently under stress. Moles and voles can eat seeds that cling to ice-heavy bushes. When you spot ice crystals near openings in snow, you might have spotted a mole hole, the naturalist said, the crystals indicating condensation of the mole's breath.  Importance of Unmowed Meadow</p>
        <p>When she skis on the Cross River -- another boon of this icy winter is that the river's surface is frozen, she said -- Ms. Herr has spotted more hawks than usual cruising overhead. The ones with short wings can fly through the trees and scoop up songbirds. Since songbirds like cedar waxwings, bluebirds and others are spending more time at backyard feeders this year, forays near the cedars are proving profitable for the predators. "It all happens in a frenzy," Ms. Herr said of the hawk attacks.</p>
        <p>Birds lucky enough to find open meadow can avoid hawks and owls by remaining hidden in the dead grasses. At the Weinberg Nature Center in Scarsdale, "standing skeletons of wildflowers are maintained as a meadow through March as a cover from birds of prey," said Walter Terrell, the center's curator.</p>
        <p>Meadows also provide valuable food above snow level for wintering creatures, said Alison Beall, curator of the Marshlands Conservancy in Rye. "An unmowed meadow is a tremendously important habitat," Ms. Beall said. "People associate nature with trees and don't want to see trees cut down, but they lose sight of the fact that a meadow habitat is a whole different community."</p>
        <p>When wildflowers die, the seeds remain, and "for wildlife, the seed is the beauty" of the flower, Ms. Beall said. She demurred from the majority view that January's weather was cruel. "Recent winters have been very mild," she said. "This is the way it used to be; it's just another cycle."</p>
        <p>In Rye, too, there are more birds at feeders than usual, she said, but the real problem for wildlife is a lack of water. Underground springs are a valuable source of fresh water, she said, which is an important reason why wetlands should not be filled in.</p>
        <p>While the rodents cavort beneath the snowy blankets and beget young, field mice are also feasting on tree bark. This "girdling" of the trees worries the County Forester, Ted Kozlowski, who said that some trees were as threatened as animals by the unusually cold conditions. He said that while most plants and animals will survive, "the weaker ones, the ones on the bubble, can be pushed over the edge" by extreme weather.</p>
        <p>"When conditions get harsh, animals don't need to go into a nice warm house," he continued. "They burrow, they hunker down -- raccoons and oppossum in trees and burrows, deer in forested areas, birds in heavy brush and dense pine trees and squirrels in tree nests and in people's attics." He said people should be "more worried about the elderly and very young children" during this weather. "They suffer the most."</p>
        <p>Here in Greenburgh, the silence is often broken by the mating hoots of the great horned owl, said Bruce Lowder, museum curator at the Greenburgh Nature Center. Owls are breeding this month and even while covered with snow will sit on their nests to incubate their eggs. As a result, their young will be big enough to prey on the newer hatchlings of other birds later in the spring, Mr. Lowder said.</p>
        <p>While groundhogs and chipmunks are hibernating -- some remaining asleep for longer periods than others -- other animals are also mating despite the cold, said William Lawyer, director of the Greenburgh Nature Center. These include skunks and raccoons, whose babies will be born later this month and in early March, and squirrels. "The squirrels mate out and around -- on the ground and in the trees" whatever the temperature, Mr. Lawyer said.</p>
        <p>On one recent afternoon when the thermometer registered in the 30's, the bushes at the nature center were thick with chirping sparrows, while chickadees and squirrels shared the seeds in several bird feeders. Squirrels cavorted on the shoulders of scarecrows, giving a lift to winter-weary onlookers. Such respites from the cold should not lead people to stop stocking their bird feeders, all of the naturalists said.</p>
        <p>If they had any advice for those wishing to help wildlife survive, it was to feed consistently if at all, continuing to provide birds with sunflower seeds, fruit and water daily until March or April. Water can be heated by placing warming devices in bird baths, Ms. Beall said. Birds should also be given suet, or some kind of congealed fat like bacon grease, in a coffee can, Mr. Kozlowski said. Breads, however, act merely as filler and have little food value, he said.</p>
        <p>The forester advised people to protect their flowering trees, fruit trees and trees with soft bark by wrapping them with heavy-duty wire and fencing them to prevent mice from gnawing below the snow line. He also suggested using deer and rabbit repellents, naming Hinder and Big Game Deer Repellent as two that should be used together.</p>
        <p>Most of the naturalists advised against feeding deer, warning that the animals would probably become a nuisance. Those who insist on helping deer should do it the right way, said Glenn Cole, regional wildlife manager for Region 3 (Westchester and a half-dozen other counties to the north and west) for the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>"It is a real commitment of time, money and energy, because you have to get food to the deer," Mr. Cole said. A mixture of hardwood and softwood -- twigs from soft maple and apple branches, for example -- as well as corn and horse feed should be taken to the deer's habitat and spread around the area, Mr. Cole said. Once begun, the feeding must continue daily through March, because the animals will become dependent on it.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 6, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>A caption on Feb. 20 with an article about wildlife in winter misidentified a bird at a feeder at the Greenburgh Nature Center. It was a chickadee, not a tufted titmouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 6, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>A caption on Feb. 20 with an article about wildlife in winter misidentified a bird at a feeder at the Greenburgh Nature Center. It was a chickadee, not a tufted titmouse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
