<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hot Vents in the Sea Floor May Drive El Nino</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="758019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EL NINO (PACIFIC OCEAN CURRENT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTHQUAKES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALKER, DANIEL A (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D81330F936A15757C0A963958260" item-length="1673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hot Vents in the Sea Floor May Drive El Nino</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EL NINO, the climatic disturbance that brings droughts to Australia, famines to Africa, and floods to California, is a global visitation of mysterious origin. It occurs every two to seven years and normally lasts one or two years, in which time it can kill hundreds of people and destroy many billions of dollars in crops, fisheries and property.</p>
        <p>Teams of scientists find new kinds of damage from El Nino all the time but have made only marginal progress in understanding its genesis. This is why there has been only modest success at global warnings and predictions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EL NINO, the climatic disturbance that brings droughts to Australia, famines to Africa, and floods to California, is a global visitation of mysterious origin. It occurs every two to seven years and normally lasts one or two years, in which time it can kill hundreds of people and destroy many billions of dollars in crops, fisheries and property.</p>
        <p>Teams of scientists find new kinds of damage from El Nino all the time but have made only marginal progress in understanding its genesis. This is why there has been only modest success at global warnings and predictions.</p>
        <p>But now an intriguing explanation has been put forward for the cause of El Nino. Surprisingly, it has little to do with the atmosphere or the sea.</p>
        <p>The proposed prime mover is fiery lava from the earth's molten interior that erupts between tectonic plates on the Pacific sea floor, heating the overlying waters enough to affect the ocean's surface and bring on the fury of El Nino.</p>
        <p>An unusual spate of such seabed eruptions and their accompanying swarms of sea quakes predated the current El Nino cycle, which at four or five years of age is unusually old. One of this cycle's repercussions has been torrential rains in California and the longest drought in Australia's recorded history.</p>
        <p>"The seismicity was totally bizarre, maybe the most anomalous it's been in the past 30 years," Dr. Daniel A. Walker, a geophysicist at the University of Hawaii who is the author of the deep-lava theory, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>El Nino researchers, who tend to be meteorologists and oceanographers, have found little of merit in Dr. Walker's theory. Some dismiss it as absurd. Others say it is probably unneeded given the advances already under way in understanding the climatic trauma.</p>
        <p>But the theory recently got a boost from Dr. D. James Baker, Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, who at a recent symposium highlighted it as a possible explanation.</p>
        <p>Moreover, new research, financed partly by the oceanic agency, is revealing that the volcanism between tectonic plates on the sea floor is one of the strongest and least understood forces on earth, producing a vast heating of the seas equal to that of 3,000 big nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>That kind of heat rising from icy Pacific depths is worthy of close study and might conceivably be the progenitor of El Nino's global wrath, Dr. Walker said, carefully adding that the case for such causation is so far unproven.</p>
        <p>"I'm not saying I have the solution," he said. "But I have something here that is very interesting and plausible."</p>
        <p>By definition, El Nino is a warming of surface waters in the eastern Pacific near the equator. Its Spanish name is an allusion to the Christ child, because the warming current often flows near South and Central America around Christmas time.</p>
        <p>In a sketchy way, its cause is well known. The trade winds that normally blow westward across the south Pacific weaken and sometimes reverse themselves. As they falter warm Pacific surface waters that usually build up near Asia begin flowing eastward toward South America, bringing usually warm currents to the region.</p>
        <p>When the changes are especially strong, South American countries along the Pacific are lashed by heavy rains and rich fisheries are destroyed by the sudden warming of coastal waters. Meanwhile, Australia, Indonesia and southern Africa can experience droughts, even as the rest of the globe suffers its own mix of atmospheric consequences.</p>
        <p>The big question in all this is why the trade winds fail. By definition, these gusts are an atmospheric imbalance between a center of high pressure near Easter Island in the eastern Pacific and a zone of low pressure near Australia. The westward breezes are nature's attempt to try to establish an equilibrium.</p>
        <p>Dr. Walker had no intention of trying to solve the trade-wind riddle in 1971 when he installed on Easter Island a seismometer, a sensitive device that records earth rumbles. He was just doing basic geological research.</p>
        <p>But he immediately noticed something strange. The seismometer picked up periodic swarms of energy coming from the nearby seafloor. Rather quickly, he concluded that he was seeing plate tectonics in action, in particular the deep mayhem of volcanic spreading.</p>
        <p>The theory of plate tectonics holds that the slow churning of the earth's hot interior creates and destroys the earth's crust as huge plates slowly move from cradle to grave. The plates form in the abyss as hot lava erupts from the sea floor, buttressing new crust on either side of the fiery gash.</p>
        <p>Dr. Walker's seismic roar was coming from the most active of the earth's many spreading centers, the East Pacific Rise, a volcanic rent that runs far out to sea for thousands of miles from Mexico past the southernmost tip of South America. Significantly, Easter Island is just 300 miles away from the nearest point of its deep pandemonium.</p>
        <p>As he analyzed the periodic roar over the years, operating his Easter Island seismometer from 1971 to 1976, Dr. Walker noted that its biggest peaks coincided with what distant seismometers in South America saw as sea quakes. Clearly, his readings were many times more sensitive and suggested that a great deal of seabed activity was going unnoticed.</p>
        <p>Then, in the early 1980's, he began paying close attention to the scientific literature on El Nino as a particularly cruel one devastated the Pacific coast of South America. He soon learned that the atmospheric upheaval was accompanied by the weakening of the high-pressure zone near Easter Island and thus the weakening of the trade winds.</p>
        <p>"That's all it took," Dr. Walker recalled. "Just that statement and my mind went click."</p>
        <p>Furiously, he began examining decades of global seismic records to see if sea quakes on the East Pacific Rise correlated with the El Nino cycles. To his eye, they did, strongly. Moreover, from personal experience he knew that those records reflected only the tip of the seismic iceberg.</p>
        <p>Sure his thesis would be hotly disputed, Dr. Walker carefully gathered more evidence and waited until 1988 to lay out his arguments in EOS, a scholarly publication of the American Geophysical Union, a professional group based in Washington. He dwelled heavily on the correlations, sketching only lightly the possible mechanism of rising hot water. If it indeed reached the surface, the water would warm the air above and weaken the high-pressure cell near Easter Island.</p>
        <p>A conspicuous gap was his inability to show this linkage. Virtually no data existed on the oceanic repercussions of deep eruptions.</p>
        <p>But that began to change in the 1990's as American scientists probed a spreading center close to the West Coast of the United States known as the Juan de Fuca ridge. Carefully monitoring the explosive fury of deep eruptions, they discovered huge upwellings of warm water, which they dubbed megaplumes. These were tracked to up to a kilometer off the sea floor, short of the surface.</p>
        <p>But a possible mechanism for the first time had begun to be documented, making surface effects all the more plausible.</p>
        <p>This January, Dr. Walker again took to the pages of EOS, noting the recent findings on hot volcanic plumes and the unusually strong set of eruptions on the East Pacific Rise that accompanied the onset of this particularly long El Nino. He also sketched possible mechanisms in new detail.</p>
        <p>In addition to direct warming of the surface, he proposed that hot plumes might alter deep currents to affect surface temperatures. Another indirect mechanism was that the nutrient value of the minerals in hot plumes might prompt prolific growths of microscopic sea creatures that would rise to the surface or whose body parts would rise. This biological matter, he speculated, could make surface waters more opaque and increasingly prone to soak up the abundant heat of sunlight.</p>
        <p>"Continuing research," he concluded cautiously, "will be needed to determine the actual existence and nature of an extension of hydrothermal effects from midlevel to surface waters."</p>
        <p>The reaction of traditional El Nino researchers to Dr. Walker's deep-lava thesis ranges from bad to worse. In essence, they feel they have already discovered the makings of a comprehensive mechanism that requires no deep heat. It holds that surging oceanic currents and associated atmospheric phenomena are natural oscillations not unlike the swings of a pendulum. The continuous back-and-forth action happens according to its own internal rhythm, which they say is beginning to be understood well enough so that El Nino behavior can be predicted about a year in advance.</p>
        <p>"It's complete nonsense," Dr. James O'Brien, an El Nino researcher at Florida State University, said of the deep-lava thesis in an interview. "This is bad science."</p>
        <p>Dr. Eugene Rasmussen, a meteorologist and senior El Nino scientist based at the University of Maryland, was more sympathetic to the theory, calling it interesting but probably unnecessary. "There's enough theory so that one doesn't need to evoke volcanoes," he said in an interview. "The dynamics of the coupled system seem to be enough."</p>
        <p>In rejoinder, Dr. Walker, the theory's author, says that periodic deep eruptions might simply modify the natural oscillations of sea and atmosphere, stressing that he is not proposing volcanism as the sole cause.</p>
        <p>Further, he charges that the specialists on El Nino are prejudiced against new thinking. He says this conservatism is probably rooted in an unconscious disciplinary bias whereby one field of science is loath to accept the intrusions of another, just as paleontologists tended to resist the idea of geologists and planetary scientists that the dinosaurs were wiped out by a speeding object from outer space.</p>
        <p>"The idea is not getting the recognition and the open mindedness that I think it deserves," he said. "It's geology, and it's being ignored. Yet at the same time we're spending millions of dollars in other disciplines to solve the El Nino problem. What does that say about science?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
