<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Along With A.L. West Competition, Rangers Also Face Heat Hurdle</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="775299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN LEAGUE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEXAS RANGERS (BASEBALL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DC123FF935A25754C0A963958260" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Along With A.L. West Competition, Rangers Also Face Heat Hurdle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs, one long-held theory goes, cannot win pennants because of the many day games they play in the hot summer months. The Texas Rangers don't play many day games, but a similar theory holds that they can't win either because the heat and humidity they play in are even more oppressive than the Cubs face.</p>
        <p>After spending a couple of days in the Arlington heat last week for the All-Star Game, baseball people who might not previously have experienced it gained a better understanding of the heat hurdle the Rangers have to overcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs, one long-held theory goes, cannot win pennants because of the many day games they play in the hot summer months. The Texas Rangers don't play many day games, but a similar theory holds that they can't win either because the heat and humidity they play in are even more oppressive than the Cubs face.</p>
        <p>After spending a couple of days in the Arlington heat last week for the All-Star Game, baseball people who might not previously have experienced it gained a better understanding of the heat hurdle the Rangers have to overcome.</p>
        <p>Charlie Hough, the retired knuckleball pitcher who has labored through more innings in that heat than any other pitcher, said he didn't know if the heat has made it more difficult for the Rangers to win.</p>
        <p>"When I was here," said Hough, an All-Star visitor, who pitched 2,307 2/3 innings for the Rangers from 1980 through 1990, "basically I think we were a little short personnel-wise. I think you can get used to the heat."</p>
        <p>But Hough and other former Rangers acknowledged that the heat can affect players, especially those who play every day.</p>
        <p>"It has an effect on you; there's no doubt," said Yankees catcher Mike Stanley, who spent five seasons with the Rangers. "Late June and July and August, those are the dog days here. It's not an easy place to play. It's physically draining each and every day. You have to stay on top of your liquids and stay out of it as much as you can."</p>
        <p>Stanley, who was platooned with the Rangers, said the weather becomes "a mental thing," too.</p>
        <p>"Just knowing as soon as you walk out of the air-conditioning, all of a sudden that heat wave hits you," he said. "It's like being baked in an oven. Another day in the hundreds. It wears on you."</p>
        <p>Stanley said the best way to handle the heat is to "allow yourself the time to do the things you need to prepare yourself for the game and once it's over, come inside in the air-conditioning."</p>
        <p>Nolan Ryan, a Ranger for five years, adopted the opposite approach.</p>
        <p>"I conditioned for the heat," he said. "I knew at my age that was going to be a situation I had to address. I knew coming in here from California, where we weren't used to humidity and we weren't used to that heat. I stayed in it all the time. I worked long periods in the heat so I would be adjusted to it."</p>
        <p>Hough, who like Ryan pitched into his 40's, said he, too, followed the sun. "That's the way I always felt about it," he said. "I felt I had to get out in the sun, get used to being hot and sweating for two, three hours. Then you take that right out to the ball game."</p>
        <p>But both Ryan and Hough agreed that what worked for them and might work for other pitchers wouldn't necessarily work for everyday players.</p>
        <p>"It wears on you," Ryan said. "I think the recovery time is longer. You just get drained. Management has to be aware of it and they have to use their bench accordingly. A good example is Pudge," he added, referring to catcher Ivan Rodriguez. "Keep him fresh. You rest those kind of guys the day before an off day or the day after so you give him a couple of days where you have a meaningful rest and you can rebound."</p>
        <p>Hough said everyday players have difficulty having a good pregame workout, then playing the game. "You can do one or the other," he said, adding that the heat eventually affects them. "It can wear them down," he said. "They have to watch the amount of work they put in."</p>
        <p>Ryan said he believed the heat can be a factor in the Rangers' quest for a division championship but added: "As long as management is aware of it, you can take the precautions that you can, but it's one of those factors you have to deal with. It's important that management realize that and use your bench more."</p>
        <p>The current Rangers management says it has such plans.</p>
        <p>"We've been talking about it since the winter," Omar Minaya, the team's professional scouting director, said. "That's why we got Valle and McLemore. People thought we overpaid for him, but he was worth more to us than to other people."</p>
        <p>Dave Valle is the backup catcher to Rodriguez; Mark McLemore was supposed to be a utility player but became a regular from the start of the season when Juan Gonzalez was out with a bad back.</p>
        <p>The Rangers never have won a division championship. They finished first last year, when it didn't count, but in their previous 22 years in Texas, the closest they came to first was four second-place finishes five games from first each time. Tewksbury's Last Laugh</p>
        <p>Just before the All-Star Game break, Bob Tewksbury pitched a six-hit shutout against the Yankees in Texas. Getting a first-row view of Tewksbury's performance was George Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>"In a pink shirt," Tewksbury said. "I looked at him every half inning."</p>
        <p>Nearly eight years ago to the day, Steinbrenner made a telephone call involving Tewksbury. "Lou," Steinbrenner said to Lou Piniella, his manager of the moment, "I just won you the pennant. I got you Steve Trout."</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner got Trout from the Chicago Cubs by trading Tewksbury, who was in his second season with the Yankees. While the Yankees have been scrapping for starting pitching ever since, Tewksbury has flourished and become one of the most consistent starters in the major leagues. From 1991 to this weekend, Tewksbury is tied for eighth for most victories with 63.</p>
        <p>Of course, there's no guarantee that as he watched the game in Texas, Steinbrenner even remembered that he once had Tewksbury. In case he doesn't remember Trout, the pitcher the owner traded for did not win the pennant for Piniella. He compiled a 0-4 record with a 6.60 earned run average. Braves Just Warming Up</p>
        <p>Fred McGriff has terrible news for would-be National League champions: The Atlanta Braves are just starting to play well.</p>
        <p>"We have a young team," said McGriff, whose hits won three games in a six-game span. "We're not the team the Braves were in '92 and '93. It's a team that had to get confidence. Lately we've been playing with a lot of confidence."</p>
        <p>The Braves won their first nine games this month, but they began their march back to first place at the middle of last month.</p>
        <p>"We had a 10-day road trip to Montreal, Colorado and Cincinnati," McGriff related. "That was a big point of our season. If we played bad on the trip, it could be a long year. But we won 7 of 10 and it gave us the confidence we needed. We knew we could play with the Cincinnatis and the Philadelphias."</p>
        <p>The Braves were five games behind the Phillies in third place when that trip began. Atlanta began last night's game five games ahead of the Phillies. Wagner's Work in Progress</p>
        <p>Paul Wagner, who struggled with his pitching before going on the disabled list with a strained groin, walked past Jim Leyland in the Pittsburgh dugout at Three Rivers Stadium before a game the other day.</p>
        <p>"I've got you scheduled to start the 21st," the Pirates' manager said. "Your arm O.K.?"</p>
        <p>"It needs work," Wagner replied.</p>
        <p>"It needs work?" Leyland repeated with mock outrage. "I know it needs work. You're 1 and 10. Obviously, it needs work." Cooling-Off Period</p>
        <p>Mike Benjamin, usually a utility infielder for the San Francisco Giants, erupted in a frenzy of hits last month, amassing 14 in 18 at-bats in a three-game stretch. In 19 games since then, he has collected 12 hits in 64 at-bats.  BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
