<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surprising Scientists, Full Moon Is Found to Play Role in Warming the Earth</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="747961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEMPERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CERVENY, RANDALL S (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BALLING, ROBERT C JR (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDD1331F933A25750C0A963958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surprising Scientists, Full Moon Is Found to Play Role in Warming the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pale light of the full Moon may not tan a midnight swimmer's skin, but scientists have discovered that it does warm Earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In a paper being published today in the journal Science, researchers at Arizona State University at Tempe present evidence that the full Moon raises the temperature of Earth's lower troposphere by more than 0.03 of one degree Fahrenheit. This region of the troposphere extends from the ground to an altitude of about three and a half miles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pale light of the full Moon may not tan a midnight swimmer's skin, but scientists have discovered that it does warm Earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In a paper being published today in the journal Science, researchers at Arizona State University at Tempe present evidence that the full Moon raises the temperature of Earth's lower troposphere by more than 0.03 of one degree Fahrenheit. This region of the troposphere extends from the ground to an altitude of about three and a half miles.</p>
        <p>Polar-orbiting satellites have furnished daily tropospheric temperature measurements spanning the world since 1979, said the scientists, Dr. Robert C. Balling Jr. and Dr. Randall S. Cerveny. Their analysis of 15 years of these measurements has turned up the surprising conclusion that a very slight but statistically significant warming reaches a peak coinciding with the full Moon.</p>
        <p>The slight daily influence of moonlight on atmospheric temperature was measured by instruments aboard satellites able to record the microwave emissions of atmospheric oxygen. The intensity of such emissions affords a precise measure of the temperature of the gas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Balling acknowledged that "the relationship between lunar phase and global temperature begs the question as to its fundamental cause," but he cited several theories that might account for it.</p>
        <p>It is likely, he said, that the main mechanism is infrared radiation from the Sun reflected by the Moon toward Earth, coupled with infrared radiation from the Moon itself. Although infrared radiation from the Moon is only one-100,000th as intense as the infrared arriving directly from the Sun, much of this radiation is absorbed in the lower atmosphere and tends to heat it.</p>
        <p>Visible light from the Moon also probably affects global temperature, the Arizona group said, although lunar light is only a millionth as strong as direct sunlight.</p>
        <p>The importance of the discovery, Dr. Balling said, is that the phase of the Moon must now be taken into account in analyzing short-time global temperature records. As many scientists have long suspected, he said, the Moon may exert an influence on atmospheric circulation patterns, and therefore on weather.</p>
        <p>"Up close, the Moon looks as dark as asphalt, but it reflects more radiation than you'd think," Dr. Balling said.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, lunar effects on terrestrial weather could be indirect; the Moon's tidal influence on Earth's atmospheric circulation, a lunar distortion of Earth's magnetic tail, or a lunar influence on the fall of meteor dust into the atmosphere have all been suggested as possibilities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
