<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Storm Unloads Rain on California</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="736802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD163FF937A25752C0A963958260" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Storm Unloads Rain on California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Jan. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new storm front rolled in off the Pacific today and began giving California yet another drenching.</p>
        <p>The front hit land first in the rugged redwood region of Humboldt and Mendocino Counties north of here, then moved steadily inland and south down a soggy coast already heavily damaged by flooding from a week and a half of rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new storm front rolled in off the Pacific today and began giving California yet another drenching.</p>
        <p>The front hit land first in the rugged redwood region of Humboldt and Mendocino Counties north of here, then moved steadily inland and south down a soggy coast already heavily damaged by flooding from a week and a half of rain.</p>
        <p>The latest storm, which according to one forecast could dump as much as six inches of rain in some areas this weekend, threatened to add to the particularly heavy flooding of the Eel and Russian Rivers in Mendocino County, perhaps the state's most severely affected region.</p>
        <p>"Now it's all going to start up again," said Ted Simon, a 63-year-old resident of Mendocino who is the author of "The River Stops Here," a book about the Eel River. "I was just in the store, and everyone's saying, 'Oh God, what are we in for?' People have been very battered by this.</p>
        <p>"Everything's been swept away. Trees have fallen right, left and center. A lot of people live in the woods, under redwoods and fir trees, so many of them have been hit by falling trees."</p>
        <p>Here in a state grown accustomed to wildfires, earthquakes and mudslides, it is nevertheless apparent that across a sprawling stretch of California -- from the rugged canyons of Trinity County in the north to the vineyards of the Napa Valley to toney Malibu -- things could hardly be worse.</p>
        <p>Much of the famed coastal Highway 1 is closed in Sonoma County, north of San Francisco, because of mud and rock slides. The California Office of Emergency Services says some 3,000 people have been forced from their homes, and the Federal Government has declared 34 counties disaster areas. About 5,000 people have already applied for assistance from the Federal Emergency Management Agency, whose director, James Lee Witt, toured California earlier this week. Hundreds of residents, scattered across the flooded region, have been without power for days.</p>
        <p>In addition, hundreds of thousands of Californians must now boil their drinking water because the floods have contaminated their water supplies. Among those so affected today were 100,000 people in Escondido, 20 miles north of San Diego, and 65,000 in Ventura, 60 miles northwest of Los Angeles. But the contamination problem has extended to the north as well, including Monterey County, the small town of Guerneville north of San Francisco and Sacramento, where a 24-inch water line in the southwestern section of the city was washed out.</p>
        <p>State officials said that the recent series of storms had already caused damage of at least $200 million and that the sum was expected to surpass easily the $304 million in damage left by winter storms two years ago. At least 11 people have died as a result of the severe weather, according to the state. Along the Russian River, near the inland city of Ukiah in Mendocino County, the current has been so deep and swift that a flood gauge station operated by the United States Geological Survey was swept away earlier this week.</p>
        <p>"The gauge house was destroyed, and the pipe that goes from the house to the river was lost," said James Mullen, a hydrologist with the Geological Survey. "But we knew about it in time to recover the instruments."</p>
        <p>Karl Swanberg, a forecaster with the National Weather Service in Northern California, said the latest storm was expected to last until Sunday. It originated in the Hawaiian islands and was strengthened by El Nino, a Pacific warming pattern that typically emerges about this time of year.</p>
        <p>"Basically we have a significant system moving in," Mr. Swanberg said, "and it is expected to aggravate the flooding situation across Northern California."</p>
        <p>Katherine Queen, executive director of the Humboldt County Farm Bureau, said, "People are preparing for the worst, because that's the information we've been getting."</p>
        <p>But even as Californians braced for another very wet weekend, this was also a day of some respite: rain from a front that had swept ashore earlier in the week tapered off across much of the state, where the new storm had not yet hit, allowing some careful assessments of the damage. Thousands of people without telephone service sought help from Pacific Bell, said David Miller, a spokesman for the company.</p>
        <p>Some of the damage has been grisly. In Humboldt County, hundreds of sheep and dairy cows drowned earlier this week in flood waters from the Eel River south of Eureka. Their carcasses are now hung on barbed wire fences near town, pushed there by the floods, and the county authorities have called in the National Guard and California conservation crews to remove them.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people were not expecting the water to rise as fast as it did," said Ms. Queen, of the Humboldt County Farm Bureau. "People were planning on Monday morning to move their animals out of the low-lying land, and Sunday evening the water rose so quickly that the animals were caught in the stream. It's horrible."</p>
        <p>But the rains have also brought acts of thoughtfulness. On Wednesday, said Mr. Simon, the Eel River chronicler, workers at a Safeway supermarket in Fort Bragg, a Mendocino County town, barbecued all the store's meat and served it to some 300 people who had lined up. "A lot of people were anxious for some hot food," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
