<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Efficient Pollution Rule Under Attack</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOTT, TRENT (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, J BENNETT (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D7113CF93BA15755C0A963958260" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Efficient Pollution Rule Under Attack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senators attacking Federal regulations have taken aim at what would seem to be one of the least burdensome but most effective of environmental rules: a requirement that manufacturers disclose how much they pollute.</p>
        <p>Senators J. Bennett Johnston, Democrat of Louisiana, and Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi, are trying to narrow the program that costs little besides paperwork and requires no specific pollution controls but that has spurred industry to reduce emissions of toxic chemicals voluntarily by billions of pounds a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senators attacking Federal regulations have taken aim at what would seem to be one of the least burdensome but most effective of environmental rules: a requirement that manufacturers disclose how much they pollute.</p>
        <p>Senators J. Bennett Johnston, Democrat of Louisiana, and Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi, are trying to narrow the program that costs little besides paperwork and requires no specific pollution controls but that has spurred industry to reduce emissions of toxic chemicals voluntarily by billions of pounds a year.</p>
        <p>At the urging of chemical companies, a provision to scale the program back has been tucked into a far-reaching regulatory-relief bill that may come to the Senate floor this week. The Administration has threatened to veto the sweeping measure; Senate Democrats are also threatening a filibuster. The House has already passed a similar measure.</p>
        <p>The provision would strike hundreds of chemicals from the list of toxic emissions that must be reported each year to the Environmental Protection Agency, which then makes the data public, state by state and factory by factory.</p>
        <p>States and local residents have found the information a powerful and versatile tool for pressing companies to reduce pollution. Local officials also use it to plan how to handle industrial accidents, and labor unions have used it to demand in contract negotiations reductions in hazardous emissions in work places.</p>
        <p>The latest reports show that industrial releases of toxic chemicals in the United States dropped by 12.6 percent in 1993, to about 2.8 billion pounds. That is a reduction of nearly 43 percent since 1988, when the program started. The scope of the disclosure law has steadily been increased since the program started. The data now cover about 23,000 factories.</p>
        <p>Some pollution reductions were required by other, more forceful regulations, but most experts say the numbers accurately reflect the effect of the disclosure requirements. On the other hand, a study of company reports in 1992 by an advocacy group, Citizen Action, found that some gains had been exaggerated.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, environmentalists and local residents object to the proposal to scale back the program. Senate aides on both sides of the issue said the amendment was drafted with the help of lobbyists for the chemical industry.</p>
        <p>Under the provision, the Environmental Protection Agency would have to drop hundreds of chemicals that were added to the list six months ago unless the agency could prove that removing a chemical from the list "presents a foreseeable significant risk to human health or the environment." The agency contends that it should bear no such burden of proof since the program requires nothing beyond disclosure.</p>
        <p>"The whole point of it is, people have a right to know," said Carol M. Browner, the agency's Administrator, who has made the program's expansion a priority.</p>
        <p>Critics of the pollution-disclosure program, known as the Toxics Release Inventory, say that the raw numbers disclose little or nothing about the risks posed by the emissions and that for this reason the program is fundamentally flawed.</p>
        <p>When Senator Lott first introduced an amendment requiring the agency to justify its listings, he said: "The E.P.A. has let the T.R.I. misrepresent the toxicity of chemicals, and permitted unnecessary anxiety within local communities. This is terrible policy."</p>
        <p>A somewhat different version of the amendment was inserted by Senator Johnston in the larger bill, which is sponsored by the Senate majority leader, Bob Dole. Senator Johnston's state ranks highest for releases of toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>But even the chemical companies that lobbied for the changes concede that the existing program has merit. "We continue to believe that T.R.I. has been a very successful venture," said Mort Mullins, vice president for regulatory affairs at the Chemical Manufacturers Association. "Our members have gotten behind it and witnessed a 50 percent reduction in pollution."</p>
        <p>But he said the proposal to change the listings "does not look unreasonable to me."</p>
        <p>Paul Orum, who heads the Working Group on Community Right-To-Know, an environmental advocacy group in Washington, said that despite its public stance, the chemical industry had been "trying to gut this law for years."</p>
        <p>Almost as soon as the information on toxic releases became widely available, big corporations promised publicly to cut their emissions voluntarily. Monsanto was the first, vowing in 1989 to reduce its worldwide air emissions of toxic chemicals by 90 percent within three years. Many others, including AT&amp;T, Dow Chemical, Dupont, Merck and 3M, quickly followed.</p>
        <p>"I frankly think that it has had more beneficial impact on stemming the discharge of chemicals into the environment than many years of traditional rule-making under the Clean Air Act," said Deborah Shprentz, an air-quality specialist at the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>The program's advocates say that chemicals are carefully screened before being added to the list and that there is already a process for petitioning to have them removed. They say the burden of proof called for in the new proposals would be impossible to meet and would lead to many hazardous chemicals' being dropped from the list.</p>
        <p>Twelve states assess fees on the basis of reports filed under the disclosure law. For example, Colorado charges companies up to $25 for each hazardous material at a site; the fee supports a small pollution-prevention fund. And seven states require pollution-prevention plans from plants reporting under the law.  Often the plans save money for the companies.</p>
        <p>Brian D. Towns, an environmental specialist for the Galileo Electro-Optics Corporation, in Sturbridge, Mass., said the company had once reported the emissions of five chemicals but in 1994 whittled emissions down to two chemicals and next year would cut emissions to the point that no reports would be required. The company estimates that it has cut its costs by $150,000 a year, he said at a conference in December.</p>
        <p>But many companies seek to avoid the program altogether.</p>
        <p>Last week, the environmental agency proposed fining 47 companies a total of $2.6 million for emitting toxic chemicals into the environment without reporting the discharges under the disclosure law.</p>
        <p>In the past, however, the agency has been willing to settle charges against violators of the rules by allowing them to take remedial steps rather than paying fines.</p>
        <p>The ripple effect from the law is steadily expanding, serving to increase the opposition of chemical manufacturers and other industries. In December, the E.P.A. expanded by 286 chemicals the list of those that must be reported.</p>
        <p>The agency is also has developing a rule that would add many nonmanufacturing firms to the program, including electric utilities, which emit several times as much mercury into the atmosphere as is currently reported under the program.</p>
        <p>And in the most notable expansion of all, the agency wants to tabulate not only how much toxic material is emitted as waste, but also how much is taken in by each plant as raw materials and sent out in the form of products, not pollution. The industry strongly opposes this idea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
