<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Days Have Become Earth Years</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="757321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D6103BF930A15757C0A963958260" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Days Have Become Earth Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Al Gore;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yesterday, even as our thoughts and prayers were focused on the tragedy in Oklahoma City, we took time to remember that 25 years ago, a simple idea for a teach-in exploded into a national event involving 20 million people that changed the course of history.  Following the first Earth Day, our nation built from scratch the most advanced health and environmental safeguards in the world. It is a great American success story that proves the old-fashioned idea that individuals can make a difference, that when the people speak, their leaders can listen and do something about it. It ought to be a source of inspiration.</p>
        <p>After all, in the past 25 years, we've cut air pollution by a third, even though we drive twice as many cars twice as many miles as we did then. We've cut emissions of lead by 98 percent, and countless children are the better for it. Twice as many rivers and lakes are safe for swimming. And where 25 years ago boxes and beer cans lined the roadways, today people of all ages are recycling in 6,000 community programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yesterday, even as our thoughts and prayers were focused on the tragedy in Oklahoma City, we took time to remember that 25 years ago, a simple idea for a teach-in exploded into a national event involving 20 million people that changed the course of history.  Following the first Earth Day, our nation built from scratch the most advanced health and environmental safeguards in the world. It is a great American success story that proves the old-fashioned idea that individuals can make a difference, that when the people speak, their leaders can listen and do something about it. It ought to be a source of inspiration.</p>
        <p>After all, in the past 25 years, we've cut air pollution by a third, even though we drive twice as many cars twice as many miles as we did then. We've cut emissions of lead by 98 percent, and countless children are the better for it. Twice as many rivers and lakes are safe for swimming. And where 25 years ago boxes and beer cans lined the roadways, today people of all ages are recycling in 6,000 community programs.</p>
        <p>What now? Where do we go from here and how do we get there?</p>
        <p>On the day after the first Earth Day, The New York Times wrote: "Conservatives were for it. Liberals were for it. Democrats, Republicans, and independents were for it. So were the ins, the outs, the executive and legislative branches of Government." Today, that support is still there. Recent polls show that 53 percent of the people think government action to protect the environment does not go far enough, while another 23 percent think we are on the right track. Only 16 percent think Government regulation on the environment has gone too far.</p>
        <p>But this time, bipartisanship is hanging by a thread. The Republican Congress is pushing an extreme anti-environmental agenda. It would freeze all health and environmental protection, effectively repeal 25 years of health protection through a "risk assessment" bill and allow industry to hold up environmental safeguards through endless lawsuits. It would even require taxpayers to pay polluters not to pollute.</p>
        <p>The Republicans have turned over the legislative process to lobbyists. The freeze on new health, safety and environmental standards was written by a coalition of wealthy special- interest lobbyists, who were even given a room off the House floor to write amendments and furnish talking points for lawmakers. The Senate committee used lobbyists to explain the legislation to staff. And the committee worked side by side with lobbyists to write loopholes into the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>So this time, the future will bring two struggles: the first, to prevent the rollback of the gains we have made, and the second, to reinvent environmental protection in order to make further gains. On the first, we will fight. On the second, we will join with those who want to build on the lessons learned since 1970.</p>
        <p>What have we learned? First, collaborative processes work better than adversarial ones. Second, flexibility works better than one-size-fits-all dictates. Third, Washington doesn't have all the answers, and we should shift some responsibilities from central bureaucracies to local communities. Fourth, pollution is often a sign of economic inefficiency, and you can make money by preventing it.</p>
        <p>Here is an example of things to come. Recently, President Clinton announced 25 reforms to make environmental protection work better and cost less. Through Project "XL" -- our project in excellence in leadership -- we will move from a one-size-fits-all system to a system based on real results and common sense. It's the first program in the next generation of environmental protection -- cleaner for the environment, cheaper for business and taxpayers and smarter and safer for our children's future. And just last week, we unveiled our new national environmental strategy to promote development and export of a new generation of technologies to improve both environmental and economic performance. This strategy is one of the best examples of "reinventing government" -- where the Federal Government acts as a partner with industry and local governments.</p>
        <p>We are also making use of the Government's purchasing power, with executive orders to cut the use of toxic substances by 50 percent by 1999 and to improve energy and water efficiency -- a move estimated to cut the Government's utility bills by $1 billion annually by the year 2005. Similarly, to boost recycling and to reduce the burden on landfills, the President signed an executive order directing Federal agencies to purchase recycled and environmentally preferable products. The Government is the largest purchaser of goods and services in the world, so it makes sense to put that purchasing power to work.</p>
        <p>There have been other actions taken in this spirit. The Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles between Government and industry will develop a new generation of vehicles up to three times more fuel efficient than today's -- and strengthen our competitiveness. A new incineration policy will result in a 95 percent reduction in emissions of dangerous pollutants. The proposed reform of the Superfund program will make life safer for the one in four Americans who still live near a toxic dump site, 14 years after Love Canal. Too much money that should have gone to clean up toxic dumps was spent on lawyers.</p>
        <p>We are also pursuing new approaches on the international front. At the 1994 International Conference on Population and Development, in Cairo, the U.S. helped forge a historic consensus on a global program to stabilize population growth through increased availability of family planning services, a commitment to improving women's health, the empowerment of women and a reduction in infant and child mortality.</p>
        <p>We are implementing a comprehensive national strategy to reduce greenhouse-gas emissions to 1990 levels in the year 2000 -- a commitment renewed last month in Berlin. Already, more than 800 of the nation's electric utility companies have signed voluntary pledges to limit greenhouse- gas emissions</p>
        <p>Similarly, in London, the U.S. took the lead among the world's nuclear powers and achieved a global ban on ocean dumping of radioactive waste. The U.S. was the first of the nuclear powers to advocate the ban. We have also succeeded in creating a whale sanctuary in the southern ocean around Antarctica. Commercial whaling will now be prohibited in an enormous area of the ocean that is home to three-quarters of the world's whales.</p>
        <p>So while others may conclude that the future of our environment is unclear, I am optimistic. And so is the President, who has made it clear that he will fight hard to prevent a return to the days before that first Earth Day 25 years and one day ago. As he said in Dallas on March 16: "I cannot and will not compromise any clean water, any clean air, any protection against toxic waste. The environment cannot protect itself. And if it requires a Presidential veto to protect it, then that's what I'll provide."  Al Gore is Vice President of the United States and author of "Earth in the Balance."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Al Gore is Vice President of the United States and author of "Earth in the Balance."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
