<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Developers' Hazard: Legal Hardball</title>
    <meta content="08COV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D8163FF93BA35751C1A960958260" item-length="2266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Developers' Hazard: Legal Hardball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Litigation is part of standard operating procedure for New York City real estate developments of any consequence; suits and threats of suits help shape strategy early in development process; project opponents need not win in court to derail or force major changes in projects; drawing; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO one knows yet whether the Columbus Circle redevelopment project will wind up as a Sears or Sotheby's, a Reebok health spa or the Museum of American Folk Art, a swank hotel or a high-priced condominium apartment tower. But there is one safe bet. It will almost certainly wind up in court.</p>
        <p>With months to go before the Metropolitan Transportation Authority selects finalists from among competing proposals for the New York Coliseum site, the chorus of litigants is already warming up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO one knows yet whether the Columbus Circle redevelopment project will wind up as a Sears or Sotheby's, a Reebok health spa or the Museum of American Folk Art, a swank hotel or a high-priced condominium apartment tower. But there is one safe bet. It will almost certainly wind up in court.</p>
        <p>With months to go before the Metropolitan Transportation Authority selects finalists from among competing proposals for the New York Coliseum site, the chorus of litigants is already warming up.</p>
        <p>Neighborhood groups are not the only ones huddling with lawyers. The Municipal Art Society may take legal action. And one competitor, Donald J. Trump, has threatened to use ''force'' (presumably of the jurisprudential variety) to protect the views from his nearly completed Trump International Hotel and Tower across Broadway.</p>
        <p>As astonishing as Mr. Trump's tactic seems, he is simply following -- with customary rhetorical flourishes -- standard operating procedure for almost any development of consequence in New York City: Project gets reviewed. Project gets approved. Project gets sued.</p>
        <p>''New York is one of the few places where litigation, and the threat of litigation, help determine strategy early on in the development process,'' said Carl Weisbrod, former president of the city's Economic Development Corporation and the 42d Street Development Project Inc.</p>
        <p>Lawsuits are no longer last resorts. They are an integral part of the process. Litigation has altered the 42d Street redevelopment in Manhattan and the building of Atlantic Center in downtown Brooklyn; it has derailed other projects entirely, like Westway and Columbus Center, the previous proposal for the Coliseum site.</p>
        <p>''It is almost impossible to finance a project when it's in litigation,'' said Bruce C. Ratner, president of Forest City Ratner Companies, which inherited Atlantic Center after the legal buffeting. ''Even if there's a remote chance that the plaintiffs will win, the banks are not going to lend the quantities of money required.''</p>
        <p>More often than not, opponents do not prevail in court. But they need not win to achieve their goal. ''Delay is money and they hope and pray that their delay will cause someone to walk out and leave the project,'' said Edward I. Koch, a lawyer himself, who faced many lawsuits in his 12 years as Mayor. ''It's a strategic effort, knowing that they have no chance of winning.''</p>
        <p>To reduce their risk, developers often begin their defense with numbingly exhaustive environmental impact statements. These documents can run to thousands of pages, and carry price tags up to $1 million or more. Legal fees easily reach hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>Add to that the costs of carrying fallow land, securing financing commitments and mounting a public-relations campaign outside the courtroom, and a lawsuit can become a multimillion-dollar item on the budget.</p>
        <p>''We've gotten to the point where part of the overall evaluation of a project, including its price, is what would be the likely impact of litigation,'' said Christopher M. Jeffries, a founder and principal of Millennium Partners, one of the Coliseum bidders. In the final meeting before submitting its proposal, the Millennium team considered six key issues. Prospective lawsuits were among them.</p>
        <p>''It's an interesting comment on the times that it's as important a consideration as the architecture,'' Mr. Jeffries said. ''The dollars involved at a project like the Coliseum are so enormous that to purchase the land and have to sit there for three or four years could be devastating to the development.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, local businesses and residents may believe they have no choice but to sue.</p>
        <p>''When you're representing community interests, a lawsuit is all you have,'' said Douglas N. Cogen, former staff counsel to the Municipal Art Society. ''You can't outbid a developer. You can't count on the governmental approval process to respect noneconomic issues. But you can file a complaint. And that gets people's attention.''</p>
        <p>It certainly got the banks' attention when Anthony Clemenza was trying to finance his 56,000-square-foot Loehmann's Seaport Plaza project, on Emmons Avenue in the Sheepshead Bay section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>In July 1995, after five years of effort, he won a variance from the Board of Standards and Appeals allowing a 28,000-square-foot store in a district with a 3,500-square-foot limit. A lawsuit by a neighborhood organization called the Bay Improvement Group faulted the absence of an environmental impact statement, charging that issues like flooding and traffic had been ignored or given short shrift.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clemenza said he was turned down by three banks and had to put his own money in the project in order to proceed with construction while the case moved through court, where he gambled on victory. Otherwise, he would have had to subdivide the space into 3,500-square-foot units.</p>
        <p>He said he was assured by Loehmann's chief counsel that the environmental review would survive scrutiny and had been encouraged by Deputy Mayors Rudy Washington and Fran Reiter. But Mr. Clemenza was out on a limb until Oct. 23, only 19 days before the Loehmann's opening, when Justice Louis B. York of State Supreme Court ruled in favor of the project.</p>
        <p>Successful as the project has become, Mr. Clemenza would not take such a risk again. ''One or two little groups can turn around and basically tie up a project for five years, lose in the end and then appeal it,'' he said. ''This stymies development.''</p>
        <p>Today's legal stage was set 25 years ago when neighbors of the Metropolitan Correctional Center in lower Manhattan sued to stop the project, warning of perils like traffic congestion. ''The issue was whether there had to be an environmental impact statement for a prison, even though it didn't have traditional environmental impacts -- forests weren't cut down and it didn't despoil the water,'' said Ross Sandler, a professor at New York Law School and former city Transportation Commissioner.</p>
        <p>In May 1972, the United States Court of Appeals found that the Government had ignored potential adverse impacts in planning the prison, ruling that environmental considerations must be construed to include urban dwellers' quality of life.</p>
        <p>Ten years later, in April 1982, a Federal judge blocked construction of the Westway, a highway that was to tunnel through landfill along the Hudson River. He found that the Army Corps of Engineers had failed to consider the impact of the landfill on the striped bass habitat.</p>
        <p>Simply put, the issue was not whether the highway would harm the fishery; it was whether planners had studied whether the highway would harm the fishery. (A frustrated Mayor Koch said, ''If those striped bass need a place to fornicate, I'll build them a motel in Poughkeepsie.'')</p>
        <p>Around this time, one of the premier land-use law firms, Rosenman &amp; Colin, added litigators at the outset to any major development case it was handling. Samuel H. Lindenbaum, of counsel to the firm, recalled, ''I started advising clients that, unfortunately, in many if not most matters, the approval process doesn't end with what was then the Board of Estimate and is now the City Council -- but in litigation.''</p>
        <p>As vexing as this is for builders, Jerold S. Kayden, associate professor of urban planning at the Harvard Graduate School of Design, said it was ''hardly surprising that in a densely populated, highly regulated city like New York, there is a cornucopia of legal hooks that citizen groups and neighbors can rely upon.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said he knew of no evidence that New Yorkers were uniquely litigious. That impression was confirmed by Con Howe, director of planning in Los Angeles and former executive director of the New York City Planning Department. ''There are just as many lawyers per acre here,'' he said. ''Whether it's community groups, environmental groups or property-rights people, it remains a litigious environment. I don't see any appreciable difference.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, he said, Angelenos may be more prone to lawsuits over developments that affect the natural environment. Clean-air lawsuits, he noted, are ''bread and butter.''</p>
        <p>There are cities, however, where land-use litigation is not commonplace. ''The ethos of suing on every project just hasn't occurred in Boston,'' said Marisa Lago, director of the Boston Redevelopment Authority and former general counsel of the New York Economic Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>Because there have been no lawsuits in Boston like that against Westway, Ms. Lago said, opponents had less precedent to embolden them. She said Boston's land-use process offers a smaller target, since the authority has considerable power over zoning and functions both as the planning and economic development arm of government. Consequently, Ms. Lago said, it was possible to count on one hand the lawsuits filed in recent years in Boston.</p>
        <p>BY contrast, you would need 10 hands -- or 5 hands and 5 feet -- to count the number of lawsuits filed against the 42d Street redevelopment project. In a remarkable twist, the developer of the first of the new office towers there, the Durst Organization, was originally one of the most aggressive litigants against the project.</p>
        <p>What bothered the late Seymour Durst about the 42d Street project was that the government was subsidizing office development by the Prudential Insurance Company of America and Park Tower Realty that would compete with the Dursts' properties along the Avenue of the Americas, which they had bought or built themselves.</p>
        <p>But that was not a cause of action. Instead, in the late 80's, the Dursts attacked on a variety of procedural fronts. They filed a suit to compel disclosure of the leases between the state and the developers. They filed a suit claiming that public notice had been defective. They filed a suit charging that the state was neglecting the Eighth Avenue portion of the site. They filed a suit asserting that the condemnation process did not guarantee payments to landowners.</p>
        <p>''The things we were unhappy about weren't things you could sue about,'' said Douglas Durst, who is now president of the Durst Organization. ''But we could sue about the fact that the Eighth Avenue part of the site was being abandoned.''</p>
        <p>Vincent Tese, who was then chairman of the state Urban Development Corporation, said of the litigants, ''They were very, very cognizant of time and hoping that any delay would either wear us down or cause the developer to throw up his hands.''</p>
        <p>''The assessed value of the property rose dramatically during the period of the lawsuits,'' Mr. Tese said. ''If it weren't for the fact that Prudential was a large company and could absorb these changes, the project might very well have not happened.''</p>
        <p>The Dursts lost every case. ''Seymour said, 'We had good lawyers but they had better judges,' '' Mr. Durst recalled. ''As it turned out, we probably didn't have to sue, because the project would have fallen apart under its own weight in any event. The real benefit to us of the lawsuits in the end was the knowledge we gained about the project.'' But he conceded that the Dursts' history as litigants ''made it very difficult'' for them to persuade Prudential and Park Tower to sell them development rights for the northeast corner of Broadway and 42d Street.</p>
        <p>This is not the only undertaking to have been reshaped by litigation without actually being stopped. In 1985, Rose Associates began Atlantic Center in Brooklyn, whose centerpiece was to have been two office buildings with 1.8 million square feet.</p>
        <p>The Board of Estimate approved the project in 1986 but four lawsuits were filed on environmental grounds and Atlantic Center became so mired that it missed the mid-80's real-estate boom. Instead, it has been recently developed as a 380,000-square-foot shopping center by Forest City Ratner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratner spied a silver lining in the legal cloud. ''Atlantic Center would have had a hard time being an office development,'' he said. ''But all of a sudden it became a great retail site.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratner believes it is getting harder for community groups to win land-use challenges, since environmental impact statements now cover ''everything from toxic-waste storage to birds nesting.''</p>
        <p>And until the market grows appreciably hotter, there may be less of a taste for litigation. ''When the market cools, the public is anxious that there isn't enough development,'' said Mr. Weisbrod, president of the Alliance for Downtown New York.</p>
        <p>THE next battlefield is almost surely Columbus Circle. ''I will not stand idly by if somebody has a design that is going to in any way interfere with the Trump International Hotel and Tower,'' Mr. Trump declared. ''An adjoining property owner has power to protect a lot of things; views among them.'' (He would not elaborate on the legal theory underlying the assertion, and no one else interviewed for this article said they knew what it might be.)</p>
        <p>The Municipal Art Society, whose 1987 lawsuit against Columbus Center proved to be a decisive blow, is concerned that government officials are not disclosing enough about their plans for Columbus Circle. ''We think it's very important to have an open public debate,'' said Brendan Sexton, president of the society. ''Will this round turn into litigation? Can't tell. Hope not.''</p>
        <p>The Committee for Environmentally Sound Development, which favors keeping the existing Coliseum, is talking to lawyers about possible challenges, said its vice president, Olive Freud, but would prefer to negotiate now than sue later.</p>
        <p>Councilwoman Ronnie M. Eldridge said it was up to state and city officials to create an open, cooperative climate. ''They encourage hostility in the community by not talking it through,'' she said. ''That, of course, is what breeds litigation in the long run.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
