<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, You Can Do Something About the Weather</title>
    <meta content="31CANE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="SCIENTIST AT WORK: Mark A. Cane" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="898572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENTIST AT WORK: Mark A. Cane"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models (Simulations)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Mark A. Cane</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cane, Mark A (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDF1030F932A05751C1A960958260" item-length="2233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, You Can Do Something About the Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Dr Mark A Cane, meteorologist and oceanographer at Columbia University's Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory and a pre-eminent expert on El Nino, the vast expanse of warm water that every few years, at irregular intervals, spreads eastward along the Equator from western Pacific to South America, setting off chain of climatic events; his computer models of El Nino have done much to advance efforts to predict droughts, floods and other disasters; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a youth in Brooklyn, he was helpless when the lords of baseball moved his beloved Dodgers to Los Angeles -- a calamity, he jokes today, that ''precipitated the decline of American civilization.''</p>
        <p>But fresh out of Harvard University in the mid-1960's, he achieved a modest measure of influence over events by joining the civil rights crusade in the South.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a youth in Brooklyn, he was helpless when the lords of baseball moved his beloved Dodgers to Los Angeles -- a calamity, he jokes today, that ''precipitated the decline of American civilization.''</p>
        <p>But fresh out of Harvard University in the mid-1960's, he achieved a modest measure of influence over events by joining the civil rights crusade in the South.</p>
        <p>And now, as a scientist on the frontier of climate research and an expert par excellence on El Nino, an important shaper of the world's year-to-year climate, Dr. Mark A. Cane of Columbia University's Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory may be able to do something about destructive forces older than humanity: droughts, floods and other climatic disasters.</p>
        <p>No one can prevent these catastrophes, of course, but rapidly evolving research has raised hope that they can be predicted for a particular region in time to avoid their worst effects -- by planting drought-resistant crops, for instance. As much as anyone, and more than most, Dr. Cane has brought his profession to the brink of being able to do just that.</p>
        <p>He and a student, Stephen E. Zebiak, made a pivotal breakthrough a decade ago when they devised a computer model that accurately predicted the comings, goings and varying strengths of El Nino. This is the expanse of warm water that every few years, at irregular intervals, spreads eastward along the Equator from the western Pacific to South America. The shift of warmth sets off a chain of climatic events that reverberate through the atmosphere, creating droughts in some places, precipitating deluges in others and altering atmospheric patterns that decide where it is hot and cold. Apart from the seasonal cycle itself, no other single phenomenon influences short-term climate so profoundly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cane was ''the first to have the foresight'' to realize that dynamic models of El Nino's workings could actually be used to make predictions, said Dr. Ants Leetmaa, senior scientist at the National Centers for Environmental Prediction at Camp Springs, Md., the nation's weather forecasting center. Without the work of Dr. Cane and Dr. Zebiak, he said, ''we'd be at least 5 or 10 years behind where we are now.''</p>
        <p>Today a number of groups around the world, building on the success of the Cane-Zebiak predictions, routinely make short-term climatic forecasts based on El Nino's cycle -- including its flip side, an occasional cooling of the eastern tropical Pacific called La Nina. Many countries, particularly the tropical ones like Australia, where the effects of El Nino are strongest and clearest, are  using the new forecasting tool in practical applications like agricultural planning. Research by Dr. Cane and others has established that there is often a direct correlation between El Nino and grain yields in these countries, including some as far away as Africa.</p>
        <p>But while El Nino is a powerful predictor, many other influences on climate have not yet been explored for their predictive utility, including variations in sea-surface temperature and pressure in the North Atlantic and North Pacific. These may have as much influence as El Nino, or even more, on temperate regions like Europe and North America, and until they have been better pinned down, the nascent field of short-term climate forecasting cannot reach maturity.</p>
        <p>So Dr. Cane has become a major figure in an ambitious new step forward: the creation of a global research and forecasting network, just established at the Lamont observatory in Palisades, N.Y., in collaboration with the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in San Diego. Its purpose is to accelerate advances in predicting short-term climate and speed the practical application of that skill around the world.</p>
        <p>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration is providing a total of $8 million this year and next to set up the new center, called the International Research Institute for Climate Prediction. The agency is also committed to assembling a multinational group of participating research centers and financial contributors.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cane's pioneering work was critical to the institute's establishment, and he will be deeply involved in its activities both as a researcher and in collaborating with research centers and governments abroad to build the global network, said Dr. Antonio Moura, the institute's first director.</p>
        <p>The prospect that Dr. Cane's research might lead to vast human benefits is ''a kind of gift,'' wholly unanticipated when simple intellectual curiosity originally attracted him to El Nino, the 52-year-old oceanographer said the other day at the Lamont observatory overlooking the Hudson River. Bearded and loquacious, he has the slimness of the squash player, tennis enthusiast and kayaker he has been, and his sharp face easily breaks up into creases of affability.</p>
        <p>Like science itself, Dr. Cane's path  owes much to chance. Born and raised in Brooklyn as the son of an engineer and a school attendance officer, he graduated from Midwood High School, where he developed an interest in math and science, especially math. It is something ''where you get a real answer,'' he said, adding, ''Life is usually not like that; even science is usually not like that.''</p>
        <p>At Harvard, he majored in pure mathematics but his interest soon shifted to applied math. ''It's more down-to-earth, less philosophical,'' he said. As an undergraduate he took many social science courses and became a political activist. He spent the summer of 1965 in Alabama, helping to organize newly enfranchised blacks. The next year, after getting a master's degree at Harvard in what would now be called computer science, he moved to New York and got a job as a computer programmer at the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies. He lived in the East Village, frequented jazz clubs (''My tolerance for smoke was pretty good, unlike now''), played touch football in the park -- and had no clear idea of what he wanted to do: ''I was just hanging out.''</p>
        <p>He married the former Barbara Haak in those years. (She is now a lawyer in Nyack, N.Y., where the Canes live; they have two grown children.) The newly married Canes moved to Henniker, N.H., where he taught math at New England College. It was so isolated, he recalls, that the high point of the day would be television shows like ''The Brady Bunch'' and ''The Odd Couple.'' Realizing that he ''wasn't cut out to be a country boy,'' he decided to ''go study with a great man.''</p>
        <p>The great man turned out to be Dr. Jule D. Charney of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a pioneer in weather research who with the famed mathematician John von Neumann was the first to use computer models to predict the weather.  Dr. Cane met Dr. Charney, now deceased, by chance when the latter worked as a consultant at the Goddard Institute. At the time, Dr. Cane and others at the institute were making fumbling attempts to learn about weather and climate. Dr. Cane found Dr. Charney ''charismatic,'' and talking with him brought ''a kind of revelation that somebody actually understood this stuff.''</p>
        <p>At M.I.T., Dr. Charney at first wanted him to work on a highly technical mathematical problem. The problem did not appeal to Dr. Cane, and he found a more physical, practical one -- making a computer model of an equatorial ocean current that a colleague did not want to make. That is how Dr. Cane became a tropical oceanographer, a move that set him up to work on El Nino.</p>
        <p>He hurried to finish his Ph.D. studies in meteorology at M.I.T. in three years because ''we were running out of money very quickly.'' For a time, the young family received aid from a special Federal program for women, infants and children. After various academic and research stints elsewhere, he returned to M.I.T. as a faculty member in 1979.</p>
        <p>His arrival happened to coincide with a new scientific interest in El Nino, set off by the severe Midwestern winter of 1977. Some suspected that El Nino had played a role, and given Dr. Cane's training as a meteorologist and his work on equatorial ocean dynamics, it was a natural research subject.</p>
        <p>Earlier researchers had discerned much about El Nino, but no one had yet put all the pieces together in a computer model simulating its workings. He and Dr. Zebiak, then a graduate student, succeeded in reproducing the self-sustaining oscillations in ocean temperature characteristic of El Nino. His interest in using the model to predict the comings and goings of El Nino was piqued by the phenomenon's appearance in 1982-83, the most destructive of the 20th century. At a scientific meeting in the fall of 1982, he recalls, an eminent researcher got up and ''said there is no El Nino and there will be no El Nino, and many experts agreed -- and we were essentially well into the biggest El Nino of the century.''</p>
        <p>Once it developed, he thought, ''This is really a good prediction problem; the state of the art should be easy to beat, because the thing was going on and we didn't know it.''</p>
        <p>He and Dr. Zebiak started by retrospectively ''hindcasting'' the 1982-83 event to see whether the model would reproduce what actually happened. ''We did that,'' he said, ''and it's probably the only thing I've ever done in science that worked the first time.'' But acceptance would not come until the two predicted El Nino's appearance in advance.</p>
        <p>In January 1986, by which time the two researchers had moved to Lamont, the model was showing that El Nino was due at the end of the year.  ''The issue was what to do with this,'' he recalled. ''Do you sit on it? People said, 'What if you're wrong?' And I said, 'What if we're right and we don't tell anybody?' '' It was a question of responsibility, he said. The Lamont leadership gave its approval, and the forecast was published in the journal Nature and announced at a news conference, ''which really made some people go ballistic,'' Dr. Cane said.</p>
        <p>The eastern Pacific had been warming on cue, but almost as soon as the news conference was over it started cooling again. ''We had a pretty miserable summer,'' Dr. Cane said, ''because it looked like we were going to be wrong. But about August, nature turned around. We turned out to be right; thank God, because we were pretty far out on a limb.''</p>
        <p>What really certified the validity of the model, however, was that it said El Nino would not appear in 1990, while other experts said it would. It did not.</p>
        <p>At one point, Dr. Cane said, he wanted the National Weather Service to take over the forecasting ''before we were wrong; it was inevitable.'' Sure enough, the Lamont model missed a warming of the eastern Pacific in early 1993, as did most other forecasters. ''That was a bust,'' Dr. Cane said, ''a real bust.''  The Cane-Zebiak model has successfully predicted all other fluctuations of El Nino's cycle since 1986-87, a period in which El Nino has appeared more frequently than usual.</p>
        <p>No forecasting system is infallible, though, and the weather service now routinely relies on its own El Nino model. The young enterprise of short-term climate prediction received another valuable seal of approval this month. In a special report, a National Research Council panel confirmed that regional-scale changes in climate linked to El Nino could indeed be predicted months to a year in advance. ''I don't expect to tell you, ever, what the weather is going to be in New York on Dec. 16 a year from now,'' Dr. Cane said. ''That doesn't mean we couldn't say something about what the winter might be like.''</p>
        <p>El Nino last visited the world in early 1995, and Dr. Cane says its next return -- typically after an interval of two to seven years -- has not yet been signaled by computer models.  In fact, the surface of the eastern Pacific is a little cooler than normal, the hangover of a mild visitation by La Nina earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Routine, global forecasting of short-term climatic change ''is going to happen,'' Dr. Cane said. ''I'm sure of that; the idea is in the air now.''  The new institute, he believes, can make it happen ''in a faster and better way.''</p>
        <p>But already he is succumbing to the intellectual allure of new problems -- the reconstruction of past climates, for instance. Unless scientists know how climate has varied in the past, they cannot accurately gauge whatever effect humans may be having on present and future climate. ''We don't have a handle'' on natural climatic variability, Dr. Cane said, ''and the only way to get at it is to go back'' and reconstruct the past -- a challenge he describes as similar to reconstructing a whole dinosaur from five fossil toes. So he is plunging into, among other things, the arcane world of chemical tracers, temperature bands on ancient corals and other clues to past climate behavior.</p>
        <p>''Some of us,'' Dr. Leetmaa said, ''get our fun from doing practical forecasts. He's working on leading edge problems.''</p>
        <p>SCIENTIST AT WORK: Mark A. Cane</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
