<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Probes Will Carry New Hope For Detecting Life on Mars</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="831267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTEROIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS PATHFINDER (SPACECRAFT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARSSURVEYOR (SPACECRAFT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE, EXTRATERRESTRIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BACTERIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D81339F933A15751C0A960958260" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Probes Will Carry New Hope For Detecting Life on Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY have no antennas or pointy little heads or the kind of death rays that H. G. Wells pictured in his "War of the Worlds." Even so, Martians may very well be real and living comfortably in secluded parts of the red planet, scientists are beginning to suspect.</p>
        <p>These hidden residents of Mars are envisioned not as large and complex organisms but as tiny specks of life smaller than a pinprick that flourish deep underground in the wet and more temperate regions of the planet's hot interior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY have no antennas or pointy little heads or the kind of death rays that H. G. Wells pictured in his "War of the Worlds." Even so, Martians may very well be real and living comfortably in secluded parts of the red planet, scientists are beginning to suspect.</p>
        <p>These hidden residents of Mars are envisioned not as large and complex organisms but as tiny specks of life smaller than a pinprick that flourish deep underground in the wet and more temperate regions of the planet's hot interior.</p>
        <p>By nature, such a microbial realm would have eluded the pair of robotic probes that landed on Mars two decades ago but found no signs of life on the dry surface. The creatures of the Martian deep, if they exist, may be hard to find and disappointing to some people because they probably resemble the scum around  a shower stall more than the freaks of science fiction.</p>
        <p>Even so, experts say, the discovery of extraterrestrial microbes would be a watershed in science. Finding life on another planet would shed light on the mystery of how it started on Earth, especially if, as some analysts believe, Martian life evolved earlier. The discovery would also help figure the odds of life arising elsewhere in the universe.</p>
        <p>A renewed hunt for life on Mars, especially microbes, is to begin latter this year. Driving the exploration are recent findings that early Mars was hotter and wetter than previously believed and that microbes love such environments.</p>
        <p>Since the Mars landings two decades ago, microbes on Earth have been found thriving in places, like seabed volcanoes, that are extraordinarily hot, dark, deep and deadly to all other forms of life. Moreover, genetic studies have shown that microbes living in these extreme environments are most closely related to the first forms of terrestrial life, suggesting that evolution began in a hothouse, as Mars might have been some four billion years ago.</p>
        <p>"We're in a different world," Dr. Michael H. Carr, a scientist with the United States Geological Survey who led some of the Mars-probe analyses two decades ago, said in an interview. "Our understanding of biology has advanced so much in the past 20 years. The probability that life could have started on Mars  is greatly increased."</p>
        <p>Dr. Jack D. Farmer, a Mars specialist at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, echoed that judgment.</p>
        <p>"We now know that liquid water was abundant at the beginning and probably still is, below the surface," he said in an interview. "So you have to ask, why  not life? What are the chances? I give it 50-50. But that's religion. What we need are more observations."</p>
        <p>Later this year, a pair of rockets carrying NASA payloads are to blast off for Mars to inaugurate a potent new round of international exploration. In the next decade or so, America, Europe, Russia and Japan are planning to send as many as 20 missions to Mars, if enough financing materializes. The main goals of the exploratory push are to find water and life.</p>
        <p>Even the discovery of fossil microbes or the biochemical forerunners of life  would be an extraordinarily precious find, scientists say. On Earth, wind, rain, erosion and geological tumult over billions of years have erased most clues to what things were like in the beginning. Mars is different.</p>
        <p>"Much of its surface is ancient and might have a record of what went on in its earliest history," said Dr. Michael A. Meyer, head of NASA's program to find extraterrestrial life. "Exploring it might give us a window into the first billion years of our solar system and the origin of life, on Earth as well as Mars."</p>
        <p>Far from the warming rays of the Sun, the rust-colored planet is about half the size of Earth and has long generated debate about the existence of extraterrestrial life. In 1877 an Italian astronomer, Giovanni Schiaparelli, described its surface as covered with canals, seas and continents, setting off an international uproar.</p>
        <p>In 1976, two Viking spacecraft photographed the planet and landed on its surface, finding a world of stark contrasts. There were giant craters and extinct volcanoes and a canyon as long as the United States is wide. Close up, Mars resembled an earthly desert strewn with rocks and windblown sand. But the orbiting cameras found much evidence that water once flowed over its surface, cutting deep channels and lakes.</p>
        <p>Samples that the landers took of the Martian soil underwent a battery of tests but showed no unambiguous signs of life. So scientists with lingering hopes set their sights on more elaborate tests in the future.</p>
        <p>Back on Earth after the landings, a quiet revolution shook the foundations of biology as scientists began to find microbes thriving in odd places at temperatures up to 235 degrees Fahrenheit -- hotter than boiling water. They were discovered in terrestrial hot springs, in volcanic vents beneath the sea, in deep hot oil reservoirs and in solid rock miles down.</p>
        <p>Dr. Carl R. Woese of the University of Illinois stunned the scientific world  by announcing that some of the heat-loving microbes constituted a third superfamily of life, distinct from that of bacteria and that of plants and animals. The newly recognized group, called Archaea, was linked to Earth's earliest known life.</p>
        <p>In 1992, Dr. Thomas Gold of Cornell University proposed that microbes might be ubiquitous throughout the upper few miles of Earth's crust, inhabiting fluid-filled pores, cracks and interstices of rocks while living off Earth's inner heat and chemicals. The total mass of this hidden biosphere, he calculated, might rival or exceed that of all surface life.</p>
        <p>"Such life may be widely disseminated in the universe," Dr. Gold wrote, "since planetary-type bodies with similar subsurface conditions may be common as solitary objects in space, as well as in other solar-type systems."</p>
        <p>It is these kinds of terrestrial findings that are giving Mars its new allure, as well as judgments that the planet was warm and wet in its early days. Dr. Norman H. Sleep of Stanford University recently proposed that originally Mars was probably more hospitable to life than Earth. Some scientists speculate  that a collision billions of years ago between an asteroid and Mars could have knocked away microbe-bearing rocks that fell to Earth. This could have sown the  seeds of life on Earth, the theory goes -- in effect, making humans the descendants of early Martians.</p>
        <p>Since the surface of Mars is now largely dry or frozen, scientists say, any microorganisms that evolved on the planet would probably have been forced to retreat into the interior of Mars to seek out warmth and moisture, possibly forming thriving colonies.</p>
        <p>"As you dig deeper, it gets warmer and warmer and eventually you're going to  hit a depth where the temperature is warm enough to melt water," said Dr. Stephen M. Clifford, a geologist at the Lunar and Planetary Institute in Houston.</p>
        <p>Martian rock, he added, might be porous enough to have ground water moving down to depths of about 10 kilometers, or six miles.</p>
        <p>"Water locked in the crust as ground ice or ground water could be equivalent  to a global Martian sea up to a full kilometer deep," Dr. Clifford said in an interview. "That's based on a lot of geological evidence."</p>
        <p>Many scientific groups, including the American Geophysical Union, are holding meetings to discuss the possibility that microbes arose on Mars and might now teem inside the planet.</p>
        <p>"If there are life forms that can live in high temperatures in great depths on Earth, this may also be possible in Mars," Dr. Karl O. Stetter, a German pioneer in the study of heat-loving microbes, told a meeting held in London this month.</p>
        <p>Dr. Farmer of NASA, who works at the Ames Research Center south of San Francisco, is analyzing terrestrial sites that might mimic Martian ones. For instance, his team is studying Yellowstone National Park and its geysers and hot springs to better understand the geological deposits and visual clues of microbe-rich springs. The aim is to have spacecraft in orbit around Mars spot such sites, either active or fossilized.</p>
        <p>"There's no reason we can't find them," Dr. Farmer said. "There's an emerging consensus to target these kinds of deposits."</p>
        <p>The new round of Mars exploration has three main aims: to search for past or  present life, to understand the Martian climate and its lessons for Earth and to search for resources of possible use by future human explorers.</p>
        <p>The unifying theme is water, so the early missions will focus on finding and  understanding its past and present states. Later missions will try to pinpoint microbes, which is a far more challenging task.</p>
        <p>The exploration is to start with twin launchings late this year, probably in  December. One is known as Mars Pathfinder, which is to fly directly to Mars and  land on the surface in an ancient flood plain that is expected to be littered with interesting rocks. Pathfinder is to transmit images of the Martian terrain  with a color camera, to monitor the weather and to deploy a small rover to explore the region around the lander and to sample soil and rocks.</p>
        <p>The other probe is known as the Mars Surveyor. It is to go into orbit around  Mars and use a battery of six instruments to scan the surface for a full Martian year (about two Earth years), seeking visual clues to water and Yellowstone-type outpourings.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, scientists say, finding microbial life on Mars may require drilling into the crust, a difficult venture that would probably require the presence of humans. "It may be that you'd have to go deep to find liquid water," Dr. Meyer of NASA said.</p>
        <p>Many scientists are keeping their fingers crossed, eager to discover that humans are not alone, even if the company turns out to be microbial slime.</p>
        <p>"Part of the reason I got into planetary science in the first place was to seek out life on other worlds," said Dr. Clifford of the Lunar and Planetary Institute. "Mars is probably the best chance we're going to have of finding it in our own solar system."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
