<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Snow Attacks A City Record (And Its Spirit)</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="830937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK, NY, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REVKIN, ANDREW C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0DC1339F93BA25751C0A960958260" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Snow Attacks A City Record (And Its Spirit)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REVKIN, ANDREW C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the latest drove of storm-delayed travelers rose achingly from the floors  of airport lounges and skiers schussed down a fabricated slope in Central Park,  the snowstorm that ended early yesterday brought New York City to the brink of a record and ushered in single-digit wind chills.</p>
        <p>In Central Park, a 10.7-inch snowfall from the fifth major storm of the season left New York only 1.5 inches below the winter record of 63.2 inches set in 1947-48, Paul Knight, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University, said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the latest drove of storm-delayed travelers rose achingly from the floors  of airport lounges and skiers schussed down a fabricated slope in Central Park,  the snowstorm that ended early yesterday brought New York City to the brink of a record and ushered in single-digit wind chills.</p>
        <p>In Central Park, a 10.7-inch snowfall from the fifth major storm of the season left New York only 1.5 inches below the winter record of 63.2 inches set in 1947-48, Paul Knight, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University, said.</p>
        <p>Even with a dusting of flurries or light snow in the forecast for today, the record is unlikely to fall this week. But, Mr. Knight added, "There's still more than a month to go before the birds really begin to chirp."</p>
        <p>At midafternoon yesterday, winds gusting to 26 miles per hour forced New Yorkers to bundle up like Arctic explorers as the wind chill sank to near zero.</p>
        <p>But a warming trend later this week, Mr. Knight said, would insure that "by next weekend this will be nothing but a soggy memory."</p>
        <p>Heavy snow across the region broke cumulative winter snowfall records in Washington, Baltimore, Philadelphia, Hartford and Providence yesterday. For the  record books, Mr. Knight said, meteorologists do not confine measurements to winter as it is defined in calendars, but include any snow falling between October and April.</p>
        <p>Many smaller cities and towns also saw new records set, with meteorologists in Danbury, Conn., popping champagne corks on Friday as the storm -- which eventually left more than a foot of snow there -- pushed the city past the local record of 80.8 inches, set in the winter of 1947-48.</p>
        <p>In New Brunswick, N.J., the storm brought total snowfall at Rutgers University to 63.7 inches, which topped the previous seasonal record of 58.9 inches set in the winter of 1960-61, David A. Robinson, New Jersey's state climatologist, said. To celebrate, Mr. Robinson said, he ran out in the snow on  Friday night and played with his children.</p>
        <p>The heaviest snow fell in a band from eastern New Jersey up the lower Hudson  Valley into western Connecticut, meteorologists said. Clifton and Elizabeth, N.J., both recorded 11 inches of snow; Ossining, N.Y, measured 12.5 inches; and  East Hartford recorded 12 inches, Mr. Knight said.</p>
        <p>The seemingly interminable duration of this winter may stem from the spread-out nature of the snowfalls, with substantial storms hitting New York City and nearby areas every few weeks so far, he said. In contrast, the winter of 1993-94 was stormier, but most of the rough weather came late in the season,  he said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the fresh blanket of snow instilled emotions ranging from joy to exasperation around the metropolitan region. At the North Meadow in Central Park, the snow came just in time for a winter carnival organized by the city's Department of Parks and Recreation and a sporting goods chain.</p>
        <p>In blazing sunshine but bundled up against strong, cold winds, several thousand people swooped down a 60-foot ski ramp, tried out cross-country skis, snow shoes and "sled dogs" -- short skis that replicate on snow the feel of roller skates. The event had been scheduled for last weekend, but was postponed  when temperatures rose into the 40's.</p>
        <p>"This weather is terrific," Parks Commissioner Henry J. Stern said.</p>
        <p>Emily Rakowicz, 16, had come into Manhattan from Queens with four friends to  vie for a trip to Bermuda in a snow sculpture contest. Their entry, a miniature  version of Manhattan, sprouted snow skyscrapers but was missing a critical feature. Emily pounded down a long rectangle of snow in the center, creating Central Park.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani visited the winter festival and said that he was happy to see New Yorkers enjoying the park, but that overall, this winter's snows had constituted a major headache for the city.</p>
        <p>"I've stopped counting," he said, when asked how much the latest round of snow-removal operations were costing. An aide later told him the tally was estimated at $4 million for the storm that ended yesterday, on top of $50 million already spent this winter.</p>
        <p>For many storm-weary residents of the region, another round of below-normal temperatures and above-normal snow accumulations meant yet another weekend of reading, video watching and other indoor activities. At One Stop Video, a tape-rental store in Bedford Hills, N.Y., Ross Perry, a clerk, said he was busy  all day on Friday with customers stocking up on tapes, and yesterday he was equally busy with a flood of returns.</p>
        <p>The stormy white winter of 1995-96 might have some spiritual value, said Rebecca Zafrany, a 33-year-old graduate student at the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan whose husband, Emile, was stuck for several hours in snowbound traffic on Friday. By showing how easily puffy piles of ice crystals can repeatedly cause human affairs to skid to a halt, the snowstorms help remind people of their fairly inconsequential place in the cosmos, she said. There is an expression in Yiddish, she said, that roughly translates to "Man thinks and God laughs."</p>
        <p>At the area's airports, exasperation and exhaustion were the norm after delays and cancellations that began piling up on Friday were still being untangled yesterday, leaving holiday travelers grumbling.</p>
        <p>At La Guardia Airport, Thomas Foley, a lawyer from Long Beach, L.I., had expected to be on a golf course in Fort Myers, Fla., yesterday with his fiancee. Mr. Foley said his four-day vacation was rapidly shrinking to a three-day vacation and -- if he didn't get a flight -- would soon be a two-day weekend.</p>
        <p>"I like winter," he said, "but I've had enough."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
