<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEEP FREEZE GRIPS SOUTHERN STATES</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKOUTS (ELECTRICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITRUSFRUITS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MISSISSIPPI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GEORGIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALABAMA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TENNESSEE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTH CAROLINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMOTHERS, RONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citrus Fruits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4DC1439F936A35751C0A960958260" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEEP FREEZE GRIPS SOUTHERN STATES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMOTHERS, RONALD</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Feb. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A deep freeze swung into the Deep South today, bringing ice, snow and temperatures below, or barely above, zero to parts of Mississippi, Georgia and Alabama.</p>
        <p>Even northern and central Florida were affected, with temperatures in the 20's leaving the state's $1.2 billion citrus industry hanging by an icy thread.  Citrus farmers sprayed their trees with water to produce an insulating cover of  ice, but high winds were frustrating many of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A deep freeze swung into the Deep South today, bringing ice, snow and temperatures below, or barely above, zero to parts of Mississippi, Georgia and Alabama.</p>
        <p>Even northern and central Florida were affected, with temperatures in the 20's leaving the state's $1.2 billion citrus industry hanging by an icy thread.  Citrus farmers sprayed their trees with water to produce an insulating cover of  ice, but high winds were frustrating many of them.</p>
        <p>A lot of the citrus trees have begun to get new buds for next year's crop," said Carl Grooms, a grower near Tampa, Fla. "If we get a hard freeze, it could devastate production for next year."</p>
        <p>The Arctic air that engulfed much of the South still held sway in much of the rest of the nation, with more record lows today from the Rockies through the Upper Midwest to the Northeast.</p>
        <p>In the New York area, those residents who could stayed inside, as the region's harsh winter reasserted itself with temperatures in the single digits.  [Page B6.]</p>
        <p>The past week of snow, ice and record cold has been blamed for 55 deaths across the lower 48 states. Traffic accidents accounted for the bulk of the deaths, but some were attributed to hypothermia among the elderly and Alzheimer's sufferers who did not or could not seek shelter and from heart attacks among the elderly.</p>
        <p>For the South, where the unseasonable temperatures were expected to continue  for at least one more day, the frigid air was accompanied by ice storms and heavy snow across Tennessee, North Carolina, and the northern sections of Mississippi, Alabama and Georgia. That brought down trees and power lines, causing hundreds of thousands of utility customers to lose power, according to emergency management agencies. Utility companies predicted that as they made repairs, electrical demand was likely to reach record levels as people return to work tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Several of the traffic fatalities were in the South, but generally officials  said people seemed to be heeding the warnings to stay inside and not travel unless absolutely necessary.</p>
        <p>Cecil Whaley, a spokesman for the Tennessee Emergency Management Agency, said that the central and eastern parts of the state had 5 to 16 inches of snow over  the weekend. But he said there were only two weather-related traffic deaths, compared with 15 deaths in a March 1993 blizzard.</p>
        <p>"We feel people are listening to us," he said. "Retail business is off sharply, but that should improve in the next two days."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile in Chicago, officials ended the two-day weather emergency in the city as temperatures rose to zero or above in much of the Midwest for the first  time since Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Temperatures were a fairly tolerable 6 degrees in Chicago today after much of the region set record-breaking lows in the past week with temperatures far below zero in parts of Minnesota, Wisconsin, Illinois and Iowa.</p>
        <p>Warmer air from the Gulf of Mexico and an area of high pressure in east Texas began crawling into the Midwest, gradually elevating its temperatures, and as a  result much of the region is expected to post temperatures in the double digits  starting on Monday.</p>
        <p>"The cold is finally beginning to moderate somewhat in the Midwest," said a spokesman for the National Weather Service in Chicago.  "But temperatures will remain well below average at least until midweek."</p>
        <p>The moderating of the cold in the Midwest came as news to residents of the northeastern Minnesota town of Embarrass, which logged its fourth day with temperatures lower than 50 degrees below zero. Sunday's low in Embarrass was 56  below and many everyday thermometers were bottoming out.</p>
        <p>"We have a lot of people in the community who are having to buy new thermometers," said Adrienne Fowler, whose husband, Roland, is a volunteer observer in Embarrass for the National Weather Service.</p>
        <p>In the Southeast, where people were unused to the kind of conditions that leave roads as slick as glass, many stayed home.</p>
        <p>A host of stores in the Atlanta area did not open on Saturday because icy roads kept workers as well as customers in their homes.</p>
        <p>But today, as residents grew accustomed to the cold and road conditions improved, shopping was brisk at Best Buys electronics store in the Northlake area just north of the city.</p>
        <p>"I guess it was cabin fever from staying in yesterday and because we were closed," said Eric Switalski, the merchandise manager, attempting to explain the rush of business that had him and other managers manning extra checkout lines. "We still have about one third of our people who didn't come in today, but the customers did."</p>
        <p>In North Carolina, Gov. Jim Hunt declared a state of emergency in all 100 of  the state's counties where ice storms had snapped trees and damaged power lines, leaving as many as 350,000 people without power in the central and western parts of the state at one point.</p>
        <p>Tom Hegele, a spokesman for the state's emergency management agency, said that the Governor was also asking President Clinton to declare the state a disaster area because of the damage and disruption from the the frigid weather.</p>
        <p>But the emergency declaration allowed the the National Guard to be sent to some areas to provide emergency services and about 60 shelters for the homeless  and those without power to be opened.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hegele said the state was now concerned about the wind that is expected tonight and tomorrow.</p>
        <p>"You take your trees and power lines already under stress and you add wind and you have increased chances of more power lines going down," he said. "It doesn't look like it is going to get any better until the temperature gets above freezing and stays there."</p>
        <p>Horace Mason, the counselor on duty at a homeless shelter in Raleigh, said that there were already about 80 people warming themselves in the shelter, which usually takes the overflow from five other, privately run homeless shelters in the state capital, and he expected to be at the 150-person capacity tonight as temperatures dip to between 5 and 10 degrees. While it was usually opened at night, he said, they were planning to stay open around the clock until the cold  abated.</p>
        <p>Just to the north in Richmond churches, where formality usually reigns, today's attire turned casual, with worshipers showing up in jeans, sneakers and  even sweat suits.</p>
        <p>"It looks like a movie theater," said Dr. Charlie Cooke, a rheumatologist, at the Second Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>The church crowd turned out despite icy roads that produced hundreds of accidents.</p>
        <p>One person in Virginia died when a snow plow hit a car, two died of hypothermia and another had a fatal heart attack.</p>
        <p>In Louisiana where frigid temperatures in the teens shocked the central and northern parts of the state, people were behaving as they usually do when extreme cold hits the region.</p>
        <p>"People spent the weekend renting movies and staying home," said Robert Ricks, a forecaster with the National Weather Service in Slidell.</p>
        <p>Across the portions of eight states in the region and among the eight million people served by the Tennessee Valley Authority, there is expected to be a record-breaking demand for electricity on Monday, when most try to return to work and get back to normal after the weekend.</p>
        <p>Peggy Pennington, a spokeswoman for the authority, said it was predicting that demand would be even higher than it was last July when temperatures were over 95. "We're not only going to break our all-time winter demand," she said Peggy Pennington, "but our record summer demand as well."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
