<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pennsylvania Flood Losses Could Reach $700 Million</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PENNSYLVANIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PENNSYLVANIA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDE1F39F930A15752C0A960958260" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pennsylvania Flood Losses Could Reach $700 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISBURG, Pa., Jan. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the flood waters of Pennsylvania's big rivers receded today from their overflow levels of the weekend, thousands of residents returned to their homes only to find them uninhabitable, and the state said the economic losses could reach $700 million.</p>
        <p>From the Susquehanna and Delaware Rivers in the eastern half of the state to  the Ohio and Monongahela Rivers out west, Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania blamed  the flooding for 14 deaths, damage to 30,000 homes, the closing of 570 roads and the destruction of 8 bridges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the flood waters of Pennsylvania's big rivers receded today from their overflow levels of the weekend, thousands of residents returned to their homes only to find them uninhabitable, and the state said the economic losses could reach $700 million.</p>
        <p>From the Susquehanna and Delaware Rivers in the eastern half of the state to  the Ohio and Monongahela Rivers out west, Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania blamed  the flooding for 14 deaths, damage to 30,000 homes, the closing of 570 roads and the destruction of 8 bridges.</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania was among the states hardest hit by this month's blizzard, which left some areas under more than 40 inches of snow. Now, its vast system of rivers have made it, so far, the state most affected by the melt.</p>
        <p>"We've never had four seasons of weather pushed together in a two-week period of time in the middle of January," Governor Ridge said at a news conference today, citing problems caused by the rapid succession of heavy snowfalls, warming temperatures and rain that flooded scores of communities around the state in the last few days.</p>
        <p>Today, the Federal Emergency Management Agency added 26 counties to the list  of those in Pennsylvania that have been declared disaster areas, bringing the total number to 32. More are expected. Mr. Ridge has asked for Federal assistance for 58 counties -- all but 9 in the state.</p>
        <p>James Lee Witt, the F.E.M.A. director, said at the news conference that the others would be assessed shortly and would probably receive Federal funds. The lag has caused a minor stir between Mr. Ridge, a Republican elected in 1994, and the White House.</p>
        <p>After touring damaged areas on Sunday, Mr. Ridge criticized the Administration for not reacting fast enough to help the state, a jab he knew the White House could not ignore, given the state's importance to President Clinton  in the 1996 elections.</p>
        <p>By Sunday night, after Mr. Ridge spoke by telephone with President Clinton, the controversy had quieted. At the news conference, which followed Mr. Ridge's  meeting with Mr. Witt and Transportation Secretary Federico F. Pena, Mr. Witt assured Mr. Ridge the state would get all the help it deserved, and that seemed  to satisfy the Governor.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ridge's remarks drew a sharp response today from Michael D. McCurry,  the White House press secretary, who said that Mr. Ridge "ran his mouth instead  of getting the work done that would have led to getting their assistance."</p>
        <p>"It's the wrong way to do business, to go out and attack the President and the Administration," Mr. McCurry said.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, Mr. Ridge said: "I don't want to respond to the President's press secretary. My job is to promote the interests of Pennsylvania  citizens."</p>
        <p>To assess the damage around the state, Mr. Witt, Mr. Pena and other Federal officials left Washington this morning for a tour of Altoona, Wilkes-Barre, Harrisburg and Pittsburgh. Along the way, they saw all manner of problems caused by the floods.</p>
        <p>State officials said that 28 water plants had been destroyed by the floods, well water had been contaminated in countless areas, 150,000 people served by 18 water systems had been told to boil water before drinking and 116 Red Cross shelters had been set up to house people who were forced to evacuate their homes.</p>
        <p>In Pittsburgh, where three major rivers -- the Monongahela, Allegheny and Ohio -- converge, cleanup crews struggled with the worst flooding in western Pennsylvania since 1972. Freezing temperatures left huge chunks of ice on roadways and riverbanks throughout the areas after the rivers crested at more than 18 feet above normal levels.</p>
        <p>Coal barges were forced to tie up when they were unable to pass through locks, but dozens of barges broke loose and remain wedged against bridge pillars or dam gates.</p>
        <p>A 200-foot barge used by the Pittsburgh Wind Symphony ended up on a low-lying city parking lot on top of several automobiles caught by the fast-rising waters.</p>
        <p>John Comey, a spokesman for the Pennsylvania Emergency Management Agency, said that a trailer park had washed away in Williamsport, that 1,300 homes in Scranton had water in their basements and that icy waters were still well above  flood level in parts of Bloomsburg, Danville and Harrisburg.</p>
        <p>Here in Harrisburg, residents of a historic section of riverfront town houses, who had been evacuated as the Susquehanna rose, suffered another blow this morning when a fire caused serious damage to five homes along Pancake Row that had been built in 1897.</p>
        <p>Denise I. Robison, deputy secretary for the State Department of Aging, lives  in a house at one end of the row. She said she was not only heartened to find that her house was still standing, but also that the flag she hangs over her balcony was still flying. It says, "Don't Give Up the Ship."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
