<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battles on Conservation Are Reaping Dividends</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE CLINTON RECORD -- Fourth of seven articles: The Environment" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="868659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD CONTAMINATION AND POISONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DA1439F932A05754C0A960958260" item-length="3631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battles on Conservation Are Reaping Dividends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr. and TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY; CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>KELLOGG, Idaho</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rust-colored river runs through the valley where Barbara Miller is trying to rear her four children, in a town of brittle-boned homes holding off age and  gravity. Neighborly howdies blend with nervous talk about the poison that keeps showing up in the blood of local children.</p>
        <p>The Silver Valley, a basin in the Idaho mountains that once produced most of  the nation's silver and much of its lead, has long been one of the most polluted places in the United States. Things are gradually getting better, Mrs. Miller said, in part because the Clinton Administration has speeded the cleanup at Superfund toxic waste sites like the one in her neighborhood where mine refuse had smothered the land in toxic filth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rust-colored river runs through the valley where Barbara Miller is trying to rear her four children, in a town of brittle-boned homes holding off age and  gravity. Neighborly howdies blend with nervous talk about the poison that keeps showing up in the blood of local children.</p>
        <p>The Silver Valley, a basin in the Idaho mountains that once produced most of  the nation's silver and much of its lead, has long been one of the most polluted places in the United States. Things are gradually getting better, Mrs. Miller said, in part because the Clinton Administration has speeded the cleanup at Superfund toxic waste sites like the one in her neighborhood where mine refuse had smothered the land in toxic filth.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Miller and her neighbors are also struggling to live with another result of President Clinton's environmental policy. Liberated from environmental restrictions thanks to a bill Mr. Clinton reluctantly signed last summer, loggers have been clearing the national forest just upstream. Early this year when the rains came, the naked hillsides could not restrain the runoff, sending  a flood coursing through the valley and shifting more than one million pounds of lead downstream where the toxic sediment settled in people's yards.</p>
        <p>"We've seen a lot of progress in this valley," said Mrs. Miller, whose yard was dug up to remove lead endangering her children. "But now, with this new logging, a lot of people are upset."</p>
        <p>If Mrs. Miller and her neighbors feel whipsawed by Federal environmental policies, their experience may also be emblematic of the Clinton Administration's entire record on the environment, capturing in one spot some of the most complex issues of natural resources and public health that define environmentalism.</p>
        <p>Torn between economic forces and ecological imperatives, the White House has  sought to satisfy entrenched advocates on both sides of divisive policy struggles, only to find itself drawn into confrontation almost every time it sought consensus.</p>
        <p>Measured by a legislative yardstick, the Administration's environmental record would rise but a few inches. There were hardly any landmark environmental laws signed in the Rose Garden, and certainly nothing to rival Theodore Roosevelt's preservation of wild spaces, or Richard M. Nixon's endorsement of the modern environmental legal structure or Jimmy Carter's protection of big parts of Alaska from development.</p>
        <p>Rather, the Administration's record is best defined by how it performed in a  colossal collision with Congress midway through its first four years. When Republicans won control in 1994, they aggressively pressed forward with an antiregulatory agenda that environmentalists saw as threatening to dismantle a whole generation of rules that not only preserved open spaces and wilderness areas, but also put protection of the public's health and safety above other considerations, including economic ones.</p>
        <p>An intense battle over how to reshape environmental regulations ensued, with  the Administration presenting its own, moderate ideas but essentially playing a  defensive game and labeling the Republicans as tools of industrial special interests. The fight made every issue, including cleaning up toxic wastes or chopping down ancient forests, a matter of pitched partisan politics.</p>
        <p>And now, it appears that the payoff is coming, not only in strong support in  polls but also in legislative accomplishments. Later this week, President Clinton will sign a new pesticides bill that strongly resembles what he proposed three years ago, imposing strict new health protections in place of limited, outmoded and scientifically flawed ones and paying special attention to protection for infants and children. The legislation was passed with stunning swiftness by unanimous voice votes in a House and Senate that seemed to have learned the political power of mainstream environmentalism.</p>
        <p>Polling by The New York Times in June showed that by a margin of nearly 2 to  1, people trusted Mr. Clinton more than the Congress to protect the environment. But even as Mr. Clinton won praise for acting as a shield against Republican efforts to roll back environmental protections, he is often criticized as someone who has fallen short on the expectations.</p>
        <p>The First Steps Economy and Ecology Breed an Ambivalence</p>
        <p>The newly formed Clinton Administration was a study in environmental ambivalence. As a candidate, Mr. Clinton was a self-styled new Democrat with an  innate knack for compromise and a commitment to the economy. As Governor of Arkansas, that had sometimes meant bowing to the needs of industry when it came  to environmental protection.</p>
        <p>But in Al Gore, Bill Clinton had chosen a Vice-Presidential nominee who had written a best seller that called "rescuing the environment the central organizing principle for civilization."</p>
        <p>The same ambivalence permeated the Cabinet and the White House staff, where there was a constant tension between people who figuratively wore green armbands and those who preferred green eyeshades. There were strong environmentalists and Gore loyalists, but also noncommittal number-crunchers and a cadre of political movers and shifters.</p>
        <p>"We spent '93 and '94 working on how to make the environment an integral part of our long-term economic strategy, but still keep high standards," the President recalled in an interview. "I do not believe the public supports a Government walking away from the environment. I just don't believe they do."</p>
        <p>The President started his term with some daring environmental initiatives, even in his economic program. Taking his advice from Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt, an ardent environmentalist from Arizona, he promised to break a century-old habit of subsidized logging, mining and grazing on public lands.</p>
        <p>But there were immediate signs that when it came to a fight with Congress --  even one still controlled by Democrats -- the White House was not as determined  as the environmentalists had imagined. The Administration, in its first budget battle with Congress, quickly retreated from initiatives to increase grazing fees on public lands and impose an energy tax. Especially in the Senate, lawmakers from energy and ranching states controlled the show, and Mr. Babbitt became something of a pariah to them.</p>
        <p>Another sign came when Congress roughed up the Administration on a proposal to elevate the Environmental Protection Agency, headed by a determined Gore loyalist, Carol M. Browner, to Cabinet status. It was mainly a symbolic move that would have done little beyond putting new brass plaques on some bureaucrats' doors. But it got nowhere, largely because conservatives -- including Democrats -- insisted on tacking on requirements that environmental rules be subject to economic tests to see if they were worth the cost.</p>
        <p>When asked to defend the Administration's record, Vice President Gore cited a long list of administrative actions, many of which received relatively little public attention, including policies on ocean dumping, recycling paper, managing fisheries and the like.</p>
        <p>Faced with a Congress that proved unable to agree on laws that govern such major issues as wetlands, endangered species, and cleaning up toxic dumps, the Administration took major steps to smooth the process of getting permits for development and completed cleanups at hundreds of Superfund sites. But that is hardly the stuff of history books.</p>
        <p>The 103d Congress, still controlled by Mr. Clinton's own party, finally approved, after a decade of debate, a huge expansion of the National Park system in California's deserts. But Congress was generally hostile to green causes, and as the 1994 election approached environmental activists glumly joked that the Mojave Desert preserve was set aside just to give them a bigger wilderness to wander in.</p>
        <p>The Confrontation Republican Triumph Spurs the Defense</p>
        <p>In the end, the Administration would make environmentalism a pillar of its program, but that was only after Congress slipped into the hands of Republicans  who mounted a broad legislative offensive to roll back environmental regulations and slash the budgets of the agencies enforcing them. The President responded with vetoes and threats of vetoes, and his popularity surged.</p>
        <p>Playing defense, supporters and critics alike agreed, the President found his footing.</p>
        <p>"What's the old principle from physics?" Mr. Gore mused when asked how the midterm election had shaped the Administration's own environmental stance. "A force creates a counterforce, an equal and opposite reaction."</p>
        <p>But for that reaction to take hold in the Clinton White House first required  that the President himself realize that wrapping himself in green would pay off  politically.</p>
        <p>It happened at about the time that Dick Morris, the pollster and political confidant, moved into the White House, bringing fresh surveys showing that even  among antiregulatory Republican conservatives in Virginia -- the heart of opposition territory -- there was a strongly held belief that environmental regulations should be stronger, not weaker.</p>
        <p>It appeared that the Republicans in Congress were making a huge political mistake.</p>
        <p>Under its new Republican majority, the House in 1995 quickly passed a bill to overhaul the making of regulatory decisions on cleaning air, water and waste sites and protecting species and the habitats where they live. Part of the Republicans' Contract With America, the bill required elaborate cost-benefit studies of any new rules and opened significant new legal avenues for industry to appeal rules they thought were too burdensome.</p>
        <p>Still shocked by an election that had created the first Republican Congress in a generation, the Administration reacted cautiously, adopting a series of administrative changes and pilot programs that it promised would give businesses more flexibility while keeping pollution control standards in place.</p>
        <p>The House also moved swiftly with revisions to the Clean Water Act to eliminate Federal jurisdiction over most wetlands and ease on controls over industrial pollutants. Republican leaders also pushed a bill that would have greatly weakened the Endangered Species Act, and another to repeal many retroactive liability provisions of the Superfund law, which force polluters to  pay for environmental damage from dumping toxic wastes.</p>
        <p>Even though environmentalists were howling, both the regulatory bill and the  water bill passed the House without anyone at the White House even murmuring the word "veto."</p>
        <p>But the mood grew increasingly combative. Sensing the political advantage of  confrontation, the President finally dived into the fight.</p>
        <p>Ms. Browner said she knew things had changed in May 1995, when George Stephanopoulos, a major political adviser to Mr. Clinton, telephoned the President as they drove to a news conference where Mr. Clinton was about to denounce the water bill and, for the first time, pledge to veto legislation rolling back an environmental protection.</p>
        <p>"Be sure he calls it the Dirty Water Act," Mr. Stephanopoulos said to Ms. Browner, signaling that the environmental issue had grabbed the attention of top political advisers. The President did so, and the bill stalled in the Senate.</p>
        <p>The Administration also deftly exploited the close involvement of business lobbyists, who were tilting their campaign contributions heavily toward Republicans, in drafting some of the new legislation. That raised the hackles of many voters, polls showed.</p>
        <p>"We've obviously stopped the wave of repealers and attacks on environmental laws," Mr. Babbitt, the Interior Secretary, said. "But the turn to a positive agenda is just barely in the making. The adversarial approach to legislation is  what this town is all about. It is a town full of lobbyists and lawyers on all sides, who are obsessively inward-looking, who do not have a feel for how these  issues work on the ground. The question for post-'96 is, are we fated to repeat  this endless cycle, or do we have an opportunity to find, and build and cement a consensus that will hold?" The Strategy Search for Consensus Is the Main Goal</p>
        <p>Indeed, a hallmark of the Administration's environmental policy is the premise that consensus can work, letting everybody win.</p>
        <p>That premise has been tested in one setting after another, with varying results. It was the basis for the Administration's approach to the Endangered Species Act, a law which has often led to court battles between antagonists but  which the Administration used instead to negotiate broad compromises on preserving habitat. Similarly, the Administration tried again and again to broker what it termed "common sense" agreements on controlling industrial pollution.</p>
        <p>Confronting a groundswell of opposition to the species law among property owners trapped in litigation and delay, the Administration set out to win over the logging companies, developers, and ranchers who were its biggest critics. In Georgia came a deal to protect the red-cockaded woodpecker while allowing logging to continue in parts of the bird's habitat. In Southern California, a similar deal was struck with housing developers to protect the gnatcatcher, a songbird.</p>
        <p>In both cases, not just a single species but an entire ecosystem could come under protection, potentially helping hundreds of plants and animals avoid eventual demise. And landowners who agreed to sign contracts for proper stewardship were promised what Mr. Babbitt called "no surprises." Once a habitat was protected, there would not be subsequent demands for further restrictions on how the land was used.</p>
        <p>Administration officials believe that the changes are permanent.</p>
        <p>"We have reinvented the way habitat protection is done in this country, and I don't think we are ever going to go back," said George Frampton, the Assistant Secretary of Interior for Fish and Wildlife who was the head of the Wilderness Society before joining the Administration.</p>
        <p>Ms. Browner said her agency had brought about permanent change.</p>
        <p>"I honestly believe that in 10 years, when you look at the regulatory portion of the agency's work that how those standards are set will be place by place, sector by sector," Ms. Browner said. "That is fundamentally different than doing it the pollutant-by-pollutant, crisis-by-crisis way of the past."</p>
        <p>It has not been easy, especially amid the anti-bureaucracy hammering from Capitol Hill, to turn her slogan of "common sense" into the agency's standard operating procedure.</p>
        <p>The difficulty was captured at a meeting of Government officials, environmentalists and industry representatives in Washington last October. The advisory committee had convened at the request of auto makers to endorse a new,  flexible approach that the Administration was proposing to meet the air pollution permit requirements of the Clean Air Act, which had passed with bipartisan support in 1990 and were signed by President George Bush.</p>
        <p>While few citizens were even aware of the new controls put on industry by Title V of that law, everybody in the room knew that billions of dollars were potentially at stake in how the regulations to carry out the law were written and that industry lobbyists were working hard on Capitol Hill to have that part  of the law rewritten..</p>
        <p>So Ms. Browner made clear to the group that she wanted a quid pro quo before  the committee endorsed her new policy and put the stamp of consensus on it. She wanted corporate lobbyists to back off from their efforts to roll back the regulations on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>"I think I asked a perfectly legitimate question," Ms. Browner said later. "The business people were sitting in the room, but man, they were getting a better deal somewhere else."</p>
        <p>In the end, the question was left hanging that day like a thin summer smog. And the essential issue -- how hard the the industry will lobby for fundamental  change in environmental regulation -- will help determine what lies ahead.</p>
        <p>But especially after Senate Democrats successfully filibustered Bob Dole's regulatory overhaul, a major part of the Contract With America, industry appeared to be once again joining the search for a middle road on environmental  regulation.</p>
        <p>This year, when the President's Council on Sustainable Development issued recommendations on a new framework for environmental regulation, it was endorsed by companies like Dow Chemical as well as by environmental groups like the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>"I truly believe," said the head of the White House Council on Environmental  Quality, Katie McGinty, "that the President will go down in history for having put in place a new generation of environmentalism, based on cooperation not confrontation: defining and securing the common ground, defining the common interest, not the special interest."</p>
        <p>Even Republican environmental leaders acknowledge that this might occur. William Ruckleshaus, who headed the E.P.A. when it was first created under Mr. Nixon and again after it was shaken by scandal in the Reagan Administration, said he hoped the political opportunity to overhaul the system would arise "sometime after the next Presidential election."</p>
        <p>"Windows of rationality, where we experience a calmer atmosphere more conducive to constructive change, open infrequently, and usually only for a short period of time," Mr. Ruckleshaus said.</p>
        <p>The Continuing War Logging Compromise Kindles Criticism</p>
        <p>In the woods, consensus has been as elusive as Sasquatch.</p>
        <p>Just ask Tom Vuyovich, as he watches the logging trucks rumble day and night  past the little motel he owns in the Oregon Cascades. All around him, big trees  are falling in the Willamette National Forest. Detroit Lake is silted in by the  inevitable erosion from heavy logging. Protesters trying to block further cutting are arrested daily.</p>
        <p>"We're right in the middle of a giant war, and they're logging everything," Mr. Vuyovich said. "Clinton said he was going to end this. So why are they taking 500-year-old trees out and scaring away all the tourists?"</p>
        <p>As a candidate, Mr. Clinton promised to end the epic conflict over the last of the nation's big trees. Barely three months into his Presidency, he tried to  fulfill that promise by convening what he called a forest summit, an extraordinary session in Portland, Ore., attended by environmentalists, timber industry executives, workers and Government officials, including the President,  nearly a third of his Cabinet and low-ranking Forest Service rangers.</p>
        <p>What came out of the summit was a plan largely to end logging on the last six million or so acres of ancient forests on public land, most of it in the Pacific Northwest. And there was a pledge to spend $1.2 billion to retrain workers and restore land torn up by excessive logging.</p>
        <p>It seemed, at first, to be a major triumph. Protests disappeared. Lawsuits were settled. Ex-loggers went to school, and unemployment in the timber communities actually fell to record low levels.</p>
        <p>But the industry continued to complain about how much timber they were allowed to have, and in mid-1995, Congress responded with what came to be called the salvage logging rider. This provision was tacked onto an unrelated spending  bill. Described by its sponsors as a measure directed at culling dead and dying  trees from ailing forests, it also opened the way for cutting many healthy stands as well, bypassing the protection of environmental laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton vetoed it. Then, stunning some top environmental aides, he reversed course and signed the measure. A Federal court then gave the broadest possible interpretation to the bill, and throughout the West, even in the very areas that Mr. Clinton had vowed to protect, logging picked up speed.</p>
        <p>"That was, indeed, our biggest mistake," Mr. Gore said, "and it never would have happened except for a miscalculation on our part about the magnitude of what was wrong with the provision. We were genuinely surprised, indeed shocked,  by the court decision, which vastly expanded the scope of something we thought could be muted by administrative action. We knew it was not good policy. But it was one of those examples of one thing imbedded in a huge, overall measure that had to pass."</p>
        <p>Critics call that a lame excuse.</p>
        <p>"Because of that rider, I give this President a 'D' on forests," said Jim Jontz, a former Democratic member of Congress now working on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club protested in a park across the street from the White House with a sarcastic 21-chain-saw salute. David Werntz of the Northwest Ecosystem Alliance summed up the feeling recently in a single word: "Betrayal!"</p>
        <p>But sound bites and photo opportunities are not the real stuff of environmental pollution. Natural resources and the public's health are, and they are harder to measure. Unlike an economic record, which can be measured in the quarterly rate of employment, gross national product, and inflation, an environmental record is written over long years and in one ordinary place at a time.</p>
        <p>What ordinary people want in the Silver Valley, Mrs. Miller said, is a river  that is no longer dead, a river that does not pose a health risk to children, a  river without the word "Superfund" attached to it.</p>
        <p>"It's in our back yard now," Mrs. Miller said. "But nobody is immune when you're talking about things that affect how we all live."</p>
        <p>Next: Criminal Justice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
