<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diesel Buses to Be Replaced In Big Anti-Pollution Switch</title>
    <meta content="12BUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DE1F3BF931A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diesel Buses to Be Replaced In Big Anti-Pollution Switch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC Transit Authority, after years of lobbying by environmentalists and under increasing pressure from NYS Gov George Pataki, agrees to replace about 500 diesel buses with ones that use natural gas or electricity in what is seen as biggest anti-pollution measure authority has ever taken (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of lobbying by environmentalists, and under pressure from Gov. George E. Pataki, the Transit Authority has agreed to replace about 500 diesel buses with ones that use natural gas or electricity in what supporters say may be the biggest anti-pollution measure the authority has ever taken.</p>
        <p>''There's probably no faster, more effective way to reduce particulate air pollution in New York than to retire old diesel buses and replace them with the cleanest-burning buses available,'' said Richard Kassel, senior attorney for the Natural Resources Defense Council, the group that took the lead in lobbying the Transit Authority to switch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years of lobbying by environmentalists, and under pressure from Gov. George E. Pataki, the Transit Authority has agreed to replace about 500 diesel buses with ones that use natural gas or electricity in what supporters say may be the biggest anti-pollution measure the authority has ever taken.</p>
        <p>''There's probably no faster, more effective way to reduce particulate air pollution in New York than to retire old diesel buses and replace them with the cleanest-burning buses available,'' said Richard Kassel, senior attorney for the Natural Resources Defense Council, the group that took the lead in lobbying the Transit Authority to switch.</p>
        <p>The Transit Authority agreed to a large-scale move into alternative fuels only under intense pressure from Governor Pataki and State Sen. Norman J. Levy, a Republican from Merrick, L.I., who is chairman of the Transportation Committee, according to participants in the talks that led to the accord. The new buses will account for around 14 percent of the Transit Authority's fleet.</p>
        <p>''We think it's terrifically important that buses in New York reduce the amount of particulates in the air,'' said Louis R. Tomson, the Governor's liaison to the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, the Transit Authority's parent agency.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Transit Authority and the M.T.A. have made the commitment verbally, and it is likely to be put in writing today or tomorrow, Mr. Kassel and transit officials said.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have assailed the Transit Authority for years for unwillingness to give up diesel buses, long after other cities had done so, though they have found Lawrence G. Reuter, who became the authority's president this year, more receptive than his predecessors. Fewer than 40 of the Transit Authority's nearly 3,600 buses run on compressed natural gas, and most of those were bought in the last year. This week's agreement ''is in stark contrast to the lack of interest they have shown in prior years,'' Mr. Levy said.</p>
        <p>The Transit Authority plans to buy 951 new buses in 1997, 1998 and 1999, at a cost of about $300 million. Making more than half of those clean-fuel buses will add tens of millions of dollars to that price, though there is considerable dispute over the actual number. But Mr. Tomson said that part of the added cost could be covered by an environmental bond issue being promoted by the Governor.</p>
        <p>Though a deal has been struck, there is still uncertainty about what kind of fuel the new buses will use. The environmentalists want the Transit Authority to use compressed natural gas, a technology that has been proven in years of use in transit systems around the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reuter and other transit officials would rather use hybrid diesel-electric buses, which exist now only as prototypes.</p>
        <p>Essentially, Mr. Kassel and his colleagues are betting that diesel-electric buses will not be commercially produced -- or, if they are, that they will not prove as reliable or as clean as natural gas -- in time for the authority to comply with the pact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reuter is betting that they will. ''We have agreed that we're going down a parallel track of CNG or hybrid electric,'' he said, ''and if the commercial hybrid electric becomes available, we would go that way.''</p>
        <p>The appeal of natural gas lies largely in what is wrong with diesel. In cities, diesel engines are the biggest source of particulate pollution -- soot -- which the Natural Resources Defense Council estimates causes 4,000 premature deaths in New York City each year. ''Diesel soot is the most underaddressed air pollution problem we have,'' Mr. Kassel said.</p>
        <p>Natural gas produces no soot when burned. It also produces far smaller amounts of pollutants like nitrogen oxides and carbon monoxide than does diesel.</p>
        <p>But servicing a fleet of natural gas buses would mean a major overhaul of three of the Transit Authority's vast depots. Mr. Reuter estimated the cost of that work at about $70 million, while Mr. Kassel said it could be as little as $29 million. In addition, natural gas buses are expected to cost 10 to 30 percent more than diesel buses, or $25 million to $35 million more for 500 of them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reuter said an advantage of hybrid diesel-electric buses is that ''you don't have to make major depot modifications.''</p>
        <p>A hybrid bus has a small diesel engine and four electric motors, one at each corner of the bus. That configuration allows the interior floor of the bus to be much lower than in conventional buses, making loading and unloading easier.</p>
        <p>Either way, Mr. Kassel said, progress is being made. ''If the hybrid ends up being a cheaper bus that's as clean as natural gas, that's great,'' he said. ''We have a commitment to 500 cleaner buses. That's what matters.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
