<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>El Nino Versus El Nonsense; Keeping Cool Heads in Midst Of Serious Ocean Warming</title>
    <meta content="Y08NIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="971315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocoa</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFD81439F93BA35752C1A961958260" item-length="2047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>El Nino Versus El Nonsense; Keeping Cool Heads in Midst Of Serious Ocean Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Nov. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Traders in commodity markets have long known that periodic warming of Pacific Ocean waters known as El Nino can have dramatic effects on weather patterns around the world; but this year, for all genuine dangers associated with latest outbreak, weather experts worry that fears of El Nino have become so exaggerated that businesses and consumers may end up overreacting to threat; one example is that prices in commodities like cocoa and coffee rose this summer, only to retreat after initial worries appeared overblown; map; graphs; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early this summer, Smith Barney Inc.'s Latin American stock trading desk in New York held a meeting for brokers and money managers on how the latest episode in the periodic warming of Pacific Ocean waters known as El Nino might affect corporate profits across that continent.</p>
        <p>''Commodities traders have been interested in El Nino events for years,'' said Jon B. Davis, the company's meteorologist, who was flown in from his office here for the gathering. ''But this was the first time I'd seen the equities side talking about it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early this summer, Smith Barney Inc.'s Latin American stock trading desk in New York held a meeting for brokers and money managers on how the latest episode in the periodic warming of Pacific Ocean waters known as El Nino might affect corporate profits across that continent.</p>
        <p>''Commodities traders have been interested in El Nino events for years,'' said Jon B. Davis, the company's meteorologist, who was flown in from his office here for the gathering. ''But this was the first time I'd seen the equities side talking about it.''</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Davis took the meeting as a healthy sign that El Nino was finally getting the respect it deserved. As traders in the energy and agricultural markets have long known, El Nino conditions are linked to drastic shifts in weather patterns across much of the globe.</p>
        <p>Since then, though, El Nino has gone on to become to weather what the O. J. Simpson case was to the legal system. Loose talk has gathered so much momentum that El Nino has smashed through the common sense barrier into misconceptions that are influencing consumer behavior and businesses in ways that leave Mr. Davis and other meteorologists shaking their heads in amazement and dismay.</p>
        <p>''I knew it was completely out of control,'' he said, ''when a broker in New York told me he'd heard people in elevators saying they didn't need to buy a coat this winter because of El Nino. You can have plenty of cold days -- you can have record cold days -- even if past El Ninos suggest that conditions in the Northeast will be milder than normal.''</p>
        <p>The misconceptions have put meteorologists in a tough position. No one wants to play down the dangers associated with this El Nino. Already, much of Southeast Asia is in the grip of a drought that threatens to cut production of internationally important crops like coffee and palm oil. Some mines in Asia dependent on hydroelectric power have even closed.</p>
        <p>Weather linked to El Nino has also cut potential wheat yields in Australia, delayed spring planting in Brazil and Argentina, and ravaged the tourist trade on the west coast of Mexico. Peru shut down all anchovy fishing for three months, forcing thousands of fishermen out of work and sending futures traders scrambling to bid up the prices of alternative animal feed ingredients. And most meteorologists believe much more is still to come, especially for North America.</p>
        <p>Still, weather experts shudder at how exaggerating the likely impact of El Nino could end up costing businesses and consumers a lot of money: unnecessarily canceled vacations, hasty and poorly executed roof repairs where they may not be needed, overconfidence about low energy prices based on projections of a mild winter in the snow belt, shady stockbrokers hyping investments in building supply companies -- the list is endless. And they worry that unchecked misconceptions will end up breeding public skepticism when El Nino hype and misinformation are  eventually exposed.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Smith, president of Weather Data Inc., a weather forecasting and consulting firm based in Wichita, Kan., said he concluded things were ''out of hand'' during a recent trip to Southern California when he heard a television weatherman there attributing a wildfire to El Nino.</p>
        <p>''You always have fires at this time of year out there,'' Mr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>In the Midwest, harsh weather is much more common and sensitivity to changes is heightened because of its effects on transportation, farming and commodity markets. But Midwesterners, too, are not immune from El Nonsense. Although there is nothing unusual about fall blizzards on the Great Plains, for instance, Mr. Smith has fielded countless calls from clients assuming El Nino played a role in the severity of the snowstorm that socked the region late last month.</p>
        <p>El Nino ''events,'' as Mr. Davis and other weather experts call them, develop every three to five years. El Nino -- a reference to the birth of Jesus -- got its name from Peruvian fishermen, who noted nearly a century ago that the periodic ocean warming often peaked around Christmas.</p>
        <p>The Peruvians realized such conditions often went hand in hand with unusually heavy rains and flooding. In recent decades, computers, satellites and vastly improved data gathering have made it clear that El Nino's tentacles spread to vast areas in Asia, Australia and Africa, which become much more susceptible to drought.</p>
        <p>The warming water pattern also increases the likelihood of hurricanes and violent weather on Mexico's west coast while tending to suppress such giant storms in the Atlantic Ocean. During the winter, much of the southern tier of the United States, from California to Florida, is likely to experience heavier, more frequent winter rains.</p>
        <p>El Nino commonly shakes up global temperatures, too, altering normal patterns enough to have an impact on certain regional energy markets. The Upper Midwest, a major cold weather market for natural gas, typically experiences milder-than-normal winters during an outbreak.</p>
        <p>El Nino began to achieve celebrity status this summer when ocean temperatures rose so rapidly that this year's episode began shaping up as the strongest yet recorded, surpassing that of the winter of 1982-83. The climbing temperatures sent marlin, swordfish and other exotic warm water species north as far as Washington State, much to the delight of American anglers and TV camera crews.</p>
        <p>But they also dredged up memories of the torrential winter rains and tornadoes in Southern California and other unusual weather attributed to the 1982-83 El Nino. By some estimates, weather linked to that El Nino killed 2,000 people around the world and caused $13.6 billion in damage.</p>
        <p>Many Californians are rushing to prepare for an equally brutal winter this year. Demand for roofing material, gutters and related products is up as much as 20 percent from a year ago, according to Matthew Janke, inventory control manager for Ace Hardware, who monitors shipments from the hardware cooperative's warehouses to Ace members. Some Ace stores are encouraging the frenzy with special end-of-aisle displays tied to El Nino.</p>
        <p>Indeed, local retailers that stand to benefit from ''El Nino'' can be quick to spread misconceptions. ''The current extreme heat displays the power of El Nino,'' trumpeted a press release on Tuesday by Pioneer Roofing Tile Inc., which is based in Fontana, Calif., about 50 miles east of Los Angeles. It was looking to gain publicity to help increase sales of its roof repair products.</p>
        <p>''That's ridiculous,'' said Mr. Davis, the Smith Barney meteorologist. No weather condition over just a few days in any one area should be blamed on El Nino, and while temperatures in Southern California were unusually high recently, extreme autumn heat there is not associated with El Nino, he said. Diane Hernandez, a spokeswoman at Waters &amp; Company, Pioneer's public relations firm, said that ''local media'' had been the source of the company's information.</p>
        <p>Lest anyone take too laid back an attitude about the potential dangers, a group of California state agencies is sponsoring El Nino preparedness briefings in communities ranging from San Diego to Chico, about 150 miles northeast of San Francisco. Local newspapers, television and radio stations feature a steady diet of El Nino-related reporting that runs the gamut from sober to silly to sarcastic.</p>
        <p>''This is the best-publicized potential disaster in history,'' said Mr. Smith, the weather consultant. ''Some of the precautions like cleaning out flood-control channels will pay off handsomely if there are problems. But people are drawing too close a parallel to 1982-83.''</p>
        <p>The deluge of coverage has spilled well beyond California, meteorologists say, and overwhelmed cautionary notes about how varied the impact of El Nino is likely to be around the country. Indeed, this year's El Nino has already diverged from the norm in many ways.</p>
        <p>As often happens during an El Nino episode, Indonesia and other parts of Southeast Asia have suffered from drought this year. That calamity became acute and big news around the world last month when fires set to clear land burned out of control. That sent choking clouds of smoke across the region. By contrast, neither Australia nor India, which are also prone to El Nino-related droughts, have had severe water problems yet.</p>
        <p>Such variations mean that it is just as easy to bet too heavily on El Nino-driven weather as to prepare too little. Cocoa future prices, which had been rising based in large part on fears that El Nino-related dryness in West Africa would limit this year's harvest, have tumbled recently with reports that those fears appear to be overblown.</p>
        <p>Investors also need to be aware that business conditions may be very different from the last big El Nino 15 years ago. Even if weather patterns in the months ahead come close to those experienced in the fearsome 1982-83 El Nino, the results this time could be quite different. Already, for example, sugar production in Central America has been less hurt by drought than some investors expected because many farmers now irrigate their fields.</p>
        <p>In any event, analysts note, bets on El Nino's impact have to be weighed against the many other factors that also affect business. Tensions with Iraq could send energy prices soaring even if this El Nino, as expected, produces a milder winter across much of North America.</p>
        <p>Rather than betting on how closely this El Nino will track previous events, some businesses are focusing on the market volatility that comes with uncertainty about the weather. Utilicorp United, an energy provider and trader based in Kansas City, Mo., recognizes that natural gas prices could tumble in a mild winter but it has opted to buy and store more gas this winter than normal, according to a company spokesman. It does not want to worry about price gyrations after each winter storm.</p>
        <p>Strange as it may seem, given El Nino's still-gathering strength and increasing fame, the biggest risk to the economy lies in what may come after El Nino has faded from the headlines. If El Nino wanes or gradually disappears altogether by next summer, as Government forecasters currently expect, farmers in the Midwest can expect fairly normal growing conditions.</p>
        <p>But if temperatures in the eastern Pacific sink early and quickly fall into lower-than-normal ranges -- an event known as La Nina -- the chances of drought here in the world's most important farm region soar. With grain supplies already near post-World War II lows, La Nina could send prices to record highs, punishing consumers around the globe while encouraging farmers in developing countries to expand their environmentally disastrous practice of setting forest fires to clear land.</p>
        <p>''Just the threat of that has limited the interest farmers have in selling all of the crop they are harvesting now or pre-selling next year,'' said Charles Flory, editor of ProFarmer Newsletter in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. ''The grain markets are saturated with information about El Nino but we certainly haven't factored in that worst-case scenario.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
