<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>El Nino's Wrath: Floods and Tickets</title>
    <meta content="Y26NIN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marlin (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DD163AF935A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>El Nino's Wrath: Floods and Tickets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>WESTPORT, Wash., Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fishermen are catching marlin and other semitropical fish in normally frigid waters off coast of Westport, Wash, as El Nino warms Pacific waters and toys with weather; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is still early in the ''weather event of the century,'' as some scientists have taken to calling El Nino, which is brewing in the Pacific, threatening a tantrum of odd and calamitous  weather late in the year.</p>
        <p>But for now, as a huge swath of the Pacific Ocean heats up in the formative stage of El Nino, the harbingers are mostly freakish, and some people are reveling in the climatic quirks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is still early in the ''weather event of the century,'' as some scientists have taken to calling El Nino, which is brewing in the Pacific, threatening a tantrum of odd and calamitous  weather late in the year.</p>
        <p>But for now, as a huge swath of the Pacific Ocean heats up in the formative stage of El Nino, the harbingers are mostly freakish, and some people are reveling in the climatic quirks.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, a retired painter pulled a 104-pound marlin, the sport fish of Baja California, from the ocean off the coast here -- the first time anyone had even seen such a fish in the normally frigid waters that batter the Northwest shore.</p>
        <p>This week, a yellowfin tuna, another semitropical fish, was landed not far from here. It was the first ever caught in the area, said state fish and wildlife officials. It makes  sense, biologists said, at a time when people are surfing here without wetsuits in near-Mediterranean water of 68 degrees, nearly 10 degrees above normal.</p>
        <p>''Unreal, isn't it?'' said Dick Miller, who caught the marlin. ''My partner and I looked at each other when that fish jumped after taking my line, and we both said, 'What the hell is that?' ''</p>
        <p>Off Northern California, mahi-mahi, swordfish and other warm-water fish have been caught in recent days, prompting the California Fish and Game Department to issue a news release with the headline, ''El Nino Brings Great Opportunity for Anglers.''</p>
        <p>Warm surface water is bringing the fish up from Mexico, said Kimberly McKee-Lewis, a marine biologist with the agency. ''People are just going berserk down here with the quality of fishing,'' she said from San Diego.</p>
        <p>Because of stronger winds and cleansing storms credited to El Nino,  Southern California may record its best year for clean air in decades. So far, there have been only 25 days with health advisories for people with respiratory problems, compared with 48 by this time last year.</p>
        <p>But the warm-water fishing and cleaner air may be some of the last positive results of El Nino in California, if predictions hold. Previous warming events were blamed for mud slides, flooding, road washouts and erosion of beaches.</p>
        <p>This week, scientists at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., distributed satellite images of El Nino, showing that the warm water mass had grown to one-and-a-half times the size of the continental United States. The main mass is off the coast of South America, while arms of warm water have been expanding up and down the coastline.</p>
        <p>El Nino, referring to the Christ Child, got its name from fishermen who as long as 200 years ago would notice warm water off Peru around Christmas time some years years. It  can occur every few years, though it has been doing so more frequently. If large enough, El Nino is believed to alter weather patterns worldwide for months, causing heavy rain in some areas, drought in others and disrupting the marine food chain. The present El Nino could be the biggest in 150 years, many scientists say. The one in 1982-83, the most severe of the last 50 years, was blamed for up to 2,000 deaths worldwide and more than $13 billion in property damage.</p>
        <p>Weather predictions based on the present maps call for pounding rainstorms in Southern California and other areas of the Southwest, and a wetter-than-usual winter in Florida, while the Pacific Northwest and the Northeast could be drier and warmer than usual.</p>
        <p>Already, this year's warming is both credited and blamed for any change in the atmosphere and ocean. ''No matter what happens, people are going to blame El Nino,'' said Troy Swauger, a spokesman for California's Fish and Game Department. ''I got a parking ticket the other day -- hey, it's El Nino's fault.''</p>
        <p>El Nino forecasts, like typical long-range weather predictions, are inexact. ''This is still a work in progress,'' said Jan Lubchenco, a marine ecologist at Oregon State University. ''There are a lot of things about it that we don't understand.''</p>
        <p>But there is no doubt that water along virtually the entire Pacific Coast has heated to levels rarely seen, bringing with it fish that follow the warm current. A warm-water sunfish called mola mola was caught off southeast Alaska this summer, while there has been an influx of sardines and anchovies off the California and Oregon coast.</p>
        <p>''The exciting part of El Nino is when you see these fish in places where they aren't supposed to be,'' said Brian Culver, a resource manager with the Washington State Fish and Wildlife Department. ''But we'll be paying dues for this for years to come. Big dues.''</p>
        <p>At the recent annual meeting of the American Fisheries Society, a professional group, the present warming was viewed as potentially the most devastating one for marine life in more than a century.</p>
        <p>The biggest fear among biologists is for salmon, already threatened on much of the West Coast because of overfishing and river dams that block spawning migration. Warmer water brings with it Pacific mackerel, which prey on juvenile salmon as they leave rivers to begin life at sea.</p>
        <p>''We know this one is going to be a doozy,'' Chuck Coutant, the past president of the American Fisheries Society, said of El Nino. ''For salmon, there's strong apprehension bordering on mild panic.''</p>
        <p>But one predator's loss is another's gain. Mike May, who caught the  rare yellowfin tuna this week, welcomes the El Nino change.</p>
        <p>''I think this is great,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Dick Miller, who caught the marlin, would trade the fish for a normal weather pattern. Mr. Miller has been fishing for salmon for more than 40 years, and he fears the effect of the warm water on the signature fish of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>''As much as a thrill as it was catching that big fish, I hate to see this El Nino again,'' Mr. Miller said. ''Salmon are in such terrible shape as it is. I fear what is to come.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
