<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Find Favorable Farm Climate, a World Map on the Web</title>
    <meta content="17WATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="916261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Utah State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DD1538F934A25750C0A961958260" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Find Favorable Farm Climate, a World Map on the Web</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists at Utah State University develop data base encompassing decades of information on water, temperature and climate for every square mile of land on Earth that could benefit farmers; World Water and Climate Atlas for Agriculture is available on CD-ROM and free of charge on Utah State Internet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers have developed a database encompassing decades of information on water, temperature and climate for every square mile of land on Earth, a tool that could benefit farmers, scientists and policymakers worldwide.</p>
        <p>Establishment of the database, the World Water and Climate Atlas for Agriculture, was announced today by scientists at the International Irrigation Management Institute and Utah State University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers have developed a database encompassing decades of information on water, temperature and climate for every square mile of land on Earth, a tool that could benefit farmers, scientists and policymakers worldwide.</p>
        <p>Establishment of the database, the World Water and Climate Atlas for Agriculture, was announced today by scientists at the International Irrigation Management Institute and Utah State University.</p>
        <p>Users of the atlas, which will be available on CD-ROM and free of charge on a Utah State Internet, will be able to extract moisture and temperature data for an area as small as one square mile. The first segment, covering Asia, is to be available by June, the entire database by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''This is a unique resource that should benefit agriculture everywhere,'' Dr. David Seckler, director of the institute, said.</p>
        <p>The institute, a research center based in Colombo, Sri Lanka, is one of 16 centers supported by the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research, an association of nations and private organizations fostering food and crop science.</p>
        <p>Members include the World Bank and the Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations. The project, which researchers estimate will cost less than $1 million, is being financed by the Japanese Government.</p>
        <p>''The atlas integrates the available agricultural climate data into one computer program and represents the most comprehensive, quality-controlled climatic data set in existence,'' said Ismail Serageldin, chairman of the international group.</p>
        <p>Donald T. Jensen, director of the Utah Climate Center at Utah State, said he and Andy Keller of the irrigation institute developed the atlas from data received from 56,000 weather stations around the world. The information, covering 1961 to 1990, came from combining data gathered by the United States, Canada, United Nations organizations and military sources worldwide.</p>
        <p>The atlas includes 10-day, monthly and annual summaries of average, maximum and minimum temperatures, rainfall and other forms of moisture, and precipitation probabilities. It also includes data on evaporation, which is compared to precipitation figures to estimate moisture availability for crops and to help locate areas needing irrigation.</p>
        <p>''The information in this database is a vast improvement over what we've had before,'' Dr. Seckler said, ''It will make us a little smarter in how we use water, especially as it becomes scarcer in the future.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Seckler said 70 percent of all water used each year goes for irrigation, which produces between 30 to 40 percent of the world's food on just 17 percent of all arable land.</p>
        <p>Using this information, the scientists said, engineers can develop better plans for irrigation and water conservation. In addition, agronomists should be able to identify areas where new types of crops might be introduced.</p>
        <p>The scientists said the database is designed to be expanded. So far it contains no information from weather and sensing satellites in space, which could add data on seasonal crop growth, among other things.</p>
        <p>The Food and Agricultural Organization has drawn a map of the soils of the world, Dr. Seckler said, and this information will be combined with the water atlas to help determine the best conditions for particular crops.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
