<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>El Nino Is Back, Scientist Says, With Threat Of Global Havoc</title>
    <meta content="21NINO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="938468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DE103EF932A15755C0A961958260" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>El Nino Is Back, Scientist Says, With Threat Of Global Havoc</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>el nino is back, scientist says, with threat of global havoc**Government scientists say potent weather disrupter known as El Nino is returning, shaping up as one of strongest climatic events of its kind on record; say latest resurgence of abnormally high ocean temperatures in eastern Pacific, which causes atmospheric chain reactions around world, could equal 1982-83 El Nino, most disruptive in this century; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The potent weather disrupter known as El Nino is returning, and Government scientists say it is shaping up as one of the strongest climatic events of its kind on record.</p>
        <p>While it is too early to know for sure, the scientists say, this latest resurgence of abnormally high ocean temperatures in the eastern Pacific, which causes atmospheric chain reactions around the world, could equal the 1982-83 El Nino, the most disruptive in this century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The potent weather disrupter known as El Nino is returning, and Government scientists say it is shaping up as one of the strongest climatic events of its kind on record.</p>
        <p>While it is too early to know for sure, the scientists say, this latest resurgence of abnormally high ocean temperatures in the eastern Pacific, which causes atmospheric chain reactions around the world, could equal the 1982-83 El Nino, the most disruptive in this century.</p>
        <p>During that fall, winter and spring, torrential rains swept California and much of the southern two-thirds of the United States, causing floods, mud slides and coast-to-coast havoc.</p>
        <p>Australia and Indonesia suffered through a killing drought, as did parts of South America and Africa. The life-giving Indian monsoon weakened. Commercial fishing off the Pacific coast of the Americas was devastated.</p>
        <p>Whether the new edition of El Nino matches that of 1982-83, forecasters say it looks as if it will rank among the strongest of the century.</p>
        <p>''This El Nino is shaping up to be similar to the strong events of 1957, 1972 and 1982-83,'' Dr. Ants Leetmaa, director of the Climate Prediction Center of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Camp Springs, Md., said this week.</p>
        <p>The magnitude of El Nino's impact on the weather is directly related to how warm the eastern Pacific gets around the Equator. There, Federal forecasters said, sea-surface temperatures last month were more than five degrees above normal. Those were the warmest seas recorded there since August 1983.</p>
        <p>The Climate Prediction Center said the warming should continue in the months ahead, bringing peak El Nino conditions next winter. The main impact should be felt from November through March, Government scientists said.</p>
        <p>Despite El Nino's rapid development, scientists said its influence on summer weather had historically been inconsistent, making a summer forecast of its impact uncertain.</p>
        <p>The current forecast for July through September in the United States, issued earlier this week, calls for above-normal temperatures along the Eastern Seaboard from New York to Florida, along the Pacific Coast and in the Southwest, with below-normal temperatures in the Plains and the Rockies. The prediction also called for above-normal precipitation from Montana eastward through the Great Lakes.</p>
        <p>El Nino's summer impact is considered especially important in the development of hurricanes. Strong westerly winds generated in the tropics by El Nino tend to shear developing hurricanes apart before they can mature. Earlier this month, forecasters at Colorado State University in Fort Collins predicted that this year's hurricane season would be more active than normal for the third consecutive year.</p>
        <p>But that forecast, said Dr. William M. Gray, its chief author, was predicated on the judgment that El Nino would not be a factor this year.</p>
        <p>As things stand now, Dr. Gray ''will probably have to revise his forecast down,'' said Vernon Kousky, an authority on El Ninos at the Climate Prediction Center.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kousky said the westerlies were already developing, and that ''the way things have grown up in the last month or so, this El Nino could well impact this hurricane season.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray could not be reached for comment, but he plans to update his hurricane forecast in August.</p>
        <p>Should El Nino develop as predicted next winter, it could affect the weather in the United States in a variety of ways. For example, while it has often brought torrential rains to California, it sometimes causes drought there. And it can have a number of effects on the Northeast.</p>
        <p>In one mode, for instance, El Nino sends strong winter storms churning up the East Coast -- and if they encounter cold Canadian air, blizzards can result. In another mode, it can block the cold air and make for a balmy winter -- as happened in January 1995, when New York had temperatures in the 60's.</p>
        <p>By this fall, Mr. Kousky said, the evolving El Nino weather pattern may give ''some indication of what winter will have in store for us.''</p>
        <p>Forecasters have developed great skill in predicting El Nino's comings and goings, but their track record is not perfect. For example, one of the first scientists to forecast El Nino successfully, Dr. Mark A. Cane of the Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory at Columbia University, said the computer model on which his predictions were based ''is not coming up'' with El Nino this year.</p>
        <p>Other models have predicted it, he said, adding that the warming tropical seas and other signs make it look ''almost unavoidable.'' But he added that ''nature has a way of fooling us, so we'll see what happens.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
