<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Preaching, the Lure of the Taboo</title>
    <meta content="24KLEI$23" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970907T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5D61F3FF937A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="2374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Preaching, the Lure of the Taboo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Richard Klein on the lure of the taboo, particularly smoking; notes that smoking is, once again, hot in entertainment media; says Hillary Rodham Clinton recently blamed Hollywood for increase in teen-age smoking; says she does not allow for possibility that films merely exploit climate of repression and censorship surrounding tobacco; says adolescents are curious about abyss between what can be said and shown about smoking, and fact that more than 25 million adults continue legally to smoke; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOWARD THE END OF THIS SUMMER'S hit film comedy ''My Best Friend's Wedding,'' Julia Roberts is hunched on the floor of a hotel hallway, her back propped against the door. The man she wants to marry is in the room getting news of her betrayals. We see her extract -- from her bra, it appears -- a pack of Marlboros. Hesitantly, shakily, she lights a cigarette. The viewer is supposed to see the cigarette and her nervous smoking as a visible counterpart to the panicky feelings of imminent loss that are sweeping over her. She's about to explode, and this cigarette, as it often is in films, is a fuse. Utterly desolate, out in the cold, Ms. Roberts never looked more appealing, huddled around a brief flame and warming cinder, smoke streaming glamorously from her nose.</p>
        <p>Smoking, once again, is hot in the entertainment media. Half the movies released between 1990 and 1995 featured a major character who chose to light up on screen, a significant increase compared with 29 percent in the 1970's, according to a recent study at the University of California, San Francisco. And the trend appears to be accelerating. In her syndicated column earlier this month, Hillary Rodham Clinton noted that 77 percent of all films last year had scenes depicting smoking, as did every film nominated for best picture at the Academy Awards. She went on to denounce films that ''equate smoking with status, power, confidence and glamour.'' Mrs. Clinton cites these facts in order to blame Hollywood for an increase in teen-age smoking, ''despite,'' she says, ''the best efforts of parents and teachers to educate children about the dangerous effects of tobacco.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOWARD THE END OF THIS SUMMER'S hit film comedy ''My Best Friend's Wedding,'' Julia Roberts is hunched on the floor of a hotel hallway, her back propped against the door. The man she wants to marry is in the room getting news of her betrayals. We see her extract -- from her bra, it appears -- a pack of Marlboros. Hesitantly, shakily, she lights a cigarette. The viewer is supposed to see the cigarette and her nervous smoking as a visible counterpart to the panicky feelings of imminent loss that are sweeping over her. She's about to explode, and this cigarette, as it often is in films, is a fuse. Utterly desolate, out in the cold, Ms. Roberts never looked more appealing, huddled around a brief flame and warming cinder, smoke streaming glamorously from her nose.</p>
        <p>Smoking, once again, is hot in the entertainment media. Half the movies released between 1990 and 1995 featured a major character who chose to light up on screen, a significant increase compared with 29 percent in the 1970's, according to a recent study at the University of California, San Francisco. And the trend appears to be accelerating. In her syndicated column earlier this month, Hillary Rodham Clinton noted that 77 percent of all films last year had scenes depicting smoking, as did every film nominated for best picture at the Academy Awards. She went on to denounce films that ''equate smoking with status, power, confidence and glamour.'' Mrs. Clinton cites these facts in order to blame Hollywood for an increase in teen-age smoking, ''despite,'' she says, ''the best efforts of parents and teachers to educate children about the dangerous effects of tobacco.''</p>
        <p>There can be no doubt about those efforts. In the last four and a half years, American teen-agers have been the object of the most sustained and systematic anti-smoking campaign ever mounted, directed at them from their earliest age by every adult institution of authority, particularly by the Clinton White House. Yet teen-age smoking during the same period has increased alarmingly. The President himself announced a 30 percent increase in smoking among 10th graders and 40 percent among 9th graders. Children are smoking more and starting earlier.</p>
        <p>Who can doubt that they are being influenced by the new aura of cool that surrounds smoking in the media? When  television isn't preaching the evils of tobacco, it's putting cigarettes in the hands of unlikable characters, the ones we love to hate. On the silver screen, the sexiest, most bewitching stars make smoking look glamorous again. Somewhere along the way, all that preaching has backfired.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton specifically points to smoking by Leonardo DiCaprio in ''Romeo and Juliet,'' and Kurt Russell in ''Escape From L.A.'' But in ''Sleepers,'' Brad Pitt did it. Arnold Schwarzenegger telling ''True Lies'' did it. Kristin Scott Thomas did it in ''The English Patient.'' John Travolta does it in practically every film he makes, even when he plays an angel, as he did last year in ''Michael.'' Sharon Stone in ''Diabolique'' smokes incessantly in order to show us she's malevolent. Mel Gibson has gone back to cigarettes in order to make a film of Christopher Buckley's witty novel ''Thank You for Smoking,'' which ridicules anti-smoking fanaticism. K. D.Lang, who doesn't smoke, just assembled an album of torch songs about smoking, called ''Drag.''</p>
        <p>Musically, on the Lang CD, taking a drag has Promethean echoes of fiery conquests and the bluesy rhythm of romantic defeats. Cigarette fetishists abound on the Internet at Web sites and in news groups, exchanging mildly pornographic scenes of people smoking. In those aroused by the spectacle of masterly women giving themselves pleasure (all nostril, mouth and fingers), smoking languorously and slow, the moment of lighting up seems to spark the most energetic erotic excitement.</p>
        <p>MRS. CLINTON ARGUES that portrayals of cigarette smoking in films neutralize or counteract the efforts of teachers, parents and Government officials. She doesn't allow for the possibility that the films are merely exploiting the climate of repression and censorship surrounding tobacco, an atmosphere that those well-meaning efforts against smoking have brewed. She herself deserves some credit, and some responsibility, for the way issues of health have been put forth in tones of moral condemnation that entice transgression. As the preaching becomes more intense, tobacco use is eroticized and surrounded by the odor of what is reckless and tabooed, intensifying pleasure. That climate is bound to thicken if the Attorney General's deal to regulate tobacco becomes law and even vaster sums are dedicated to discouraging its use.</p>
        <p>There is a sharp contrast between the image of smoking on television and in films. In the new era, it is forbidden, for example, to show cigarettes used in romantic situations, especially on television. It's hard to remember that in 1952 there was a CBS series called ''The Continental.'' It featured Renzo Cesana, billed as the ''first electronic gigolo,'' dressed in a tuxedo, delivering a monologue but conducting an on-screen seduction, in accents that were suave and lightly Italian. He spoke to the camera as if it were a beautiful woman he was trying to charm with subtle forms of verbal flattery and sexy body language. He compliments you on your dress in ways that are not at all obvious -- are witty, touching, personal. He avoids vulgar flatteries, only telling you what you deeply want to hear. He's never lewd but endlessly suggestive. At the beginning of the show you see a sterling silver cockleshell, on which two cigarettes are smoking. One has lipstick on the tip. He takes them both in his fingers and extends the lipsticked one to you. It is as if his hand is coming through the screen nonchalantly offering you a drag. The gesture is full of erotic implications. If at that moment you yourself reach for a cigarette (mingling your smoke in unison across the tube), it means he has made another conquest and you've been continentaled.</p>
        <p>These days, when smoking is seen on television (five times less often than in the movies), it bears the signs of depravity, obliquity and inveterate corruption. Consider how tobacco companies have recently come to play the role of the Evil Empire, the embodiment of the purest evil and the most profound moral turpitude. In a segment of ''Touched by an Angel,'' Della Reese, in sonorous tones, advises her erring client that God wants him to stop working for the maliciously named Fairchild tobacco company and to stop smoking. ''Thou shalt not smoke'' has become the 11th Commandment. Recently on ''The Newshour With Jim Lehrer,'' several leaders of the anti-smoking campaign repeatedly compared negotiating with the tobacco companies to dealing with the Devil, with whom, it is well known, one negotiates at one's peril. As in a dream, our Granny Government echoes the piety of anti-smoking voices at the turn of the last century, who raised the cry ''Tobacco is a filthy weed, and from the Devil doth proceed.'' Our leaders also sound like temperance crusaders denouncing the ''demon rum.'' Hearing this, one doesn't need to be 16 to have some sympathy for the Devil.</p>
        <p>In the opening frames of one episode of Fox's drama series ''The X-Files,'' before you see the face of the Cigarette Smoking Man (William B. Davis), you see a rat between his feet, cloaked in shadows. Then a smoking butt drops to the floor and chases the rat away. According to the principle, what chases resembles what is chased: the cigarette is ratty.</p>
        <p>And so, by metonymy, is the character, vermin to the core, whose odious lips it recently touched. Everywhere in ''The X-Files,'' in which evil men mostly smoke, the cigarette is the index of the perverse underworld and filthy underside of what is seen in public. You thought Lee Harvey Oswald killed the President; it was actually Cancer Man (as fans and the show's lead character now call the smoking character) obeying the dictates of a hypersecret, intergovernmental conspiracy. When Cancer Man observes his patsy Oswald being arrested in the movie theater for the crime he himself has committed, he lights up a cigarette of cruel satisfaction. For us in the 90's, the great classic cigarette of triumph has become an ironic token of horror -- the pure poison of heartless intentions. In some ''X-Files'' segments, the smoke is the blue embodiment of the dark motives that surround the evil deeds these men hatch in the name of zealous patriotism. When the plotters order an assassination or determine someone's fate, like Delphic oracles their words seem to come from behind the tangible haze of their innumerable cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Smoking on television hasn't always been a sign of villainy, of course. It's still surprising to see Desi Arnaz in 1953, smoking like a fiend in the maternity waiting room, on the famous episode when Lucy gives birth to Little Ricky. You never see the mother, of course, only the expectant father sucking on his cigarette, being brave for his wife but fighting hysterical panic, oblivious to the cigarette he's madly consuming, and we can't stop watching. Cigarettes, it's well known, are magnificent instruments for mitigating anxiety. They are the friend of soldiers, journalists and actors in the wings -- people who must wait for fateful events to occur.</p>
        <p>It is even more surprising, today, looking at early television, to see the title character of ''Dr. Kildare'' offering a light to one of his troubled patients. In the very first scene of the premiere show, in 1961, Dr. Kildare, played handsomely by Richard Chamberlain, bounds up the hospital stairs and puts quarters in a cigarette machine in the lobby. On the show, cigarettes are practically his signature and convey the pervasive assumption that all good doctors smoke. Offering a light or a cigarette, in the hospital, is a sign of sympathetic attention, a gesture of conviviality and sociality that made Dr. Kildare's hospital, before HMO's, a close-knit community. Smoking for the good doctor is a way of taking a break while keeping awake; sleep is what the cigarette wards off as the doctor pursues his exhausting rounds. It is an infallible sign of his thoughtfulness: whenever Dr. Kildare is faced with a grim alternative, he pulls out a cigarette. It indicates to the viewer that the doctor's intervention is not only physical but mental and even intellectual. He knows how to take the time to think, in the time of a cigarette, whose beautiful smoke billowing around his head is the material embodiment of his calmly evolving thoughts.</p>
        <p>One shouldn't forget that cigarette advertising during the period sought and regularly received endorsements from doctors. Philip Morris was ''recommended by eminent nose and throat specialists to those who smoke.'' On Ted Mack's ''Original Amateur Hour,'' the Old Gold dancing pack and her sidekick, the box of matches, once did a special little dance on the television screen to support the New York Heart Fund Campaign.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, in a television discussion of smoking in the movies, the newswoman Cokie Roberts tried to defend ''My Best Friend's Wedding'' from criticism by reminding us that ''Julia Roberts didn't get the guy in the movie,'' that ''it was the wholesome girl who won in the end.'' But it's an old story. We always love a bad girl, and the bad girl smokes.</p>
        <p>Eva Marie Saint had a classic scene in ''Wish on the Moon,'' a 1950's ''Goodyear TV Playhouse'' production. At the beginning of the hour, she's riding a train, going to the Big Apple to make her fortune. She's dressed like a country girl, sitting next to Phyllis Kirk, who looks sophisticated, reading a book and smoking. Saint Eva Marie  declines a cigarette and offers an apple in return. But by the end of the hour she has undergone a startling metamorphosis. She has become a tough Hollywood star. In the famous last scene, what once was innocence is dressed to kill in a tight black sheath, her hair teased, her neckline plunging. She is brashly doing business on the phone, a cigarette permanently between her teeth or twirled at her fingertips. When she takes a puff, she blows the smoke back up her nose, the sign of a hardened smoker who likes her poison double. The cigarette she smokes, like certain cigars, is a sign that she has arrived.</p>
        <p>OUR LEADERS OFTEN ASSUME that teen-agers read naively and will imitate what they are told is good for them and avoid what is disapproved. But one consequence of such assumptions is the present forms of censorship, which, however well meaning, may reinforce the behavior they seek to banish. Young people need information, not preaching, about the harm that smoking does to their development, to their bodies and to their futures. Confronted instead with censorship, they become skilled in and devoted to reading between the lines. In the end, the censor always incites aggressive curiosity about the very thing it aims to keep from view.</p>
        <p>The censorship effect has clearly been at work in America in recent years, especially where teen-agers, inherently curious and skeptical of authority, are concerned. The abyss between what can be said and shown about smoking and the fact that more than 25 million adults continue legally to smoke, despite the warnings, constitutes an enigma that gets the attention of every adolescent. They don't fail to notice either that there's a lot of secret smoking going down.</p>
        <p>Richard Klein is the author of ''Cigarettes Are Sublime'' and ''Eat Fat.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 7, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 24 about smoking in films and on television referred incorrectly to Lucille Ball's character on the CBS series ''I Love Lucy.'' She was not shown smoking during her pregnancy; the photograph was from an earlier episode of the series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 7, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 24 about smoking in films and on television referred incorrectly to Lucille Ball's character on the CBS series ''I Love Lucy.'' She was not shown smoking during her pregnancy; the photograph was from an earlier episode of the series.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Klein is the author of ''Cigarettes Are Sublime'' and ''Eat Fat.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
