<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Choosing Whites From Bordeaux</title>
    <meta content="1WINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="WINE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="WINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bordeaux (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalish, Geoff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Bordeaux</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D8153AF932A35755C0A961958260" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Choosing Whites From Bordeaux</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEOFF KALISH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kalish, Geoff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoff Kalish article on white wines of Bordeaux (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEST known for its reds, Bordeaux now produces a range of flavorful whites that marry perfectly with summertime fare. And, based on a recent sampling, some sensibly priced brands are available.</p>
        <p>Particular value was found in bottles from the Pessac-Leognan district just south of the city of Bordeaux. Pessac-Leognan has been considered a separate district only since 1987. Previously, its bottles were classified as being from Graves, a larger region, which surrounds the city of Bordeaux and extends southeasterly past Sauternes. One purpose of the new designation was to recognize the somewhat extraordinary characteristics of the wine produced in the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEST known for its reds, Bordeaux now produces a range of flavorful whites that marry perfectly with summertime fare. And, based on a recent sampling, some sensibly priced brands are available.</p>
        <p>Particular value was found in bottles from the Pessac-Leognan district just south of the city of Bordeaux. Pessac-Leognan has been considered a separate district only since 1987. Previously, its bottles were classified as being from Graves, a larger region, which surrounds the city of Bordeaux and extends southeasterly past Sauternes. One purpose of the new designation was to recognize the somewhat extraordinary characteristics of the wine produced in the area.</p>
        <p>Unlike its rival, Burgundy, where most whites are made from the chardonnay varietal, sauvignon blanc is the predominant grape in dry whites from Bordeaux. Other varietals allowed include semillon, merlot blanc and muscadelle. But the gravelly soil and the relatively mild, humid climate of the Pessac-Leognan region also have major impact on the bouquet and taste of the final product. In general, the wines of the area have a distinctly herbal bouquet, dry flavors of melons and exotic spice and a crisp, tart finish.</p>
        <p>Also, unlike top vintages from Burgundy, the dry whites of Bordeaux are usually best when consumed within a few years. In fact, dry white Bordeaux, even from peak years, rarely gains enhanced levels of flavor from prolonged aging in the bottle. For example, a 1989 Chateau Smith-Haut-Lafite, a high-end label, recently showed tired flavors and a too soft finish. In addition, while white Burgundy rarely suffers from warming to room temperature, whites from Bordeaux usually require sufficient chill to maintain fresh flavor.</p>
        <p>Three bargains are a 1994 Michel Lynch White Bordeaux, a 1994 Chateau Doms Blanc and a 1996 Michel Lynch Sauvignon Blanc. The two Michel Lynch bottles are produced by Jean-Michel Gazes, proprietor of the Lynch-Bayes estate in Pauillac. The White Bordeaux ($7.49 a bottle at Zachy's Wine and Liquor, 16 East Parkway, Scarsdale) has a pale yellow color, earthy bouquet and dry fruity taste with a lively finish. The Sauvignon Blanc ($7.99 a bottle at Dodd's Liquor City, intersection of Routes 120 and 133, Millwood) has a straw-yellow color, a restrained bouquet of new-mown grass and a taste of lemons and anise. The Doms Blanc ($8.99 a bottle at Suburban Wine and Liquor Store, Route 118 and Downing Drive, Yorktown Heights) has a straw-yellow color, simple taste of melons and spice and a soft pleasant finish. All three go well with grilled shrimp, boiled lobster and barbecued chicken.</p>
        <p>A 1994 Chateau de Rochemorin and a 1994 Chateau la Louviere provide complex, elegant flavors that match well with grilled vegetables, charcoal-broiled salmon and pasta primavera. Both are produced by the Lurton family. The Chateau de Rochemorin is made from 90 percent sauvignon blanc and 10 percent semillon. After vinification, the wine is aged for six months in new oak barrels. It has a medium-yellow color, a bouquet of vanilla and anise, a multilayered taste of melons and ripe fruit and a hint of honey in the finish. At $10.99 a bottle (at Dodds) it far surpasses the value of most California sauvignon blancs.</p>
        <p>The 1994 Chateau la Louviere has a medium-gold color, a smoky bouquet with hints of figs and melons, a taste of lemon and vanilla and a long, memorable finish. This wine offers excellent accompaniment to grilled tuna, veal and sauteed soft-shell crabs. It also provides a refreshing foil for smoked salmon and trout. It is available at $28 to $30 a bottle at Wine and Spirits Emporium of Bronxville (98 Pondfield Road, Bronxville), Rochambeau Wines and Liquors (389 Broadway, Dobbs Ferry) and Aries Wines and Spirits (128 West Post Road, White Plains).</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, one of the most highly regarded and most expensive whites of Bordeaux, a 1994 Chateau de Fieuzal, was quite controversial. Made of a blend of 50 percent sauvignon blanc and 50 percent semillon and aged in new oak barrels, the wine had too intense a bouquet of spice to match successfully with all but rather bland cheeses. It is available at $39.99 a bottle at Rochambeau Wines and Liquors.</p>
        <p>WINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
