<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style; Let's Go: Fashion Spring '98</title>
    <meta content="01FASHIOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="53" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DA103BF932A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style; Let's Go: Fashion Spring '98</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Morris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Guide to the spring ready-to-wear collections; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every fall and spring, the ready-to-wear collections appear like trendy islands on the churning sea of popular culture. Overnight, the cities of Milan, Paris and New York fill up with picky arbiters who traffic in opinions and accessorize well. Like bird-watchers on the lookout for anything with wings, they go from show to show in order to find, amid the more than 200 collections, a flurry of ideas that will migrate out into the great beyond. Their language, an advanced dialect of fashionese, is peppered with terms like ruching, shirring and on the bias. Able to pronounce Xuly Bet and Hussein Chalayan with ease, they also make easy pronouncements on such things as the difference between cobalt blue and cornflower, the new femininity, the Guggenheim in Bilbao and the genius of stretch jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every fall and spring, the ready-to-wear collections appear like trendy islands on the churning sea of popular culture. Overnight, the cities of Milan, Paris and New York fill up with picky arbiters who traffic in opinions and accessorize well. Like bird-watchers on the lookout for anything with wings, they go from show to show in order to find, amid the more than 200 collections, a flurry of ideas that will migrate out into the great beyond. Their language, an advanced dialect of fashionese, is peppered with terms like ruching, shirring and on the bias. Able to pronounce Xuly Bet and Hussein Chalayan with ease, they also make easy pronouncements on such things as the difference between cobalt blue and cornflower, the new femininity, the Guggenheim in Bilbao and the genius of stretch jersey.</p>
        <p>Naturally, for the more casual visitor, it's useful to be able to read the signs, too, even if you can't speak the language. That's what this guide is for. It covers the points of interest and main attractions of the spring collections, and it outlines the key vocabulary you'll need in order to speak about trends fluently. For instance, you'll want to know about pleats, drawstrings, ruffles, fringe and asymmetrical hems. You may also want to familiarize yourself with Ivanka Trump, the bugle bead and the avant-garde influence of the Japanese on fabric. Decorative embellishments like embroidery and brocade are another common sight. Also covered: climate (a warming trend from the chill of minimalism); currency (being current); rituals (power seating); cuisine (bottled water), and religion (celebrity worship).</p>
        <p>MILAN</p>
        <p>GUCCI  Have you driven a Ford lately? Tom Ford, the stiletto man, has a new fashion hazard for spring -- a handbag with a strap that wraps around the neck, like a noose. Other ideas are easier to handle -- tight skirts to the knee, coats in pink satin. For fans disappointed that the power-chic thing of last season has been watered down, there's still lots of leather, skin and sexy waistlines, dropped low enough to expose G-string straps riding up the hipbones.</p>
        <p>PRADA  Continues to give good status. Consistently overbooked. Everyone's favorite tour guide, Miuccia Prada, led an expedition into the future with cropped pants and draped dresses finished with lots of quirky, handmade touches -- painted flowers, randomly tied ribbons, puckered pleats and bugle beads. Canvas totes and Dr. Scholl-like sandals promise to be in short supply. Call ahead.</p>
        <p>JIL SANDER  This is the designer to try if you're in the mood for relaxed and fabulous at once. For spring, Sander's mood is Japanese, with asymmetrical and intricately twisted dresses -- sure to be a crowd pleaser with intellectually engaged fashion insiders. Her Teva-inspired sandals are Uber-easy on the feet.</p>
        <p>ROMEO GIGLI  This tried-and-true purveyor of eclectic luxury added some shimmer and lace to his typical menu of velvet and satin. The pace of the models was excruciatingly slow, but in the end the clothes were worth the wait.</p>
        <p>DOLCE &amp; GABBANA  The champions of the Sicilian-earth-goddess and her devout, shawl-wearing-nona staged a mock funeral procession in the baroque mansion they call home. Mourners wore net covered corsets, pinstriped capris and plenty of butterflies appliques. The Virgin Mary made an appearance too, but only as a vision on some miraculously sheer ensembles. Not recommended for church suppers.</p>
        <p>FERRE  There were long dusters and Edwardian men's wear, but it was the safari suits that seemed most appropriate. Models kicked sand in the faces of front-row pooh-bas, and the temperature was as hot as the Sahara.</p>
        <p>VERSACE  Taking over from her brother, Donatella cruised the red-light district, with halters and hot pants. There was lots of skin, chain-mail, leather, and body-hugging fabrics, all ingeniously twisted and slit. With an unusually high quotient of celebrities and homage-paying designers, the show was a power tripper's dream vacation. Madonna's latest single, ''Frozen,'' previewed on the soundtrack.</p>
        <p>ARMANI  Everyone knows that the truly powerful speak so softly that you have to lean in to hear them. This delicate yet sensual collection of fluid jackets, silky trousers and divinely diaphanous evening gowns beaded with water lilies is like a perfectly chilled martini -- it stirs but doesn't shake you.</p>
        <p>NARCISO RODRIGUEZ  His reputation was upgraded when he made headlines for designing Carolyn Bessette-Kennedy's wedding dress. But really, Narciso never flew coach. With this his first solo collection of cotton tops tied like aprons, high-waisted dresses and silky blouses, all liberally sprinkled with sequins, this guy's taking off.</p>
        <p>GENNY  Though Rebecca Moses presented her collection of quilted tube dresses, gold knits and lots of shocking pink in what used to be a leper's hospital, all medical precautions had been lifted. The preshow dinner found the in crowd touring the outcasts former home.</p>
        <p>PARIS</p>
        <p>CHRISTIAN DIOR  John Galliano is learning to mind his manners at the grown-up's table. In his latest collection for Dior, he leaves the antics and eccentricity behind to feast on the regal beauty of belle epoque shapes, the sensuous chic of satin smoking jackets, and the devil-may-care fringe of a flapper dress. A connoisseur's delight!</p>
        <p>CHLOE  The clothing may not have been rock-and-roll, but the crowd was: Ringo Starr was ringside with the designer's parents, Sir Paul and Linda. The billowing blouses, satiny floor-length-skirts and see-through camisoles brought down the house. For romantics with day jobs, Stella McCartney also offered expertly tailored suits.</p>
        <p>YOHJI YAMAMOTO  Japanese design was a central reference point on the fashion map this spring, and for many fashion travelers all roads led to Yohji. Made into fishing trousers, kimonos, blouses and ball gowns, his fabrics were rolled, pleated, knotted, wrapped, shirred and so beautifully ruched that they resembled theater curtains, or more poetically, a rippling sea.</p>
        <p>GIVENCHY  The less adventurous may find this Dolly Parton-inspired show of cowgirl hooker-wear to be as appealing as an undercooked chicken fried steak. But those who celebrate irony may say ''yee-ha'' to Alexander McQueen's wacky western applique work and lunatic leather fringe.</p>
        <p>ANN DEMEULEMEESTER  If it's Tuesday, it must be the Belgian, who showed her trademark asymmetry and provocative shapes in architecturally complex white shirts, sheer tank dresses and low-slung trousers. Some of her skirts were so slouchy that they slid right off the hips of the nearly hipless models.</p>
        <p>JOHN GALLIANO  The military chateau where this show was staged was so far from the center of Paris that it could have been Africa -- or Latin America, both of which served as the inspiration for the ikat prints in this sophisticated collection, with its enchantingly ethnic accent.</p>
        <p>CHANEL  Just when romance and extravagance are making a comeback, Karl Lagerfeld tones his act for Chanel way down. For spring, he offers all kinds of charmingly wearable dresses, decorated with typical embellishments, from chain belts to fringe. As always, his tweed suits are just the thing for women who make incredibly strenuous demands on others with insouciant ease.</p>
        <p>HELMUT LANG  Once they had the rigor of spa cuisine. But this season, the clothes of this artsy Austrian -- giant pleats and loose ruffles, frosted with a cool sheen -- take a confectionary turn. Dresses and trousers of distressed organza and netted silk are bunched and pleated to incorporate a more generous shape. Gauzy, nylon skirts with big, open pleats have a particularly happy bounce for spring.</p>
        <p>VALENTINO  Among those celebrities who rode into town for Valentino's cowboy-inspired couture were Matt Dillon and Cameron Diaz. Is this longtime favorite of Sharon Stone and reed-thin socialites now catching on with Hollywood hipsters ?</p>
        <p>JEAN-PAUL GAULTIER  Not satisfied with just the sight of these beautiful Frida-Kahlo-inspired clothes -- aprons and serapelike skirts with ruffles and lace, layered in savage, Gypsy style -- many of the guests helped themselves to the crates of produce adorning the stage.</p>
        <p>VIVIENNE WESTWOOD  The history-hawking bondage queen, Vivenne Westwood, called her flamboyant, pirate-themed show ''Tied to the Mast.'' Among the hoop-skirted gowns and H.M.S. pinafores were more than a few boldly appealing ideas, with ingenious cuts that turned striped fabrics into zigzags.</p>
        <p>MARTINE SITBON  Clam diggers make an appearance here, but it's the chiffon skirts and color-blocked minidresses in sorbet colors that are the pieces de resistance.</p>
        <p>COMMES DES GARCONS  Rei Kawakubo piled on the layers, with gathers and flounces that skewed the cotton muslin as it fell -- an effect that will be widely admired but worn only by the intrepid fashion adventurer.</p>
        <p>CHRISTIAN LACROIX  Even if the pendulum is beginning to swing back toward opulence, it still has a ways to go before it reaches Lacroix's lavishly exuberant mix of fabrics, shapes and colors. One critic suggested the collection had been ''taken over by a band of bohemian hippie sprites.'' That or the spirit of Le Cirque 3000.</p>
        <p>ISSEY MIYAKE  Alanis Morissette's music on the soundtrack set the mood, and Miyake rose to the occasion, with lightweight fabrics that wrapped and twisted around the body. Not everyone can make packable, fabrics look romantic.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>JOHN BARTLETT  This show had references to paparazzi violence and Hitchcock classics, so it seemed appropriate that after waiting for an hour to be seated the audience almost went psycho. ''Vogue is leaving,'' one editor yelled. Fortunately, it was worth the wait. As revisited by Bartlett, last season's tough-chic felt like a new attraction.</p>
        <p>ANNA SUI  Gidget goes global in this witty world-tour of surfwear, tunics, saris and sarongs, done in gold mesh, bandanna prints, denim and beaded chiffon. While some of Sui's fans may miss her grunge and Gothic motifs, most will savor this psychedelic pu pu platter for polyglot hipsters.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KORS  This eminently wearable yet sophisticated collection of American sportwear features what every soignee traveler needs: a red taffeta trench coat, a great white shirt and navy blue pajama pants. There were also jazzy shantung capri pants and white kidskin trousers. Next season, Kors will become an American in Paris, when he begins designing for Celine.</p>
        <p>OSCAR DE LA RENTA  With more variety than a tapas bar, this favorite of the ladies who lunch serves up everything from simple crepe sheaths to door-filling taffeta skirts.</p>
        <p>RALPH LAUREN  Ugly is not in this American's vocabulary. Lauren delivers his flawless leather shirt jackets and double-breasted blazers with the mellow assurance of a man who never makes a false turn. These clothes favor elegance over eccentricity; the trendy need not apply.</p>
        <p>BILL BLASS  The term directional took on new meaning at this runway show, which began with the song ''Downtown'' and ended with ''Uptown Girl,'' which pretty much epitomizes Blass's clientele. Afterward, some uptown girls could not find their drivers.</p>
        <p>ISAAC MIZRAHI  Inspired by a vision of a Greek goddess, Mizrahi resisted the trend toward a more generous silhouette, presenting clothes that are wrapped tight against the body. The audience at his show, included three comic goddesses -- Ellen DeGeneres, Sandra Bernhard, and Polly Mellen, Allure's creative director, who liked the collection minus the bugle beads. ''I'm beaded out,'' she said. So long as she wasn't unzipped.</p>
        <p>CALVIN KLEIN  In less skillful hands, Calvin's ''belief'' in track pants and warm-up gear could be the sartorial equivalent of a day trip to Atlantic City. Here, the master pilot of American minimalism uses these egalitarian classics to whip up tempting souffles from parachute silk, gauze and wool voile.</p>
        <p>DONNA KARAN  Soupy, deep colors shimmer like water here. But although this collection is inspired by the bay near her East Hampton home, there wasn't a clam digger in sight. Instead, she proposed roomy dresses and wispy skirts in layers of organza and chiffon. Come on in; the water's fine.</p>
        <p>MARC JACOBS  Last season it was the Gucci stiletto. This spring, the item most likely to launch a thousand shipments is Jacobs's pleated skirt. It has all the innocence of an American coed before the era of Madonna (who attended the show). Wear it with any of Jacob's sweet pea cashmere cardigans, or shells, and you'll be the ultimate ingenue at the orgy. Make your reservation now.</p>
        <p>RICHARD TYLER  A day trip to Richard Tyler's mansion off Gramercy Park, revealed exquisitely tailored suits, evening dresses and gowns with sexy cowl backs, slits and spirals of lace. There may be no place like home, but for the woman out on the town, this is the ticket.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
