<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POSTINGS: Going Up in Palisades, N.Y.; An Institute For Studying The Climate</title>
    <meta content="16APOST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Palisades (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scripps Institution of Oceanography</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (Noaa)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Research Institute for Climate Prediction</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DE153AF935A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POSTINGS: Going Up in Palisades, N.Y.; An Institute For Studying The Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, Scripps Institution of Oceanography and National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration are building home for International Research Institute for Climate Prediction on Lamont-Doherty campus, Palisades, NY; institute will study weathher phenomena; photo of model (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A long, low building, curved to follow the contours of the land, has begun to rise on the campus of the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, the earth sciences research division of Columbia University, in Palisades, N.Y., just over the New Jersey border.</p>
        <p>The one-story building is being built atop the Palisades Cliffs, a ridge rising 300 feet above the Hudson River, and will house the International Research Institute for Climate Prediction, which will study weather phenomena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A long, low building, curved to follow the contours of the land, has begun to rise on the campus of the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, the earth sciences research division of Columbia University, in Palisades, N.Y., just over the New Jersey border.</p>
        <p>The one-story building is being built atop the Palisades Cliffs, a ridge rising 300 feet above the Hudson River, and will house the International Research Institute for Climate Prediction, which will study weather phenomena.</p>
        <p>The building is integrated into the landscape and is nearly invisible from across the Hudson. A clerestory window that runs the length of the roof will provide natural light and natural ventilation.</p>
        <p>The idea was ''to have the building interact with the weather,'' said the project manager, Charles Blomberg of Rafael Vinoly Architects, which was the building's designer. In the spring, for example, breezes from the river will blow through the open office windows, as the warm air rises and drifts out through the clerestory window. Because of its blustery location, the building is also designed to withstand high winds.</p>
        <p>Offices will be on the river side of the 600-foot-long building; across the corridor, facing the wooded Lamont campus, will be conference rooms, computer laboratories and staff offices. The $10 million, 27,000-square-foot building will also include a 200-seat auditorium.</p>
        <p>''It's quite inspiring for the work we do, with wonderful views from the Palisades toward the Hudson River,'' said Antonio Moura, director of the research institute, a joint venture of Lamont, the Scripps Institution of Oceanography and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
        <p>Scientists can do more about the weather than just talk about it, said Peter Eisenberger, director of Lamont. One focus of the institute's scientists will be El Nino -- the warming phenomenon in the equatorial Pacific that affects climate around the globe -- and La Nina, its associated cooling phase. ''We are able to predict six to 12 months in advance when El Nino will come and how bad it will be,'' said Dr. Eisenberger. Researchers will continue ''to make models to predict El Nino's occurrence and to work to mitigate its impact,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The building is scheduled to open in August 1999. The following October it will be host to an international conference on agriculture and climate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
