<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Green Can Germany Get?</title>
    <meta content="06EAST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Easterbrook, Gregg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DE1F38F935A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Green Can Germany Get?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gregg Easterbrook</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Easterbrook, Gregg</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Gregg Easterbrook, author and senior editor at The New Republic, on expectation that next German Chancellor, Gerhard Schroder, will align his Social Democrats with Green Party; questions whether Greens will be able to reign in fundamentalist faction and respond pragmatically to environmental issues (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Imagine it is January 2001, and President-elect Al Gore is about to be sworn in along with his running mate: an antitechnology crusader from Earth First! Such a pairing is roughly analogous to what the next German Chancellor, Gerhard Schroder, is expected to make in aligning his Social Democrats with the country's Greens.</p>
        <p>Of course, a Gore-Earth First! administration might unravel from day one, as the new Vice President boycotts the inauguration because trees were felled to build the reviewing stand. Likewise, Mr. Schroder could well see his partners cause a theatrical crack-up of the ''Red-Green'' coalition's ability to govern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Imagine it is January 2001, and President-elect Al Gore is about to be sworn in along with his running mate: an antitechnology crusader from Earth First! Such a pairing is roughly analogous to what the next German Chancellor, Gerhard Schroder, is expected to make in aligning his Social Democrats with the country's Greens.</p>
        <p>Of course, a Gore-Earth First! administration might unravel from day one, as the new Vice President boycotts the inauguration because trees were felled to build the reviewing stand. Likewise, Mr. Schroder could well see his partners cause a theatrical crack-up of the ''Red-Green'' coalition's ability to govern.</p>
        <p>Mainstream American environmentalism has become button-down, incremental in approach, and is open to market-based solutions. The Greens, by contrast, remain psychologically rooted in the 60's dream of instantaneous social transformation.</p>
        <p>In the past they have pushed for total bans on logging, land development and the use of chemicals. Today they advocate shutting down civilian nuclear power, raising taxes on gasoline so that it would cost $12 a gallon, and starting a goofy antitourism policy under which each person would be allowed to take an airline trip for personal reasons only once every five years.</p>
        <p>Environmentalism would have become a force in German politics even if the Greens didn't exist: all major German candidates of the last quarter-century have advocated ecological protection, in part because nature has a mythic standing in Teutonic culture. As a party, the Greens had their origin not so much in ecological awareness but in opposition to the placement of Pershing II missiles by NATO, an issue that convulsed German politics in the early 1980's. By 1987, the Greens had gone from a standing start to controlling about 8 percent of the Bundestag and were taking hard-left stands on a range of social issues.</p>
        <p>Then everything unraveled. Public skepticism of the Greens' Marxist tilt was inflamed in the late 80's when an East German agent was exposed in the party hierarchy. Then the Greens came out against German reunification, declaring ozone-layer protection a higher priority. It is hard to imagine a worse reading of public sentiment. In the 1990 elections, the entire Green delegation was tossed out of the Bundestag. Commentators pronounced the party a woolly mammoth.</p>
        <p>But the Greens did not fall extinct. Rather, they split into two factions: the ''realos,'' pragmatists who accept compromise with consumer culture and constituent politics, and the ''fundis'' or fundamentalists, who insist on banning nearly all products and commerce. The leader of the realos, Joschka Fischer, has pushed his group to present a responsible face and demonstrate as much concern for public opinion as for dogma.</p>
        <p>If there is a Red-Green coalition, Mr. Fischer may become foreign minister. As recently as 1995, when the Greens were calling for the disbanding of the German army and of NATO, the notion of a Green foreign minister in Bonn, scanning the classified traffic and chatting on the phone with Pentagon officials, would have seemed hallucinogenic.</p>
        <p>If seated at the table of power, will the Greens cleave mainly to the realo or fundi aspect of their split personality? Here another analogy to Al Gore may be useful. The Vice President's environmental rhetoric occasionally employs off-the-charts doomsday exaggeration, but as a national leader, Mr. Gore has taken actions that have been temperate and sensible. The Greens may undergo similar moderation.</p>
        <p>Party officials will realize, for example, that shutting down Germany's nuclear plants, an action they call vital, would render impossible a reduction in greenhouse-gas emissions, which the Greens also call vital. Party leaders will also have to confront the fact that, however desirable energy efficiency may be, tripling gas prices would harm the working classes far more than the wealthy.</p>
        <p>And the Greens will have to rethink their campaign against resource consumption. The rising gap between rich and poor is a powerful problem in all Western economies. By contrast, automobile pollution, shopping malls and airplane noise are mere technical issues, amenable to regulatory and technical solutions.</p>
        <p>The Greens will serve Germany well if they work to make their nation more just. They'll be wasting their breath, and quickly be out on the street again, if they crusade against vacations.</p>
        <p>Gregg Easterbrook is a senior editor at The New Republic and author of the forthcoming ''Beside Still Waters.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gregg Easterbrook is a senior editor at The New Republic and author of the forthcoming ''Beside Still Waters.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
