<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ah, Winter, a Season Both Mild and Gentle, but Fickle</title>
    <meta content="10WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Monte</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DD1739F933A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ah, Winter, a Season Both Mild and Gentle, but Fickle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONTE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Monte</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unusually warm winter weather has blanketed New York metropolitan region since beginning of year; daytime temperatures have hovered daily between 50 degrees and 65 degrees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spiro Catchesis, the co-owner of Playland Market, a grocery store in Rye, N.Y., paused at work yesterday to wax poetic about the surprising warmth of January. ''Winter is nonexistent, except when I look up at the trees and see their leafless branches through the fog.''</p>
        <p>And so went another springlike day, as people all over the metropolitan region doffed their hats, pulled off their parkas and full-length wool coats and left their scarves and earmuffs home to enjoy the warmth, marred only by silver-gray skies and the knowledge that temperatures were soon to drop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spiro Catchesis, the co-owner of Playland Market, a grocery store in Rye, N.Y., paused at work yesterday to wax poetic about the surprising warmth of January. ''Winter is nonexistent, except when I look up at the trees and see their leafless branches through the fog.''</p>
        <p>And so went another springlike day, as people all over the metropolitan region doffed their hats, pulled off their parkas and full-length wool coats and left their scarves and earmuffs home to enjoy the warmth, marred only by silver-gray skies and the knowledge that temperatures were soon to drop.</p>
        <p>''It's almost surreal,'' said Mr. Catchesis, who owns a waterfront home in Stamford, Conn. ''I took a walk on the beach the other night -- the warm, humid air, the fog, the mist -- incredible.''</p>
        <p>With the exception of New Year's Day, New York City's daily high temperature has reached 50 degrees or above this month; four of those days it went to 60 degrees or higher.</p>
        <p>And yesterday was no exception: a high of 63 degrees in Central Park fell one degree short of the record for Jan. 9, which was reached in 1937. Newark's high temperature of 67 degrees broke a record of 66, set on the same day in 1937.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's weather nearly mimicked Wednesday's, when temperatures soared to a record 65 degrees in Central Park, one degree higher than the record for January 8 set in 1930.</p>
        <p>The mercury in Newark on Wednesday reached 70 degrees, which was 10 degrees higher than the record set on the same date in 1949.</p>
        <p>The mild weather was in stark contrast to that elsewhere in the Northeast and Canada, some parts of which were hit by a brutal ice storm, and others by relentless rain.</p>
        <p>The metropolitan area was spared by a slowly evolving pattern in the jet stream, a fast-moving river of air along the East Coast in which there has been a large northward bulge.</p>
        <p>And despite popular opinion, El Nino, a warming of ocean temperatures in the central and eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean, has nothing to do with the rising temperatures, said Sam Perugini, a meteorologist with the Pennsylvania State University department of meteorology.</p>
        <p>But Lucy Stein, 22, the manager of the 2d Street Cafe in Park Slope, Brooklyn, had different ideas. She was giving all the credit to El Nino.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to have a bumper sticker on the back that says I love El Nino,'' she said, laughing. ''I know the weather won't last, but I love it for what it is. You can sit around anticipating the next big winter storm, but I prefer to enjoy the warmth while it's here.''</p>
        <p>Ilana Polyak, 26, who moved to Manhattan from Southern California, said she loved more than the unseasonable warmth: The fog pleased her as well.</p>
        <p>''I'm not flying and I'm not driving, so I find the fog and the mist beautiful,'' she said. ''There's a warmth that envelops me, puts me in a great mood. I can wear just a sweater, and it feels like spring is about to come.''</p>
        <p>Michael Stark, 30, a chef at the Tribeca Grill and a resident of Park Slope, Brooklyn, agreed. ''This weather has been great,'' he said. ''Two years ago we had a huge blizzard and today I'm almost sweating.''</p>
        <p>Other people, although pleased by the warm temperatures, found something unsettling about them. ''I love the warm weather but there's something weird about it,'' said Jennie Pedro, an entrepreneur and client relations coordinator who lives in Mamaroneck, N.Y. There is ''something weird and ethereal about the fog. It takes away any sense of where we are in time, where we are on the calendar.''</p>
        <p>But last night, the calendar began to make sense as the temperature dipped to 50.</p>
        <p>Today's weather, according to the Penn State meteorology department, should bring past Januaries to mind for metropolitan residents, as temperatures are expected to drop back to the 40's.</p>
        <p>By the middle of next week, a cold front is expected to move into the area.</p>
        <p>Some of the people who have not appreciated the warm weather have included those who look fondly on drier conditions, even if they are colder.</p>
        <p>Leo Lopani, the owner of Rye Hair Port, a hair-dressing salon, said that since the weather turned foggy, ''everybody's complaining about the frizzies.''</p>
        <p>Hair tends to friz up in the intense humidity, so he has been doing a lot of body waves to combat the friz. ''No one wants to look like a mop,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The weather was also a matter of business for Mike Saracino, one of the owners of Rye Shoe Store, where  boot sales have been very slow. ''I prefer snow in winter, and broiling heat in summer,'' he said. ''I like the weather to be appropriate to the season. If I wanted this, I'd move to California,'' said Mr. Saracino, who noted that some customers were buying sneakers in anticipation of the spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
