<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>El Nino's Warmth Is Providing the Island With a Mild Winter</title>
    <meta content="SNOW.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDF133FF931A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>El Nino's Warmth Is Providing the Island With a Mild Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>El Nino, which has brought so much havoc and destruction to other parts of country, is bringing Long Island one of its mildest winters on record; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EL Nino, which has racked the West Coast with floods and mudslides and drenched the Southeast, is bringing Long Island one of its mildest winters on record.</p>
        <p>With what is normally the worst of the winter season now over and hardly measurable snow, meteorologists said El Nino-related patterns had kept Arctic air far north and confined the heaviest rains to the south.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EL Nino, which has racked the West Coast with floods and mudslides and drenched the Southeast, is bringing Long Island one of its mildest winters on record.</p>
        <p>With what is normally the worst of the winter season now over and hardly measurable snow, meteorologists said El Nino-related patterns had kept Arctic air far north and confined the heaviest rains to the south.</p>
        <p>Unseasonable warm weather linked to El Nino in the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast regions. the meterologists said, means that many storms moving up the East Coast brought rain and high winds but little snow.</p>
        <p>The warming was disastrous for upstate, eastern Canada and northern New England, where precipitation that would have been snow fell as ice, snow and freezing rain, snapping power lines and trees and leaving wide areas without power for days.</p>
        <p>But on Long Island, where El Nino was for the first time a topic among local officials and weather-watchers, temperatures were far above normal in January and higher than normal for the first two weeks of February as El Nino's benign effects were felt.</p>
        <p>The meteorologist in charge at the National Weather Service forecast office at the Brookhaven National Laboratory, Michael E. Wyllie, said El Nino was partly responsible for coastal storms that caused moderate erosion and flooding here.</p>
        <p>The storms indicate the difference between this winter and the almost equally mild winter of 1996-'97.</p>
        <p>''Last year,'' Mr. Wyllie said, ''there were very few coastal storms. But this year there have been quite a few. And this can be somewhat attributed to El Nino. Our subtropical jet stream is so far north this year that it's bringing storms from of the Gulf Coast and southern Atlantic coast all the way up the Atlantic Coast and giving us heavy rains, coastal flooding and high winds.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyllie said air temperatures 5 to 15 degrees above normal along with higher than normal temperatures in the Atlantic Ocean and a thin snowpack in New England prevailed this winter.</p>
        <p>Heavy snow on the ground in New England chills northeasterly winds that blow down across the New York metropolitan region. But without the snowpack, ''even when we get northeast winds prior to these coastal storms, it's not cold enough to give us a snow situation,'' said Mr. Wyllie.</p>
        <p>In 1983, the year of the last major El Nino warming in the Pacific, Long Island also had a relatively mild winter. But wider weather patterns caused by El Nino were little discussed and less understood then. ''Now, El Nino is the buzzword of the 90's,'' Mr. Wyllie said. ''It gets the blame for everything.''</p>
        <p>The Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton measured two inches of snow in December, one inch in January and none through the first two weeks of February. The lab measured 18 inches of snow in the winter of 1996-97. The normal winter snowfall is 30.2 inches.</p>
        <p>The rainfall in December 1997 of 4.7 inches was about normal. But the slightly more than 7 inches of rain in January was nearly 3 inches above the 4.16 that fall in a normal year, the lab reported. The January precipitation would have resulted in about seven feet of snow.</p>
        <p>The figures also showed that in January the mean temperature of 37.9 degrees nearly matched the record high, 38, in 1950. The normal mean for January is 29.8. Temperatures in December and for the first two weeks of February were also higher than average.</p>
        <p>''You have to attribute some of the weather this winter to the El Nino effect,'' said Victor A. Cassella, a meteorologist for the laboratory.</p>
        <p>The warmth has helped lead to surpluses in snow budgets on the Island, where allocations for snow removal have been moving downward.</p>
        <p>In Suffolk County, so confident were officials about the weather that the County Legislature voted this month to remove $500,000 from the $1,554,000 snow-removal budget.</p>
        <p>The money will instead be used for more than 15 dredging projects in six towns, Public Works Commissioner Charles J. Bartha said, adding:</p>
        <p>''These are important projects. Recreational boating is a big item on Long Island. And the County Executive was looking for ways to accomplish them without an impact on the taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>In Nassau County, the $840,000 budgeted for snow removal was untouched two weeks into February. ''So far we have spent nothing,'' said David A. Vieser, a spokesman for the County Executive. Last year, which encompassed the end of the mild winter of 1996-1997 and the start of this winter, the county spent $628,000 of its $1.4 million snow budget. In the cold and snowy winter of 1995-'96, it spent $2.2 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vieser said surpluses were ''used to defray other areas where there may be a shortfall'' and to hold down property taxes. In years when snow-removal costs exceed budgets, local governments are permitted to sell bonds to close deficits. But that has not been necessary this year.</p>
        <p>''We have gotten this far without a major snowstorm, and even if there is a significant snow event now, the daylight hours are longer and the ocean is warmer,'' Mr. Vieser said.</p>
        <p>In the Town of Hempstead, Highway Superintendent Anthony J. Califano said snow-removal crews had not ''gone out at all this season.'' His department, he said, had ''spent zero'' of the $1.6 million budgeted for snow removal.</p>
        <p>''It's all El Nino,'' Mr. Califano said. ''I have been following it, and it's definitely the cause.''</p>
        <p>Some officials hesitated to mention the absence of snow. ''It could jinx us,'' said Susan McGowan, a spokeswoman for the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
        <p>Mr. Califano said with weeks of winter left it was too soon to talk of a season without any snowstorms. ''We still have the crazy month of March, and that could offset everything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Even though we have an El Nino year and everything has been warmer than normal, it's still not out of the picture for us to get hit with a major snowstorm,'' Mr. Wyllie said. ''With these coastal storms that keep forming, all you have to do is get a cold outbreak and one of these storms coming up the coast at just the right time, and we could easily get a foot of snow.''</p>
        <p>The State Transportation Department will be ready, said John J. Cahill, the equipment coordinator for Region 10, which includes Nassau and Suffolk. The department is responsible for clearing the Long Island Expressway and other major state roads.</p>
        <p>''We make routine checks of equipment continually to make sure that if it ever snows some day we will be able to handle the situation,'' Mr. Cahill said. ''We haven't had anything major for two winters now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cahill said his office held a snow school in November in Melville for employees. About 400 employees and 198 plow trucks are ready, he said, and piles of salt and sand are untouched.</p>
        <p>The benefits of a warm winter include unimpeded shopping and  fewer fender benders. Such winters are the bane of schoolchildren who hope for snow that cancels classes. The warm weather also means hundreds of millions of dollars less spent on heating.</p>
        <p>The president of the Meenan Oil Company of Syosset, Paul A. Vermylan Jr., said oil deliveries were 30 percent less than average last month and 20 percent less than average for the first two weeks of February. ''It's what we call a bad year,'' Mr. Vermylan said.</p>
        <p>Unlike last year, the supply has been high. Retail prices averaged $1.20, down 15 cents from last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vermylan said the company was following El Nino but would never base inventories on long-range forecasts. ''We can't afford to be ready for anything but a cold winter,'' he said. ''We can't be caught short.''</p>
        <p>Meenan has 110,000 customers in New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania, including 25,000 on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Christopher L. Hirsch, sales manager of the Hirsch Fuel Company in Hauppauge, said 25 percent lower deliveries last number was ''a hurtful number'' for the company, which has 6,000 customers in Suffolk.</p>
        <p>''When you are 25 percent off in what should be your largest consumption month,'' Mr. Hirsch said, ''you have to tighten your belt. But it's something that really nobody has any control over. I would rather be here than in California.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyllie said a prolonged El Nino could bring hurricane protection to the East Coast despite the higher Atlantic temperatures. ''If El Nino is still in effect when the hurricane season comes,'' he said, ''most of the hurricanes would not be able to develop, because upper-level wind fields would shear the top of these storms.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
