<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Gray Matters; Darling, It's Better Up Where It's Wetter</title>
    <meta content="08EGAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1000640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DF1630F93BA35750C0A96E958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Gray Matters; Darling, It's Better Up Where It's Wetter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on how people in Seattle shrug off rain, mist and clouds and carry on normal lives, in year when El Nino has put Southern Californians in severe funk; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the midst of California's biblical downpour last month, The San Francisco Chronicle dispatched a reporter to Seattle to figure out how people here live with the wet, the gloom -- the horror! -- of perpetual precipitation.</p>
        <p>The meteorological anthropologist discovered, somewhat to his astonishment, that Seattleites wash their cars, go to parties, play soccer and generally shrug off whatever is misting from the sky. What's more, the natives do not use umbrellas, the reporter found. Tourists use umbrellas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the midst of California's biblical downpour last month, The San Francisco Chronicle dispatched a reporter to Seattle to figure out how people here live with the wet, the gloom -- the horror! -- of perpetual precipitation.</p>
        <p>The meteorological anthropologist discovered, somewhat to his astonishment, that Seattleites wash their cars, go to parties, play soccer and generally shrug off whatever is misting from the sky. What's more, the natives do not use umbrellas, the reporter found. Tourists use umbrellas.</p>
        <p>Seattle is to rain what New York is to jaywalking, or used to be until Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani decided to try to make his town more like this one, where lone pedestrians wait for the light to change in a gale at 2 A.M.</p>
        <p>Rain is a signature. ''O! How horriable is the day,'' Lewis and Clark wrote of a typical winter afternoon on the Northwest coast in 1806. Tom Robbins, a Northwest novelist who has come up with as many ways to describe rain as Eskimos have to describe snow, once put it this way: ''The day was rumpled and dreary. It looked like Edgar Allan Poe's pajamas.''</p>
        <p>Part of the Package</p>
        <p>But people here are proprietary about the weather. And when it rains in great, newsmaking deluges elsewhere while mere anonymous drizzle coats the Rain City, people here can feel neglected.</p>
        <p>When asked about the weather -- and they always are -- Seattleites trot out two lines of thought: one, that it does not really rain very much here; and two, that it does, but nobody is greatly bothered by it, unlike those pathetic wimps in other cities.</p>
        <p>The statistics back up the first argument. Seattle receives 38 inches of rain a year on average -- less than every major East Coast city. And nearly half of Seattle's rain falls during November, December and January. The wettest year on record, 1950, saw 55.14 inches of rain, still below the annual average for New Orleans and Miami. Gullywashers are rare. It is usually bone dry from July through September.</p>
        <p>So what's the big deal? The moisture does not really fall as much as it lingers, the skies ever-pregnant with gray. Seattle has 158 days with at least some trace amounts of rain, more than virtually every East Coast city, including New York, which averages 119 days with some moisture, and just under 43 inches a year.</p>
        <p>Play Misty for Me</p>
        <p>The most positive spin on the rain comes from people who have tried to quantify things like drizzle. In his new book on Northwest weather, ''Rains All the Time'' (Sasquatch Publishing), David Laskin recounts how Phil Church, a retired professor of atmospheric sciences at the University of Washington, tried to debunk Seattle rain.</p>
        <p>Drizzle, the professor noted, makes up 72 percent of the city's precipitation, while heavy rain -- greater than 0.16 inch in a day -- is a mere 1.5 percent of the wetness. Ergo, he said, ''Because of the preponderance of drizzle intensities, one might truthfully say it rarely 'rains' in Seattle.''</p>
        <p>Okay, so how did Seattle become the only city in National Basketball Association history to have a rain-out indoors? A roof leaked, demonstrating the penetrating power of drizzle. And where did the term ''sunbreaks,'' which appears as a balm about every four days in a Seattle forecast, come from? From a place with a forecast on auto-pilot: the ubiquitous ''rain turning to showers.''</p>
        <p>Mood Music</p>
        <p>What Seattle has is mood weather. Artists and writers love it. There is a great preponderance of seasonal affective disorder, or SAD, a malady brought on by light starvation during the dark Northwest winter. But contrary to popular belief, suicide is not that high. The desert region encompassing Nevada, Utah and Arizona has a higher suicide rate than the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>As for the wimpiness factor, it is true that Seattleites revel in stories of people elsewhere being afraid of rain. No dinner party of late has passed without stories about social events being canceled in Los Angeles because of rain threats, or of how television news crews in California go live to the skies to record the simple falling of water.</p>
        <p>El Nino, the warming of the Pacific that has become the all-purpose scapegoat for anything remotely odd this year and last, has brought out the Schadenfreude and moral tut-tutting of a webfoot's view of rain. People are more productive making airplanes, software and new coffee drinks here, the line goes, because rain is linked to the work ethic. Real people need real weather for character, or something like that.</p>
        <p>Californians, by contrast, are ''sun-baked barbarians,'' in the words of Emmett Watson, the dean of Seattle newspaper columnists. And if they do not see the sun for 20 consecutive days, well, try 40 days, a possibility on the Olympic foothills of Washington state, known for 200 inches of annual precipitation and the site of the only rain forest in the lower 48 states.</p>
        <p>To be fair, San Francisco has been hit by 38.61 inches of rain since last July -- nearly double the amount in a normal year -- and Los Angeles has received 22.43 inches, 50 percent above the usual average. But they know this is temporary.</p>
        <p>In Seattle, if it isn't raining right now, it soon will be. Most people would have it no other way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
