<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Time, Experts Say, El Nino Probably Had a Role</title>
    <meta content="Y24NIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FLORIDA TWISTERS: THE BLAME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE1DE143EF937A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Time, Experts Say, El Nino Probably Had a Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists say El Nino, warm Pacific ocean current, probably set stage for deadly series of tornadoes in Central Florida (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems as though every flake of snow or drop of rain this winter is attributed to the warming of Pacific waters known as El Nino. While that troubles scientists who study the weather, they say that El Nino may well have set the stage for the deadly series of tornadoes that tore through Florida early today.</p>
        <p>''El Nino has certainly gotten oversold,'' said Dr. Chris Landsea, a meteorologist with the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration in Miami, ''but this is one where I would have no problem saying El Nino plays a role.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seems as though every flake of snow or drop of rain this winter is attributed to the warming of Pacific waters known as El Nino. While that troubles scientists who study the weather, they say that El Nino may well have set the stage for the deadly series of tornadoes that tore through Florida early today.</p>
        <p>''El Nino has certainly gotten oversold,'' said Dr. Chris Landsea, a meteorologist with the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration in Miami, ''but this is one where I would have no problem saying El Nino plays a role.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Landsea and other experts caution that it is impossible to draw a direct link between an individual storm and El Nino. Rather, the powerful weather maker plays an indirect role, fostering a climate that is conducive to turning Florida's normally benign winter thunderstorms into more severe ones. Those severe thunderstorms, in turn, can spawn tornadoes.</p>
        <p>''You never blame a single storm on El Nino,'' said Lee Grenci, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University. ''If you want to blame anything, winter is to blame, and El Nino is one of the cronies of winter.''</p>
        <p>El Nino is a vast pool of abnormally warm water that results from natural fluctuations in atmospheric pressure and ocean movements in the equatorial Pacific, altering climate patterns around the world. It has contributed to intense rainfall and flooding in California, drought in Indonesia and colder and wetter weather than usual in the southeastern United States, from Texas to North Carolina. At the same time, the mild hurricane season last fall has been attributed to El Nino.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Florida tornadoes today, which killed more than three dozen people and left more than 260 injured, Mr. Grenci and others explained El Nino's role this way: El Nino creates warming in the eastern Pacific, enhancing the usual temperature contrasts between the Equator and the earth's poles.</p>
        <p>In Florida, those contrasts set the stage for a stronger-than-usual southern branch of the jet stream, the region of rapidly moving winds that separates cooler air masses in the north from warmer ones in the south. When a low pressure system is energized by those potent winds, it can easily spawn thunderstorms, which can spin out into tornadoes.</p>
        <p>El Nino is ''the usual suspect in these conditions,'' said Larry Riddle, a climatologist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of San Diego. ''The thunderstorms become more severe, and the greater the temperature disparity and the more moisture, the more severe the thunderstorm.''</p>
        <p>But, said Patrick Michaels, the Virginia state climatologist, not everyone agrees with this theory, in part because statistical analyses have not shown strong correlations between factors known to be associated with El Nino and various weather phenomena.</p>
        <p>''The correlations in general aren't that high,'' Mr. Michaels said. ''It leaves guys like us in a ticklish situation.''</p>
        <p>That may be because El Ninos have been identified by scientists relatively recently, in the latter half of the 20th century, and so experts have not compiled extensive data on them. The only other El Nino on record whose strength is comparable to this year's occurred in 1982-83, causing more than 1,000 deaths worldwide.</p>
        <p>Many weather experts complain that the public and the press are gripped by El Nino hysteria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riddle, the climatologist at the Scripps Institution, complained: ''I see weathermen on TV getting up there and arguing about whether this is an El Nino storm or it isn't. Well, I do research on this stuff, and I don't know what an El Nino storm is.''</p>
        <p>Then again, Mr. Riddle said, the public may finally be catching onto the idea that El Nino is not the root of all weather evil. Not long ago, he walked into his local Target store and spotted a T-shirt on the rack. The slogan: ''Blame it on El Nino.''</p>
        <p>He bought it.</p>
        <p>FLORIDA TWISTERS: THE BLAME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
