<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Dwight G. Smith; Tracking Birds for Insights on All of Nature</title>
    <meta content="13SMIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dwight G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dubrow, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Connecticut Birding Guide (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DD133EF930A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Dwight G. Smith; Tracking Birds for Insights on All of Nature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT DUBROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dubrow, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts of interview with Southern Connecticut State University biology Prof Dwight G Smith, birdwatcher who has published ten books including Connecticut Birding Guide; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DWIGHT G. SMITH spends much of his time outdoors, observing birds. Dr. Smith, a professor of biology at Southern Connecticut State University, has published 10 books including  the Connecticut Birding Guide (Thomson-Shore, 1996), written with Arnold (Buzz) Devine. His bird work extends to the western United States, Alaska, Siberia, southern Africa and Venezuela.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smith, 55, lives with his wife, Elinor, in Hamden. In a recent interview, he discussed his work. Following are excerpts from that conversation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DWIGHT G. SMITH spends much of his time outdoors, observing birds. Dr. Smith, a professor of biology at Southern Connecticut State University, has published 10 books including  the Connecticut Birding Guide (Thomson-Shore, 1996), written with Arnold (Buzz) Devine. His bird work extends to the western United States, Alaska, Siberia, southern Africa and Venezuela.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smith, 55, lives with his wife, Elinor, in Hamden. In a recent interview, he discussed his work. Following are excerpts from that conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. What do you like about birding?</p>
        <p>A. The excitement of finding new birds, of being out in the wild. It's a good, healthy, active, outdoor activity where you're not hurting anything, you're enjoying nature. You can combine your interest in birds with interests in trees, shrubs, wildflowers. You can get the whole spectrum of wildlife in any habitat you want. If you get bored looking around the shore, you just throw your binoculars in the car and head inland.</p>
        <p>Birds are abundant, they're beautiful, they're adaptive, they have interesting behaviors. They're a challenge -- identifying the different species, the different varieties, finding as many as possible. It's a lot of fun.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the ecological importance of birds?</p>
        <p>A. They're common, abundant consumers. They consume plant matter: for example, seeds. They consume insects and other pests. Without the birds, everything from Japanese beetles to mosquitos and gnats would be tremendously more abundant.</p>
        <p>They're good indicators of the well-being of ecosystems. If we're tracking birds, we can fairly quickly detect when there's something wrong with an ecosystem -- there's pollution, there's human interference, there's habitat fragmentation.</p>
        <p>Q. Is Connecticut a good state for birding?</p>
        <p>A. It's not very big, but it's one of the best. We've got a huge variety of habitats -- shorelines, rivers, highlands. After you've seen the 190 species that actually nest in the state, you can treat yourself to more than 200 additional species that are coming and going. We sit on the Atlantic Coast flyway, a major migratory route. Every fall and spring we have hordes of raptors, shorebirds and songbirds going through the state.</p>
        <p>We're advantageously placed because we're at the southern limit for several northern species that nest in the state, and we're also at the northern limit for more southern species.</p>
        <p>Q. What changes have there been in Connecticut's bird population over the past few decades?</p>
        <p>A. An interesting change is the influx of more southerly species nesting in the state as the climate is warming up, like Carolina wren, prothonotary warbler and summer tanager. Even the cardinal moved in within the last 20 or 30 years.</p>
        <p>On the negative side, Connecticut is having trouble because of habitat fragmentation. The populations of some of our wood warblers that need big woodland reserves are slowly diminishing. Some of the raptors, the birds of prey, are area-sensitive species. As the woodlands are fragmented, their populations grow smaller, before they disappear.</p>
        <p>Q. Why do birds like cardinals, sparrows, blue jays, robbins and crows thrive in suburban habitats?</p>
        <p>A. Before humans were around, their natural habitats were meadow and edge habitats -- where we have a grassland and a woodland next to one another.</p>
        <p>We move in, we take a woodland and we convert it into meadow and edge habitats. They ignore our houses and they're in their favorite habitat, so they're almost super-abundant critters. House finches, pigeons, starlings love that kind of habitat. Then the native birds like eastern bluebirds have a problem. House sparrows and starlings are very aggressive. They'll chase a bluebird right out and kill it to get to a particular nest site.</p>
        <p>Q. What are some of the state's rare birds?</p>
        <p>A. There are the storm blown rarities that come in the state following tropical storms -- like pelicans, sooty terns, some of the shearwaters and kittiwakes. Even though the Connecticut warbler is named for the state, it nests in upper New England. We only find it during its migration, and it's fairly uncommon, so there will only be one or two sightings a year. In terms of nesting birds in the state, we're all keeping our track on yellow-throated warblers, which are possibly nesting in White Memorial and Kent. They're a more southern species that hasn't nested in the state before. Some of the other more interesting ones we're trying to keep track of are blue grosbeak, alder flycatcher and golden-winged warbler.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your favorite species?</p>
        <p>A. I like the hawks and owls. I've done a lot of work over the years with owls -- the eastern screech owl. We have little traps that catch them unharmed. I used to trap them and put radio transmitters on them, and then I'd follow them at night, when they'd come out from their daytime roost sites and go hunting. I'd see where they were, what they hunted, how often they hunted. You're out there all night long tracking them. I enjoyed that quite a bit.</p>
        <p>Also, when they were nesting in a hollow tree, I would construct a blind in back of the tree and I'd keep track of which adult, the male or female, came in, what kind of food they would bring to the young, and how often they brought the food. I'd strap myself in and make sure I didn't fall asleep and roll out of the blind.</p>
        <p>Q. How do bird watching opportunities vary by season?</p>
        <p>A. Our best birding seasons are during the spring and fall migrations. On a good day you'll easily find between 50 and 150 species. Fall migration is very good for raptors and shorebirds. Spring is best for songbird migration.</p>
        <p>Winter is slow, but challenging. Early summer's best for the nesting species, but you've got to hunt around and find them. Different species nest in bogs, in wetlands, along the shore, in the woodland interior.</p>
        <p>Q. You describe 88 different birding sites in your book. What process did you go through for each site?</p>
        <p>A. We went to hundreds of sites. We visited every natural site, state forest, state park, town park, nature conservancy, Audubon center -- and these 88 are the best. We picked the sites to give the greatest variety of habitats and birds throughout the year, or because a site was a focal point for migration or a nesting concentration of birds.</p>
        <p>We walked through each of the 88 sites, over and over again for several years, during each season of the year, with a notebook in hand. We could identify birds by either seeing them or by their songs. We visited each site at least 30 or 40 times; some we visited hundreds of times. We started writing the book in the mid-80's and were finished by the mid-90's.</p>
        <p>A lot of birding guides just say, ''Here is East Rock Park and this is a list of birds you can find there.'' We take you on a walking tour around each site and tell you what you can find in each habitat in each season.</p>
        <p>Q. Of the 88 sites, which would you recommend as the best?</p>
        <p>A. White Memorial Foundation in Litchfield -- 30 miles of trails, dozens of different birding habitats -- would be one of the best sites for inland birds. Milford Point is one of the premier sites in the Northeast for fall migrations of shorebirds. Lighthouse Point Park in New Haven is famous as a hawk watch site. At Hammonasset Beach State Park in  Madison you get a good influx of migrants in spring and fall; you get a variety of wintering bird species. Bluff Point Coastal Reserve in Groton has excellent migrants.</p>
        <p>Q. What can people do in their backyards to help bird populations?</p>
        <p>A. Birdhouses in the summer and bird feeders in the winter. You can shape some of your nest boxes down so you'll attract eastern bluebirds. Make the hole just large enough for eastern bluebirds, but too small for house sparrows and starlings. Then you hope they're going to come.</p>
        <p>Hummingbird feeders; keep the cats indoors. To birdscape your yard, put in cherry trees, dogwood trees and elderberry shrubs. They're attractive ornamentals, but they also provide nesting habitat and food.</p>
        <p>We've documented that 45 species of birds will eat the fruit from elderberry. You want to include some arborvitae that provide good nesting sites. You can to some extent focus on particular species by the kinds of nest boxes you have and the kinds of birdscaping you do.</p>
        <p>Q. How can someone who wants to begin birding get started?</p>
        <p>A. Buy a pair of binoculars. Buy a field guide like Peterson's. Buy our book. Join a local bird club. Go to Lighthouse Point Park during the migration season. There will be a lot of people there who are just starting out. There will be people around to help them.</p>
        <p>Birders tend to be a friendly, informative bunch. If somebody's standing beside them who doesn't know what that bird is, they will be more than happy to tell them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
