<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Along the Atlantic Coast, A New Schedule for Summer</title>
    <meta content="10OCEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Phenomenon)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crowley, Michael F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7D61131F933A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Along the Atlantic Coast, A New Schedule for Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVER PETERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Changing national weather patterns caused by El Nino are having unexpected effect along Atlantic Coast, warming ocean enough to bring early start swimming season and attracting fish closer to shore; scientists are warning that early rise in water temperature may create conditions late in summer that could cause fish to die off in large numbers; Michael F Crowley of Rutgers University comments on higher-than-normal temperatures in Atlantic Ocean; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The changing national weather patterns caused by El Nino are having an unexpected effect along the Atlantic Coast, warming the ocean just enough to bring an early start to the swimming season and attracting fish closer to shore so that fishermen should improve their luck.</p>
        <p>But scientists are also warning that the early rise in water temperature may create conditions late in the summer that could cause fish to die off in large numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The changing national weather patterns caused by El Nino are having an unexpected effect along the Atlantic Coast, warming the ocean just enough to bring an early start to the swimming season and attracting fish closer to shore so that fishermen should improve their luck.</p>
        <p>But scientists are also warning that the early rise in water temperature may create conditions late in the summer that could cause fish to die off in large numbers.</p>
        <p>Surface temperature readings done by satellite for the Institute of Marine and Coastal Sciences at Rutgers University have found water temperatures running as high as 56 degrees, or five degrees above normal for early May, in a 25-square mile section of ocean off Great Bay, just north of Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Michael F. Crowley, director of the institute's Marine Remote Sensing Laboratory, said that although his data focused on New Jersey, similar conditions were likely to exist from the tip of Long Island to Cape Hatteras in North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''It is only a difference of a few degrees,'' Mr. Crowley said, ''but there's a lot of water out there and those few degrees translate into a lot of energy that has been transferred into the water. So we're about three weeks ahead of schedule, and instead of hitting the beaches in June we're looking at people going to the beach in May.''</p>
        <p>And catching fluke in April, of all things, said Capt. Mark Rosen of  Story Teller, a charter boat.</p>
        <p>''We've been catching bluefish in the inlet for two weeks already, and it's usually another week or two from now that we see them,'' Captain Rosen, who runs charters out of Waretown, on Barnegat Bay, said on Friday. ''We had fluke the first week of April, and I never remember having fluke until the middle of May. And a friend called to say they were catching yellow fin tuna offshore, and that's months early.''</p>
        <p>The warm surface water can also cut off oxygen to deep water, threatening marine life. Each summer, a layer of warm water forms a cap over the colder water below, cutting off the usual churning of surface and deep water that brings fresh oxygen to deeper layers of the ocean.</p>
        <p>This capping off generally occurs each year in July or August, and it is broken up by the fall storm season and strong northeast winds. If the cap forms a month or longer before normal, Mr. Crowley said, the waters beneath the cap would be left without fresh oxygen that much longer, and with a corresponding danger to marine life.</p>
        <p>Similar conditions in 1976 led to the death of a large amount of algae, depleting oxygen over the July 4 weekend in 1976 and killing a large number of fish in the Atlantic waters off New York Bay. But Mr. Crowley said the same sequence would not necessarily happen this year.</p>
        <p>David Caron, an oceanographer at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution on Cape Cod, said: ''A lot of people have noticed that water temperatures are running ahead of other years, but what the consequences are of that you can't say at this point.</p>
        <p>''I often describe it by saying that the North Atlantic is like a bell that has certain modes of behavior, and you can ring it through all sorts of mechanisms,'' Dr. Caron went on. ''And what has happened is that this very strong El Nino has the ocean ringing in all kinds of modes this year.''</p>
        <p>For example, at the end of March the sea surface off the Rutgers Marine Institute's Marine Field Station at Tuckerton, on the central New Jersey shore, reached 56 degrees , a level that the water does not usually reach until about the end of April. Temperatures fell to the high side of normal during the cooler weather in the first week of April, but they shot back up to about 60 degrees by May 1.</p>
        <p>Cloud cover has kept the satellite from collecting its data since then, but Mr. Crowley said that last week's persistent rains may have helped to slow the rise in temperature.</p>
        <p>Still, data from the Rutgers Institute's satellite and undersea sensors collected before May 1 showed that temperatures at lower levels in the research quadrant had begun to drop, indicating some capping off, or stratification, already.</p>
        <p>''Stratification isn't supposed to start for a while,'' Mr. Crowley said, ''but we're already seeing sea-bottom temps breaking away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Crowley said that two events determined whether oxygen depletion, as a result of capping off by warm surface waters, persisted, .  One is known as upwelling, and follows a steady blow from the Northeast -- the blinding northeasters that often rake the Jersey shore and Long Island in the late summer and fall -- that pushes warm surface waters away from shore and allows colder deep water to well up to the surface close to shore.</p>
        <p>Tropical storms and hurricanes also stir oxygen into the ocean.</p>
        <p>''We need those storms,'' Mr. Crowley said. ''The people at the beach don't like them, but from our perspective they're good, because they totally destroy stratification.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
