<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Officials Split on Move on Gas Additive</title>
    <meta content="Y28GAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1126574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mtbe (Gasoline Additive)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7D61F3EF93BA15754C0A96F958260" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Officials Split on Move on Gas Additive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State environmental officials are divided over whether Congress should act to reduce use of gasoline additive MTBE, which helps reduce carbon monoxide but sometimes pollutes water; oil companies begin figuring out how to comply with possible rule change; producers of ethanol, competing additive, begin work to cash in (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State environmental officials were divided today over whether Congress should act to reduce the use of a chemical used in gasoline that helps keep the air clean but sometimes pollutes water.</p>
        <p>Oil companies were also beginning to figure out how to comply with the possible change in the rules, while producers of ethanol, a competing chemical, began work to cash in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State environmental officials were divided today over whether Congress should act to reduce the use of a chemical used in gasoline that helps keep the air clean but sometimes pollutes water.</p>
        <p>Oil companies were also beginning to figure out how to comply with the possible change in the rules, while producers of ethanol, a competing chemical, began work to cash in.</p>
        <p>In Massachusetts, one of the most aggressive states in fighting air pollution, Nancy L. Seidman, deputy director of the Department of Environmental Protection, said she worried about what oil companies would use in place of the chemical, M.T.B.E. Ms. Seidman said the state had lost the use of some wells from contamination by M.T.B.E., which, when leaked, dissolves in water, but ''we're not convinced there are significant water-supply issues here,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Other officials responsible for air quality said that the public seemed to be more concerned with water pollution from M.T.B.E., which scientists say may be carcinogenic, than air pollution from components of gasoline that are proven to cause cancer.</p>
        <p>''It's what you can see and taste versus what you can't,'' said Jane K. Stahl, the deputy commissioner of the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection, in Hartford. ''What made M.T.B.E. come to the forefront is that you could smell it in your water, and taste it. It smells like you're drinking gasoline, and that's very scary and very offensive.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Stahl and officials in other states said M.T.B.E. was generally not a public health hazard. She said, though, that they favored gradual reductions in M.T.B.E. use to reduce the risk to water.</p>
        <p>Congress passed a law in 1990 that resulted in heavy M.T.B.E. use in California and on the East Coast in an effort to cut carbon monoxide and smog. But clean air experts say its main benefit has been a reduction in more toxic cancer-causing chemicals in gasoline, like benzene and toluene. When spilled, though, M.T.B.E. moves through the soil faster than those natural hydrocarbons and has made some wells useless because it makes the water reek.</p>
        <p>A panel of experts appointed by the Environmental Protection Agency formally reported today on M.T.B.E., and said its use should be reduced substantially. Carol M. Browner, the agency's administrator, said even before the report was released that she would work with Congress to modify the law.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act amendments of 1990 require that areas with air pollution problems use reformulated gasoline that includes an ''oxygenate,'' a molecule that incorporates an oxygen atom. M.T.B.E. is used in 85 percent of reformulated gasoline, while ethanol, which is made from corn, accounts for almost all the rest.</p>
        <p>Ethanol producers were planning legislative strategy to maintain their market, which exists mostly because of the oxygenate requirement.</p>
        <p>Todd C. Sneller, the administrator of the Nebraska Ethanol Board, a state agency, said that ''it would be difficult to advance a proposal to eliminate the oxygen standard without some ethanol-related provision,'' and that Congress still liked ethanol's ability to reduce oil imports and greenhouse gas emissions. ''The agriculture lobby and the ethanol lobby can have some influence,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneller said that in the next 10 days supporters in Congress would introduce legislation requiring that some fraction of gasoline come from ''renewable'' sources like ethanol, just as some states, in restructuring their electric utilities, were requiring that each company have some electricity from renewable sources, like solar or wind power.</p>
        <p>The big oil companies started making M.T.B.E. in the early 1980's as a substitute for lead, which the Government had ordered be phased out of gasoline. Both lead and M.T.B.E. raise octane, a measure of gasoline's ability to withstand premature detonation in an engine.</p>
        <p>Even today, M.T.B.E. and ethanol are used in places where no oxygenate is required. So even if the oxygenate requirement is dropped, it will continue to be used, although at lower levels, oil executives say.</p>
        <p>Supporters of oxygenates said that incorporating an oxygen atom into the fuel makes the mixture in a car's cylinders leaner, and thus cuts pollution. But in the years since the mandate, cars have been built with sensors that continuously sense the richness of the mixture, and adjust the fuel-air mixture accordingly, leading some experts to say that oxygenates are no longer so useful for controlling carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>Oil companies, though, have always maintained that Congress' reason was political, to help corn growers, and reduce reliance on imported fuel.</p>
        <p>Robert H. Campbell, the chairman and chief executive of Sunoco, said that if the oxygenate requirement were lifted, his company would probably reduce its use by 70 to 80 percent, but that something else would have to take M.T.B.E.'s place, and ''they're not going to let us use benzene or other compounds they consider very toxic.''</p>
        <p>''Somebody's going to have to invest in producing other barrels to fill that gap,'' he said, because customers would want the same number of gallons. A likely candidate to make up the volume, he said, is alkylates, a class of chemicals produced in refineries by taking smaller molecules and combining them; the smaller molecules can cause pollution because they are prone to evaporate before they are burned, and form the raw materials for smog.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
