<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rosemary In Spring: Power With Restraint</title>
    <meta content="12ROSE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1106944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Herbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rosemary (Herb)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Molly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Herbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DC123FF931A25756C0A96F958260" item-length="2298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rosemary In Spring: Power With Restraint</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOLLY O'NEILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Neill, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Molly O'Neill article on pleasures she takes in her perennial rosemary bush; recipes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEARLY 17 springs ago, I was given a spindly little rosemary tree. Observed at a distance, it looked like bonsai; up close, it resembled the sort of brown stick topped with green cloud that a child might draw and call a tree. But unlike the naivete of a child's artwork, my rosemary tree never became more refined or precise. It grew taller and thicker and wild.</p>
        <p>And for reasons that may be more sentimental than culinary, I get a bad case of rosemary chauvinism in the spring. My motivation could not be culinary; I pinch little sprigs from the bush all year round and, traditionally, rosemary is teamed with fall and wintery dishes. Still, when I cart new basil and chervil, oregano, parsley and thyme onto the terrace every spring, I fuss with them briefly and then dote on my rosemary. Next to the fragile baby annuals, the perennial rosemary is so valiant, thriving in the perpetual fumes of trucks and cars and forgiving my erratic attentions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEARLY 17 springs ago, I was given a spindly little rosemary tree. Observed at a distance, it looked like bonsai; up close, it resembled the sort of brown stick topped with green cloud that a child might draw and call a tree. But unlike the naivete of a child's artwork, my rosemary tree never became more refined or precise. It grew taller and thicker and wild.</p>
        <p>And for reasons that may be more sentimental than culinary, I get a bad case of rosemary chauvinism in the spring. My motivation could not be culinary; I pinch little sprigs from the bush all year round and, traditionally, rosemary is teamed with fall and wintery dishes. Still, when I cart new basil and chervil, oregano, parsley and thyme onto the terrace every spring, I fuss with them briefly and then dote on my rosemary. Next to the fragile baby annuals, the perennial rosemary is so valiant, thriving in the perpetual fumes of trucks and cars and forgiving my erratic attentions.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, I did not maintain the plant as a botanical sculpture. I trimmed it erratically when I wanted branches for grilling or making kebabs, pinched back its needlelike leaves when I needed a fresh herb. It grew from plant to shrub on the terrace. The little pot eventually became a bushel basket, a two-person moving operation, a counter space glutton, and sometimes, a disturbing mirror.</p>
        <p>When the bush is parched, so am I, in ways that the frenzy of modern life would rather I ignore. It reminds me to slow down and tend to the little things.</p>
        <p>Sure, I've resented my rosemary. It's big and it won't go away. But I've never considered a serious pruning or a separation. The herb is too central to my cooking, its aroma too closely tied to the smell of coming home, its folk cures too automatic in our household to deem dispensable.</p>
        <p>Over the years, I've rejected the traditional role of rosemary -- the dominatrix of grilled food and heavy winter dishes. There's a delicacy and a need to merge with other aromatics in the herb, a perfume that's never fully realized when rosemary is allowed to rampage alone in a dish. Used judiciously, rosemary performs a subtle magic in cooking. The herb brings a hint of forest and briny sea air, camphorlike and breezy, to anything from wild game to delicate seafood, from pasta and potatoes to custards and sorbet.</p>
        <p>But when the fresh herb is deployed with abandon, or when the dried herb is used at all, rosemary is bad news: like a dark urge, unrestrained. For this reason, the late Elizabeth David hated rosemary.</p>
        <p>In ''Spices, Salt and Aromatics in the English Kitchen,'' she wrote that ''rosemary figures in my kitchen as a decoration only,'' complaining of the lavish manner in which rosemary is used by some Italians in marinades or stews: ''The meat is drowned in the acrid taste of the herb, and the spiky little leaves get stuck between your teeth.''</p>
        <p>But even Mrs. David swooned for fresh fish basted with a branch of green rosemary dipped in olive oil as it grilled. And therein lies the difference between the dried herb and the fresh one: used carefully, the fresh herb is neither acrid nor a dental nightmare.</p>
        <p>I've learned to restrain my rosemary impulse, dish by dish. But the more I've learned about rosemary, the more dishes I seem to crave with its piney, turpentine scent.</p>
        <p>Rosmarinus officinalis figured prominently in literature, folklore and sacred texts long before 1390, when it was first mentioned in ''The Forme of Cury,'' the earliest surviving culinary text, as an essential element to salad.</p>
        <p>The herb's name derives from two Latin words -- ''ros'' and ''marinus'' -- meaning, respectively, ''dew'' and ''sea,'' perhaps because the plant thrives under the harsh sun and in the sandy soil of the Mediterranean. The climate in California and even along the Eastern Seaboard also suits the herb, which seems to prefer its water misted all over its leaves rather than drenched in the soil. For this reason, my rosemary bush is happiest near the stove in the winter, when soups and pasta water provide moist hot heat.</p>
        <p>Along with bay, thyme, savory, sage, marjoram, oregano and lavender, rosemary is among the plants some cooks call turpentine herbs. Some botanists say that the herbs shared soil and climate with seaside pines for so many millenniums that they acquired a faint piney flavor.</p>
        <p>If this speculation is true, the genetic imprint is very strong indeed. On my terrace, my bush may be treated to nascent breezes from the Hudson, but it is mainly exposed to exhaust fumes. Still, its leaves continue to impart a sense of sea-meeting-woodland, a whiff of Provence, of Italy and of the first time I ate in Chez Panisse more than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>The aroma of rosemary is so potent that ancient texts refer to it as incense, though perhaps this association has to do with religious myths.</p>
        <p>In one, it is said that the Blessed Virgin laid the family's laundry on rosemary shrubs to dry, lending a sacred aura to the herb. Early Christian cults of the Virgin changed its name to Rose (of) Mary. The church-and-herb connection may have fostered rosemary's prominence in the herbal pharmacology practiced by clerical healers.</p>
        <p>Even today, herbalists claim that rosemary promotes blood circulation -- and when used in shampoos or, as in Curacao and Spain, in a paste applied to a bald spot, encourages hair to grow. Romans used rosemary pastes for nervous headaches, and scholars wore wreaths of fresh rosemary on their heads to improve memory.</p>
        <p>Memory, in fact, is the herb's attribute most celebrated in poetry and old wives' tales. In medieval Europe, brides carried rosemary branches in their wedding bouquets to remind their husbands to be faithful. It is the herb most associated with friendship and loyalty and, along with primrose and violets, was used in bouquets carried by courting gentlemen, as well as in the nosegays that women exchanged.</p>
        <p>It is said that scattering rosemary's tiny blue flowers in a bed protects sleepers from bad dreams.</p>
        <p>And in Cuba, a poultice of rosemary and ginger is applied to the forehead to cure insomnia. In some ancient food-cure systems, rosemary liniment is used to treat rheumatism and gout.</p>
        <p>My family sip rosemary tea when we feel low, add rosemary oil to our bath water, use rosemary soap and rosemary shampoo.</p>
        <p>And apparently we are not alone. The shelves of health food stores and luxury bath shops seem to sprout more and more rosemary-scented products every day.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, unbridled use of the herb is just as distasteful in cosmetics as it is in cuisine. Rosemary needs to be melded, to become a base note in an aromatic melange -- and kept on a very tight leash.</p>
        <p>The herb provides an illusive bite, for instance, when used with other aromatics to make soda (it is rumored to be an ingredient in cola), snacks like chips with barbecue or ranch flavors, some Belgian pilsners and even Chartreuse, the green liquor that Carthusian monks have made since 1607.</p>
        <p>In general, the cook should use half as much rosemary as any other spice or herb in a dish. Minced with thyme, and even lavender, rosemary does wonderful things for lamb, veal, sausage meat, game or beef. Using the herbs is like bringing the perfume of grazing land back to the meat.</p>
        <p>Most commonly, rosemary is found, along with garlic and onion or lemon, tucked into the cavity of chicken, with additional leaves pushed between the bird's flesh and skin. It is delicious. And so are roasted potatoes tossed with rosemary, olive oil, salt and pepper; the same combination can be worked into dough for pizza, focaccia or pasta.</p>
        <p>Rosemary seems to make tomato sauces sunnier and gives a lemony, piney nuance to soups and stews.</p>
        <p>After years of living with rosemary, I finally began using it in custards and sorbets, and the result defied my general distrust of using savory things in sweets. Used sparingly in milky desserts, rosemary can function like pepper, nutmeg, cinnamon or allspice to provide a sharp contrast to the sugar.</p>
        <p>Even more recently, I was surprised to detect rosemary among the Asian aromatics in a vinaigrette served with a lobster and daikon roll at the Vong restaurant in Manhattan. Soy and ginger seems to coax a sweet hint of heliotrope from the herb.</p>
        <p>Modern cooks would not automatically think of consigning rosemary to a bit part in a dish; parsimony in rosemary defies the current more-is-better mindset in American cuisine. But living with rosemary, I've found that the less you notice the bush, the more powerful it is.</p>
        <p>My rosemary was, last fall, given an acid-bath by the construction crew that was re- pointing our building. She had a tough winter, and eventually I gave her to a friend for safekeeping.</p>
        <p>Upon entering her temporary digs the other day, I was buffeted with a sense of endurance and well-being and an urge to cook, to bathe, to arrange flowers. If I knew how to sew, I would probably have considered making sachets.</p>
        <p>Rosemary, you see, abides like memories. And like the unnamed sources of joy and sadness in any person's life, rosemary is best as an unnoticed thread in the intricate and complicated fabric of a life.</p>
        <p>SLOW-BRAISED TUNA IN ROSEMARY OIL  Time: 2 hours 10 minutes, plus 4 to 24 hours' resting time</p>
        <p>1 quart olive oil  1 bunch rosemary  1 2-pound center cut piece of fresh tuna.</p>
        <p>1. Place olive oil in a saucepan over low heat. Wash rosemary, and pluck leaves from the stems (reserve the stems for grilling or making kebabs). Dry the leaves in paper towels; you should have 1 to 1 1/2 cups.</p>
        <p>2. Place rosemary in the warming oil, and continue to cook over lowest possible heat until warm to the touch, about 15 minutes.  Remove from heat, and allow to cool. Ladle half the oil into a very clean glass container, leaving the rosemary behind.</p>
        <p>3. Place the second half of the oil in a blender with the rosemary leaves, and blend very well. Add this mixture to the glass container, and shake to combine. Place in the refrigerator for at least 4 hours and up to 24 hours.</p>
        <p>4. Bring the oil to room temperature. Place the tuna in a small but deep pan, and pour the oil over to cover completely. Place over low heat, and cook 90 minutes. Remove from heat. and allow to sit for 30 minutes. Drain tuna, discard the oil and cut the fish into 6 steaks. Serve warm with boiled parsley potatoes or use in nicoise or tuna salad.  Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>ROSEMARY-SCENTED ASIAN LOBSTER SALAD  Adapted from Vong Time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>For the vinaigrette:  2 tablespoons honey  6 tablespoons sherry vinegar  2 tablespoons soy sauce  1 half-inch piece ginger, peeled and chopped  1 stalk rosemary  1 mild fresh chili, seeded, deveined and coarsely chopped  1 1/2 cups grape seed or other light, mild-tasting vegetable oil</p>
        <p>For the salad:  4 lobsters, cooked and shucked</p>
        <p>1/4 cup pickled ginger slices, patted dry and julienned  8 radishes, sliced wafer thin  1 cup daikon sprouts  4 cups watercress, arugula or other bitter greens, rinsed, dried and coarsely chopped.</p>
        <p>1. To make the vinaigrette, place all the ingredients but the oil in a blender or food processor and puree. While still processing, slowly drizzle a steady stream of oil into the mixture to make a thick vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>2. Cut the lobster meat into one-inch chunks. In a large bowl, toss the lobster with the ginger and radishes and enough vinaigrette to barely moisten the mixture (half to three-quarters of a cup). Divide the bitter greens among four plates, place the lobster mixture on top and top with the sprouts. Drizzle a little additional vinaigrette over the greens and around them on the plate and serve.  Yield: 4 servings.  Note: Leftover vinaigrette makes a marvelous marinade for chicken or pork.</p>
        <p>ROSEMARY AND LEMON SORBET  Adapted from ''La Varenne Pratique'' (Crown Publishing, 1989)  Time: 20 minutes, plus up to 30 minutes to freeze</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cups sugar  Grated zest and juice of 2 lemons, plus additional for garnish  1 to 2 tablespoons fresh rosemary leaves, plus additional leaves for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. In a medium saucepan over medium heat, heat 5 cups water with sugar. When the sugar has dissolved, raise the heat to high, and boil 3 minutes. Pour half the syrup into a second saucepan, and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Add lemon zest to the remaining syrup, return to low heat and simmer about 10 minutes. Add lemon juice, remove syrup from heat and set aside to cool.</p>
        <p>3. Immerse rosemary in the other half of the syrup, place over high heat and bring to a boil. Reduce heat to very low, and simmer  10 minutes.</p>
        <p>4. Remove from heat, and allow to cool. Strain rosemary syrup into the lemon syrup. Taste, adding more lemon or sugar to suit. Cool in the refrigerator, and then freeze until firm according to the directions of your ice cream maker. Serve garnished with lemon slices and sprigs of fresh rosemary.  Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
