<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And Now Your Local Weather</title>
    <meta content="01THU4$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1096780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="THE RURAL LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D61739F932A35757C0A96F958260" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And Now Your Local Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERLYN KLINKENBORG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg, in Rural Life column, notes that her two brothers, who own farm in Massachusetts, have become very accurate in predicting weather (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are 290 bales of hay in the barn loft, enough to last my four horses well into the warmth and the tall grass that I presume is coming. Every couple of weeks, since late October, I've gone to visit two brothers who raise hay and milk-cows on a Massachusetts hillside. While the brothers stack bales in my pickup, they grouse about the weather and the calamitously low price of hogs and the $6 drop in the price per hundredweight for milk. I write a check for the hay -- a commodity whose price never seems to fall -- and, as part of the deal, I bring news of the weather in other parts of the country -- the snow that fell in south Texas in early December, the high winds last month in Lander, Wyo., the knee-high oats and the peach orchards now blooming in central California.</p>
        <p>There's a refrain to these visits. The older brother, who is in his early 70's, compares the actual weather with the predictions published in the Farmer's Almanac. The younger brother complains in turn about the inaccuracy of computerized weather reports. I always listen to this singsong with a sense of irony, yet the weather report I want to hear is exactly the kind these old farmers deliver, based as it is on their keen sense of the difference between conditions on their hillside and conditions on mine, eight miles away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are 290 bales of hay in the barn loft, enough to last my four horses well into the warmth and the tall grass that I presume is coming. Every couple of weeks, since late October, I've gone to visit two brothers who raise hay and milk-cows on a Massachusetts hillside. While the brothers stack bales in my pickup, they grouse about the weather and the calamitously low price of hogs and the $6 drop in the price per hundredweight for milk. I write a check for the hay -- a commodity whose price never seems to fall -- and, as part of the deal, I bring news of the weather in other parts of the country -- the snow that fell in south Texas in early December, the high winds last month in Lander, Wyo., the knee-high oats and the peach orchards now blooming in central California.</p>
        <p>There's a refrain to these visits. The older brother, who is in his early 70's, compares the actual weather with the predictions published in the Farmer's Almanac. The younger brother complains in turn about the inaccuracy of computerized weather reports. I always listen to this singsong with a sense of irony, yet the weather report I want to hear is exactly the kind these old farmers deliver, based as it is on their keen sense of the difference between conditions on their hillside and conditions on mine, eight miles away.</p>
        <p>They told me last weekend that the frost is finally out of the earth, all but a crust that is. They learned this while driving fence posts in a nearby pasture. The woods, they said, are nearly dry enough for the loggers. The brothers recalled that last year they had turned the heifers out onto grass by now and that when the two of them were young boys the oats had to be in the ground by April 15, though they haven't planted that early in a long, long time. This is not the atmospheric science of air masses and isobars and Nexrad Doppler radar. This is the weather in a world of outdoor labor, weather with a long human memory, where April's drought or flood is still felt in August's hayfield, and for many Augusts and Aprils in the mind thereafter.</p>
        <p>My father-in-law records the weather every day in a small notebook, and now that I live in the country I'm tempted to do the same. But the weather is just too various to note succinctly, especially at this time of year and in a climate where it's always wise to be looking ahead. By the time I feed out the hay I stacked last weekend a year will have passed since it was baled, and my two farmer friends will be baling again.</p>
        <p>After I stacked hay, I took the chain saw down to a pile of logs that had been drying in the lower pasture for a full year, logs that, split and stacked, will dry another summer and burn next winter. The top logs were warm in the sun, but ice still clung to the lengths of ash and birch that lay on the bottom. Snowdrops and aconites had pushed through the brown thatch near a hickory tree and across the slope to where I sat on a stone outcrop, resting. It was spring, and it wasn't. The bees droned in the sunshine, hovering near the lengths of wood I had just finished cutting. In this still early season, the sap that oozed from the heartwood was the sweetest thing to be found.</p>
        <p>VERLYN KLINKENBORG</p>
        <p>THE RURAL LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
