<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting Things Right In the Everglades</title>
    <meta content="13EVER$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1099784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Everglades (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Everglades National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDB1E38F930A25757C0A96F958260" item-length="3401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting Things Right In the Everglades</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal and Florida Governments will seek to restore supply of slow-flowing fresh water to Everglades; slow-flowing fresh water is eco-system's lifeblood, but less than half as much of it flows through Shark River Slough now than did a century ago; as a consequence, huge marsh produces far less life than it used to; main reason for decline is successful effort to supply fresh water to cities and farms and to protect them from flooding, which has siphoned off too much of natural flow of water; Federal and State governments now plan to spend $8 billion over 20 years to replumb Everglades so that natural conditions can be re-established or at least mimicked; photo; drawings compare water flows in Everglades in late 1800's with present day's disrupted ecosystem (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From a helicopter scudding over South Florida, a ribbon of green farms stretches off to the East. There the avocados and mangoes are in bloom, tomatoes are green on the vine and field workers are picking beans.  Just beyond are acres and acres of suburban Miami's characteristic orange-pink roofs.</p>
        <p>But directly below, wild nature still holds sway. Or tries to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From a helicopter scudding over South Florida, a ribbon of green farms stretches off to the East. There the avocados and mangoes are in bloom, tomatoes are green on the vine and field workers are picking beans.  Just beyond are acres and acres of suburban Miami's characteristic orange-pink roofs.</p>
        <p>But directly below, wild nature still holds sway. Or tries to.</p>
        <p>What looks like a tawny Western grassland studded by green tree islands stretches off to the north, west and south. It is the dry season, and only isolated little pools of water mark the course of Shark River Slough, a broad but shallow sluice that for 5,000 years has been the main freshwater channel through what is now Everglades National Park.</p>
        <p>This winter-and-spring ''dry-down,'' as it is called, is normal. One of its effects is to concentrate the fish that proliferate during the summer wet season, and on which the Everglades' famous wading birds subsist.  The dense concentrations are what fuel the birds' nesting activities and feed their hatchlings; and as the helicopter clatters overhead, groups of ibises, wood storks, egrets, anhingas, herons and a multitude of other species are flocking to the pools.</p>
        <p>''This is pristine Everglades,'' said Mike Slayton, the deputy director of the South Florida Water Management District. It is also an Everglades in serious decline.</p>
        <p>Slow-flowing fresh water is the ecosystem's lifeblood, but less than half as much of it flows through Shark River Slough today, on average, as did a century ago. On the whole, water is insufficient in the Everglades at large, and it often flows to a given place at the wrong time or in the wrong amount.</p>
        <p>So the huge marsh produces far less life than it used to. Despite the occasional groups of wading birds, the populations that once were the hallmark of the Everglades have diminished by more than 90 percent. Ecologists consider this the best single indicator of the ecosystem's ill health.</p>
        <p>The main reason for the decline is that in a  successful effort to supply fresh water to cities and farms and to protect them from flooding, people have siphoned off too much of the natural flow of water that once stretched in a continuous sheet from Lake Okeechobee in the north to Florida Bay in the south. Billions of gallons a year are now routinely shunted out to sea. Levees divide what remains of the sheet flow into a series of disconnected pools. The result of all this is an ecosystem out of kilter.</p>
        <p>Now, in the nation's most ambitious attempt at ecological restoration, Federal and state governments are about to try to put things right. The idea is to spend $8 billion over 20 years to replumb the Everglades so that natural conditions can be re-established or at least mimicked. The latest version of a complex plan to do this was made public last week and after further revision is to be delivered to Congress on July 1.</p>
        <p>The project, almost six years in the planning, has provoked both high hopes and high anxiety, and it raises a number of fundamental questions: can the unique, world-class natural area really be restored, given what has been done to it? If so, to what extent? And will the proposed project do enough?</p>
        <p>The Plan  Redirecting Water, Finding Hope</p>
        <p>No one believes that South Florida can be put back the way it was before people started altering it about a century ago. For one thing, about half the area of the original ecosystem has been converted to urban areas and farms. Some environmentalists argue that much of the farmland should be bought out and re-converted to natural areas. But that idea appears dead politically, and even if it were successfully revived, the natural system still would not recover its original size.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, South Florida's population of six million is expected to double over the next half century, and some experts fear that pressure to develop some of what is left of the Everglades -- and to appropriate the water -- will only increase.</p>
        <p>Despite this cloud on the horizon, the replumbing plan assumes that the system will remain essentially its present size for the next 50 years.</p>
        <p>Based on that assumption, it aims to recapture most of the billions of gallons of water that now flow to the Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico each year. This water will be stored in a variety of reservoirs, including limestone quarries and aquifers, to be redistributed as needed to the Everglades, the farms and the cities.</p>
        <p>The project is intended to deliver the right amount of clean water to the Everglades at the right place at the right time, in as natural a manner as possible. The hope is to recreate conditions in which the Everglades can revive and recover much of their essential character -- though in a different and truncated form compared with the original.</p>
        <p>''I think the plan gets us very close'' to that goal, said Michael L. Davis, an ecologist and deputy assistant secretary of the Army. He oversees the Army Corps of Engineers, which devised the plan with many Federal, state and local agencies under the aegis of the Interior Department, and he has been deeply involved in the plan's preparation.</p>
        <p>No one claims that the plan is perfect, or ever will be. After the initial version was made public in October, some scientists and environmentalists criticized it on  grounds that it did not go far enough in removing the welter of artificial plumbing in which the system is trussed up, and that it would take too long to gain results. It has since been revised after negotiations among the Army Corps and other groups, notably the National Park Service.</p>
        <p>Under the plan in its present form, Mr. Davis said, 80 percent of the  water that now goes out to sea would be redirected into the Everglades.  This, he said, would give the Everglades half the total expanded water supply; now, farms and cities get 70 percent of a smaller supply.</p>
        <p>In the southern part of Shark River Slough, in the heart of the national park, the flow would be 90 percent of what computer models suggest was its historic volume. That should be enough to insure recovery, said Richard G. Ring, the park superintendent.  In the plan as originally proposed last fall, the restored flow would have been about 70 percent of the historical volume. Mr. Ring and his staff protested, and after intense talks, the target was changed.</p>
        <p>The additional water will come mostly from treated urban runoff, and it remains to be seen how successfully that water can be purified.  The planners envision a series of filtering marshes to remove agricultural runoff and other pollutants from reclaimed water before it flows into the natural system.</p>
        <p>The project also is intended to break down the compartmentalization of the Everglades somewhat by removing some levees and canals.  The first phase of decompartmentalization has been speeded up as a result of the recent talks, and is to be completed by 2010. In all, roughly two-thirds of the project is to be finished by then.</p>
        <p>Some critics are reserving judgment pending more detailed study.  But, ''we're pretty encouraged'' by the recent improvements, said Mr. Ring, whose staff scientists have been among the most vocal critics.  ''There is nothing in the plan that's a showstopper'' in achieving ecological recovery, he said.</p>
        <p>The History  A 'Perfect' System Is Segmented</p>
        <p>In the depths of the last ice age some 18,000 years ago, what is now the Everglades was an open grassland punctuated by oak and pine. As the climate warmed and South Florida became semitropical, conditions jelled for the formation of a freshwater marsh within a shallow limestone saucer bounded by low ridges on Florida's east and west. The saucer was tilted slightly from north to south, so that the water in the marsh ran ever so slowly into Florida Bay.  Rising seas helped retard runoff and hold the water in place, and the Everglades were in place by about the time the Sumerian civilization rose in Mesopotamia 5,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>One key to the Everglades' ecological character was that the slow movement of water enabled the system to store enormous amounts of rainfall from one season to the next.  Another key was the system's huge size and variety of habitats. As water levels rose and fell between wet and dry seasons, for instance, wading birds could always move about and find both nesting habitat and food.</p>
        <p>Over the last century, the region was gradually covered by a latticework of levees (one, stretching all the way from Lake Okeechobee nearly to Florida Bay, protects Florida's east coast from floods), canals, sluice gates and pumping stations.  The far northern part of the system, where neat green rows of sugar cane and emerald fields of sod for suburban lawns stretch across the landscape, was converted to agriculture.</p>
        <p>South of this Everglades Agricultural Area, the central part of the marsh was compartmentalized into five big pools called water conservation areas. Still farther south is Everglades National Park itself, the most nearly pristine part of the ecosystem. But the park is at the mercy of water flow from the north. Not only have the wetlands to the north been diminished, but in some places, outcroppings of development create backwaters that further prevent water from flowing south. Since the Everglades north of the park have been diminished in size much more than the park, re-establishing the sheet flow into the park would result in a far narrower flow than was the case historically.</p>
        <p>While there is some sheet flow within the divided compartments, the chopping-up of the system has greatly degraded its ecological character. For instance, water in some parts of the national park is too deep for ecological health, while other parts are too dry. Because of this, for example, the endangered Cape Sable seaside sparrow has trouble finding suitable habitats.</p>
        <p>Similarly, levees on the southern edges of compartments cause ''ponding'' as southward-flowing water piles up, while other areas have become too shallow, and even permanently dry. The marsh soil in these areas has disintegrated and subsided.</p>
        <p>Though the marsh is still extensive, its patchwork pattern greatly reduces its value to creatures like wading birds, who become confused about where they can feed and nest, says John C. Ogden, a Water Management District ecologist. Three or four decades ago, the Everglades were home to huge ''super colonies'' of nesting wading birds; today these colonies have disappeared.</p>
        <p>The Flow  Reconnection And Priorities</p>
        <p>Since levees, pumps and canals altered the system, they are also seen by many experts as essential in fixing it. ''This system will never be a natural system,'' said Dr. Mark Kraus of the National Audubon Society, which has long been deeply involved in the restoration. ''You have to keep people dry and put water back into the system. Water delivery has to be by pumps and canals.''</p>
        <p>The general aim, nevertheless, is to keep elaborate engineering projects on the periphery of the remaining natural area, rather than inside it. For instance, say advocates of the plan, it will be necessary to install new pumps, canals and water storage areas just outside the Everglades, so that water now flowing to the oceans can be recaptured and pumped, sometimes around obstacles, where it is needed.</p>
        <p>But within the natural area, the goal is to remove as many artificial structures as possible. More than 240 miles of levees and canals are to be so eliminated. An important move of this kind involves the major thoroughfare called Tamiami Trail, which runs westward out of Miami and divides the national park from the rest of the natural system to the north. The highway will be raised and a series of causeways or bridges will be built, under which water will flow essentially unimpeded between two of the Everglades' biggest compartments for the first time in decades . This part of the project is to be completed by 2010.</p>
        <p>But experts are divided over the extent to which the historic sheet flow can and should be re-established. Some believe that the top priority should be re-establishing the natural depths and timing of water flows, while others believe that sheet flow itself should be the top priority. These goals are not always compatible. For example, if sheet flow were fully restored, subsidence of the land in some places would make the water too deep to support much Everglades life.</p>
        <p>Also, ponding caused partly by subsidence just northeast of Tamiami Trail discourages the desire to improve sheet flow by removing a miles-long major levee to the west.  In a recent compromise, it was decided that a series of notches, or weirs, are to be cut into the levee through which some water can spill in the wet season. Eventually, if the subsidence problem can be fixed by filling or is resolved naturally, the levee can then be removed. (Originally, the Army Corps proposed to put in more elaborate gates instead of weirs. Park scientists and others argued successfully that weirs could be more easily and less expensively removed later, and were a good interim step.)</p>
        <p>Another obstacle is posed by a pocket of homes just east of the national park that impedes the water flow into Taylor Slough, a channel on the east side of the park that is the main conduit of fresh water to Florida Bay. Part of the bay, some scientists say, has become too salty as a result of diminished flow from Taylor Slough and is in ecological decline as a result. A buyout of the homes has been proposed.</p>
        <p>Even if the Everglades' water flow were perfectly re-established, that would not complete the work of restoration. There are the problems of soil loss and subsidence to contend with. And much of the Everglades has been taken over by exotic plants from abroad, which are crowding out native species. Some strides have been made in eliminating one of the most aggressive, the melaleuca tree.</p>
        <p>In a pine-forest island in the Everglades, park scientists have, after a long period of trial and error, simply begun scraping the land down to bedrock to eliminate another interloper, Brazilian pepper. Natural vegetation is springing up again, but there is a long way to go in cleansing the ecosystem of vegetative pollution.</p>
        <p>Based on what is known of the Everglades' past and on computer modeling studies, the scores of specialists most deeply involved in the restoration project typically express high hopes for the future, tempered by realities. ''We will never recover the original Everglades,'' Mr. Ogden says, but ''we can make it much healthier than the current system.''</p>
        <p>The Future  Optimism And Nervousness</p>
        <p>One reason for the experts' optimism is that unlike the situation in many degraded ecosystems, most of the ecological pieces of the Everglades are still there, albeit in reduced numbers.</p>
        <p>In the version of the replumbing plan made public last week, the Army Corps and the Water Management District predict that once the plan is executed, the abundance of creatures at all levels of the food web, from minnows and frogs to herons, ibis, otter and alligators, will increase and return to more natural distribution patterns. A few of the effects, the plan predicts, will be seen as early as a decade from now. About two-thirds of the plan's components should be in place by then, but other important ones will not be until about 2020, and some later. Moreover, there is likely to be a lag between the establishment of a new pattern of flow and the ecological response.</p>
        <p>A big uncertainty in all this is the possible impact of rising seas. If a warming climate causes the global sea level to rise over the next few decades as mainstream scientists predict, large areas of the southern Everglades could be inundated or converted to a saltwater marsh.</p>
        <p>Apart from that, no one knows exactly how the system will respond to the replumbing; since there is no detailed record of how the original system functioned, predictions and targets are based on the computer models. The plan, therefore, is ''a broad blueprint and a starting point,'' said Dr. Mark Schaefer, a biologist who is a deputy assistant secretary of the Interior. The key to success, he and many others believe, is to remain flexible so that midcourse corrections can be made. In that sense, the replumbing plan -- and the project itself -- is a perpetual work in progress.</p>
        <p>This has made some environmentalists nervous. They fear that unless as many details as possible are nailed down now, political sentiment could change in the future, and urban and agricultural interests could press for greater advantage at the expense of the natural system.</p>
        <p>Projections call for the population of South Florida to grow from 6 million to 12 million or more in 50 years, the target period for the restoration project. All of those people are going to need housing, and housing will need water that might otherwise go to the natural system.</p>
        <p>''My greatest fear,'' Mike Slayton, the Water Management District official, said as the helicopter flew over the sugar cane fields just north of the Everglades, ''is that the Everglades Agricultural Area will turn into a bedroom community in 20 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ring, the park superintendent, puts it this way:</p>
        <p>''Unless we figure out a way that changes how we grow and build, the built system is going to continue to move into the natural system.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
