<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answers Are Sought on Blackout's Causes</title>
    <meta content="08POWE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1121903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="AFTERMATH OF A HEAT WAVE: THE POWER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington Heights (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D9173CF93BA35754C0A96F958260" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answers Are Sought on Blackout's Causes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consolidated Edison officials shut off power to Washington Heights after fire erupted at local substation on July 6; power is restored to most of northern Manhattan on July 7, but many questions remain about cause of short circuits in power cables, cause of fire, and ability of city's electricity distribution system to function reliably under increasing summertime demand; diagram; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly after 10 on Tuesday night, after hours of work on seven short-circuited power cables serving the north end of Manhattan, Consolidated Edison workers prepared to turn two of them back on. The goal was to restore electricity to 15,000 customers who had been without power all that scorching day and much of the night before.</p>
        <p>At that point, most of Washington Heights and Inwood still had power because seven other cables carrying electricity to the neighborhoods from the local distribution station worked. Things were looking good,  Michael Spall, a Con Edison spokesman, said. ''We were close to restoring everything up there,'' he added.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly after 10 on Tuesday night, after hours of work on seven short-circuited power cables serving the north end of Manhattan, Consolidated Edison workers prepared to turn two of them back on. The goal was to restore electricity to 15,000 customers who had been without power all that scorching day and much of the night before.</p>
        <p>At that point, most of Washington Heights and Inwood still had power because seven other cables carrying electricity to the neighborhoods from the local distribution station worked. Things were looking good,  Michael Spall, a Con Edison spokesman, said. ''We were close to restoring everything up there,'' he added.</p>
        <p>But then everything went wrong. As the power flowed, one repaired cable failed again, a circuit breaker burst and a smoky fire erupted, Con Edison officials said.</p>
        <p>To prevent further damage, at 10:11 P.M., Con Edison officials at the utility's main control center on the Upper West Side -- with a representative of City Hall in the room --  shut off power with the click of a computer mouse to all 200,000 people living north of 155th Street.</p>
        <p>The result in the overheated city was the first prolonged large blackout since July 13, 1977, when lightning caused a cascade of failures that plunged eight million New Yorkers into darkness. A May 1996 blackout affected 40 percent of Queens, but lasted less than five hours in most places. Mr. Spall said that there was never any danger that the problems in upper Manhattan would spread to the rest of the city. Even so, he said, the fire required the prompt shutdown of the entire network at the north end of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''If we'd continued,'' he said, ''there was a good chance that the remaining cables would overload, overheat and short circuit, and then we would have had much more work to repair today.''</p>
        <p>Late yesterday, almost all of the stilled appliances and lights came back on across upper Manhattan, but many questions remained about the cause of the short circuits in the power cables, the cause of the fire, and the ability of New York City's electricity distribution system to function reliably under increasing summertime demand.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and elected officials representing the affected communities called for an immediate review of Con Edison's backup systems. After touring affected neighborhoods, Guillermo Linares, a City Council member representing most of upper Manhattan, said, ''There are many questions about the circumstances that led to the blackout of this particular sector rather than others.''</p>
        <p>He added that the city and Con Edison should look ahead to greater demands for power and anticipate the effect of long-term warming changes in the climate. ''What they say is a rarity is likely to be more commonplace,'' Mr. Linares said. ''We will be holding hearings to address this issue and make sure this does not occur again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spall said Con Edison regretted the problems that the blackout caused, but added that over all, the utility, according to independent industry surveys, had the best record of any large utility in the country for sending power reliably to customers.</p>
        <p>Last night, he and other Con Edison officials said they had not yet pinpointed how the record heat might have resulted in the cable failures or even indirectly caused the fire. And they could not explain why it was the northern tip of Manhattan, not Wall Street or Brownsville or somewhere else, where the power cables failed.</p>
        <p>Thomas Bisky, another spokesman for Con Edison, said the problems that occurred in upper Manhattan could happen anywhere in the system when heavy power use causes cables to heat up and to short circuit. Typically, he said, short circuits occur at splices or weak spots created where road salt seeps through cracks in insulation and corrodes wiring.</p>
        <p>The result is sparking or arcs of electricity that cause small fires. The fires, in turn, can cause gases to build up under the street, and the resulting pressure pops manhole covers off. And, in fact, manhole covers did pop in several places in Inwood on Monday night.</p>
        <p>He said the cables that failed would be examined over the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spall said that each spring, the company studies the load it expects on peak hot days in the coming summer and bolsters cables and  other systems. This year, Con Edison predicted that the highest usage on any one day would be 11,650 megawatts, and Tuesday's usage exceeded that by 200 megawatts, hitting a Con Edison record of 11,850 megawatts at the peak at 1 P.M.</p>
        <p>The record usage came from a combination of the record temperatures coupled with continued strong growth in the economy, Mr. Spall said. The economy has increased the occupancy of buildings and the purchase of appliances like computers and air-conditioners, all contributing to the growing demand.</p>
        <p>Around New York City, there are 1,157 13,000-volt ''feeder cables'' like the ones that failed in upper Manhattan, Mr. Spall said. Last spring, in a rotating testing program, the company tested 200 of those cables, he said, although yesterday he was unable to determine whether any of the tested cables were in upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Of the tested cables, 153 were upgraded by replacing sections with heavier wire capable of handling more electricity, he said. On Tuesday, 50 of the 1,157 feeder cables around the city failed, including the 7 at the north end of Manhattan, Mr. Spall said. But the only large-scale power loss occurred uptown.</p>
        <p>''We feel our summer preparations were adequate,'' Mr. Spall said. ''We'll certainly take a look at what happened in Washington Heights to see what lessons are to be learned.''</p>
        <p>According to the New York State Public Service Commission, a Con Edison customer, on average, goes more than eight years between power failures. The interval between power failures around the rest of the state averages once every 11 months, the commission says.</p>
        <p>Even so, private environmental groups said the power problems showed that the city and New York State should boost support for energy conservation so the system has fewer days when it is straining under record loads. In recent years, the state has sharply cut programs requiring utilities to help customers conserve energy. On July 23, 1991, Con Edison set a record with peak demand of 10,700 megawatts. That record was broken on July 17, 1997, at 11,013.</p>
        <p>Con Edison currently cannot generate or import more than 12,700 megawatts through the existing network of high-power transmission lines, said Ashok Gupta, an economist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, a private group, so Tuesday's record of 11,850 megawatts means that it is inching ever closer to an energy deficit.</p>
        <p>Larry Shapiro, a lawyer for the New York Public Interest Research Group, said, ''The gutting of the energy conservation program has increased power demand and made events like this more likely.''</p>
        <p>AFTERMATH OF A HEAT WAVE: THE POWER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
