<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Down But Not Out on the Family Farm</title>
    <meta content="24FARM$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1080012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Citrus Fruits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oranges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lemons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, W Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Marti</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citrus Fruits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7DB1F30F937A15752C0A96F958260" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Down But Not Out on the Family Farm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>W Michael Bennett and his wife, Marti, citrus farmers and cattle ranchers in California's San Joaquin Valley, lose an estimated $115,000 when entire crop of naval oranges and lemons falls victim to freeze in last days of 1998; disaster insurance and savings give them a safety net against foreclosure, but they and the two children have to cut expenses wherever they can; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the last days of 1998, W. Michael Bennett, a citrus grower and cattle rancher in California's San Joaquin Valley, began a frenzied race against the thermometer.</p>
        <p>As sunset temperatures slipped below freezing, Mr. Bennett threaded his truck through 150 acres planted with fruit and vines. In the glare of headlights, he switched on irrigation pumps and wind machines that spewed out clouds of warming moisture. After a quick bite and a few hours' sleep, he returned to the groves to repeat the process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the last days of 1998, W. Michael Bennett, a citrus grower and cattle rancher in California's San Joaquin Valley, began a frenzied race against the thermometer.</p>
        <p>As sunset temperatures slipped below freezing, Mr. Bennett threaded his truck through 150 acres planted with fruit and vines. In the glare of headlights, he switched on irrigation pumps and wind machines that spewed out clouds of warming moisture. After a quick bite and a few hours' sleep, he returned to the groves to repeat the process.</p>
        <p>It was all to no avail; the entire crop of navel oranges and lemons, valued the previous year at $115,000, failed. State agriculture officials estimate that the weather damage to the state's citrus crop reached $634 million. And Tulare County, where Mr. Bennett's farm is located, was the hardest hit. ''As cold as it got, we needed more help,'' Mr. Bennett.</p>
        <p>Nasty weather is the ancient enemy of farmers, of course, and even in this age of high-technology, nobody has yet figured out how to end a drought or stave off wind and freezing rain. The victims can only do what they have always done: tighten their belts and hope for better luck next season.</p>
        <p>For the Bennetts, that means making lists of trips to forgo, purchases to postpone and farm operations to put off. While disaster insurance and savings give them a safety net against foreclosure, the couple are determined to get expenses in line with income -- and everybody in the family, including the two of their four children who still live at home, is expected to pitch in.</p>
        <p>''I've got a game plan,'' said Mr. Bennett, 52, whose father is also a Central Valley grower. But, he adds, ''I don't know if it's going to work out.''</p>
        <p>His wife, Marti, 47, isn't about to sink into self pity. The couple's home, a 3,000-acre ranch in the Sierra Nevada foothills, five miles from the citrus farm, was part of an original homestead staked out in 1887 by her great-grandparents, and she displays a stoicism born of four generations of harsh experience. ''It doesn't do a thing to pound your head against the wall,'' she said. ''We'll work with the hand we got.''</p>
        <p>So, in addition to the long hours she spends on the ranch, she will do substitute teaching at the high school 15 miles away in Porterville, a drive she makes anyway to drop off and pick up her two teen-agers.</p>
        <p>Even so, the couple have postponed improvements they planned for the ranch. They won't buy an $8,500 computer-connected digital scale, and so will have to continue hauling their cows to the nearby ranch of Mrs. Bennett's brother to be weighed. Paying $7,000 to increase their stock of bulls from six to eight, in a herd of 200 cattle, will also have to wait another year.</p>
        <p>HE Bennetts have shelved plans to remodel their home, which was built by Mrs. Bennett's grandparents in 1953, and will let the energy-efficient windows they purchased for the remodeling collect dust in storage. ''That stopped dead. We're going to use that money on the ranch for operating funds,'' Mrs. Bennett said.</p>
        <p>Another spending cut will be borne by the children, who raise their own mini-herds of show cows to make money for college. With weekend livestock fairs charging entrance fees of $30 a head, Brooke, 14, and her brother Casey, 15, will be taking only four calves, instead of eight, to competitions.</p>
        <p>Catastrophic crop insurance, made available to California growers by the Federal Government after an even harsher freeze in 1990, will ease the Bennetts' financial pain but will not erase it. The insurance pays half of a grower's production costs, which average $1,500 an acre, said Shirley A. Batchman, a spokeswoman for the Exeter-based California Citrus Mutual, a grower's association whose 800 members farm 40 percent of the state's citrus acreage. For most growers, that will not even cover payments for the land, she said. Moreover, she said, ''It doesn't give you a penny to live on.''</p>
        <p>Applying that formula, Mr. Bennett would qualify for $112,000 (though he hopes to salvage some fruit and expects to receive less aid). Even so, that won't cover all his debt on his 35 acres and the 115 acres he owns jointly with his brothers, Robert and Richard. ''I'll have to go to the lender to ask for a postponement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While the Bennetts are unusual among farm families in that they have saved a year's worth of income, Mr. Bennett is reluctant to liquidate what he had mentally stashed away for retirement to meet operating needs. So he is considering refinancing some land to preserve that capital.</p>
        <p>He is also reluctantly weighing cuts in citrus operations, like fertilizer feedings and pruning, which are likely to curb future crop yields and revenue. He has already temporarily let go two employees, a foreman who worked for him for 15 years and another farmhand, both eligible for emergency aid.</p>
        <p>Few crop failures force farmers from their land, said Mark L. Prendergast, a certified financial planner in Fresno. Instead, they end up with higher debt. ''When they have good years, they buy tractors; when they have a bad one, they fire their foreman,'' he said. Mr. Prendergast calculated that if the Bennetts sold their land and invested the proceeds, they would make more in interest and dividends than they make from farming in the best years.</p>
        <p>The prospect seems unfathomable to Mr. Bennett, though. ''That would be one of my last choices,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
