<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlantic Salmon Elude Even Dogged Pursuit</title>
    <meta content="25OUTD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1126079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salmon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Matapedia River (Quebec)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Restigouche (River (Quebec)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Nelson</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Outdoors (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDA103EF936A15754C0A96F958260" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlantic Salmon Elude Even Dogged Pursuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bryant, Nelson</byline>
      <dateline>MATAPEDIA, Quebec</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nelson Bryant Outdoors column on fly-fishing for Atlantic Salmon in Matapedia and Restigouche rivers of Quebec; says hot, dry weather has plagued many of Canada's rivers; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I think we'll try a Green Machine,'' said my guide, Charles Irving, thus opening another chapter in my quest for Atlantic salmon, which had it beginnings 55 years ago on the River Towy in Wales.</p>
        <p>Then, I had wandered to the stream from a nearby hospital where I was recovering from a chest wound I had received a few days after jumping into Normandy on D-Day the month before, and an elderly angler let me make a few feeble casts with his two-handed fly rod. Most of the afternoon was spent chatting about salmon and salmon fishing and speculating on when the monstrous anger of the guns would be silenced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I think we'll try a Green Machine,'' said my guide, Charles Irving, thus opening another chapter in my quest for Atlantic salmon, which had it beginnings 55 years ago on the River Towy in Wales.</p>
        <p>Then, I had wandered to the stream from a nearby hospital where I was recovering from a chest wound I had received a few days after jumping into Normandy on D-Day the month before, and an elderly angler let me make a few feeble casts with his two-handed fly rod. Most of the afternoon was spent chatting about salmon and salmon fishing and speculating on when the monstrous anger of the guns would be silenced.</p>
        <p>Now, Charles had anchored our canoe in the confluence of the Matapedia and Restigouche rivers. Joan Wulff of Lew Beach, N.Y., was in a canoe below us with her guide, and Murray and Kay Bring of Manhattan were similarly ensconced a short distance upstream. We were fishing Ristigouche Salmon Club waters as the guests of Joseph Cullman, 3d of Manhattan. (The club clings to the old spelling of the river: ''Ristigouche.'')</p>
        <p>Fly-fishing for Atlantic salmon often involves wild emotional swings. One sometimes flails away for hours and even days without raising a fish, desperately striving to keep alert by honing one's casting techniques or experimenting with various fly patterns. But the tedium is erased by one savage strike or the water erupting under a dry fly.</p>
        <p>The Green Machine that Charles Irving gave me is a fat, stubby fly, the body of which is clipped deer hair dyed green. If I am left to my own devices when the water is low, I almost always start with the venerable Blue Charm, but I yielded to Charles, whose skills I respect.</p>
        <p>Soon after I began casting the Green Machine, a big grilse hit and flung himself out of the fast water. A grilse is a salmon, usually a male of about five pounds, that returns to its natal stream after only one year at sea. Charles pulled up the anchor and poled into the shallows where the fish could be easily netted.</p>
        <p>The grilse tore about the pool, leaping three more times and I was reveling at being a few minutes away from early success when the line went slack. The hook had pulled loose. No matter. There were many more fish in the pool, including some large salmon. After another half hour of casting, a second fish hit. It was much larger than the grilse. It didn't jump, but I could feel the weight of it and I had the notion that it hadn't yet divined its predicament. Once again the anchor was pulled and we started toward shore with me waiting for the fish to begin its first long run. Again the hook pulled free.</p>
        <p>Before the morning ended, I had one more heavy strike, but that time around the fish wasn't hooked.</p>
        <p>Joan Wulff, who tried both wet and dry flies, rose no salmon that morning, but Murray Bring vaulted into a top rod status that he never relinquished the entire trip, catching a 12-pound salmon and a grilse and losing a salmon estimated at 16 pounds at the net. Kay, his wife, took a 10-pounder. The salmon were released.</p>
        <p>Back at Cullman's Runnymeade Lodge on the Restigouche for lunch, our host suggested that he and I, the Brings and Joan Wulff go to Two Brook camp on the Upsalquitch River that afternoon while the other members of our party, the entertainer Linda Hart and her husband, Bill Forster, could remain to fish Runnymeade waters. Two Brook, owned by Joe and his brother Edgar, is on the Upsalquitch, a lower Restigouche tributary in New Brunswick. Twisting down through steep valleys, the Upsalquitch is a haunting, intimate stream.</p>
        <p>Hot, dry weather has plagued many of Canada's Atlantic salmon rivers this summer. Rivers have been low and warm, conditions that salmon and salmon anglers abhor. The fishing logs at both Runnymeade and Two Brook told a sad story: only nine salmon or grilse taken at Runnymeade the entire season up to July 12 and only 18 at Two Brook up to the same date.</p>
        <p>The day before we arrived, however, more than two inches of rain fell in the region and both the Restigouche and the Upsalquitch had risen more than seven inches and the weather and water had cooled.</p>
        <p>At Two Brook, Murray caught a 10-pounder and a grilse. Cullman and Joan Wulff each caught a grilse and Joan lost another that rose to a dry fly. With the guide Gerry Thomas as my long-suffering companion, I spotted, raised -- with both wet and dry flies -- or occasionally hooked more salmon or grilse than anyone else, but failed to land any of them.</p>
        <p>Back at Runnymeade two nights later we learned that the Forsters, who had never used fly rods before, had lost two grilse with Runnymeade's manager Lorne Irvine.</p>
        <p>The rivers were falling rapidly and warming as we fished them, the days were growing hotter and the salmon were sulking. Joe and I visited Fraser's Pool on the Matapedia as guests of Jack Powers of Manhattan. My host insisted that I do all the casting. He wanted me to have a fish to take home, but it was not to be, even though we had two superb guides, the agile octogenarian Richard Adams and the incomparable Jack Lyons, a fellow who can cover more water with a dry fly in half an hour than an ordinary mortal can in half a day.</p>
        <p>At our final festive meal at Runnymeade late that night, it seemed clear that the Forsters had been smitten by Atlantic salmon fever. Joan Wulff had given them a fly-casting lesson, they had hooked a brace of grilse and they got a crash course in salmon and salmon fishing.</p>
        <p>They had also learned how deeply Joe Cullman cares for the Atlantic salmon. Cullman has played a major role in salmon conservation efforts. He was in on the founding, in 1969, of what is now the most influential conservation organization of its kind in the world, the Canadian-American Atlantic Salmon Federation, was long its president and continues to spur the effort to save the salmon from inexcusable exploitation and neglect. In April, for example, the federation announced that Cullman had recently pledged $5 million to the organization.</p>
        <p>I learned that Murray Bring has a big heart. He gave me one of his two grilse. Twenty years ago I would have refused, but false pride no longer bedevils me.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
