<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Warn of Mars on the Cheap</title>
    <meta content="Y08MAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1159263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Polar Lander (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Climate Orbiter (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DC1E3EF93BA35751C1A96F958260" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Warn of Mars on the Cheap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA officials and private experts say string of embarrassing mistakes that doomed $125 million Mars Climate Orbiter in September may have helped pave way for disappearance of $165 million Mars Polar Lander; blame combination of inadequate funding and inadequate management preparation for low-budget missions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A string of embarrassing mistakes that doomed the $125 million Mars Climate Orbiter in September may have helped pave the way for the disappearance of the $165 million Mars Polar Lander this week, NASA officials and private experts said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Last month, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration issued a blistering 45-page report on the loss of the climate orbiter, the first of two spacecraft meant to renew NASA's exploratory push this year to the red planet. The report's findings and recommendations included suggested ways to avert disaster with the sister craft, which has fallen silent since trying to make its planned landing on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A string of embarrassing mistakes that doomed the $125 million Mars Climate Orbiter in September may have helped pave the way for the disappearance of the $165 million Mars Polar Lander this week, NASA officials and private experts said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Last month, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration issued a blistering 45-page report on the loss of the climate orbiter, the first of two spacecraft meant to renew NASA's exploratory push this year to the red planet. The report's findings and recommendations included suggested ways to avert disaster with the sister craft, which has fallen silent since trying to make its planned landing on Friday.</p>
        <p>Among other things, the November report found potential problems in the complexity of the lander's engines and called for much last-minute polishing and repairing to try to increase the odds of a safe touchdown near the Martian south pole.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in light of the new failure, experts inside and outside the space agency said common troubles in the sister programs and perhaps the anticipated engine woes accounted for the current ominous silence.</p>
        <p>''We fell into cutting too many corners,'' a senior official at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., which designed the two spacecraft, said in an interview. ''We have to be smarter.''</p>
        <p>John E. Pike, head of space policy at the Federation of American Scientists, a Washington group, said NASA's climate orbiter investigation showed that the Mars program had been desperately short of time, personnel and money, with designers pushed to the breaking point.</p>
        <p>''We've all seen this,'' Mr. Pike said. ''Anybody who has tried to do too much work without enough people immediately recognizes the symptoms. Stuff doesn't get done. Things fail.''</p>
        <p>The common problem behind the  setbacks, Mr. Pike added, ''is some combination of inadequate funding and inadequate management preparation for low-budget missions.''</p>
        <p>The analysis of the first failed mission found poor training, communication and support for the spacecraft team. Such failings, experts said, will be key suspects in the new investigation as well.</p>
        <p>Unlike the successful 1997 Mars Pathfinder mission, which the Jet Propulsion Laboratory built and ran, the Mars Climate Orbiter and Mars Polar Lander were designed by the Pasadena laboratory but, in a cost-cutting move, built by Lockheed Martin Astronautics of Denver.</p>
        <p>The current pair of lost spacecraft cost about half as much as their predecessors, the $270 million Pathfinder and its companion orbiter, the $300 million Mars Global Surveyor.</p>
        <p>The investigation into the recent climate orbiter failure was conducted by a nine-member NASA panel led by Arthur G. Stephenson of the Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, Ala., and its findings were made public Nov. 10.</p>
        <p>The panel, painting a picture of widespread design and management woes, cited not only a single main culprit but eight contributing factors ''that led directly or indirectly to the loss of the spacecraft.''</p>
        <p>A mixup between English and metric units in navigation data was cited as the main reason the spacecraft went off course, and probably to its destruction, as it was trying to orbit Mars in September. All radio contact with the craft was lost.</p>
        <p>Contributing flaws cited by the panel included insufficient team training, undetected errors in computer models of thruster firings, failures of the navigation team to know the spacecraft's orientation in space, inadequate effort by system engineers to track and double-check all mission aspects, a tendency for communications to be too informal, failure to weigh the need for an additional engine firing and the overworking of the navigation team.</p>
        <p>The investigators also faulted communications between the design team at the Pasadena laboratory and the spacecraft builders in Denver, calling some of the technical dialogues ''inadequate.''</p>
        <p>Additionally, the panel made eight observations and recommendations about the Mars Polar Lander in a bid to ward off related failures. Several significant ones centered on the engines and the lander's descent.</p>
        <p>In particular, the panel warned that the hydrazine fuel for the lander's retrorockets might freeze in space, producing ignition delays, irregular pulses and possibly leading to a topsy-turvy landing.</p>
        <p>The panel suggested that fuel-line heaters be turned on early to begin warming the hydrazine, a precaution that NASA officials yesterday said was taken before the lander began its descent on Friday.</p>
        <p>The panel also expressed worry that the lander's 12 thrusters had to act ''in unison to ensure a stable descent,'' and that such a complex feat had never been tried.</p>
        <p>''It should be recognized that under extreme, worst-case conditions,'' the panel said, ''some thrusters could produce near zero thrust and some could produce nearly twice the expected thrust.''</p>
        <p>It called for the design team to thoroughly review descent preparations ''because of the extreme complexity of this landing maneuver.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Edward Stone, the Jet Propulsion Laboratory's director, said in reaction to the November report that the laboratory had ''mobilized the very best talent'' to fix identified flaws. ''Special attention,'' he said, ''is being directed at navigation and propulsion issues.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, a member of the reporting panel said its findings were ''very valid'' in light of the new failure and were ''the beginning of what we're doing'' by way of conducting an intensified probe.</p>
        <p>Dr. Edward Weiler, NASA's head of space science, told reporters yesterday that a formal investigation of the polar lander disappearance would include many experts who had investigated the loss of the orbiter.</p>
        <p>He added that the particular kind of navigation error that doomed the Mars Climate Orbiter in September was clearly not to blame in the current vanishing act, since all signs in the final hours and minutes of mission indicated that the Mars probe was right on target.</p>
        <p>However, he added that factors like quality control would be looked into carefully in the new investigation.</p>
        <p>''Nothing's off the table,'' Dr. Weiler said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
