<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Remember El Nino? His Sister Has Shown Up, and She's Angry</title>
    <meta content="Y27EXTR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1080527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Nina (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DD1339F934A15752C0A96F958260" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Remember El Nino? His Sister Has Shown Up, and She's Angry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts attribute abnormal weather patterns across US to La Nina, abnormally cold ocean current stretching across equatorial Pacific that causes far-flung changes in atmosphere's behavior; phenomenon is opposite of El Nino, which warms Pacific instead of cooling it, but also causes severe weather disruptions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Record snows in Buffalo and Chicago. Record numbers of tornadoes in the country's midsection. All-time low temperatures in Indiana and Maine. Double the normal amount of precipitation, coupled with an extended warm spell, in New York. What accounts for this month's run of extreme weather?</p>
        <p>One big factor, experts say, is probably La Nina: an abnormally cold pool of water stretching across the equatorial Pacific that causes far-flung changes in the atmosphere's behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Record snows in Buffalo and Chicago. Record numbers of tornadoes in the country's midsection. All-time low temperatures in Indiana and Maine. Double the normal amount of precipitation, coupled with an extended warm spell, in New York. What accounts for this month's run of extreme weather?</p>
        <p>One big factor, experts say, is probably La Nina: an abnormally cold pool of water stretching across the equatorial Pacific that causes far-flung changes in the atmosphere's behavior.</p>
        <p>La Nina may not be as familiar as its opposite number, El Nino, which warms the Pacific instead of cooling it. It does not appear as often, and its impact is somewhat less predictable and clear-cut. But this winter, Government scientists say, its interaction with routine climate behavior has produced an unusual run of weather in North America.</p>
        <p>''It's La Nina plus the normal chaotic variability of the atmosphere,'' said Dr. Gerry Bell, a researcher at the Climate Prediction Center of the National Weather Service in Camp Springs, Md. While no single weather event can be directly attributed to La Nina (or to El Nino, for that matter), it has been ''a big player'' in this winter's events, Dr. Bell said.</p>
        <p>The El Nino-La Nina cycle is wholly natural. But some scientists believe that extreme weather generally is increasing as a result of an observed rise in the average global surface temperature of 1 degree Fahrenheit over the last century. A warmer atmosphere stimulates more precipitation, for instance. Whether the warming is also modifying the El Nino-La Nina cycle in some way is an open question.</p>
        <p>It was only a year ago that the most recent edition of El Nino, one of the two most powerful on record, altered and strengthened storm tracks flowing from the Pacific into North America. As a result, storm after storm slammed into California and skimmed across the southern tier of the country. Mudslides plagued the West Coast, while killer tornadoes ravaged Florida.</p>
        <p>But in May, the extra-warm Pacific waters that define El Nino began to lose much of their heat, and by  autumn those waters had become abnormally cool, ushering in La Nina. Now sea-surface temperatures along the Equator are 2 to 5 degrees Fahrenheit below normal, marking what the Federal scientists call ''mature La Nina conditions.''</p>
        <p>Those conditions are expected to persist until May or June, then begin to decay. What will happen after that is uncertain.</p>
        <p>La Nina's effects on the atmosphere now, as it impinges on North America, seem clear. Its main impact has been to alter the path of the jet stream, the high-altitude river of air that runs from west to east and marks the boundary between cold air masses from the north and warm ones from the tropics. It is along this boundary, where warm and cold air clash, that most winter storms develop.</p>
        <p>La Nina's main signature in North America is an exaggerated pattern of jet stream flow in which the jet, leaving the North Pacific region, frequently curves northward around a vast high-pressure system near Alaska, then plunges down into Montana and the Northern Plains and then into the central part of the country before curving northeastward again. On the northern and western sides of the downward bulge is cold winter air from Canada; on the southern and eastern sides, warm tropical air from the South. These circulation patterns typically span the entire country. The weather any locality gets depends on where it is situated in relation to them.</p>
        <p>The clash of the two big air masses is what led to this month's tornadoes -- more than 100 so far, almost double the previous record for January,  52. Thirty-one twisters touched down in Tennessee, Arkansas and Mississippi on Jan. 17, followed by an outbreak of 55 more across the South on Jan. 21 and 22.</p>
        <p>In a normal winter, a southward bulge of cold air would enter the United States farther east, in the Great Lakes region or the Northeast, or both. This year, under La Nina's influence, the bulges have materialized farther west, and then the masses of cold air behind them have drifted slowly to the east.</p>
        <p>Wherever the cold air has gone  this winter, it has brought harsh conditions. Chicago broke a single-day snowfall record for the city with 18.6 inches of snow on Jan. 2. Buffalo, which styles itself the nation's snow capital, received a record five feet of snow in two weeks earlier this month. Indiana had a temperature of minus 36 degrees Fahrenheit, lower than any ever recorded there; three feet of snow fell on South Bend.</p>
        <p>In the east, between the periodic arrivals of cold air drifting in from the west, the weather has often stayed unseasonably warm -- as in New York's ''January thaw.'' From time to time, the country as a whole  warmed up as the Alaskan high-pressure system broke down. The jet stream, no longer having to surge far to the north as it climbed over the high, resumed a more or less straight west-to-east course, wafting warm Pacific air clear across the continent.</p>
        <p>Then the Alaskan high would build up again, and the exaggerated southward bulge of cold air would come once more.</p>
        <p>The other major effects of La Nina, Dr. Bell said, have been mostly in the tropics. For instance, there have been good rains in Indonesia, just the opposite of El Nino's drought last year. But La Nina, he said, has also ''completely shut down'' rainfall in the eastern tropical Pacific.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
