<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Late-Winter Blast, Snow Sweeps New York Region</title>
    <meta content="16SNOW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1092865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7D8113EF935A25750C0A96F958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Late-Winter Blast, Snow Sweeps New York Region</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>YORKTOWN, N.Y., March 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Late winter storm blankets New York City metropolitan area with snow, causing dozens of traffic accidents, fallen tree branches, school closings and electrical blackouts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when the winter storm warnings were broadcast Sunday night, Toni McCloskey, like many residents of southern New York, Connecticut, and New Jersey, refused to take the bait.</p>
        <p>''This was the third time they told us a major storm was coming,'' said Ms. McCloskey, a mother of three from Valhalla, in northern Westchester County. The previous storms had only brushed the area, she said, ''so we pretty much wrote this one off.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even when the winter storm warnings were broadcast Sunday night, Toni McCloskey, like many residents of southern New York, Connecticut, and New Jersey, refused to take the bait.</p>
        <p>''This was the third time they told us a major storm was coming,'' said Ms. McCloskey, a mother of three from Valhalla, in northern Westchester County. The previous storms had only brushed the area, she said, ''so we pretty much wrote this one off.''</p>
        <p>But this morning she was standing with about 100 other snow lovers atop a prime sledding hill near a closed school here, dispensing inner tubes, sleds and a snowboard to her children and two nephews, who sprinted to the thickly blanketed white slopes.</p>
        <p>''Hey, Mom, it works,'' said Eddie, Ms. McCloskey's 11-year-old son, triumphantly holding up the flashy snowboard that he used for the first time today.</p>
        <p>It was a Christmas present -- in 1997.</p>
        <p>Five days before spring's arrival, the metropolitan region had a decent dose of winter. Between 4 and 10 inches of snow fell overnight as a powerful storm swept out of the Midwest and merged with a coastal storm before heading toward Maine. Heavy snow fell in two bands, one running from western New Jersey up the Hudson Valley and the other from eastern Long Island into Connecticut.</p>
        <p>It was not all fun, with dozens of traffic accidents on slick roads and tens of thousands of households losing electricity after snow-burdened branches struck wires.</p>
        <p>The Palisades Interstate Parkway resembled a toboggan run on Sunday night, according to several travelers, with cars slithering off the highway every few miles. Early this morning, a six-car accident disrupted commuters for several hours on the upper level of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge.</p>
        <p>About 100,000 customers in Connecticut lost power during the storm, with more than 39,000 still lacking electricity at dusk today, said Debra Durbin, a spokeswoman for Northeast Utilities.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, nearly 108,000 Long Island Power Authority customers scattered across the island lost electricity at the peak of the storm early this morning, said Tracy Levy, a spokeswoman for the power authority.</p>
        <p>Although the heaviest snow bypassed it, New York City still had its biggest snowfall of the winter, according to the National Weather Service: four inches measured by meteorologists in Central Park. Altogether, the city has seen only 12.2 inches of snow this season, compared with more than 28 inches in an average year, said Bob McElhearn, a meteorologist for the weather service.</p>
        <p>Most of central New Jersey received about five inches of snow, making this the biggest snowfall for much of the state since 1996, said David A. Robinson, a climatologist at Rutgers University who is the official state climatologist.</p>
        <p>At the Mountain Creek ski resort in Vernon, a 10-inch snowfall allowed the resort to operate for the first time this winter without making snow, Sally Johnstone, a spokeswoman for the resort, told The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people who have school and work off are here today,'' Ms. Johnstone said. ''And even some people who didn't are here, I suspect.''</p>
        <p>The storm caught many people by surprise, beginning Sunday afternoon as a misty rain, which had some figuring this would be another near miss. But the shift to snow came rapidly.</p>
        <p>Every snowfall has different characteristics, fluffy or wet, sugary or flaky. Across much of the suburban arc around New York City, this time,  big flakes pelted the landscape like windblown wads of soggy cotton, sticking to the upwind side of trees, piling up on the slenderest twigs or telephone lines, turning parked cars into mushrooms.</p>
        <p>In the city, much of the snow that fell had turned to shoe-soaking slush by this morning. Even so, freelance snow shovelers made the best of the situation. In the Park Slope section of Brooklyn, Steven Sanchez, 34, a carpenter, was ringing doorbells and offering to shovel stoops and sidewalks for $10.</p>
        <p>In the suburbs, the pickup trucks of freelance snow plowers, many of whom are landscapers by summer, raced from driveway to driveway early this morning, garnering at least a little income in a winter largely bereft of enduring snow.</p>
        <p>Late today, the sun broke through the clouds in many places, releasing snowball-size clods of wet snow that smacked into passing cars.</p>
        <p>The pockets of sunshine were a portent of things to come, said Joseph Koval, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University. ''We should have a warming trend settling in for the next 6 to 10 days,'' he said, with temperatures around New York City reaching well into the 50's by Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''This may in fact be winter's last hurrah,'' Mr. Koval said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
