<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blizzard Buries New York, Slowing Region to a Crawl</title>
    <meta content="31SNOW$20" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/31/nyregion/31SNOW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BLIZZARD OF 2000: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDE153BF932A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blizzard Buries New York, Slowing Region to a Crawl</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blizzard strikes New York City and Northeast with blustery winds and whiteout snow that reaches depths of 9 to 20 inches; classic northeaster moves up coast in daylong assault that obliterates landscapes of 10 states from Delaware to Maine and buries Philadelphia, New York, Boston and other cities in its path; thousands of air, train and bus travelers are stranded or delayed, and highways turn treacherous; storm comes at start of long holiday weekend, leaving two full days for snow-frolicking and cleanup before return to work and school on Jan 2; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An awesome, end-of-the-real-millennium blizzard struck New York City and the Northeast yesterday with blustery winds and whiteout snow that reached depths of 9 to 20 inches. It disrupted travel and commerce, but draped a dazzling winter gown over the region for tonight's New Year's revelry.</p>
        <p>The gigantic storm, a swirling comma-shape 150 miles wide and 500 miles long, formed east of Washington before dawn and moved up the coast in a daylong assault that obliterated the landscapes of 10 states from Delaware to Maine and buried Philadelphia, New York, Boston and other cities in its path. Three deaths -- a New Jersey motorist and two men in Yonkers who had been shoveling snow -- were reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An awesome, end-of-the-real-millennium blizzard struck New York City and the Northeast yesterday with blustery winds and whiteout snow that reached depths of 9 to 20 inches. It disrupted travel and commerce, but draped a dazzling winter gown over the region for tonight's New Year's revelry.</p>
        <p>The gigantic storm, a swirling comma-shape 150 miles wide and 500 miles long, formed east of Washington before dawn and moved up the coast in a daylong assault that obliterated the landscapes of 10 states from Delaware to Maine and buried Philadelphia, New York, Boston and other cities in its path. Three deaths -- a New Jersey motorist and two men in Yonkers who had been shoveling snow -- were reported.</p>
        <p>It was a classic northeaster: powerful, dangerous, true on course up the Atlantic Seaboard. At times, it featured lightning flashes and rumbling thunder. But the storm's timing was fortunate, coming at the start of the long holiday weekend and leaving two full days for snow-frolicking and cleanup before the return to work and school on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The biggest winter blow since the Blizzard of 1996, which left 20 to 30 inches of snow across the region on Jan. 7-8, the storm stranded or delayed thousands of air, train and bus travelers, turned highways treacherous and scuttled many holiday plans.</p>
        <p>The storm bypassed Washington and Baltimore and hit hardest in New York City and its suburbs in New Jersey, Connecticut, Long Island and the upstate counties of Westchester, Rockland and Orange. Last night, after the snow had stopped, temperatures were expected to drop into the low 20's.</p>
        <p>Across the nation, the effects of an ice storm that killed 37 people and devastated much of the Southern Plains all week lingered on, and thousands of homes and businesses in Arkansas, Oklahoma and Texas were expected to remain without power for 5 to 10 days.</p>
        <p>In Florida, freezing temperatures threatened citrus crops last night. And more snow fell early yesterday in snowbound Chicago and Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>In the brindled winter light, the snow began falling in southern New Jersey after midnight, and by 3 a.m. had reached New York City and its suburbs. It came down slowly at first, just a few tiny geometric shapes illuminated in the cones of headlights and street lamps.</p>
        <p>But it quickly turned into the heavy snow forecasters had been predicting for days. Over the silent city streets and suburban tracts of New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, it fell in great hissing sweeps at rates that varied from 1 to 3 inches an hour, and it swiftly transformed the region into a traveler's nightmare.</p>
        <p>La Guardia and Newark International Airports were closed in the morning, and Kennedy Airport had only one of four runways open until shortly after noon, according to Steven Coleman, a spokesman for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. One of Kennedy's runways reopened at 6 p.m., and Newark and were expected to reopen by midnight, said Alan Hicks, another Port Authority spokesman. The runways had been closed because the snow was falling too fast for them to be sufficiently cleaned.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City International Airport was also closed, and 500 passengers were stranded in the terminal in Egg Harbor Township. Thomas Rafter, the airport director, said it was unclear when flights would resume. ''It all depends on the weather,'' he said. ''Every time the plows move the snow, the wind just comes along and covers it up again.''</p>
        <p>Most airlines operating in New York and New Jersey canceled flights even before the snow began to fall -- Continental alone struck off 225 flights -- and more were canceled as the day wore on. Flights in Baltimore and Philadelphia also were taken off the boards, and thousands of holiday travelers were stranded or delayed. At La Guardia's Delta terminal, hundreds of people sat around watching the snow.</p>
        <p>At Westchester Airport, operations were off and on, alternating every half hour so that runways could be cleared, ''They can only have a half-inch on the runway before they have to broom it off,'' said Susan Tolchin, a spokeswoman for Andrew J. Spano, the county executive. County officials turned away the New York Knicks, who had wanted to land their private charter jet at 2:30 p.m., Ms. Tolchin said. The airport planned to close after the long day at 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>The snow began to taper off around 3 p.m., leaving the biggest accumulations in New Jersey: 20 inches in West Milford, 18 inches in Union County, 16 in Bergen County and 13 in Newark. A few towns in the state reported as much as 25 inches.</p>
        <p>In New York, totals included 21 inches in Warwick, in Orange County; 15 in Oceanside, in Nassau County; 14 in White Plains and 12 at La Guardia Airport and in Central Park, eclipsing the previous record for the date, 2.9 inches, set in 1939.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, 11 inches fell in Danbury and 9 fell in Bridgeport. Philadelphia had nearly 7 inches. Boston and its suberbs were expected to get up to 8 inches before the storm moved out to sea early today, according to Todd J. Minor, a meteorologist with Penn State University.</p>
        <p>Homeowners and apartment personnel were out on sidewalks with salt and shovels as soon as the snow began falling. Public officials -- mindful of the political consequences of ignoring the anguished cries of snowbound voters -- had hundreds of salt spreaders and snowplows out early on highways and city arteries.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said that the city's 350 salt spreaders had been sent out as soon as the first snow flakes appeared, and its 1,600 plow-fitted trucks were out as soon as the snow became 3 inches deep.</p>
        <p>By 7 a.m., all the main highways had been plowed once, and the trucks began work on secondary arteries before returning to the highways in a daylong effort to keep up with the falling snow, the mayor told reporters at the city's emergency command bunker in the World Trade Center. He said that all the city's bridges and tunnels were open, and that subways were running on schedule. He said 11 people were injured using snow blowers, with seven of them losing fingers. Police in Farmingdale, L.I., also reported that a man badly cut his hand clearing a blocked snowblower.</p>
        <p>The mayor, noting that the city's biggest problems had been centered at La Guardia, Kennedy and Newark International Airports, sharply criticized the Port Authority for what he called ''a lack of cooperation'' with city agencies during the storm. It was a remarkable statement; normally, in storms and other public emergencies, officials are effusive in praise of one another.</p>
        <p>''They showed up here 15 minutes ago,'' the mayor said of Port Authority officials at an 11 a.m. news conference at the bunker, where all major city agencies had been represented through the night as the storm developed. He said he had been obliged to call Gov. George E. Pataki's office at 10 a.m. to ask the Port Authority officials to join them.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki later called it a communications problem and said, ''To my understanding, there are no needs that have not been met.''</p>
        <p>The mayor said the city had set up 10 ''warming centers'' for people whose homes or apartments have no heat. He noted, though, that there had been fewer heat complaints than normal, and the number of people in homeless shelters was also smaller than usual.</p>
        <p>A car pileup shut down the Jackie Robinson Parkway near Cypress Hills in Queens, a snow-laden scaffolding collapsed on West 57th Street in Manhattan and 100 city buses were stuck on snow-clogged roads, but Mayor Giuliani was upbeat. ''Although it's cold, it's not unbearable,'' he said, dismissing suggestions that the storm might disrupt New Year's Eve celebrations in Times Square.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for New York City Transit, Albert O'Leary, said that a dozen of the 201 bus routes in the five boroughs had been suspended in hilly areas of upper Manhattan, the Bronx and Staten Island.</p>
        <p>''Once you get a couple of buses stuck in a particular area with no alternative around it, there is no point adding to that pileup,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Consolidated Edison said that no problems had been reported by mid-morning, primarily because there was no ice to topple trees and power lines. There were no power problems immediately reported in New Jersey or Connecticut.</p>
        <p>But on Long Island, 1,650 homes and businesses in Nassau and Suffolk Counties, mainly in North Shore coastal towns, lost power for varying periods after midnight, the Long Island Power Authority reported. By afternoon, power had been restored to all but about 500 customers.</p>
        <p>In Nassau County, state Humvees -- four-wheel drive, all-terrain vehicles -- were used to ferry county police officers after their patrol cars were unable to navigate the snows, officials said.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, 1,300 plows could not keep up with the snow. Speeds were restricted to 35 miles an hour on the New Jersey Turnpike and the Atlantic City Expressway.</p>
        <p>Frederick Dorst, 66, of Oak Ridge, N.J., was killed when he lost control of his car on a snow-glazed highway in the Passaic County community of West Milford at 6:30 a.m., and crashed into a utility pole, the West Milford police reported. His wife, Helen, 59, sustained minor injuries, they said.</p>
        <p>In Yonkers, two men in their 70's suffered fatal heart attacks while shoveling snow at their homes, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>There were reports of minor accidents all over New Jersey, New York and Connecticut. No major highways were closed, but lanes accumulating snow occasionally closed lanes and caused traffic bottlenecks.</p>
        <p>Amtrak canceled its Metroliner service between Washington and New York. New Jersey Transit suspended its bus service in Bergen, Hudson, Essex, Middlesex, Union and Passaic Counties, and all bus service in and out of the Port Authority Bus Terminal in Manhattan was suspended as the snow grew deep.</p>
        <p>Metro-North and Long Island Rail Road commuter lines reported scattered delays of 5 to 15 minutes. Both lines had locomotives fitted with plows to keep the tracks open, and extra crews on duty to keep switches from freezing. Utilities across the region also mustered extra crews to work around the clock, if necessary, to cope with possible power failures.</p>
        <p>There had been warnings of coastal flooding from Cape May, N.J., to Montauk Point, with abnormally high tides in the storm. But weather officials said little or no flooding occurred because high winds were pushing seaward, heaving the breakers back.</p>
        <p>''I think we escaped one today,'' said Robert Levy, chief of emergency services in Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>The holiday-weekend timing of the storm lightened its consequences. Except for emergency services, most government agencies were closed, along with countless offices and businesses. For most people, there was no need to commute, to shop or to get out to the mall or Saturday entertainments.</p>
        <p>While hundreds of thousands were expected in Times Square tonight for the dropping of the New Year's ball, officials said the crowds would be nothing like last year's throng of 2 million, who gathered a year prematurely to celebrate the Millennium. Purists insist that tonight, at midnight, is the real turn of the thousand-year cycle.</p>
        <p>Many residents of the metropolitan area were taking a wait-and-see attitude about attending other New Year's Eve celebrations. As for coping with the storm yesterday, most residents had stocked up on groceries, batteries and other supplies and were prepared for a mini-siege.</p>
        <p>Cut off from the competitive world for a day, some found time to take the children sledding, to go for a walk through the tumultuous privacy of the storm or just to relax at home, taking in the silvery beauty of the snow and its soft ice cream drifts.</p>
        <p>It was the first major storm of the winter in the New York metropolitan region, and by any measure it was a whopper. Its accumulations rivaled New York City's total for all of last winter, 16.3 inches.</p>
        <p>The storm was a new experience for Barnum's Kaleidoscape Circus, which has spent most of its two years on the West Coast. Yesterday, snow piled up on its 60-foot-tall tent in Bryant Park in Midtown Manhattan, threatening to bring down the show. But Tim Holst, the vice president in charge of talent, had a solution: the high-wire act.</p>
        <p>Alex Petrov, 28, thus performed twice -- first, suspended by a rope atop the tent, to push away pockets of snow, and later at a mere 16 feet inside atop an inclined wire with a pole balanced on his head and a lady atop the pole.</p>
        <p>His strategy was the same for both: ''Don't fall down.''</p>
        <p>THE BLIZZARD OF 2000: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
