<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Glass Ceiling</title>
    <meta content="07HERB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6D6163EF934A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Glass Ceiling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column examines'ancient attitudes' that govern why Americans are so unwilling to elect women to high public office (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bad news is that 16 percent of the women in this country and 17 percent of the men say they would not vote for a woman for president.</p>
        <p>The good news is that those percentages are sharply lower than just eight years ago, when 26 percent of American women and nearly 4 out of every 10 men said they could not pull the lever for a woman running for president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bad news is that 16 percent of the women in this country and 17 percent of the men say they would not vote for a woman for president.</p>
        <p>The good news is that those percentages are sharply lower than just eight years ago, when 26 percent of American women and nearly 4 out of every 10 men said they could not pull the lever for a woman running for president.</p>
        <p>We may be in the 21st century, and life may be improving, but a fair number of us still hold some ancient attitudes.</p>
        <p>The presidential race this year is wide open and the most exciting in a long time. But all of the contenders, as usual, are men in suits (or earth-tone sweaters and cowboy boots). Elizabeth Dole spent a minute or two warming up, but she couldn't even rally the wholehearted support of her husband.</p>
        <p>A woman in the White House? What if a war were to break out? What if the economy went south? What in the world would she do?</p>
        <p>Marie Wilson, the president of the Ms. Foundation for Women and one of the creators of Take Our Daughters to Work Day, has had enough of the bogus fears and the stereotyping and the ignorance. She is on a campaign to raise the consciousness of Americans to the leadership potential in that half of the population that is routinely taken less seriously than men.</p>
        <p>She calls her campaign, which has $3 million in financing so far, the White House Project. Her goal is to hasten the day when a woman is elected president, but not just that.</p>
        <p>''What we're trying to do is change the climate in America, to make it friendly toward women's leadership,'' she said. ''As long as there are only one or two women who are seen as potential leaders, the focus will be on gender. We want to permanently increase the number of women who run for office in this country. We want to normalize the whole process so that it is not about one woman at a time.''</p>
        <p>People were calling 1992 the ''year of the woman'' in politics. But now, nearly a decade later, there are only 9 women among the 100 U.S. senators, 56 women in the 435-member House of Representatives and just 3 women among the 50 governors.</p>
        <p>The women who aspire to high public office are often viewed differently than male candidates. A survey commissioned by Deloitte &amp; Touche and released last month found that the public, in general, ''puts more stock in a male candidate's ability to tackle tough issues.''</p>
        <p>Thus, the tougher the job is perceived to be -- and nothing is considered tougher than the presidency -- the less likely it is that a woman will get the nod.</p>
        <p>A report that accompanied the Deloitte &amp; Touche survey said:</p>
        <p>''The results of the poll show that on the surface Americans express widespread support for women in high political office. However, the public's underlying attitudes toward women reveal persistent stereotypes that serve to undermine women's chances for election to high public office.''</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton, who officially announced her run for the Senate yesterday, was asked by a radio reporter a couple of weeks ago about the venomous reaction she elicits in some quarters. She replied: ''I know it's out there and I think some of it is because of the positions that I've taken and maybe a little of it is because I'm a woman taking those positions. And maybe some of it is people don't like my hair style. I don't know what it is.''</p>
        <p>There was a venomous reaction in some quarters to that answer. And maybe it wasn't particularly politic. But, surely, some of the heat Mrs. Clinton is taking is because she's a woman.</p>
        <p>Marie Wilson has been scrupulously nonpartisan in her campaign to promote women for high public office. And she doesn't want voters to vote for women simply because they are women.</p>
        <p>What she wants, she says, is to accelerate the improvement in the public's acceptance of women in high office that has been occurring over the past several years, and to radically expand the number of women seeking top leadership positions.</p>
        <p>She is sponsoring media campaigns, commissioning surveys, conducting mock elections, doing whatever it takes to spread the word that women are as capable as men of running the government of the United States of America.</p>
        <p>IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
