<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weather Outside The Bubble Is Frightful</title>
    <meta content="30GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/30/superbowl/30GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1258999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DF143BF933A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weather Outside The Bubble Is Frightful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Dec. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants practice for playoffs inside stadium bubble because of cold weather; as top-seeded NFC team, Giants have drawn featured, late-afternoon spot in playoff schedule, which could mean very cold weather at kickoff; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his Thursday night monologue, the comedian David Letterman said it was so cold in New York that when the Giants practiced, they ''went into their huddle and didn't come out.''</p>
        <p>In truth, it is so cold the Giants huddle indoors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his Thursday night monologue, the comedian David Letterman said it was so cold in New York that when the Giants practiced, they ''went into their huddle and didn't come out.''</p>
        <p>In truth, it is so cold the Giants huddle indoors.</p>
        <p>It may be winter and the Giants may continually be referred to as a cold-weather team, but they practice inside the Giants Stadium bubble, a facility with an artificial surface enveloped by a plastic, dome-shaped shell. Protected though the team may be during practice, it has not kept the weather from being a frequent topic of conversation among the Giants this week.</p>
        <p>Perhaps influenced by forecasts for stormy weather this weekend, the Giants expect it to be frigid, and maybe snowy, when they play their National Football Conference semifinal game Jan. 7 at Giants Stadium, especially since the game's kickoff is scheduled for 4:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>As the top-seeded N.F.C. team, the Giants have drawn the featured, late-Sunday-afternoon spot in next weekend's playoff schedule, which means the second-half kickoff will come well after sundown. The conventional thinking is that such conditions will give the Giants an edge.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, both teams have to play in the same weather,'' Giants Coach Jim Fassel said today.</p>
        <p>But one of the teams the Giants may face in that game, St. Louis, plays its home games in a dome. Another potential opponent, Tampa Bay, has never won a game played in temperatures that were 40 degrees or below. The other possibility, Philadelphia, plays in similarly wintry weather. But should the Giants get to the conference championship, two other potential opponents, Minnesota and New Orleans, also play in domes.</p>
        <p>Shouldn't the Giants at least be far more familiar with winter conditions than any other N.F.C. playoff team except Philadelphia?</p>
        <p>To that, Fassel had a more revealing answer.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to keep my team focused,'' he said. ''The minute your team thinks they don't have to come ready to play because they are the cold-weather team and the other side isn't, then your team won't come ready to play.''</p>
        <p>So maybe the Giants have not gone into their huddle and refused to come out, but Fassel is circling the wagons to keep out the distractions. A more traditional approach for Giants coaches, most notably Bill Parcells, was to embrace the cold, even plead for snow and messy conditions. In the Parcells years in particular, the Giants were a defensive-minded team with a strong running game that felt a certain invincibility in wintry weather.</p>
        <p>They also practiced outside. Parcells's teams were 5-1 in playoff games at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>The 2000 Giants are also strong defensively with a solid running game. Fassel, however, may be hesitant to make too much of the weather conditions. His 1997 Giants lost a playoff game at Giants Stadium -- a game played in a cold, driving rain.</p>
        <p>''It was cold, and they still won,'' Fassel said of the opponent, the Minnesota Vikings.</p>
        <p>More likely, if Fassel is not outwardly warming to the idea that colder is better, it is probably just one more motivational ploy for him in a season of considerable button-pushing because Fassel knows his Giants already feel an advantage in the chill of winter.</p>
        <p>''We are used to it,'' he said today. ''We live in it.''</p>
        <p>And Fassel understands that his defense, known for its physical play, will just be that much more menacing on a hard or frozen field.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Fassel is concentrating on his team's other advantage at Giants Stadium -- the home crowd.</p>
        <p>''The fans are our biggest advantage,'' Fassel said. ''They were really good last week.''</p>
        <p>Although it is a sensitive subject around Giants Stadium, many people associated with the team believe Giants fans were not very vocal earlier this season -- at least compared with home fans in other cities. It might have been because the Giants' last winning season was 1997 or it might have been because the then-slumbering Giants offense had put the fans to sleep. But some players, coaches and team officials felt the Giants Stadium crowd was impassive.</p>
        <p>The Giants, after winning seven of their first nine games, were also routed in back-to-back games at Giants Stadium in mid-November. That could not have boosted the enthusiasm of Giants fans.</p>
        <p>''All I can say is, last week they really helped us out,'' Fassel said. ''When our offense was starting out on our own 1-yard line, we were trailing in the game and we needed to get it out of there, and they were chanting and cheering for the offense.''</p>
        <p>Quarterback Kerry Collins said: ''I think everyone in the huddle heard that and felt it. As a player, it makes you feel like you can do more. They're with you against the defense.''</p>
        <p>The Giants got out of that poor field position, which became a pivotal sequence in their comeback victory over Jacksonville.</p>
        <p>''It might be cold and nasty -- that's fine,'' Fassel said. ''But our biggest edge is just being home.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>JIM FASSEL gave his players the weekend off, but his coaches will be back in the team's offices Sunday to begin preparations for the next game. If the St. Louis Rams win at New Orleans on Saturday, they will play the Giants on Jan. 7. If the Rams lose, the Giants will play the winner of Sunday's Tampa Bay-Philadelphia game. . . . Fassel wondered Friday if the snow forecast for Saturday would affect Tampa Bay's travel plans to Philadelphia (which it did, moving up the Buccaneers' arrival to Friday night). ''That's tough,'' Fassel said. ''First you work to get in the tournament, then you work just to get into the city.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
