<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Fiction</title>
    <meta content="30SCIFIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1195764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jonas, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkinson, Nalo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bova, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarke, Arthur C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baxter, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Midnight Robber (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Venus (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Light of Other Days, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF1E31F933A05757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerald Jonas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jonas, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerald Jonas reviews following books: Midnight Robber by Nalo Hopkinson; Venus by Ben Bova; and The Light of Other Days by Arthur C Clarke and Stephen Baxter (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nalo Hopkinson's ''Brown Girl in the Ring'' (1998) brought a new sensibility to science fiction. The novel's characters, who spoke a mellifluous Caribbean patois, did not have to travel to other worlds to confront strange life-forms; the spirits of West African religious tradition were all around them in a decaying near-future Toronto, intervening in their everyday lives for good or ill. Without offering any scientific explanation for the witchcraft she evoked, Hopkinson treated the spirit world with the same rigor and respect other writers bring to rocket science or molecular biology.</p>
        <p>Hopkinson's second novel, MIDNIGHT ROBBER (Aspect/Warner, paper, $13.95), succeeds on an even grander scale. When people hear voices on Toussaint -- a planet settled by colonists of Caribbean background -- they know it is the worldwide computer speaking through ''nanotech'' interfaces embedded in everyone's brain. Tan-Tan, the young daughter of Mayor Antonio of Cockpit County, lives a pampered life, surrounded by high-tech toys and doting servants. But the breakdown of her parents' marriage leads to violence, and Tan-Tan ends up with her father on the prison world New Half-Way Tree.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nalo Hopkinson's ''Brown Girl in the Ring'' (1998) brought a new sensibility to science fiction. The novel's characters, who spoke a mellifluous Caribbean patois, did not have to travel to other worlds to confront strange life-forms; the spirits of West African religious tradition were all around them in a decaying near-future Toronto, intervening in their everyday lives for good or ill. Without offering any scientific explanation for the witchcraft she evoked, Hopkinson treated the spirit world with the same rigor and respect other writers bring to rocket science or molecular biology.</p>
        <p>Hopkinson's second novel, MIDNIGHT ROBBER (Aspect/Warner, paper, $13.95), succeeds on an even grander scale. When people hear voices on Toussaint -- a planet settled by colonists of Caribbean background -- they know it is the worldwide computer speaking through ''nanotech'' interfaces embedded in everyone's brain. Tan-Tan, the young daughter of Mayor Antonio of Cockpit County, lives a pampered life, surrounded by high-tech toys and doting servants. But the breakdown of her parents' marriage leads to violence, and Tan-Tan ends up with her father on the prison world New Half-Way Tree.</p>
        <p>Staying alive on this harsh planet depends on learning from the locals, both the convicted criminals who have come before and the indigenous intelligent species -- birdlike creatures who have picked up the humans' ''Anglopatwa'' and who call themselves ''douen people.'' Tan-Tan recognizes the word from the Caribbean-flavored tales recited by her nurse: ''Douens were children who'd died before they had their naming ceremonies.'' Many of the exiles on New Half-Way Tree do in fact treat the natives ''like children.'' Tan-Tan learns better, forming a mutually beneficial bond with the douen called Chichibud.</p>
        <p>Seen through the lens of Caribbean and West African folklore, the ecology of New Half-Way Tree becomes more approachable if no less alien. Tan-Tan's attempt to live like a douen is both funny and touching, but it is her adoption of the persona of the Robber Queen, a figure out of carnival tradition, that drives the narrative toward a deeply satisfying resolution.</p>
        <p>Best of all is the language. I urge readers not to be put off by the vocabulary, syntax and cadence of the opening sentences: ''Oho. Like it starting, oui? Don't be frightened, sweetness; is for the best. I go be with you the whole time. Trust me and let me distract you little bit with one anasi story: It had a woman, you see, a strong hard-back woman with skin like cocoa-tea. She two foot-them tough from hiking through the diable bush.'' The substitution of nominative for possessive pronouns (''she'' for ''her''), the exotic words and compounds that become clear in context, and the lilting, infectious rhythms are no harder to decipher than the scientific and futuristic jargon of more conventional science fiction. Indeed, Hopkinson's narrative voice has a way of getting under the skin, like a nanotech interface. Long after putting the book down, I would catch myself phrasing thoughts in what I came to call Tan-Tan talk. As the narrator herself puts it, ''One look in she eyes, and you fall for she already.''</p>
        <p>VENUS (Tor/Tom Doherty, $24.95), by Ben Bova, takes us to the second planet from the sun -- a ''hellish place'' with surface temperatures ''hot enough to melt aluminum,'' atmospheric pressures high enough to crush spacecraft ''as if they were flimsy cardboard cartons'' and a sky perpetually overcast with ''clouds of sulfuric acid.''</p>
        <p>To the obvious question, ''Why would any sane person want to go there?,'' Bova offers two answers. We learn in the first chapter that an astronaut, Alex Humphries, has died on Venus, trying to discover if the planet's overheated environment holds any lessons for a 21st-century Earth undergoing dire climate changes triggered by greenhouse warming. When Alex's father, Martin, offers a $10 billion prize to anyone who can ''bring back what's left of my son to me,'' his despised second son, Van -- a sickly dilettante known as Runt -- unexpectedly takes up the challenge. Van soon has competition from Lars Fuchs, an asteroid miner with good reason to hate the imperious Martin Humphries.</p>
        <p>The first half of the book is good, if predictable, science fiction, with a thin coating of melodrama -- the race to Venus -- wrapped around a core of information about the forbidding planet. Indeed, the characters synopsize their personal histories for us the way they itemize the facts of planetary science: ''She was my mother! The mother I had never known. The mother who had died giving birth to me. . . . The mother whose drug addiction had saddled me with chronic anemia from birth.'' But when Venus turns out to be even more dangerous than advertised, the relationship between the rivals surprisingly moves to center stage. To survive the physical challenges of Venus, both Van and Lars must let go of the past, and Bova proves himself equal to the task of showing how adversity can temper character in unforeseen ways.</p>
        <p>Arthur C. Clarke, the dean of living science fiction writers, has lent his name in recent years to a number of collaborative projects, with mixed results. In THE LIGHT OF OTHER DAYS (Tor/Tom Doherty, $24.95) the 82-year-old Clarke joins with the British science fiction writer Stephen Baxter to tell the story of an invention that changes the world. By taming anomalies in the structure of space known as ''wormholes,'' scientists working for a technology tycoon, Hiram Patterson, find a way to connect any two points in the universe instantaneously. While no matter can pass through a wormhole, light can. It soon becomes apparent that this is the perfect eavesdropping device. When everyone gains access to easily operated ''WormCams,'' privacy as we know it ends. The only way to hide from WormCam surveillance is to live in total darkness, as some mavericks attempt to do. Others defiantly act as if they have nothing to hide, going naked, copulating in public and so on.</p>
        <p>But as if exploring the psychological and cultural ramifications of life without privacy is not enough of a challenge, Clarke and Baxter keep upping the technological ante. Revealing that WormCams can also see into the past, they invite us to peer over their shoulders to discover how humans evolved and what really happened in Jesus' day. Meanwhile, a giant planetoid nicknamed Wormwood is on a collision course with Earth. And the two sons of Hiram Patterson are locked in a deadly battle with their demoniacal father, who . . . I confess I lost interest in who was doing what to whom before the book was half over. Even in the most imaginative science fiction, sometimes more is less.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
