<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Afghan Drought Inflicts Its Own Misery</title>
    <meta content="16DROU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/16/international/asia/16DROU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1351977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: CLIMATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Nina (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4D81F3FF935A25751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Afghan Drought Inflicts Its Own Misery</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Afghan Drought Inflicts Its Own Misery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monumental task of rebuilding Afghanistan is made even more difficult by drought that has gripped much of southwestern Asia for three years; photos; maps; climate experts say there is chance that worst drought in region in 50 to 100 years may end this winter but they warn that damage to fields, grazing and water supplies will linger for years, hampering efforts to feed millions of refugees and restore Afghanistan's shattered economy; soil and seeds have blown away, vegetation has baked brown, livestock has been slaughtered and wells and rivers have run dry all across borders; unusually warm winters have caused runoffs too early to be of any help; Columbia University analysis links rare variation on La Nina cycle in Pacific Ocean thousands of miles away (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The monumental task of rebuilding Afghanistan after the war has been made far more difficult, experts say, by a problem that would have existed even without the Taliban and Osama bin Laden: the drought that has gripped the country and much of southwestern Asia for three years.</p>
        <p>There is a chance that the drought -- the worst in much of the region for 50 to 100 years -- may end this winter, experts on global climate and agriculture said in interviews over the last week. But they warned that damage to fields, grazing land and water supplies would linger for years, hampering efforts to feed millions of famished refugees and restore Afghanistan's shattered economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The monumental task of rebuilding Afghanistan has been made far more difficult by the drought that has gripped the country for three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The monumental task of rebuilding Afghanistan after the war has been made far more difficult, experts say, by a problem that would have existed even without the Taliban and Osama bin Laden: the drought that has gripped the country and much of southwestern Asia for three years.</p>
        <p>There is a chance that the drought -- the worst in much of the region for 50 to 100 years -- may end this winter, experts on global climate and agriculture said in interviews over the last week. But they warned that damage to fields, grazing land and water supplies would linger for years, hampering efforts to feed millions of famished refugees and restore Afghanistan's shattered economy.</p>
        <p>The damage has not been confined to Afghanistan. Throughout much of southwestern Asia, soil and seeds have blown away, vegetation has baked brown, livestock have been slaughtered and wells and rivers have run dry. Parts of northwestern Iran have had no measurable rainfall in 30 months, and more than 200,000 nomadic herders there have lost their source of income as flocks of sheep and goats have been slaughtered or died. Cities and villages have instituted water rationing.</p>
        <p>The wide reach of the drought means that Afghan refugees heading west to Iran or east to the dry side of Pakistan have found little comfort. At one camp along the Pakistan border, well drillers had to bore a mile deep before reaching the greatly sunken water table, relief workers reported.</p>
        <p>When the war ends, political tensions are bound to rise as Afghanistan rebuilds its northern provinces and begins drawing more water out of the Amu Darya, which forms part of its borders with three former Soviet republics -- Tajikistan, Uzbekistan and Turkmenistan. The river is already taxed to the limit, with every drop of its annual flow of 19 cubic miles of water -- nearly four times the flow of the Colorado -- siphoned by irrigation and for water supplies before reaching the shriveled Aral Sea.</p>
        <p>''In this region, water is more important than money,'' said Dr. Michael H. Glantz, a senior scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., who has studied the Amu Darya.</p>
        <p>But the continuing lack of water and food will pose particularly daunting challenges in Afghanistan itself, where farming is the basis for more than 80 percent of the economy. Even after a generation of warfare and violence, the drought remains ''the single most important factor influencing the Afghan economy,'' Kofi Annan, the United Nations secretary general, said in a report to the General Assembly this month.</p>
        <p>The latest assessments remain bleak, even with the chance that a change in global weather patterns -- which many scientists say is long overdue -- could bring rain and snow to Afghanistan this winter.</p>
        <p>During the wheat-planting season, which started in October and ended two weeks ago, rainfall across the northern provinces, where most wheat is grown, was extremely scant, according to a report released last week by the Foreign Agricultural Service of the Department of Agriculture.</p>
        <p>For the wheat-growing regions, the report said, cumulative precipitation from Oct. 1 to Dec. 12 was only 29 percent of the average for the period. Without rain during planting, seed rarely sprouts in the spring. The lack of rainfall in October and November came as a blow to farmers because September -- just before the planting season -- was tantalizingly wet.</p>
        <p>Even the temperature has conspired against the Afghan farmers. Runoff from melting snows and spring rains supplies most of the region's rivers and irrigation systems, but a string of unusually warm winters melted mountain snows, causing ''ill-timed runoff'' too early to be of any help, the report said. This month, the mountain weather is warmer than usual once again.</p>
        <p>The farmers' problems have been compounded by extensive damage to irrigation canals and pipelines from the continuing warfare.</p>
        <p>If the drought persists, agriculture experts say, a further consequence could be more planting of opium poppies, which tolerate dry conditions far better than wheat.</p>
        <p>By the middle of January, the United Nations, the World Bank and other international institutions hope to create a plan for rebuilding the country. But experts say the drought will prove a lasting hindrance.</p>
        <p>''The deficit in groundwater is so severe that even with a normal or above-normal winter, you'd have to expect a two to three year recovery period,'' said Dr. Matthew A. Barlow, an author of an analysis of the drought by the International Research Institute for Climate Prediction at Columbia University. ''In some instances,'' he added, ''that would be a little on the optimistic side.''</p>
        <p>The report (available online at http://iri.columbia.edu) says the drought may be linked to unusual conditions thousands of miles away: raised temperatures in the western Pacific and frequent rainstorms over the Indian Ocean. Indirectly, the scientists say, these changes appear to be preventing winter storms from sweeping east out of the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>A preliminary analysis by the Columbia scientists suggests that the last severe drought in the region, from 1970 to 1972, occurred when similar ocean conditions developed. That dry spell, State Department experts say, helped topple a previous Afghan government, that of the former king, Mohammad Zahir Shah, in 1973.</p>
        <p>The ocean condition is a rare variation on La Niña, part of a regular cycle of Pacific warming and cooling episodes that can influence weather patterns around the world. In a typical La Niña year, unusually cool water covers the eastern Pacific along the Equator, contrasting with warm water to the west. For the last several years, the Pacific has been locked in La Niña conditions, but the western waters have been particularly warm.</p>
        <p>Many scientists say the Pacific is overdue for a shift back to the opposite pattern, called El Niño, in which warm water spreads east toward South America. But that has not happened yet, and La Niña could hang on for another winter.</p>
        <p>If that happens and the Columbia scientists are right, Afghanistan's plight could go on even longer. Still, they say more research will be required to confirm the relationship between La Niña and the drought.</p>
        <p>Looking ahead, climate experts said an important part of any rebuilding of Afghanistan would be prompt re-establishment of basic, regular measurements of precipitation and other weather conditions. No local weather data have been collected for several years, and without a long-term record it is difficult to spot trends that might indicate a return of drought conditions, said Dr. Barlow at Columbia.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Dr. Barlow said, researchers hope to be able to use close monitoring of telltale shifts in global patterns to predict future severe droughts in the region and help governments and relief agencies gird for battle.</p>
        <p>The same feature of the drought that made it so destructive -- its vast size -- also raises scientists' hopes that the forces that conspired to create it can be discerned.</p>
        <p>''The good thing about its size is that it's probably more than just a chance occurrence,'' Dr. Barlow said. ''The larger scale something is, the more likely it is that we can understand and then predict it.''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: CLIMATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
