<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blown Away The Wrong Way By Paradise</title>
    <meta content="PARADI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/04/travel/PARADISE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1267994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bahama Islands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freedman, Samuel G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/The Bahamas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DF113FF937A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blown Away The Wrong Way By Paradise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freedman, Samuel G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Samuel G Freedman travel essay on unexpectedly cold and windy weather during December vacation on Paradise Island in the Bahamas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE were lying awake on the first night of our Christmas beach vacation, listening to the wind caterwauling outside our windows, when my wife rolled over in bed to face me and ask, ''Did you notice that nobody has a tan?'' I had to admit the thought had already occurred to me. Now we had to figure out how to keep the truth from our children, blissfully asleep, expecting a full week of warming sun and gentle surf.</p>
        <p>I had promised them this trip to the Bahamas resort called Atlantis, an extravagance on our budget, as compensation for our one summer vacation on Long Island, 10 days of dreary skies and autumnal winds in Montauk. With its vast stretch of beach and its array of pools and water slides, with its tanks of turtles and sharks and stingrays, even with its hilariously garish architecture, Atlantis promised to banish the memory of all those drizzly afternoons spent in the East Hampton Library, a pleasant enough place but not exactly a tourist destination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE were lying awake on the first night of our Christmas beach vacation, listening to the wind caterwauling outside our windows, when my wife rolled over in bed to face me and ask, ''Did you notice that nobody has a tan?'' I had to admit the thought had already occurred to me. Now we had to figure out how to keep the truth from our children, blissfully asleep, expecting a full week of warming sun and gentle surf.</p>
        <p>I had promised them this trip to the Bahamas resort called Atlantis, an extravagance on our budget, as compensation for our one summer vacation on Long Island, 10 days of dreary skies and autumnal winds in Montauk. With its vast stretch of beach and its array of pools and water slides, with its tanks of turtles and sharks and stingrays, even with its hilariously garish architecture, Atlantis promised to banish the memory of all those drizzly afternoons spent in the East Hampton Library, a pleasant enough place but not exactly a tourist destination.</p>
        <p>We had landed in Paradise Island 12 hours earlier in a steady rain and reached  our hotel along streets flooded by some earlier deluge, the fellow passengers on our bus watching in funereal silence as the shoppers in downtown Nassau perched like seabirds on high chunks of pavement. Along the shore at Atlantis, an eastern wind snapped the red flag warning of rough waters.</p>
        <p>''They're called the Christmas winds,'' said my wife, Cynthia, who had lived for three years in the Virgin Islands long before we met and is my personal authority on all matters tropical. During a brief break in the rain, we tiptoed with our children, Aaron, 8,  and Sarah, 6, into four different pools, each  colder than the last, before letting them into the more tepid water of an ocean-fed lagoon. On a nearby jetty, a Bahamian lifeguard hunched with knees to chest for warmth. They were Christmas winds all right, the kind I remembered howling off Lake Michigan when I was a young reporter in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Until this moment, I had assumed seasons in the Bahamas consisted only of wet or dry, warm or hot. Literally speaking, of course, we weren't in the tropics or even in the Caribbean. The border for both runs roughly along Cuba, while Paradise Island sits almost due east of Miami.</p>
        <p>Still, Cynthia and I had done our homework before buying our nonrefundable tickets. The typical late-December day in Paradise Island had highs well into the 70's, and the rainfall for the entire month came to less than two inches.</p>
        <p>So we had to assume our first day was an anomaly, soon to be swept away by the Gulf Stream. Indeed we awoke that next morning to find the sun cracking apart the overcast. When I stepped onto our sixth-floor terrace to admire the view, though, I could feel the wind unabated. A few palm trees near the beach had been decapitated overnight. A freighter had moored on the horizon, a sign that seas were even higher in the open ocean. The flagpole visible at the Sheraton next door bore a red banner with a single diagonal white stripe.</p>
        <p>''Storm warning,'' Cynthia told me. We dialed the number for the local weather. ''Small-craft advisory,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Still, we gamely tugged on our swimsuits and padded through the lobby toward the water. We passed guests in running suits and fleece pullovers, families in jeans and sweatshirts playing Scrabble. We picked up a list of daily events. It included a special category: Windy Day Activities. Ignoring them, we let Aaron and Sarah snorkel again in the lagoon and noticed that the lifeguard today was wearing a down jacket.</p>
        <p>And that gave Cynthia her brainstorm. It was Boxing Day, celebrated in the Bahamas as a holiday in the British tradition, but Cynthia finally found a dive shop that was open and had wet suits, knees to neck to elbows, in children's sizes. We tried out one of the Atlantis water slides. Aaron careered down it inured to the chill; I followed, wincing every time the slide deposited me neck-deep in a cold pool.</p>
        <p>Maybe on an 80-degree day the plunge would have refreshed me. With strong winds on a sunless day in the 60's, I soon felt my toes and fingertips going numb, the sensation I always associated with fasting on Yom Kippur. I just couldn't imagine what I was supposed to be repenting for now, except the noble intention of making up to my children for our last fiasco of a vacation.</p>
        <p>We returned to the room, me shivering and Cynthia smug. Hardly anyone besides another set of kids with wet suits had gone into the water deeper than their shins. Toward evening, Cynthia found herself sharing an elevator with a couple. ''You laughed at me when I packed this,'' the husband said, indicating his corduroy shirt. ''Next time I go to the Bahamas, remind me to bring long underwear.''</p>
        <p>THE next two days brought respite and delusion. The winds lulled, the sky cleared, the temperatures reached into the mid-70's, comfortable albeit still below average. We hiked in our bathing suits to a secluded cove; we broke out the sunscreen; we sweated when we jogged. So that night, when the weather news turned ominous, I discounted every warning. Yes, CNN was predicting heavy snow two days later in New York. Yes, the Miami station was forecasting lows in the 40's, giving the wind-chill factor for the night of the Orange Bowl Parade. Yes, Cynthia said after calling the airline, we could get a flight back to New York just before the storm if we left Atlantis one day early. I refused. With their wet suits, Aaron and Sarah could keep swimming. If Manhattan got buried, we would gloat.</p>
        <p>The morning of Dec. 30, Snow Day in New York, our wind switched violently to the northwest. Gray clouds piled together. The temperature overnight had dropped into the 50's. And now, with La Guardia Airport closed, we would have to pay for two more days in Atlantis before we could get another flight home.</p>
        <p>That afternoon, I consented to Aaron's wish that we ascend Atlantis's imitation Maya temple and from its summit take a serpentine interior water slide. As we climbed, I heard a soca band at poolside playing a cover of ''Margaritaville'' for several hundred empty chaise longues. I listened to two resort workers, fully clothed and wearing gloves, debating whether the temperature that night might hit zero Celsius. At the highest platform of the ersatz pyramid, with the wind turning my bare torso into so much goose flesh, I thought less of sultry Chichén Itzá than the bare crown of Spruce Peak at Stowe, where you at least got to wear a wool blanket on the chairlift.</p>
        <p>Aaron shoved off first, and as I trailed him through the dark twists I could hear him shrieking in delight. For me, just being protected from the elements qualified as a facsimile of warmth. At the bottom of the slide, rudely exposed to the elements again, Aaron declared, ''Let's go again.'' Why not, I figured, my nose hadn't stopped running all week anyway. Three more times, we repeated our trudge up the temple and our race down.</p>
        <p>Then we hurled ourselves into a hot tub, the only crowded place at Atlantis this day except for the casino, and promised to take the slide even more times the next day and the one after that, our last. Cynthia and Sarah joined us there in the broth, with Sarah exulting about the really big fish she had spotted while snorkeling.</p>
        <p>I knew a few things by now. I would never again trust the Christmas weather anywhere north of San Juan. I would not expect sun and warmth on a vacation unless, with my luck, it was a ski trip. But between two wet suits and a juvenile heedlessness of climate, Aaron and Sarah had thrived so much that they were griping about going home. Which was enough to salvage the vacation for me.</p>
        <p>So when I returned our beach towels on the final afternoon and an attendant said, ''You got your tan, mon,'' I smiled and nodded even though I knew whatever color I had was windburn.</p>
        <p>SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN is a professor of journalism at Columbia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN is a professor of journalism at Columbia.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
