<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Now, Government Is the Solution, Not the Problem</title>
    <meta content="30TONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/30/weekinreview/30TONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Economic Policy Institute</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Economic Policy Institute</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lake, Celinda</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lake, Celinda</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DA173DF933A0575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Now, Government Is the Solution, Not the Problem</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Now, Government Is the Solution, Not the Problem</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government is now seen the solution, not the problem; after 20 years of exulting in power of private sector, in deregulation, tax cuts and reining in Washington bureaucrats, Republicans and Democrats alike are talking about muscular new role for government in aftermath of Sept 11 terrorist attacks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUDDENLY, the political language of a generation looks dated: Nobody wants to get the government off their backs. Nobody really wants to hear that the era of big government is over.</p>
        <p>After 20 years of exulting in the power of the private sector, in deregulation, tax cuts and reining in the Washington bureaucrats, Republicans and Democrats alike are talking about a muscular new role for government in the aftermath of the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks. They are bailing out the airlines, establishing a new Office of Homeland Security, passing a big new aid package to rebuild the areas devastated by the attacks and pondering an even bigger effort to stimulate an ailing economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suddenly, the political language of a generation looks dated: Nobody wants to get the government off their backs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUDDENLY, the political language of a generation looks dated: Nobody wants to get the government off their backs. Nobody really wants to hear that the era of big government is over.</p>
        <p>After 20 years of exulting in the power of the private sector, in deregulation, tax cuts and reining in the Washington bureaucrats, Republicans and Democrats alike are talking about a muscular new role for government in the aftermath of the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks. They are bailing out the airlines, establishing a new Office of Homeland Security, passing a big new aid package to rebuild the areas devastated by the attacks and pondering an even bigger effort to stimulate an ailing economy.</p>
        <p>The public, pollsters say, expects nothing less. Americans' attitudes toward government are warming, part of a general rallying around the flag, the president, even institutions like the news media in the past few weeks. ''This is the most collective mood we've seen in America for a long time,'' said Celinda Lake, a Democratic pollster. ''And it's coming off one of the most individualistic eras in American history.''</p>
        <p>Liberals see it as the nation's inevitable turn to government in a time of need. But they hope the crisis also brings a more fundamental recognition of the limits of the old ideology, which scorned public workers and revered the rugged dot-com individualists of the new economy.</p>
        <p>''When the chips are down, where do we turn?'' wrote Jeff Faux, president of the liberal Economic Policy Institute, in a recent column in The American Prospect. ''To the government's firefighters, police officers, rescue teams. To the nonprofit sector's blood banks and shelters. And to big government's Army, Navy and Air Force.''</p>
        <p>Representative David Obey, the veteran Wisconsin Democrat and senior member of the Appropriations Committee, said he hoped that people ''rethink all this rhetoric about the role of government.'' For example, he said, ''To me there's no question that we've had under-investment by the government for a lot of years in everything from airport security to security on the rails and highways.''</p>
        <p>Some, mindful of the risk of bioterrorism, add the nation's public health system to the list of the under-financed. Still others, looking at the approach of recession, put health insurance and unemployment benefits on the list. Fiscal discipline, in short, is no longer the most transcendent value on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Conservatives, some still reeling from the sudden shift in political terrain, see government's resurgence as an aberration -- but one that liberals will try to prolong.</p>
        <p>''If the question is, will the left use this as an excuse to try to go back to the same old agenda of bigger, slower bureaucracies that don't deliver much, yes,'' said Newt Gingrich, the former speaker of the House.</p>
        <p>Clearly, conservatives are alarmed at the implications for spending, which they believed had finally been restrained in a lasting way by President Bush's tax cut on one side, and by the bipartisan pledges to protect the Social Security surplus on the other.</p>
        <p>''Four weeks ago, the next 10 years of spending were known,'' said Grover G. Norquist, the conservative strategist who heads Americans for Tax Reform. ''There was a fixed number in a way there hadn't been for decades.'' Nothing, he added, looks quite so settled now -- particularly since the pressures to spend are bipartisan.</p>
        <p>Nobody knows how long this climate will last. A new Washington Post poll found that 64 percent of Americans now say they trust the federal government to do the right thing ''nearly always'' or ''most of the time'' -- the highest level of trust in government since 1966. That confidence level was double what it was a year ago.</p>
        <p>But the erosion of trust in government, which laid the groundwork for the Reagan revolution and the Democratic reaction of the Clinton years, is a long-standing trend. Most analysts see its roots in the Vietnam War, Watergate and the upheaval of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>The public's trust in government increased during the war in the Persian Gulf, but those gains quickly dissipated, noted Stanley B. Greenberg, a Democratic pollster.</p>
        <p>The public also rallied around its government after the Oklahoma City bombing in 1995. Bruce Reed, former domestic policy adviser in the Clinton administration, said: ''It helped put a stop to the virulent anti-government rhetoric that was popular at the time. And that's never come back in the same way.''</p>
        <p>MANY analysts say this crisis will have a far more profound effect. Elizabeth Cobbs Hoffman, a history professor at San Diego State University and the author of ''All You Need Is Love: The Peace Corps and the Spirit of the 1960's,'' argued that what was undermined in the 60's was not just public trust but also the public's confidence in ''the morality and rightness of America's mission in the world.'' The events of Sept. 11, and the surge of patriotism that followed, have done much to restore that, she argued.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the combination of threats to national security and an imminent recession means ''the American public feels it needs the federal government much more than they have in a long time,'' said Andrew Kohut, the director of the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press.</p>
        <p>Alan Brinkley, a history professor at Columbia University and the author of ''The End of Reform: New Deal Liberalism in Recession and War,'' noted, ''What sustained the idea of a large and active government for so long was first the Depression, then the war, and then the cold war -- all things that really did require a government response to do things the private sector simply could not do.''</p>
        <p>Since the end of the cold war, many have argued that the rationale for a strong presidency -- and a strong federal government -- had been diminished. But with Washington back on war footing, Mr. Brinkley said, ''that can't help but affect the attitudes toward government.</p>
        <p>There is an irony here: That a president who came to office with a promise of huge tax cuts, partial privatization of Social Security and Medicare, and a conservative conviction that ''it's not the government's money,'' will now preside over a major new crisis  mobilization. Last week, he was sending National Guardsmen into airports and announcing a substantial new federal role in airport security.</p>
        <p>President Bush could well end up signing economic stimulus legislation that includes not just the tax cuts the conservatives envision, but substantial new safety net programs that the Democrats will insist on. And his attorney general has already begun pushing for new anti-terrorism legislation that many conservatives join liberals in asserting is far too great a government intrusion into Americans' privacy.</p>
        <p>''There is a little of the Nixon-to-China phenomenon,'' said Ms. Lake, the pollster. ''As long as it's under Republican watch, government can get bigger faster because the natural critics are silent.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps. But last week, Mr. Norquist was already keeping watch for profligate lawmakers on Capitol Hill. ''There's something a little obscene about using this attack on America to get your favorite pork-barrel program through,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
