<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LOCATION: EVERYWHERE; Together, in Sickness and in Health</title>
    <meta content="06INTROT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="67" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/06/magazine/06INTRO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1290883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="1. CASE STUDY: GLOBALIZATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ebola Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Angier, Natalie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Colds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Ebola Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Infections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DA1F39F935A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LOCATION: EVERYWHERE; Together, in Sickness and in Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Natalie Angier</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Angier, Natalie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Natalie Angier reports on 'globalization' of illness and diseases, noting that nowadays diseases as common as the cold and rare as Ebola are circling the globe with near telephone speed, making long-distance connections and intercontinental infections almost as if by satellite; observes that microbes travel by land, sea, air, nose, blows, glove, love, sewage, steerage, rat packs, hat racks, uncooked burritos, overlooked mosquitos; notes every day brings fresh evidence of how intimate are links that lash together nations, peoples, bodies, species (L) (Special issue of Magazine, The Cure Hunters)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not long ago, my older brother, Joe, flew in from Los Angeles for a family gathering at my home outside Washington, looking paler than a dieting vampire and muttering that he might be ''coming down with something.'' The rest of us eyed him warily, washed our hands compulsively and broke out the echinacea and vitamin C.</p>
        <p>By the time my brother-in-law, Dave, had flown back to Oregon, he was too sick to return to work. My daughter and I also took to bed for a day or two, but then gamely pulled ourselves together to attend a big party at my mother's apartment in Manhattan -- after which we collapsed once more in fevered, achy near-delirium. Later my mother told me that party guests from two different states had called to complain that I had given them some sort of ''bug.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not long ago, my older brother, Joe, flew in from Los Angeles for a family gathering at my home outside Washington, looking paler than a dieting vampire and muttering that he might be ''coming down with something.'' The rest of us eyed him warily, washed our hands compulsively and broke out the echinacea and vitamin C.</p>
        <p>By the time my brother-in-law, Dave, had flown back to Oregon, he was too sick to return to work. My daughter and I also took to bed for a day or two, but then gamely pulled ourselves together to attend a big party at my mother's apartment in Manhattan -- after which we collapsed once more in fevered, achy near-delirium. Later my mother told me that party guests from two different states had called to complain that I had given them some sort of ''bug.''</p>
        <p>And so from one humble plucking of the kinship bond came an Attila-scale distribution of the season's flu virus, itself a strain that most likely had its genesis in Asia. My story is hardly unusual, and that is exactly my point. Today, diseases as common as the cold and as rare as Ebola are circling the globe with near telephonic speed, making long-distance connections and intercontinental infections almost as if by satellite. You needn't even bother to reach out and touch someone. If you live, if you're homeothermic biomass, you will be reached and touched. Microbes are, after all, members of the most ancient, zealous and Darwinically gilded 24-7 delivery consortium. They travel by land, sea, air, nose, blows, glove, love, sewage, steerage, rat backs, hat racks, uncooked burritos, overlooked mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>And, oh, how they love the global village. How readily, for microbes, that village feels like home. Whether it's the recent outbreak of cholera in Buenos Aires, after years during which Latin America was free of the disease, or the debut in the emergency rooms of Manhattan of an African-born illness like West Nile fever, the globalization of disease is an unavoidable byproduct of the high holy multicultural hustle. And though microbes have always had the traveling bug, in centuries past, it at least took a few weeks or months for sailors to deliver a ship of rats bearing fleas with bubonic-plague bacteria from the Orient to Europe. Nowadays, a mosquito infested with the malaria parasite can be buzzing in Ghana at dawn and dining on an airport employee in Boston by cocktail hour.</p>
        <p>Every day brings fresh evidence of how intimate are the links that lash together nations, peoples, bodies, species. One land's meat, for example, seems every land's poison, as hapless Britain has struggled with a double whammy on its livestock. Since 1988, nearly 180,000 cases of bovine spongiform encephalopathy -- aka mad cow disease -- have been reported in British cattle, along with several thousand cases elsewhere in Europe, raising fears that we're eating tainted hamburgers capable of delivering into our brains the deadly agent of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, and prompting the Department of Agriculture to ban animal protein products from Europe. Vegetarianism has beckoned even more brightly in the last few weeks with the televised images of macabre mass barbecues, as Britain, the Netherlands and a number of other countries have struggled to combat the recent outbreak of foot-and-mouth disease among their livestock. Nearly five million animals in Britain and hundreds of thousands elsewhere in Europe have been killed or await execution, resulting in meat, dairy and leather shortages worldwide, not to mention the tanning of the political hide of the British prime minister, Tony Blair.</p>
        <p>''The globalization of health and disease is an incontrovertible fact,'' said Christopher J. Murray, a policy director with the World Health Organization in Geneva and an author of an influential report, ''The Global Burden of Disease.'' ''The travel and interaction between continents, and the exchange of people, animals, animal products, food products, disease vectors, are all vastly greater than in the past, and so is the potential for pathogens to move quickly from one place to another.''</p>
        <p>''Today I can be in a place like Mecca, where there's an outbreak of meningitis, and I would not know I was sick with it until I got home,'' said David L. Heymann, executive director in charge of communicable diseases at the World Health Organization in Geneva. ''And think of all the people I'd expose on my trip back.'' Especially given the robustly recycled vaporous substance that passes for air in a modern jetliner.</p>
        <p>The United States can give as well as it gets. In 1998, nearly 1,500 athletes from around the world competed in a triathlon in Springfield, Ill., where they were exposed during the swim portion of the event to leptospirosis bacteria, which can cause fever, chills, jaundice, meningitis and kidney failure. Of these, 72 sought medical attention, and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention spent many weeks tracking down all the participants to warn them of possible symptoms and to seek immediate treatment should they arise, before permanent organ damage set in. Moreover, there was some risk of infected people releasing leptospirosis microbes into local water supplies through urination, further dispensing America's inadvertent gift to the spirit of international competition. ''There's no epidemic in even the smallest corner of the globe that the world can afford to ignore,'' said Jacquelyn C. Campbell, a professor at Johns Hopkins School of Nursing and a former member of the Institute of Medicine's Board on Global Health. ''We're so interconnected that an isolationist's perspective is no longer an option.''</p>
        <p>A true understanding of that growing interconnectedness has to include the developing world, where most of the people on the planet live and where infectious diseases account for almost half the deaths each year. Half of those deaths can be attributed to three ''pedestrian'' yet persistently devastating diseases: malaria, H.I.V./AIDS and tuberculosis. Malaria kills more than one million people annually, the overwhelming majority of them children in sub-Saharan Africa. Many millions of other people living in more than 90 countries suffer from malaria, sometimes contracting it repeatedly year after year. Though they don't die of the disease, the debility and cost are enormous. By one estimate, Africa's gross domestic product would be $100 billion greater today than it is if malaria had been eliminated. And the warming global climate is carrying those malaria-bearing mosquitoes north. So is the 2:43 out of Kinshasa: planes landing in Charles de Gaulle Airport have recently been found to be carrying more than a few nonpaying passengers, leading European airlines to step up their preflight extermination efforts.</p>
        <p>Sub-Saharan Africa also has taken the most brutal jackhammering from the AIDS epidemic. Of the 35 million people living with H.I.V. or AIDS in the world, 25 million are in sub-Saharan Africa. Of the 5.4 million people who are newly infected with the virus each year, 4 million live in sub-Saharan Africa. Helen Epstein, a former instructor at Makerere University School of Medicine in Uganda, wrote recently in The New York Review of Books that ''the AIDS epidemic in Africa may turn out to be the worst health crisis in the history of the human race.'' Thanks to the effectiveness of new drug regimens, Westerners have developed the false sense that AIDS is no longer a lethal disease. But apart from the fact that nobody knows how long patients on the new drug regimens will survive before the virus finally outmutates the current armamentarium, these drugs are expensive and difficult to take.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the AIDS epidemic in Africa is unlikely to remain confined to Africa: the strains of H.I.V. running rampant there, if left unchecked, are sure to gain novel malevolence that would allow them to spread elsewhere and overwhelm whatever resources we have devoted to defeating our Western-bred strains. And keep in mind that other highly populous countries like China and India are just beginning to feel the brunt of the disease. There's a perversely poetic loopiness at work: a disease that presumably had its origins in Africa made its first angry mark in America, then exploded in Africa, and is now moving onward, outward and back again, cat's-cradle style. It's not ''Africa's'' health crisis alone.</p>
        <p>The only sane response to the world's AIDS crisis remains prevention -- a response that hardly attracts an ounce of attention, let alone pounds, dollars or rubles. Last year, a total of $165 million from all sources was devoted to AIDS prevention in sub-Saharan Africa, compared with the $2.5 billion estimated as necessary to do even a perfunctory job. ''When you see $9billion going into the response to Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, where you would expect a few hundred or maybe a few thousand cases at the most, while other, far greater public health problems are seriously neglected, we have to ask if we're getting the bang for our health bucks that we ought to get,'' said Joshua Lederberg, a Nobel-laureate infectious-disease expert at Rockefeller University. Don't look to the United States to swoop in and fix it: of the top 20 industrialized nations, the United States devotes the smallest percentage of its gross domestic product to battling these international epidemics.</p>
        <p>But disease isn't the only thing moving around the globe with increasing speed, binding far-flung countries together in a mutual medical destiny. Medicines and methods of treatment are also part of the worldwide exchange. Pharmaceutical companies in the United States and Europe export a vast array of medications -- from penicillin to protease inhibitors -- to the developing world. And by seeking out alternative, local solutions from around the world, those companies, along with the best-endowed Western hospitals and research facilities, are beginning to level the balance of trade.</p>
        <p>Where their citizens' health is concerned, some developing nations clearly have the edge over us on doing much more at fire-sale prices. In Chile, for example, the per-capita income today is about $5,000, the same as it was in the United States in the year 1900. But while the average life expectancy in our country a century ago was 47, in Chile today it is 76 -- pretty much the same as ours is now. And while Cuba remains an economic backwater, Castro's commitment to universal health care has paid off: the infant mortality rate there is the lowest by far in Latin America. (Meanwhile, the United States, which has the finest available health care, was ranked 54th by the World Health Organization in terms of equality of access.) Whatever our squeamishness over methodology, we have a lot to learn from these countries and from others that have demonstrated successes in treating disease with a fraction of our resources.</p>
        <p>We also have a lot to learn about the potential medical applications of herbs and extracts native to obscure corners of the continents. Seeking them out and bringing them back to the lab for study -- bioprospecting, as these hunting expeditions have come to be known -- has become a big business unto itself, incorporating the quest not only for flora, fauna and fungi, but even for exotic human genes to which biotech companies now routinely purchase the rights in hopes they will yield some insight, and some profit.</p>
        <p>Globalization has also underscored a potentially universal source of human strength: in the tribe. We are clansfolk at heart, hardly past the mutual flea-plucking stage, and evolved to traffic comfortably with a few scores of people at best. As a result, global health care workers have found that the most effective health programs are local and inclusive. For example, says Patricia L. Rosenfield of the Carnegie Corporation in New York and a former member of the Board on Global Health, ''Thailand has one of the most effective AIDS programs in the world because they take the power of the community seriously.'' Their education efforts are concentrated locally on individual villages, schools, groups of prostitutes. The lesson of ''think global, nag local'' can work here too: when doctors in Minnesota took the time to contact families whose children need follow-up booster shots, the overall effectiveness of the local vaccination program rose markedly. And tuberculosis outbreaks in both Africa and New York have been tamed by keeping an eye on infected people and ensuring that they take their medications every day.</p>
        <p>As a number of articles in this issue make clear, the world is moving beyond the old polarities of ancient and modern, global and vernacular, high-tech and no-tech. We're not just mixing our microbes; we're hybridizing our medical traditions. Elisabeth Rosenthal describes a promising treatment being used at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center that was developed by a folk healer in rural China. Matthew Steinglass visits a tribal doctor in South Africa who dispenses Western analgesics along with his herbal potions. In an article about a family of noble Italian lineage whose members suffer from an exceedingly rare genetic disease called fatal familial insomnia, D.T. Max describes the insights that the affliction has yielded into the general nature of prions, rogue proteins believed to be responsible for a number of brain disorders, mad cow disease among them.</p>
        <p>It's not always easy to admit that other tribes are more enlightened than we are. America refuses to adopt the metric system, by gum, and we're way behind most countries of the world when it comes to the promotion and acceptance of the finest form of disease prevention known to medicine -- breast-feeding. Sara Corbett describes the outrage and disgust that a Delaware woman elicits because she nurses her 4-year-old twins, though in many traditional societies breast-feeding children of 4, 5, 6 years of age is considered a sign of superlative mothering. And despite the sustained scoffery of American doctors, a number of ''folk'' remedies may be every bit as worthy as their mainstream pharmaco-counterparts, as Sheryl Gay Stolberg makes clear in her discussion of herbs like black cohosh, widely used in Europe but not here, to treat the symptoms of menopause.</p>
        <p>In the end, then, the great global agora of medicine is all about barter: buying, selling, swapping, titting, tatting, seducing and swindling. We import a malign parasite here, we export a rotten fast-food franchise there. Merck donates medicines for river blindness to Africa. Americans fly to Thailand for discount plastic surgery. Through the Internet, too, we've become an obligate if virtual superorganism, busy bees without borders, compulsively foraging through a billion sites for sensation, guidance, palliatives or cures for lupus, chronic fatigue syndrome, nailbiting, insomnia, narcissism.</p>
        <p>There is something unnerving about the distending volume of health information ricocheting through our cyberhive, much of it unexpurgated, unedited and unconfirmed. At the same time, there is something glorious -- O.K., I'll call it miraculous -- about anybody anywhere having free, instant computer access to Medline and all the papers published in thousands of medical journals around the world. Our modems have become medical devices, and as fast as microbes can move nowadays, ideas, Google willing, will always outrun them.</p>
        <p>1. CASE STUDY: GLOBALIZATION Natalie Angier writes about science for The New York Times. Her latest book is ''Woman: An Intimate Geography.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Natalie Angier writes about science for The New York Times. Her latest book is ''Woman: An Intimate Geography.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
