<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Wildlife, Some Reasons to Celebrate, and to Join the Party</title>
    <meta content="20WILD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dolphins and Porpoises</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D8103AF933A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Wildlife, Some Reasons to Celebrate, and to Join the Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DeMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on increasing numbers of shore birds, birthing dolphins and other marine life that can be seen along New Jersey shores; photos (Special Issue: Summer in New Jersey) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LARGE, brown pelicans can often be seen gliding above the breakers just offshore or perched on wooden pilings. Atlantic bottlenose dolphins can be spotted giving birth just off the beach, and even, on rare occasions, a manatee can be seen swimming along the shore.</p>
        <p>Although such sights were always common in Florida or South Carolina, they are increasingly common close to home. Because of the dynamics of nature, the variety of animal life visible off the New Jersey coast is always changing. Some of the reasons are known. In other cases, they remain a mystery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LARGE, brown pelicans can often be seen gliding above the breakers just offshore or perched on wooden pilings. Atlantic bottlenose dolphins can be spotted giving birth just off the beach, and even, on rare occasions, a manatee can be seen swimming along the shore.</p>
        <p>Although such sights were always common in Florida or South Carolina, they are increasingly common close to home. Because of the dynamics of nature, the variety of animal life visible off the New Jersey coast is always changing. Some of the reasons are known. In other cases, they remain a mystery.</p>
        <p>For the most part, the number of species that can be seen -- or, in some cases, caught -- is increasing. A few are dwindling or in trouble. These ebbs and flows are almost  always as a result of something done by human beings.</p>
        <p>''As people, we almost always do what is right for us, often without regard to other living things,'' said Peter Dunne, vice president of the New Jersey Audubon Society. ''But we are incredibly lucky to be alive now and not 100 years ago. Environmentalists often press the gloom and doom button, but in reality, we have a great deal to celebrate.</p>
        <p>''I never take a walk in southern New Jersey without seeing birds that would have been extremely rare 100 years ago,'' he added. ''This is mecca on the bird-watching circuit, which is why I live here.''</p>
        <p>Brown pelicans have been seen along the Jersey Shore in recent years, when in the past they never came farther north than North Carolina, said Dave Jenkins, principal zoologist with the New Jersey Division of Fish and Wildlife's Endangered and Nongame Species Program. But they still do not nest here and probably never will because the summer season is too short. Why the pelicans have ventured to New Jersey remains a mystery.</p>
        <p>''It could be the improvement in water quality or it could be the increase in the availability of fish for food,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Other birds, like piping plovers, herons and egrets, which were decimated at the turn of the century, have returned because hunting has been banned and their nesting habitats are being protected.</p>
        <p>''The first piping plover I ever saw was on my grandmother's hat -- the whole stuffed bird just perched there,'' Mr. Dunne said. ''The entire Northeast was environmentally pauperized by unregulated hunting and egg collecting.''</p>
        <p>Other birds, like the least and common terns and black skimmers, are not faring as well, probably because of development and human disturbance, Mr. Jenkins said.</p>
        <p>A large number of nonprofit organizations and for-profit companies are available to show off the variety of animal life at the shore. Following are examples of activities available this summer. Additional information can be obtained from the county tourism offices in Monmouth, (732) 431-7476; Ocean, (800) 365-6933; Atlantic, (888) 228-4748; and Cape May, (800) 227-2297.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Audubon Society conducts walks throughout the spring, summer and fall, primarily in southern New Jersey, but elsewhere in the state as well.</p>
        <p>''There is never a walk from March to November that we do not see a Forster's tern,'' Mr. Dunne said. ''That would have been really rare 100 years ago.''</p>
        <p>Bald eagles, which were reduced to one failing pair in 1975, mostly because of the use of pesticides, are making a comeback and there are now 26 pairs in the state. The birds are the last to recover from DDT and other pesticides that accumulate in the birds' fat layers and soften the eggshells.</p>
        <p>Glossy ibis and black vultures, not found here in the past, have expanded their territories and are now common in New Jersey. So are cardinals, cattle and mockingbirds.</p>
        <p>The state Audubon Society can be reached at (609) 861-0700.</p>
        <p>With the help of a network of volunteers, the Marine Mammal Stranding Center in Brigantine rescues injured and abandoned animals from the beach and also maintains a facility where seals and other recuperating animals can be viewed.</p>
        <p>''What people should look for this summer from the beach is birthing dolphins,'' said Robert Schoelkopf, director of the center. ''Bottlenose dolphins can be seen close to shore. When you see them circling, those are the midwives that are there to help get the baby to the surface for its first breath of air.''</p>
        <p>People are also more aware of the need to protect sea turtles, which can range from 5 to 800 pounds, when they appear off the coast or in the back bays.</p>
        <p>''It may be because of the cleaner water but it is definitely also because of the warming climate,'' Mr. Schoelkopf said. ''The air temperature is warmer and these animals are air breathers.''</p>
        <p>In the winter, more seals of all types are being seen, including the Arctic species of harp, gray and hooded seals, as well as the harbor seal, which is a temperate-climate animal that has always been in New Jersey. The increase in numbers could be because of overpopulation in the northern waters and competition for food.</p>
        <p>The Marine Mammal Stranding Center can be reached at (609) 266-0538.</p>
        <p>The Nature Conservancy of New Jersey is dedicated to preserving the land and water habitats needed for plants and animals to survive.</p>
        <p>This spring members will help count the thousands of shore birds, including red knots, ruddy turnstones, semipalmated sandpipers and sanderlings that stop on the Delaware Bay in May to feast on millions of horseshoe crab eggs laid on the beach. At that point, the birds are about midway on a 10,000-mile trip from South America to the Arctic and need the stopover to refuel. In the fall, bald eagles, hawks and peregrine falcons pass through the area, as do thousands of black ducks and mallards.</p>
        <p>The conservancy has built observation platforms, boat ramps and trails and provides maps as well as guided walks through the Pine Barrens and in conservation areas along the shore, the back bays and rivers to allow people to see the endangered Pine Barrens tree frog and rattlesnake, the threatened northern pine snake, a wide range of birds and rare plants like the curly grass fern, the Pine Barrens gentian and the swamp pink.</p>
        <p>For walks in southern New Jersey the Nature Conservancy can be reached at (609) 861-0600 and in the Pine Barrens at (609) 735-2200.</p>
        <p>At one time the osprey, a black-and-white shorebird with a six-foot wing span, was a common site along with the large nests that it built atop any high structure with a view of the water. Then the use of DDT and other pesticides nearly eliminated the bird. Now it is one of the success stories of conservation, although the Atlantic coast population is not as well established as the Delaware Bay birds, said Dr. Roger Wood, director of research at the Wetlands Institute in Stone Harbor and a professor of zoology at Stockton State College.</p>
        <p>The Wetlands Institute has a video hookup that allows visitors to see a nesting osprey pair. The birds' nests also can be seen on platforms built on top of poles in the marshes in southern New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''The video camera makes it feel like you are in the nest with the birds,'' Dr. Wood said.</p>
        <p>The Wetlands Institute has a wide variety of walks, classes and other programs for adults and children as well as an annual Wings 'n' Water Festival, which this year will be held Sept. 15 and 16. The institute can be reached at (609) 368-1211.</p>
        <p>Viewing animals is not limited to the warm-weather months. Several businesses along the coastline take tourists out in the ocean in the winter to see the many whales that migrate past New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The rare right whale, as well as the more common humpback, fin and minke varieties, can be spotted off the coast, according to Francis Bogan, who captains fishing boats and boats for whale and dolphin viewing out of Brielle. Whales can be seen at all times except summer, though Captain Bogan's trips take place January through March. North Atlantic common dolphins also are seen frequently.</p>
        <p>For the fishermen, striped bass have made a comeback since restrictions have been placed on catching them, a variety of types of tuna can be caught off the coast and bottom fish like fluke have made a strong comeback, Captain Bogan said.</p>
        <p>Jeff George, who captains cruises out of Atlantic City's Historic Gardner's Basin, said his family had maintained a cruise business for more than 30 years and in recent years the sea floor has been visible through 15 feet of water.</p>
        <p>''We take people on sightseeing cruises down the coastline and on the back bays, and it is now easy to spot great white and blue herons, peregrine falcons, red wing blackbirds, boat-tailed grackles, as well as dolphins in the summer and whales in the winter,'' Mr. George said.</p>
        <p>Unlike in some southern areas of the United States, it is illegal to swim with dolphins or feed any wild animals in New Jersey, he added.</p>
        <p>Additional information on Atlantic City cruises is available at www.atlanticcitycruises.com and Captain Bogan can be reached at (732) 528-6620.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
