<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Forest Primeval, Trees With Stories; Solving Riddles of Growth Rings In an Ancient New Jersey Swamp</title>
    <meta content="26TREE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/26/nyregion/26TREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1426742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pine Trees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pine Barrens (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Millville (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bear Swamp (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River Valley</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Black Gum Trees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EED71039F935A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Forest Primeval, Trees With Stories; Solving Riddles of Growth Rings In an Ancient New Jersey Swamp</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Forest Primeval, Trees With Stories</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>MILLVILLE, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bear Swamp in southern New Jersey is extolled by tree experts as example of North American lowland hardwood forest that shows little evidence of human impact; group gets permission from private owner to study age and survival of tree species such as black gum, which has moved over centuries through Hudson River Valley; photos; oldest black gum is 400-550 years old, unusual for Northeast and Pine Barrens, where common pitch pines live about 200 years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 17 tree lovers shuffled, bent over, fighting their way through the low-hanging vines and branches like Groucho Marx impersonators, resplendent in their vapor trail of insect repellent, swamp and sweat.</p>
        <p>They were on the hunt, looking for the biggest, oldest trees in the Northeast, and on this day at least, New Jersey -- known more for its turnpike than its timber -- seemed a likely place to look.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A small group of tree researchers got a chance to look at the trees, and history, of New Jersey's near pristine Bear Swamp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 17 tree lovers shuffled, bent over, fighting their way through the low-hanging vines and branches like Groucho Marx impersonators, resplendent in their vapor trail of insect repellent, swamp and sweat.</p>
        <p>They were on the hunt, looking for the biggest, oldest trees in the Northeast, and on this day at least, New Jersey -- known more for its turnpike than its timber -- seemed a likely place to look.</p>
        <p>''Holy mackerel!'' a voice bellowed from up ahead. ''Look at the size of this black gum!''</p>
        <p>Every old tree, no matter where it has taken root, is a mystery story, a testament to time and perseverance wrapped in the riddles of growth rings and scarred bark. But the story of Bear Swamp in New Jersey, which has been talked about in tree-hugger circles since at least 1908, has at times seemed more like legend. Rumors abounded of great shaggy-barked Methuselahs, holdovers of a lost world before Plymouth Rock and Jamestown, perhaps even before Columbus.</p>
        <p>The handful of biologists and old-tree enthusiasts who had been allowed here onto the privately owned property over the years said the forest was almost certainly ancient, with little evidence of human impact.</p>
        <p>So on a Saturday, having once more negotiated permission from the owner, a sand and gravel mining company, they were back, aiming this time for the hard numbers.</p>
        <p>Armed with hand-crank tree borers to take cores and a global satellite positioning system to mark the exact coordinates of each sample, the group hoped to emerge with the definitive word on what the swamp was or was not. How had it come to be spared? What might it offer to the increasingly important science of climate reconstruction, which uses tree rings as calendar markers for drought and cold and atmospheric upheaval in the past?</p>
        <p>But things did not turn out quite as the expedition participants had imagined. The global positioning system did not work, for starters, partly because there was too much canopy overhead.</p>
        <p>The satellite, in other words, could not make out the trees for the forest. And most of the trees, especially the biggest, oldest-looking ones, were hollow, making a precise count of their growth rings, and thus their ages, impossible.</p>
        <p>What was left only deepened the mystery of the swamp itself. Of the dozen or so trees tested, the oldest, a black gum, was 400 to 550 years old, based on the partial core, scientists at Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory said. Certainly, there are many trees older than that, especially in the West, where bristle-cone pines can live for more than 4,000 years.</p>
        <p>But scientists say that tree species in the Northeast generally do not live much past 600 years; in arboreal terms, it is a live-fast-die-young culture. Much of the Pine Barrens -- perhaps New Jersey's most famous forest, just north of Millville -- is dominated by the pitch pine, which typically lives only 200 years or so.</p>
        <p>Bear Swamp, scientists say, offers context: a particular kind of forest of native lowland hardwood, and the human story of how and why it was left alone. With an estimated 88 acres of old-growth trees, a vast majority untested for age, it is also big enough, they say, to offer biological diversity. These are not just a few old trees that somehow dodged the ax, but an old and apparently intact ecosystem in a place where most people would least expect to find it. The legend lives on.</p>
        <p>''The evidence is that this forest was never disturbed in any way,'' said Stevens Heckscher, a conservation biologist with the Natural Lands Trust, who has tromped perhaps a dozen times through these woods. ''It's truly primeval, something that most people would not think could occur in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>The main reason Bear Swamp survived the centuries, Dr. Heckscher and other forest experts say, is apparently that no one wanted what it contained. Through the Colonial and early American era, when forests were mainly appraised for the board feet they held, and then through the paved-over era of suburbanization and sprawl that followed, Bear Swamp moldered on in its mossy, tree-bearded silence. The land was too boggy and low for farming, too thick with species once derided as trash trees to be worth cutting down.</p>
        <p>In other words, this is not exactly a piece of pristine old North American nature, but the leftovers.</p>
        <p>Chris Walbrecht could not care less. Mr. Walbrecht, a member of the Bear Swamp expedition, became charmed as a boy by the mystique of old bark when he was chopping wood on his family's dairy farm in upstate New York. Inside one split log, he found a bullet imbedded deep in the wood. He showed his father, and together they counted the rings that had grown over and around the wound, tracing the entry mark back about 80 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walbrecht, now an organic vegetable farmer on eastern Long Island, was enthralled with the way the tree had, in a way, suspended that moment in time -- one errant shot in the woods.</p>
        <p>Matt Largess, who drove from Rhode Island to see Bear Swamp's trees, also had a transcendent tree experience. Mr. Largess, who has been given the nickname Twig because of his arboreal ardor, is a former logger who was hired to cut down a stand of old American beech trees near Newport five years ago to make way for a luxury housing development. He could not do it. He threw down his saw -- though he still works as a tree surgeon -- and became a tree advocate, hiring out as a consultant to forest preservation groups.</p>
        <p>''The experience changed my life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Passion aside, there is hot science in what old trees teach, especially as evidence has mounted that human impact is altering the world's climate. Neil Pederson, a doctoral candidate at Columbia who cored the trees at Bear Swamp, is studying how trees like the black gums, which grow in profusion throughout the Southern states, marched north over the centuries through the climate belt of the Hudson River Valley. His working theory is that a warming climate in the Northeast -- because of flukes and channels like the Hudson Valley -- could produce a far different and more complicated forest mix than most climatologists and foresters have suggested.</p>
        <p>The human story of Bear Swamp is also far from over. The company that owns the swamp, the U.S. Silica Company, is negotiating with New Jersey for a land swap that would permanently protect the swamp. Under the proposal, Bear Swamp and another 5,000 acres owned by the company would become state land. In return, the company would obtain the right to mine sand and gravel on another piece of state-owned property nearby. So the combination of human and tree nature that conspired to save the swamp in the past continues.</p>
        <p>''The timing of this trip was serendipitous,'' said C. Scott Eves, the senior environmental specialist at the Better Minerals and Aggregates Corporation, which is the parent company of U.S. Silica. Mr. Eves, who accompanied the tree team into the swamp, said the company did not solicit scientific interest, but has welcomed it.</p>
        <p>''It's not our purpose to demonstrate the value of this land,'' Mr. Eves said. ''We hope the state already understands that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
