<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Seasons Will Do Just Fine</title>
    <meta content="07COLU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Helen (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2D6103AF934A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Seasons Will Do Just Fine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger Jersey column, praising absence of cold winter, describes what Rutgers University anthropologist Helen Fisher says might happen if New Jersey had only three seasons; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS being April, it now seems safe to draw the following meteorological conclusion:</p>
        <p>We had, essentially, no winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS being April, it now seems safe to draw the following meteorological conclusion:</p>
        <p>We had, essentially, no winter.</p>
        <p>And from that conclusion we can extrapolate the following consensus:</p>
        <p>Good!</p>
        <p>Sure, there are global-warming crybabies and a maybe few skiers who actually lament the lack of winter this year. And admittedly if this kind of thing were to continue there might be some adverse consequences, like the melting icecaps would cause the Atlantic to rise, and everything from Long Branch to Freehold would be underwater.</p>
        <p>But that's a sacrifice I think most of us are willing to make, because frankly, winter as it used to be was a poor idea, a miserable season full of fender benders and frostbite and avalanches.</p>
        <p>Anyone who doubts it is invited to recall the second week of January 1996, when we were buried up to our bellybuttons by one of the worst snowstorms of the century. I use the term ''we'' somewhat loosely since I actually got trapped at work in New York and was forced to spend two nights in the Midtown Marriott while the wife and daughter and every other New Jerseyan dug out. But even from that distance, I could feel your pain.</p>
        <p>Who wants to go through that kind of hardship again? Yet I'm not one to endorse radical alteration of the climate cavalierly. So I've consulted some actual experts on what it would mean for life in New Jersey if every winter were like the one just gone by. And there's good news: if it never snowed here again, we'd all feel a lot sexier.</p>
        <p>''There really is something called spring fever, and we probably would see a good deal more of that,'' said Helen Fisher, an anthropologist at Rutgers University who has explored the primal side of our 21st-century selves in books like ''The Sex Contract: The Evolution of Human Behavior.''</p>
        <p>Our ancestors, if what the scientists say is true, morphed into humanness in warm parts of the world, deeply attuned to nature's rhythms. That wiring, Ms. Fisher said, is still there, buried under millenniums of civilization and its hangups.</p>
        <p>''We evolved in a tropical climate where the smells of plants and flowers were all around us,'' she said. ''We spent a lot of time in the trees with a lot of sunlight and no clothes.''</p>
        <p>Replace the old-style winter with an extended autumn and we would edge back toward our true tropical selves, pulsating with warm-weather urges. The state would be alive with the types of mating rituals normally seen only in movies aimed at teenagers.</p>
        <p>''We would see more parading for longer periods of time, and more of the sensuousness that comes from parading,'' Ms. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>Who doesn't love a parade? We might also feel more generally alert, she said, because with warmer weather we'd spend more time outside in the winter months and thus get more exposure to sun, a proven energizer.</p>
        <p>Fred Kelly, dean of the School of Business Administration at Monmouth University, sounded as if he would be one of those leading the charge into the outdoors if we lost winter as we've known it.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't put my golf clubs away nearly as early as I did,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Knowing that owners of ski areas and snowplowing services would whine if my proposal to abolish winter were to become law, I asked Mr. Kelly for an economic assessment. Yes, he said, there would be disruption, but there would also be new possibilities.</p>
        <p>''Part of the concept of the free enterprise system is that as these changes occur, people step up to see them as opportunities,'' he said. So resorts would alter their sales tactics, clothiers would change the types of goods they make and sell and some entrepreneur might even come up with an indoor ski slope.</p>
        <p>What little agriculture we have left would also be affected, Mr. Kelly said -- badly if the future nonwinters were like the one that just ended, but perhaps for the better if it started raining regularly again, since the growing season would be extended. (And I want to here point out that I'm not advocating a moistureless winter, just a snowless one. It could rain from time to time, preferably at night.)</p>
        <p>The bottom line economically? ''It's an ill wind that doesn't benefit somebody,'' Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>So there you have it: more golf, fewer clothes. What's not to like? Yeah, there would probably be a few thousand environmental consequences if we went winterless, like the Pinelands would become the Scrub Maple-lands. But, as previously noted, most of the Pinelands would be underwater anyway, so we'd hardly notice.</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
