<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rally Pits Cars Against Pollution</title>
    <meta content="24TOUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/24/automobiles/24TOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1394799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="DRIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De Sol (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DB1F38F937A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rally Pits Cars Against Pollution</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rally Pits Cars Against Pollution</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on Tour de Sol, annual race that shows off pioneering solar-, battery- and hybrid-power vehicles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO cars were offered for sale near the starting gate of the Tour de Sol, an annual race that shows off pioneering solar-, battery- and hybrid-power vehicles. One was a new Honda Civic gasoline-electric hybrid, in a silvery color that Honda calls Opal Blue. A decal on the side said, ''50 Miles Per Gallon, Available Now.'' A throng of curious spectators admired the car's turquoise digital dashboard and its plush interior. The sticker price: $20,010, including shipping.</p>
        <p>Olaf Bleck, a former car builder who is now a graduate student at M.I.T., also had a vehicle for sale. His was one-of-a-kind, and it also had a sign on the front fender, hand-lettered and with an arrow pointing to a loop of wire. It said, ''Pull off, emergency manual disconnect.'' The asking price: $14,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two cars were offered for sale near the starting gate of the Tour de Sol, an annual race that shows off pioneering solar-, battery- and hybrid-power vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO cars were offered for sale near the starting gate of the Tour de Sol, an annual race that shows off pioneering solar-, battery- and hybrid-power vehicles. One was a new Honda Civic gasoline-electric hybrid, in a silvery color that Honda calls Opal Blue. A decal on the side said, ''50 Miles Per Gallon, Available Now.'' A throng of curious spectators admired the car's turquoise digital dashboard and its plush interior. The sticker price: $20,010, including shipping.</p>
        <p>Olaf Bleck, a former car builder who is now a graduate student at M.I.T., also had a vehicle for sale. His was one-of-a-kind, and it also had a sign on the front fender, hand-lettered and with an arrow pointing to a loop of wire. It said, ''Pull off, emergency manual disconnect.'' The asking price: $14,000.</p>
        <p>''It's just the sticker price,'' Mr. Bleck said. ''You could probably do better.''</p>
        <p>The Tour de Sol, which had its 14th running last week, is a road rally, run in stages, with show-and-tell demonstrations of the technology along the way. Vehicles are graded on handling, acceleration, energy efficiency, greenhouse gas emissions and reliability.</p>
        <p>The tour has always been diverse, but there are now new entrants fighting the tyranny of gasoline-powered cars: the car companies themselves, heavily represented this year by Daimler-Chrysler and Honda.</p>
        <p>''It certainly is a mélange,'' said Nancy Hazard, the race organizer and the associate director of the sponsoring organization, the Northeast Sustainable Energy Association in Greenfield, Mass. But there is nothing wrong with that, she added.</p>
        <p>What began as a showcase for vehicles running on alternative energy, many of them developed by college and high-school teams, has turned into a parade of cars using various combinations of electric motors and gasoline or diesel engines to run the wheels.</p>
        <p>In the first Tour de Sol in 1989, now legendary, there were six entries at the starting post and only four at the finish. An early competitor, James Worden, who founded Solectria, a Boston manufacturer of electric drive components, was famous for spending all-nighters under cars, trying to improve performance. Often, it wasn't even his car, but a competitor's. Of course, that competitor was also a customer, since he sold components to most participants.</p>
        <p>Solectria was followed by bigger, more timid companies, like Ford, General Motors and Toyota, that later backed away from purely electric cars. So a wave never developed, leaving relics like Mr. Bleck's car. It began life as a 1992 Geo Metro but was converted to run on batteries. Solectria had bought dozens of Metros, junked their engines and equipped them with electric motors, lead-acid batteries and a new name, the Force. Solectria then sold them to technophiles, energy-independency diehards and a few inventive companies around the country. This year, Solectria's participation was limited to supplying parts for a hybrid bus.</p>
        <p>There was a clear dividing line between the amateur efforts and those of the big car companies. Here was Chrysler, showing off a hybrid fuel cell-battery van and a hybrid gasoline-electric Sebring sedan.</p>
        <p>Philip M. Benjamin, the engineer supervising the project, worried about the sorts of problems that never disturbed the high-school teams. One was how the dashboard design would affect a car's marketability: should the dashboard indicate the state of charge, the torque level for each powertrain and the direction of energy flow? For now, he has settled on a minimal display.</p>
        <p>''Customer research says that they want something, especially if we charge them for it,'' he said. On the other hand, too many readouts could prove distracting to the driver.</p>
        <p>In contrast, a team from West Philadelphia High School lovingly built a fiberglass body on the frame of a Chevy S-10 pickup, loaded it with batteries and an engine burning biodiesel fuel (oil from vegetables or animals, often recovered and refined from kitchen waste) and painted it just before the race. There was no time to pull together a fancy instrument panel, so the dashboard is made of plywood, the labels scrawled with a red marker. The turn signals are operated by a toggle switch turned sideways.</p>
        <p>But James Drewery, a 16-year-old member of the West Philadelphia team, was not cowed by the smooth curves of the corporate entries, His team's car, with open gaps between the fiberglass panels, was technically more ambitious, if not more polished. It will look better next year, he said. The team wants to find a Lamborghini body to use instead.</p>
        <p>''We'll import one,'' Mr. Drewery said. ''Probably from out of state.''</p>
        <p>DRIVING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
