<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wet Weather Creates Scheduling Quagmire</title>
    <meta content="MB014115" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1420748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DF1F3FF930A3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wet Weather Creates Scheduling Quagmire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tennis Notebook discusses impact of rain on US Open scheduling (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rain is the enemy.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, when 12 men's and women's singles matches were scheduled in the United States Open, only one was completed before rain ended the day. Yesterday, when 19 men's and women's singles matches were scheduled, the rain did not relent; the first match, scheduled for 11 a.m., did not start until 6:18 p.m. All the junior boys' and girls' matches were postponed for a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rain is the enemy.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, when 12 men's and women's singles matches were scheduled in the United States Open, only one was completed before rain ended the day. Yesterday, when 19 men's and women's singles matches were scheduled, the rain did not relent; the first match, scheduled for 11 a.m., did not start until 6:18 p.m. All the junior boys' and girls' matches were postponed for a day.</p>
        <p>If the rain delays frustrated players and spectators, they became a nightmare for Brian Earley, in his 10th year as the tournament referee.</p>
        <p>''Since we've been here, we've never lost more than two sessions any year,'' Earley said.</p>
        <p>He hopes to avoid the logistical horror of 1987, when rain on the final Saturday forced postponement of the women's final and the men's semifinals to Sunday and the men's final to Monday.</p>
        <p>Earley's main concern was men's singles because it would be cruel for a player to face the possibility of two five-set matches in two days. In addition, the top half of the men's draw was one round ahead of the bottom half, creating another potentially unfair situation.</p>
        <p>Earley said the finals were still on schedule: mixed doubles Thursday, men's and women's doubles Friday, women's singles Saturday night and men's singles Sunday afternoon.</p>
        <p>''The players become very cooperative in this situation,'' he said. ''All they want to do is play. If you're a player, do you want to stay until 9 tonight and play or do you want to play tomorrow and Wednesday? We have started matches as late as 10 at night. I don't say we will now.''</p>
        <p>For the immediate future, Earley was prepared to move matches involving high-seeded players from the show courts (Arthur Ashe and Louis Armstrong Stadiums and the Grandstand) to side courts with no-frills seating. ''We've got great light on outside courts,'' he said. ''We can play there forever.''</p>
        <p>At 5:22 p.m. yesterday, the rain having barely stopped, 30 workers with squeegees and towels descended on the Ashe Stadium court. At 5:50 p.m., the surface was mostly dry and the players started warming up. It didn't take long before Lindsay Davenport started serving against the Italian Silvia Farina Elia in the first match of the day.</p>
        <p>''We didn't even get a chance to warm up,'' the fourth-seeded Davenport said after her 6-3, 6-1 victory. ''I hit serves on the wettest court I've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
