<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting There: How to Beat the Traffic Blues</title>
    <meta content="17EASE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/17/automobiles/17EASE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1392884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="DRIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Better, Nancy M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DD1E39F934A25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting There: How to Beat the Traffic Blues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting There: How to Beat the Traffic Blues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NANCY M. BETTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Better, Nancy M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advice on coping with long car trips and delays in getting to vacation destinations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUDDENLY, it is at least possible to imagine summer. You have bought or rented or borrowed your way into the perfect weekend home, and you cannot wait to start showing up at the office on Friday mornings in Bermuda shorts and sandals.</p>
        <p>At 4 p.m., you will toss your bags in the car, grab a couple of cold drinks and hit the road, only to languish in bumper-to-bumper traffic until the last glimmer of daylight fades to dusk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are going to be trapped in gridlock this summer for five hours at a time, you will need plenty of creature comforts to survive the drive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUDDENLY, it is at least possible to imagine summer. You have bought or rented or borrowed your way into the perfect weekend home, and you cannot wait to start showing up at the office on Friday mornings in Bermuda shorts and sandals.</p>
        <p>At 4 p.m., you will toss your bags in the car, grab a couple of cold drinks and hit the road, only to languish in bumper-to-bumper traffic until the last glimmer of daylight fades to dusk.</p>
        <p>Unless there is a chopper in your future (and at $1,200 to $3,000 one way, it hardly warrants consideration) there is little you can do to relieve the seasonal congestion. Between Memorial Day weekend, which starts next Friday, and Labor Day, traffic on the nation's most popular escape routes grows even denser and more frustrating, so that the amount of energy spent fighting the traffic seems to defeat the purpose of taking a vacation at all.</p>
        <p>If you are going to be trapped in gridlock with your spouse or friends or -- horrors -- small children for five hours, you will need plenty of creature comforts to survive the drive. Making hourly pit stops is not an option when every minute in transit is a minute less in paradise.</p>
        <p>Stay Cool</p>
        <p>The first thing you will need is a cooler. Forget about the lightweight plastic or plastic foam models that end up submerging cans in a sea of turgid water. For $100, L.L. Bean (800-441-5713; www.llbean.com) offers a portable model that plugs into the dashboard lighter. With a 10-foot detachable cord and an AC adapter for indoor use, the Car Cooler can keep nine 12-ounce cans at 40 degrees below air temperature throughout the trip.</p>
        <p>Get a Jolt</p>
        <p>After the initial weekend euphoria wears off, and drowsiness sets in, it is coffee time.</p>
        <p>The Vector Deluxe Coffee Maker, marketed primarily to truck drivers, can produce five cups of fresh coffee while hooked up to a 12-volt power source, a k a the dashboard lighter. The tempered glass carafe has lock-in and drip-stop features, which is bound to be handy when you put the pedal to the metal. Electronics Outpost (www.electronicsoutpost.com) carries the Vector VEC216, as it is named, for $24.</p>
        <p>If you are going solo, skip the coffee maker in favor of the thermostatically controlled Smart Mug. Available in translucent red or blue, this high-tech cup looks like a souvenir from a NASA mission. You set the temperature on a switch panel, and the liquid's status is displayed on an L.E.D. indicator.</p>
        <p>Plug it into the dashboard and 16 ounces of coffee -- or tea, hot chocolate or soup -- will hit the near-boiling point in seconds.</p>
        <p>Through a retailer called Gifts and Gadgets Online (www.giftsand gadgetsonline.com), the Smart Mug was $28.95. It is also useful for warming formula.</p>
        <p>Road Food</p>
        <p>Ready for a snack? With the Road Pro Portable Oven ($39.95 from www.shoplifestyle.com), you can toast bagels and heat sandwiches as you travel.</p>
        <p>''Stop wasting time and money on overpriced roadside restaurants,'' the manufacturer says. ''You'll wonder how you ever lived without it.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. If the kids are getting antsy while watching the rear-seat VCR or DVD, whip up a bucket of fresh popcorn with another of Road Pro's products, the 12-volt Portable Popcorn Popper ($29.99 from www.shoplifestyle.com).</p>
        <p>Freshen the Air</p>
        <p>Of course, dining on the go can generate a malodorous climate in the car. If it is too hot or too cold to roll down the windows, Brookstone (800-926-7000; www.brookstone.com) has the answer: the $39.95 Ionizer/Air Purifier.</p>
        <p>Plug this device into your 12-volt socket and billions of negatively charged ions will rid the air of dust, odors, smoke, bacteria and exhaust pollution. It also takes care of the chemical smell of freon coursing through the air-conditioning system.</p>
        <p>Car Sickness</p>
        <p>Sometimes even a breath of fresh air does not help nauseous travelers. If one of your riders has a sensitive stomach , consider springing for the $99 ReliefBand, a patented drug free remedy which has been cleared by the Food and Drug Administration for treating motion sickness.</p>
        <p>Styled like a slick black sports watch, the ReliefBand is worn with its face on the underside of the wrist, near the pulse, where it intermittently emits a low-level electrical current across two small electrodes. Available with a 144-hour nonrechargeable battery from Carefree Travel (www.carefreetravel.com).</p>
        <p>Massage Time</p>
        <p>Should your back start to ache after several hours, plug in the Sharper Image's Deep-Kneading Massage Cushion ($125.95, 800-344-5555; www.sharperimage.com).Grip the remote control, and flip between the four spinning nodes that provide a shiatsu-style back massage and six dual-speed motors that emit vibrations throughout the seat.</p>
        <p>Plenty of Power</p>
        <p>How are you supposed to plug in all these gizmos and still charge your cellphone or check your e-mail? For $15, Brookstone carries a two-in-one multisocket adapter that converts your cigarette lighter into two 12-volt sockets. Multitaskers should opt for the three-in-one adapter from the Sharper Image for $9.95.</p>
        <p>With a tilting feature and a vent to keep the unit from overheating, this device can handle a cellphone, a laptop and a cooler -- enough to make it the first choice on any weekend commuter's list.</p>
        <p>DRIVING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
