<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Trees Outgrow Rural Cousins, and Study Credits Urban Chemistry</title>
    <meta content="10TREE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/10/nyregion/10TREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1503436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cottonwood Trees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorman, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gregg, Jillian W (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EED6133DF933A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Trees Outgrow Rural Cousins, and Study Credits Urban Chemistry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City Trees Outgrow Rural Cousins, and Study Credits Urban Chemistry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GORMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gorman, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jillian W Gregg and colleagues report that Eastern cottonwood cuttings grown over several seasons in New York City grow twice as fast as saplings grown in rural parts of state; say reason is that ozone, which is known to harm plants and animals, can be worse in rural areas than in city, where ozone is not only produced but is also broken down by variety of processes, including action by some of very chemicals that are precursors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone knows that trees grow in Brooklyn. Now, scientists have discovered that they also flourish in the Bronx and Queens. In fact, cottonwood trees grow twice as fast in the chewy air of New York City as they do in the pastoral reaches of the Hudson Valley and eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>In today's issue of the journal Nature, Jillian W. Gregg, a research ecologist, and colleagues report that Eastern cottonwood cuttings grown over several seasons in New York City and in rural areas of the state showed a consistent pattern. Each September, when the researchers measured the trees, the city saplings were twice as big.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have discovered that trees flourish in the Bronx and Queens and cottonwood trees grow twice as fast in the city as they do in Hudson Valley and Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everyone knows that trees grow in Brooklyn. Now, scientists have discovered that they also flourish in the Bronx and Queens. In fact, cottonwood trees grow twice as fast in the chewy air of New York City as they do in the pastoral reaches of the Hudson Valley and eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>In today's issue of the journal Nature, Jillian W. Gregg, a research ecologist, and colleagues report that Eastern cottonwood cuttings grown over several seasons in New York City and in rural areas of the state showed a consistent pattern. Each September, when the researchers measured the trees, the city saplings were twice as big.</p>
        <p>The result may seem to fly in the face of common sense. Sure, city rats are known to grow to the size of Shetland ponies, and cockroaches can multiply faster than a math whiz at the Bronx High School of Science. But trees?</p>
        <p>The explanation, it turns out, has to do with ozone. It is known to harm plants and animals, and it can be worse in rural areas than in the city. In general, Dr. Gregg writes, rural areas in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut have higher concentrations of ozone near the ground than cities do. (In the stratosphere, ozone forms a layer that protects life on earth from ultraviolet radiation; that layer has been decreasing, while ozone concentrations in the air that people breathe have been increasing.)</p>
        <p>Dr. Gregg was a graduate student in ecology at Cornell University and at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in Millbrook, N.Y., when she conducted the research, along with Clive G. Jones, an ecologist at the institute, and Todd E. Dawson, a plant physiologist who was then at Cornell and is now at the University of California at Berkeley. Dr. Gregg has just finished a postdoctoral stint with the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>She started with genetically identical rooted cuttings of cottonwoods planted in irrigated pots at urban and rural sites. The city cottonwoods were set out in open fields at the New York Botanical Garden and Hunts Point in the Bronx; the Con Edison fuel depot in Astoria, Queens; and Eisenhower Park in East Meadow, Nassau County, the last being not quite New York City, but close enough.</p>
        <p>The country trees, also in irrigated pots, grew in fields in Millbrook; at Cornell University's Horticultural Research Laboratory in Riverhead, Suffolk County; and at the Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton, also in Suffolk. When the saplings were harvested by the researchers, the city trees were often found to be almost six feet tall, the country saplings waist-high. The researchers dried the wood and then weighed it. The results showed that the city saplings were not just tall and skinny: they weighed twice as much.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gregg did not set out to give the city good publicity. Nor was she focusing on the effects of ozone. In fact, she said in an interview, she suspected that the sheer variety of nasty chemicals in city air would make the city saplings unable to match their country cousins.</p>
        <p>In scientific terms, she wanted to examine a complex system that would subject the trees to the combined effect of all forms of air pollution. To measure the effects of air pollution alone, she controlled most other conditions -- soil, light, water and genetic composition. When she sorted through the effects of pollutants, only one seemed to make a difference. Higher cumulative concentrations of ozone in rural areas had handicapped the rural trees, she concluded. It was not so much that the city trees were thriving as that the country trees were suffering.</p>
        <p>In one sense, said Eva J. Pell, a professor of agricultural sciences at Pennsylvania State University, the study is ''not so surprising.'' Plants vary in sensitivity to ozone, said Dr. Pell, who is not connected with the study, and cottonwoods are known to be somewhat sensitive. It is also known that pollution in urban areas could produce larger ozone concentrations downwind.</p>
        <p>But Steward T. A. Pickett, a colleague of Dr. Gregg's and Dr. Jones's at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies, said the research was significant because of the complexity of the situation, the many pollutants and effects considered, and the ''very elegant and controlled way'' that the action of ozone emerged from a welter of other influences.</p>
        <p>Thomas M. Hinckley, a tree physiologist at the University of Washington, agreed. ''It's how she conducted the study that makes it so robust,'' he said. It is easy enough to take a canary into a mine, but all canaries are different, and in this case, he added, ''she eliminated the variability from one canary to another.''</p>
        <p>The research also dealt with particularly complex atmospheric chemistry. Cities do have more kinds of pollution than rural areas, and some of these pollutants are the chemical precursors of ozone, like nitrogen oxides. Sunlight acts on these substances, initiating chemical reactions that produce ozone.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, in cities, ozone is not only produced but is also broken down by a variety of processes, including action by some of the very chemicals that are precursors. In cities, ozone is created and destroyed, created and destroyed, like celebrities and cultural fads. In rural areas, which lack this atmosphere of ferment and change, ozone lasts and lasts.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for the most dedicated urbanites, Dr. Gregg's study has little relevance for sidewalk trees. Ozone is the least of their worries. There is winter salt, excessive heat, lack of sun and the abiding nightmare of every sidewalk plant: the dog.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
