<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pluto Defies Expectations And Physics, Warming Up</title>
    <meta content="Y10PLUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/10/national/10PLUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1503383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pluto (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pluto (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3D8133DF933A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pluto Defies Expectations And Physics, Warming Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pluto Defies Expectations and Physics, Warming Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists report in journal Nature that planet Pluto appears to have warmed, seemingly in defiance of basic physics, as it has moved away from the Sun on its elliptical orbit; some of planet's nitrogen ice has evaporated off its surface into atmosphere, doubling Pluto's atmospheric pressure since 1988; atmospheric measurements are based on two 2002 eclipses observed when Pluto passed in front of distant stars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The planet Pluto appears to have warmed as it has moved away from the Sun, contrary to most expectations and seemingly in defiance of basic physics, scientists are reporting today.</p>
        <p>In the process, some of Pluto's nitrogen ice has evaporated off its surface into the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The planet Pluto appears to have warmed as it has moved away from the Sun, contrary to most expectations and seemingly in defiance of basic physics, scientists are reporting today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The planet Pluto appears to have warmed as it has moved away from the Sun, contrary to most expectations and seemingly in defiance of basic physics, scientists are reporting today.</p>
        <p>In the process, some of Pluto's nitrogen ice has evaporated off its surface into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The shifting climate raises chances that Pluto, the solar system's outermost planet and the only one not yet observed close up by a spacecraft, will still have an atmosphere when a NASA probe is to fly by, in 2015 or 2016.</p>
        <p>Some experts had been concerned that as Pluto receded along its elliptical orbit, most of its air would turn to frost before then, leaving astronomers unable to study weather on Pluto until it next warmed up centuries from now.</p>
        <p>The atmospheric measurements are based on two eclipses last year when Pluto, by chance, passed in front of distant stars, once in July and once in August. If Pluto had been airless, the light of the eclipsed star would have winked out suddenly.</p>
        <p>Instead, Pluto's nitrogen atmosphere caused the starlight to dim more gradually. ''It's a bigger and fuzzier shadow,'' Dr. Bruno Sicardy, an astronomer at the Paris Observatory who studied the eclipses, said.</p>
        <p>From the rate of dimming, scientists can calculate the density of the air. Pluto's atmosphere is extremely thin, probably less than one twenty-thousandth the density of Earth's.</p>
        <p>Such an eclipse had been observed only twice before, in 1985 and 1988.</p>
        <p>Two groups of scientists who observed last year's eclipses, one led by Dr. Sicardy, the other by Dr. James L. Elliot of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, came to the same conclusion: the increase in nitrogen gas has doubled Pluto's atmospheric pressure since 1988. The two groups describe their findings in today's issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>''This is the biggest change in pressure ever detected in a planetary atmosphere,'' said Dr. S. Alan Stern, director of space studies at the Southwest Research Institute in Boulder, Colo., and principal investigator for NASA's New Horizons mission to Pluto.</p>
        <p>The Earth's atmosphere has not experienced so drastic a change in atmospheric pressure in the last four billion years, and even Mars, known for its rapidly changing atmosphere, experiences seasonal swings of only 30 percent, Dr. Stern said.</p>
        <p>For the pressure to double on Pluto, the temperature of nitrogen ice on the surface, about minus-390 degrees Fahrenheit, would have had to rise about two degrees, Dr. Elliot said.</p>
        <p>Most scientists had expected Pluto to cool because less sunlight is reaching it now. Pluto passed its point closest to the Sun, 2.7 billion miles, in 1989.</p>
        <p>But the dynamics of Pluto are not simple. Pluto's axis is steeply tipped over, so its polar regions pass through long periods of continuous sunlight and continuous darkness during its 248-year orbit.</p>
        <p>The thickening atmosphere fits predictions by Dr. Candice J. Hansen, a scientist at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., and Dr. David A. Paige, a professor of planetary sciences at the University of California at Los Angeles in 1996. Their computer models indicated that as one of Pluto's polar caps passed from darkness to sunshine in this period, more nitrogen gas would evaporate, adding to its atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Parts of the surface now coming into sunlight might also be darker, absorbing more sunlight.</p>
        <p>But with the heat from the Sun continuing to diminish, the trend is expected to turn around soon. The computer models predict that the atmosphere ''will peak in 2005 and then start to go down very quickly,'' Dr. Paige said, although it should persist until at least 2025.</p>
        <p>During the eclipse, the astronomers also observed sudden spikes in the brightness of the starlight that result from sudden changes in air density.</p>
        <p>''That's probably caused by some kind of temperature wave, turbulence in the atmosphere,'' Dr. Elliot said.</p>
        <p>Because Pluto will pass in front of the central plane of the Milky Way galaxy in the coming years, many more eclipses should occur, allowing astronomers to track other changes.</p>
        <p>But details will have to await New Horizons, to be launched in January 2006. It is to reach Pluto in July 2015 or the next year.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, this creates a lot more interest and curiosity about what we're going to see when the mission gets there,'' Dr. Elliot said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
