<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BLIZZARD BURIES NORTHEASTERN U.S., DISRUPTING TRAVEL</title>
    <meta content="18SNOW$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/18/nyregion/18SNOW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="STORM IN THE NORTHEAST: OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents' Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rhode Island</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Virginia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Weather Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED91F3AF93BA25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BLIZZARD BURIES NORTHEASTERN U.S., DISRUPTING TRAVEL</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blizzard Buries Northeastern U.S., Disrupting Travel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biggest blizzard in seven years buries New York region and much of Northeast in one to two feet of snow, disrupting air and highway travel and raising chest-high drifts on wintry landscape of 10 states; for millions home on Presidents' Day, it offers holiday break, not hardships; storm, driven by 55-miles-an-hour winds, churns onto Eastern Seaboard on Feb 16 and moves from Virginia and Washington up the coast on Feb 17, at times dropping one to two inches an hour on New Jersey, New York, Conn, Rhode Island and Mass; airports are closed, flight schedules obliterated and thousands of travelers are stranded; there are countless traffic accidents, many buses and trains are late or delayed; emergency declarations are issued in six states; two deaths in metropolitan area are attributed to storm, as are two in West Virginia and 10 more in Midwest; timely arrival of storm on Presidents' Day weekend, and on week when New York City public schools are in recess, diminish its impact significantly; many businesses are closed for holiday and millions of people had day off to frolic in drifts or labor with shovels; National Weather Service calls this biggest storm since blizzard of Jan 7-8, 1996; snow in Central Park reaches depth of 19.8 inches, just short of 1996 total of 20.2 inches; photos; maps; chart (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The biggest blizzard in seven years buried the New York region and much of the Northeast in one to two feet of snow yesterday, disrupting air and highway travel and raising chest-high drifts on the wintry landscapes of 10 states. But for millions home on Presidents' Day, it offered a holiday break, not hardships.</p>
        <p>Driven by winds that gusted to 55 miles an hour, the storm -- a smudge 750 miles wide on satellite photos and a blinding whiteout on the ground -- churned onto the Eastern Seaboard on Sunday and moved from Virginia and Washington up the coast yesterday, at times dropping one to two inches an hour on New Jersey, New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island and Massachusetts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The biggest blizzard in seven years buried the New York region and much of the Northeast in one to two feet of snow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The biggest blizzard in seven years buried the New York region and much of the Northeast in one to two feet of snow yesterday, disrupting air and highway travel and raising chest-high drifts on the wintry landscapes of 10 states. But for millions home on Presidents' Day, it offered a holiday break, not hardships.</p>
        <p>Driven by winds that gusted to 55 miles an hour, the storm -- a smudge 750 miles wide on satellite photos and a blinding whiteout on the ground -- churned onto the Eastern Seaboard on Sunday and moved from Virginia and Washington up the coast yesterday, at times dropping one to two inches an hour on New Jersey, New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island and Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>It closed airports, obliterated flight schedules and stranded thousands of travelers. It caused countless traffic accidents, halted or delayed buses and trains, prompted emergency declarations in six states and brought life without sleds, skis or S.U.V.'s to a virtual standstill in Washington, Baltimore, Atlantic City, Philadelphia, New York, Boston and the rest of the Northeast Corridor.</p>
        <p>Two deaths in the metropolitan area were attributed to the storm. In the Bronx, a 67-year-old man died of carbon monoxide poisoning while he was warming up his car; the tailpipe was blocked with snow, the police said. In New Jersey, a 23-year-old man was killed and four people were injured in the collapse of a snow-laden roof at a Job Corps Academy training center in Edison, but no one was hurt when the roof of a Rite Aid drug store in Clifton fell in.</p>
        <p>Two people in West Virginia and 10 more in the Midwest were killed in earlier deaths attributed to the storm.</p>
        <p>But there was beauty as well as treachery in the storm. In woodlands and parks, on anonymous suburban streets, in cities where skylines vanished, the storm was a dream world of blowing snow and muffled sound: The distant scrape of plows and shovels, a child's shout in the wind, gave the day an old-fashioned feel, tumultuous yet private, the stillness of a small town, silent in winter.</p>
        <p>The timely arrival of the storm on Presidents' Day weekend, and on a week when New York City public schools are on recess, diminished its impact significantly. Many businesses were closed for the holiday, most theaters were dark, nonemergency government services were shut down, there were no mail deliveries, and millions of people had the day off to frolic in the drifts or labor with shovels and snowblowers.</p>
        <p>It was hardly the Storm of the Century, although its bluster brought out the expansiveness of television forecasters. But the National Weather Service and meteorologists at Pennsylvania State University called it the biggest since the blizzard of Jan. 7-8, 1996, which left two to three feet of snow over the Northeast.</p>
        <p>In New York City, the snow in Central Park by evening had reached a depth of 19.8 inches, just short of the 1996 total of 20.2 inches, but well behind the record of 26.4 inches, set in the blizzard of Dec. 26-27 in 1947.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the city, the totals were higher. In Queens, 25.6 inches at Kennedy International Airport and 28 in Howard Beach eclipsed the 1996 snows. All last winter, only 3.5 inches of snow fell in New York City, and yesterday's snowfall almost doubled the 25 inches recorded earlier this winter.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, Farmingdale reported 23.5 inches, while New Hyde Park had 21 and North Babylon in Suffolk County had 22. Sparkill in Rockland County reported 24.3 inches. Evening totals in Connecticut included 19 inches at Darien and 18 at New Canaan.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, West Milford had 26 inches, Little Egg Harbor 24 inches, West Caldwell 23.2 inches, Newark Liberty International Airport 21.8 inches, Ringwood in Passaic County 19, and Williamstown in Gloucester County 22. Elsewhere, Philadelphia had 19 inches, Washington 15 and the Baltimore-Washington Airport a record 26.6 inches.</p>
        <p>Garrett County, in Maryland, reported the storm's highest total, a whopping 44 inches.</p>
        <p>There were no major power failures in the New York area, apparently because the snow was relatively dry and did not stick to -- and bring down -- trees and power lines. But the storm brought major power failures elsewhere. In West Virginia, 95,000 residents were without electricity and were told that power would not be restored before tomorrow. More than 130,000 homes in Virginia, the Carolinas and Ohio were left without power earlier.</p>
        <p>For thousands of air travelers, it was virtually impossible to escape the storm. Airports in Washington, Baltimore, Philadelphia and Windsor Locks, Conn., were closed, along with La Guardia Airport in New York. Kennedy and Newark Airports remained open, but extensive flight cancellations made the distinction almost meaningless.</p>
        <p>Subways were running with some disruptions, including on elevated portions, but service on some city bus lines was suspended and bus service was halted in and out of the Port Authority Bus Terminal.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit suspended all bus service, but ran trains with scattered delays. A spokesman said New Jersey Transit would operate what it called an enhanced Saturday schedule today, adding trains on the Northeast Corridor, Montclair-Boonton, Pascack Valley and Port Jervis lines. Midtown Direct will continue to run to Hoboken instead of Pennsylvania Station, the line said.</p>
        <p>Metro-North switched from a holiday schedule to a more limited Sunday schedule, using diesels instead of electric locomotives on its Hudson, Harlem and New Haven lines. Diesels run better in deep snow. Late yesterday, Metro-North cut service further, running trains out of Grand Central Terminal only every two hours.</p>
        <p>Dan Brucker, a spokesman, said Metro-North planned to run a Sunday schedule again today, instead of its regular weekday rush-hour service. ''We believe a lot of our customers will be shoveling themselves out tomorrow morning,'' Mr. Brucker said. ''If they all show up, we'll make adjustments.''</p>
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road reported scattered delays of 15 to 30 minutes, and suspended service on its main line between Ronkonkoma and Greenport, providing shuttle buses for riders. The line said it expected to operate its regular morning rush service this morning, although riders were cautioned to expect delays.</p>
        <p>In the Northeast Corridor, Amtrak canceled much of its service, but ran empty trains to keep snow from blocking the tracks.</p>
        <p>Despite the storm, the Lincoln and Holland Tunnels and the George Washington Bridge reported no backups, but traffic was light and slow-moving everywhere, and speed limits were cut to 25 miles an hour on the bridges linking Staten Island and New Jersey. Speeds on the New Jersey Turnpike and the Garden State Parkway also were reduced.</p>
        <p>Major highways were open in Connecticut, with 632 plows from the State Department of Transportation, supplemented by 242 contractors, clearing the roadways. Many of Connecticut's largest shopping malls, including West Farms, in Farmington, closed shortly after noon. The blizzard even prompted the Mount Southington Ski Resort, south of Hartford, to shut down for the day.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki declared a snow emergency for the New York metropolitan area and a dozen other counties hit by the storm. The step mobilized seven state agencies to provide assistance.</p>
        <p>In New York City, 2,700 sanitation workers used 1,500 plows and 350 salt spreaders and cleared the major arteries in the five boroughs. But most side streets were choked with drifts late yesterday, and were probably not going to be open by today when the workweek resumes.</p>
        <p>''It's very pretty,'' Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said as the storm swirled outside a sanitation garage on the West Side of Manhattan where he met reporters. ''It's also very inconvenient and very expensive.''</p>
        <p>The mayor said that the city had already spent more than the $19 million that had been budgeted for snow removal this year, and that this storm could cost $20 million more -- $1 million for every inch of snow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg warned that the city's 6,000 miles of side streets would probably not be plowed until tomorrow, and advised New Yorkers to take mass transit wherever possible. ''It's going to be a rough commute,'' he added. ''But everyone will get there.''</p>
        <p>Few cars were moving on New York streets, and most of the parked cars were trapped behind silvery walls of snow shoved aside by the plows. With sidewalks all but impassable under the drifts, New Yorkers who ventured out took to the roadways, and some found city parks irresistible.</p>
        <p>''You feel like you're in a wonderland,'' Ann Gorewitz said as she and her husband, Steve Barcan, strolled through Central Park, surrounded by studies in black and white: rock outcroppings jutting up in the drifts, silhouettes of darkly skeletal trees trimmed with white lace. ''It's just really special.''</p>
        <p>The main street of Maplewood, N.J., was special for Leighann Narum-Miller, who grew up in Wisconsin. She was skiing up the barely plowed thoroughfare, and her friend, Jutta Gassner-Snyder, who is from Austria, felt right at home walking briskly alongside her.</p>
        <p>Nearby, Bill and Susan Gyves were pulling their 3-year-old daughter, Katie, on a sled. ''It's a great day,'' Mr. Gyves said. ''Tomorrow's the challenge.''</p>
        <p>STORM IN THE NORTHEAST: OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
