<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heavy Rain and Snow Break Drought's Hold on Northeast</title>
    <meta content="23DROU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/nyregion/23DROU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard Lezin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D91730F930A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heavy Rain and Snow Break Drought's Hold on Northeast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Heavy Rain and Snow Break Drought's Hold on Northeast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD LEZIN JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard Lezin</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, March 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Changing weather patterns marked by autumn of heavy rains and snowy winter bring relief to Northeast, which has been gripped by drought since late 1990's; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day last fall, Gary Donaldson looked up and the recalcitrant heavens over his Hackettstown farm finally let loose. One drop at first, followed by sheets of rain. Day after day it continued, bringing precious water to a region withered by drought for the better part of three years.</p>
        <p>''It was like it just started raining and wouldn't stop,'' recalled Mr. Donaldson, 46, who grows melons, sweet potatoes and Jersey tomatoes with his brother Greg about 50 miles west of Manhattan. ''Just watching the weather patterns, you could see things were changing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWARK, March 22  One day last fall, Gary Donaldson looked up and the recalcitrant heavens over his Hackettstown farm finally let loose. One drop at first, followed by sheets of rain. Day after day it continued,bringing precious water to a region withered by drought for the better part of three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One day last fall, Gary Donaldson looked up and the recalcitrant heavens over his Hackettstown farm finally let loose. One drop at first, followed by sheets of rain. Day after day it continued, bringing precious water to a region withered by drought for the better part of three years.</p>
        <p>''It was like it just started raining and wouldn't stop,'' recalled Mr. Donaldson, 46, who grows melons, sweet potatoes and Jersey tomatoes with his brother Greg about 50 miles west of Manhattan. ''Just watching the weather patterns, you could see things were changing.''</p>
        <p>After an autumn of heavy rains followed by a snowy winter, meteorologists and climate experts have quietly confirmed what many in the parched Northeast have come to believe: the drought that has gripped the region since the late 1990's is effectively over.</p>
        <p>In fact, meteorologists are now saying that all that snow could cause spring flooding.</p>
        <p>And the drought is not just over in the New York area. Climatologists have said that thanks to heavy snow -- as much as twice the typical accumulations in some areas -- water levels in rivers and reservoirs have risen all along the Eastern Seaboard.</p>
        <p>Weather experts caution, however, that the drought, driven by an enduring El Niño warming pattern over the past few years, persists throughout the West and lingers in pockets of New England.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, climatologists say, much of the worst is over. Even before the recent pronouncement of its demise, the drought had lost much of its sting in the Middle Atlantic.</p>
        <p>In October, New York City ended its drought emergency. A few weeks later, Westchester County followed suit. And at the start of the year, New Jersey did the same.</p>
        <p>However, municipal and state governments sometimes make such decisions using a different standard than the one applied by meteorologists. Some government bodies lifted their drought emergencies based on promising measurements of water in rivers and reservoirs, even though in many cases, deeper groundwater and aquifer levels remained low.</p>
        <p>And although some surface water storage areas have been topped off since the beginning of the year, climatologists had lingering concerns about levels in aquifers and underground wells.</p>
        <p>Recent measurements, however, have shown that in some places, groundwater and aquifer levels have reached their highest point in several years.</p>
        <p>Those measures coincide with a steep increase in water storage at regional reservoirs. For example, at the beginning of last year, storage at the Delaware River Basin, whose tributaries supply some of New York City's reservoirs, stood at around 70 billion gallons, according to figures from the basin commission. However, measurements taken Friday indicate that the basin had 254 billion gallons.</p>
        <p>''Reservoirs are pretty full, everything's in good shape,'' said Michael Evans, a meteorologist at the National Weather Service in Binghamton, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans said the robust water levels could be traced to the same factor that closed schools, clogged highways and blocked driveways this winter.</p>
        <p>''While our precipitation was not too far from normal, snowfalls were well above normal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New York City, which receives about 21 inches of snow in a typical winter, was covered with 45.3 inches this winter, he said. The Catskills, which get 80 to 150 inches, got 100 to 200 this winter. Newark, typically dusted by 24.1 inches, was blanketed this winter by 47.9.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Evans said all of this snow might end up having some unpleasant side effects.</p>
        <p>''We have deep snowpack in the Appalachians, which is melting,'' he said. ''So we may have some flooding.''</p>
        <p>Delaware River Basin Commission officials have issued some of the same warnings after reporting that the snowpack in some portions of the basin -- which includes parts of New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Delaware -- were at their highest levels in seven years.</p>
        <p>For Gary Donaldson, who in a couple of weeks will begin the most promising planting season in years, the basin numbers and the flood warnings are just proof of the capriciousness and whim of the weather patterns that he and other farmers rely on for their livelihood.</p>
        <p>''It's funny,'' he said, ''it's like you get it all at once or you don't get it at all.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
