<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Love and Ruin</title>
    <meta content="14BOOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/14/fashion/14BOOK1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1627150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bensimon, Kelly Killoren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Cruz, Melissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rabinovitz, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Penelope</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Style (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fashionista Files, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DA163FF937A25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Love and Ruin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Love and Ruin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Penelope Green</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Penelope</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Penelope Green reviews books American Style by Kelly Killoren Bensimon and The Fashionista Files: Adventures in Four-Inch Heels and Faux Pas by Melissa de la Cruz and Karen Rabinovitz; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN STYLE  By Kelly Killoren Bensimon  Assouline, $50.</p>
        <p>THE FASHIONISTA FILES  Adventures in Four-Inch Heels and Faux Pas  By Melissa de la Cruz and Karen Robinovitz  Ballantine Books, $13.95.</p>
        <p>THERE are odd juxtapositions in ''American Style,'' a grab bag of lush images illustrating the paradox contained in the title and the principle of e pluribus unum, as Harold Koda, curator of the Costume Institute at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, writes in his introduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN STYLE.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICAN STYLE  By Kelly Killoren Bensimon  Assouline, $50.</p>
        <p>THE FASHIONISTA FILES  Adventures in Four-Inch Heels and Faux Pas  By Melissa de la Cruz and Karen Robinovitz  Ballantine Books, $13.95.</p>
        <p>THERE are odd juxtapositions in ''American Style,'' a grab bag of lush images illustrating the paradox contained in the title and the principle of e pluribus unum, as Harold Koda, curator of the Costume Institute at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, writes in his introduction.</p>
        <p>And so a portrait of Lil' Kim is paired with one of Wallis Simpson; Kid Rock, all dressed up in a red undershirt, shares a spread with an archival photograph of Bergdorf-Goodman. In no particular order and organized only by the engine of democracy, says its author, Kelly Killoren Bensimon, there are head scratchers as well as satisfying moments: a photograph representing Halloween is a portrait of J.F.K. in the Oval Office, flanked by Caroline and John Jr. in full Halloween costume (or so you assume; you can't see their faces). Another, captioned ''Quilting,'' is rich portraiture of a 70's mother and child seated on a quilted couch. There are no page numbers, so it's impossible to cross-reference photo credits with images. Ms. Bensimon, a former model who is married to Gilles Bensimon, the fashion photographer and publication director of Elle, bristled when asked how she assembled the pictures, some of which were taken by her husband.</p>
        <p>''Everyone says, 'Gilles just gives Kelly all his stuff,' '' she said last week by telephone. ''They don't realize how much research I did. It's the same way I got Dick Avedon's picture or Patrick Demarchelier's. I just asked him, and he said, 'Yeah.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bensimon was initially interested in making a book highlighting American designers from the turn of the 20th century. ''But the images were either nonexistent or unavailable,'' she said. ''So that's when I began to explore American icons.''</p>
        <p>Warming to her theme, she stressed that those icons ''weren't taken from the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bensimon continued: ''I really want to emphasize that every aspect of my life has contributed to this book. From my education at Columbia to reading Hemingway in Paris to cutting my hair bilevel, it's like I was a sponge. This is not a feel-good book, something light and fluffy. I want it to empower people. In this political climate, there's a reason this book had to come out.''</p>
        <p>The precious picture-book title is the signature of the Assouline imprint, now four years old in this country. Its principal, Prosper Assouline, explained by telephone his intention to build a luxury brand of books, with Assouline boutiques in Saks Fifth Avenue stores. Rather than publishing books about fashion, his notion is to make fashionable books -- objects in themselves, or book couture.</p>
        <p>Open last week in Manhattan, the Assouline boutique sells candles scented like libraries for $45. Then there is ''the maximum item,'' for $9,500, a steamer trunk made by Goyard and filled with 100 photographic biographies published by Assouline. A special edition of a book called ''Rajasthan'' is printed on cotton, covered in silk, and wrapped in a vintage sari. At $600, Mr. Assouline explained in his highly accented, cinematic English, ''it cost the same as a pair of Manolos.''</p>
        <p>The price of shoes, particularly Manolos, is the dark undercurrent of an ostensibly fluffy book called ''The Fashionista Files: Adventures in Four-Inch Heels and Faux Pas.'' Its authors, Karen Robinovitz and Melissa de la Cruz, have toiled in and around the fashion/style/entertainment media for years. With their noses pressed right up against the glass, the two share a love of clothes and celebrity so extreme it has nearly beggered them both. Folded into this how-to manual of style is a cautionary mini-memoir that explores the pathology of fashion in a story that is as sad as any other addict's tale: ''Postcards From the Edge of the Runway'' might be a worthy subtitle.</p>
        <p>Sitting in a therapist's office, Ms. Robinovitz wonders how she'll pay her doctor, who suggests she limit her expenses to $3,000 a season. Ms. Robinovitz, who confesses a continued inability to pay her taxes and has exactly $12 to her name at that particular moment, is aghast: ''I'm wearing $3,000!''</p>
        <p>Ms. de la Cruz writes of relationships strained to breaking by debt. ''Sometimes when I call, my friends don't even bother to say, 'Hello,' only 'How much?' ''</p>
        <p>The disconnect between those confessionals and a sidebar, for example, on how to get front-row seats at a fashion show is bizarre and jarring, flashes of insight flattened with inanity.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Ms. de la Cruz reports, she was at her nadir, utterly broke: ''I owned a closetful of designer clothes I hardly wore, an apartment full of furniture for people I'll never entertain and absolutely nothing to show for the hundreds of thousands of dollars I've made except for multiple taxi receipts, torn dinner chits, club invitations, souvenir champagne corks and maybe a Polaroid of me, completely decked out, smiling garishly into the flashing lights.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
