<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warming Trends: Build a Fire (or Fly to an Island)</title>
    <meta content="11ctcold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/11/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/11ctcold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1724244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT AT ITS BEST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1D61131F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warming Trends: Build a Fire (or Fly to an Island)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Warming Trends: Build a Fire (or Fly to an Island)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACEY STOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUDI BASS is a self-described ''winter person'' and lifelong skier whose husband, Duane, directs the ski racing program at Mount Southington. Après-ski at their home in Southington, the couple used to enjoy nothing more than curling up in front of a roaring fire except for one thing: it was cold.</p>
        <p>''It was lovely to look at, but it sucked all of the heat right out of the house,'' Ms. Bass said. So last year, the Basses replaced their masonry fireplace with a wood burning stove. ''We had to consider the cost of heat,'' she said. ''It's gotten crazy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year, the ice, the slush and the chapped lips have been overshadowed by the cost of heating fuel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUDI BASS is a self-described ''winter person'' and lifelong skier whose husband, Duane, directs the ski racing program at Mount Southington. Après-ski at their home in Southington, the couple used to enjoy nothing more than curling up in front of a roaring fire except for one thing: it was cold.</p>
        <p>''It was lovely to look at, but it sucked all of the heat right out of the house,'' Ms. Bass said. So last year, the Basses replaced their masonry fireplace with a wood burning stove. ''We had to consider the cost of heat,'' she said. ''It's gotten crazy.''</p>
        <p>Even for winter sports enthusiasts, the months December through March have a downside: the ice, the slush and the chapped lips. This year, these routine complaints have been overshadowed by a biggie: the cost of heating fuel.</p>
        <p>More than half of Connecticut residents heat their homes with oil, a commodity that is expected to cost 25 percent more this year for households in the Northeast, according to data from the Energy Information Administration of the federal Department of Energy. And for natural gas, which is used by roughly a third of state residents, the expected increase is 27 percent.</p>
        <p>According to the Independent Connecticut Petroleum Association, citing statistics from the Connecticut Office of Policy and Management, heating oil was $2.41 a gallon as of Dec. 5 this year. That compares with $2.49 a gallon on Nov. 8 and $1.39 in November 2003. Christian Herb, the spokesman for the association, an advocacy group of 450 companies, said that more than half of customers locked in oil prices last spring by pre-buying oil.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people want to lock in and not be subject to geopolitical events, weather and whatever else can affect costs,'' Mr. Herb said.</p>
        <p>On a raw day in mid-November, a delivery truck from Kasden Fuel pulled up to Joanne Hoye's home in West Hartford. It was her second delivery of the autumn; she paid $2.40 a gallon for 125 gallons, having locked in the price earlier in the year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hoye, an agent with Prudential Connecticut Realty, said clients were increasingly concerned with energy costs.</p>
        <p>''From starter homes to large places, people want to know the cost of last year's heat,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But when the temperatures dip to zero and below, people are forced to turn up the heat, she said, especially when they have young children.</p>
        <p>''At other times, they'll just buy more Irish sweaters, fleece and mohair throws,'' said Ms. Hoye, a realtor for 29 years.</p>
        <p>In addition to keeping an eye on the thermostat, Connecticut residents have turned to other sources of energy. Ms. Bass, who works with children with disabilities, estimated that she had cut her heating costs in half by using a wood stove.</p>
        <p>Mark Tiso, manager of Dean's Stove and Spa in Southington, said sales were brisk for stoves using wood, gas and pellets. Dean's has limited the sale of the pellets -- a wood product the size of gerbil food -- to customers who had bought pellet stoves from the store, he said. As for the stoves, ''we've seen an increase in sales of between 25 and 40 percent, depending on the models,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, pellets were back-ordered because of high demand. At the Home Depot in Waterbury, where they cost $229 a ton, there was a 10-week wait as of mid-November.</p>
        <p>Firewood suppliers, such as Phil Snow, owner of Snow's Farm in Easton, are also having a banner year. Sales have increased 50 percent, with customers ordering three to four cords of wood this year to mitigate the cost of heating oil and natural gas, he said.</p>
        <p>''It used to be that people bought wood for cosmetic reasons -- romance, you know, aesthetics,'' said Mr. Snow, whose family has owned Snow's Farm for 93 years. ''Now it's necessary. They're trying to save money.''</p>
        <p>Orders are also up at the Wood Yard, a firewood cutting and delivery program for homeless and addicted men that is part of the Open Hearth, a mission in Hartford, said Michael Woolworth, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>Keeping the cold air out is also keeping residents busy. Electric blankets and heating pads were selling well at the Linens 'n Things in Jewett City in mid-November, and supplies were low at a Target store in Farmington.</p>
        <p>Despite a string of warm late-autumn days, sales of winterizing materials have been brisk at Pfau's Hardware in West Hartford, said Russell Hunter, the owner. Top sellers are foam or rubber strips to seal air leaks, spray-on foam insulation to wrap pipes and a shrink-wrap plastic to eliminate window drafts. There has also been a run on portable heaters, which allow empty nesters rattling around a big house to warm up a den or study without raising the thermostat in the rest of the house.</p>
        <p>Escaping the cold is another popular strategy for those who are carefree or affluent enough.</p>
        <p>Dave Walsh, a produce manager at Stop &amp; Shop and his wife, Mary Ellen, a dental assistant, were strolling around the Mohegan Sun Casino on a weekday last month, tanned from a recent Caribbean cruise. They noted without too much smugness that they had locked in their oil price this summer at $2.19 a gallon but said they nevertheless worry about energy costs.</p>
        <p>''We put on sweaters and blankets, everything to keep warm at home,'' Ms. Walsh said.</p>
        <p>Her husband added with a grin, ''But we're already thinking about what island to go to next.''</p>
        <p>At Sanditz Travel in West Hartford, warm travel destinations for the winter season are, well, hot, according to Bernice Czertak, a travel agent for more than two decades. Ms. Czertak said that there were few warm-weather options left for Christmas and New Year's, but that she was booking plenty of islands and cruises for the rest of the winter season. For those flying out of Hartford, she recommends Puerto Rico. ''It's a nonstop flight,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In Greenwich, where the well heeled plan vacations six months ahead, school calendar in hand, destinations like St. Bart's and Raffles Resort in the Grenadines are popular, said Doug Knight, owner of the Travel Desk of Connecticut, based in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>For those who are staying closer to home, maybe in front of a fireplace, or a wood stove, more modest pleasures will have to suffice. Nelson Veiga, owner of Dotcom Wine and Spirits in West Hartford, recommends a nice glass of port, a fortified wine that is very warming, he said.</p>
        <p>For those on a budget, Mr. Veiga suggested a Fonseca Bin 27.</p>
        <p>The price is $17.99 a bottle: more than a gallon of fuel oil, but much, much cheaper than a vacation in St. Bart's.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT AT ITS BEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
