<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharapova and Serena Williams Beat Heat on Way to a Rematch</title>
    <meta content="25TENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/25/sports/tennis/25tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1644885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mauresmo, Amelie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharapova, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Serena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED81F38F936A15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharapova and Serena Williams Beat Heat on Way to a Rematch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sharapova and Serena Williams Beat Heat on Way to a Rematch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, Tuesday, Jan. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serena Williams defeats Amelie Mauresmo in Australian Open quarterfinals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maria Sharapova suffered in the Australian summer heat, grimacing and seeking shade between points with as much determination as she usually seeks out the lines. Serena Williams seemed hardly bothered by the thermometer reading at all, warming up for her quarterfinal in long sleeves and her now-traditional boots and dashing around the court as if it were April in Paris.</p>
        <p>But though the method and style differed greatly, Sharapova and Williams emerged from this dry-roasted Tuesday -- close to 120 degrees on the court -- with victories and another chance to play each other in a high-profile match.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Serena Williams will play Maria Sharapova in the semifinals after shrugging off the heat and overwhelming Amélie Mauresmo, 6-2, 6-2, on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maria Sharapova suffered in the Australian summer heat, grimacing and seeking shade between points with as much determination as she usually seeks out the lines. Serena Williams seemed hardly bothered by the thermometer reading at all, warming up for her quarterfinal in long sleeves and her now-traditional boots and dashing around the court as if it were April in Paris.</p>
        <p>But though the method and style differed greatly, Sharapova and Williams emerged from this dry-roasted Tuesday -- close to 120 degrees on the court -- with victories and another chance to play each other in a high-profile match.</p>
        <p>Sharapova, the 17-year-old Russian with the American accent, has won their past two encounters, becoming a star by surprising Williams in last year's Wimbledon final, then proving it was no fluke by trumping her again in the final of the Tour championships in Williams's home city, Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>This summit meeting will take place Thursday in the semifinals of the Australian Open. ''I can't wait,'' Williams said after finishing off No. 2-seeded Amélie Mauresmo, visibly diminished by a leg injury, in little more than an hour, 6-2, 6-2.</p>
        <p>Sharapova had to work a great deal harder in the day's first match at Rod Laver Arena to overcome her sturdy compatriot Svetlana Kuz-netsova, 4-6, 6-2, 6-2.</p>
        <p>''It was hot out there, and she had to play three sets, so I'm sure that wasn't easy to do,'' Williams said of Sharapova. ''To be honest, I feel I don't have anything to lose. I was way too nervous at Wimbledon. I couldn't sleep. I couldn't breathe. Sometimes you want it too bad that you just freak yourself out. So now I feel fine.''</p>
        <p>Williams won this tournament in 2003, completing her self-dubbed ''Serena Slam'' with her fourth consecutive Grand Slam singles title. But she missed last year's Australian Open after having knee surgery and dealing with the murder of her half sister Yetunde Price. She arrived in Melbourne this year seeded seventh, and she is the only member of her remarkable family still in contention: her older sister Venus was beaten, 7-5, 7-6 (3), by the big-serving Australian Alicia Molik in a fourth-round match on Monday.</p>
        <p>But Serena Williams does not take kindly to assertions that she and her sister are in decline. ''I don't appreciate that language, to be honest with you,'' she said. ''I'm tired of not saying anything, but that's not fair. We've been practicing really hard, we've had some serious injuries. I had surgery, and after surgery I got to the finals of Wimbledon. I don't know too many people that have done that.''</p>
        <p>''Venus played a player yesterday who just played out of her mind, and Venus made some errors she probably shouldn't have made,'' Williams continued. ''And to top it off, we have a very, very, very, very close family, and to be in some situation we've been placed in the past little over a year, it's not easy to come out and just perform at your best when you realize there are so many things that are so important. So, no, we're not declining. We're here, and I don't have to win this tournament to prove anything.''</p>
        <p>The quality of play was very sketchy in Sharapova's 2-hour 17-minute test of character, particularly from Kuznetsova, who lost her powerful serve eight times in a row in the second and third sets.</p>
        <p>''My body was there, but my mind was not there at all,'' said Kuznetsova, the United States Open champion who is seeded fifth. ''I didn't do anything to win this match. I didn't deserve to win.''</p>
        <p>With temperatures off court approaching 100 degrees and temperatures on court closer to 120, Sharapova's father, Yuri, and the accompanying entourage were wrapped up in towels and reaching for their water bottles although they were doing nothing more than sitting on the edge of their seats.</p>
        <p>''I've played in hot weather, but never played three sets in hot weather and never played the quarterfinals of the Australian Open in hot weather, so this was a first for me,'' said Sharapova, who lives and trains in steamy Florida yet looked out of her element.</p>
        <p>But no matter the climate, she retained her uncommon will to win, and though Kuznetsova won the first set and produced just enough winners under pressure in the final set to keep the suspense bubbling, Sharapova was the one who ended up letting her racket fly in relief after hitting a forehand passing shot crosscourt to take the match.</p>
        <p>As she thrust her long arms into the air and covered her face with her hands with a mixture of disbelief and relief, it looked as if she had won her first Australian Open instead of her first quarterfinal. ''I need a wheelchair,'' the fourth-seeded Sharapova said.</p>
        <p>Serena Williams required no such assistance. Her victory over Mauresmo was her ninth in 10 matches against the talented but fragile Frenchwoman, and though Mauresmo had shown flashes of superior form coming into this quarterfinal, Williams was the more focused, confident and consistent player.</p>
        <p>Mauresmo, her left thigh wrapped and her movement limited, never posed a threat, despite the fact that this high-bouncing surface suits her game (she reached her only Grand Slam singles final here in 1999).</p>
        <p>''I thought I would recover pretty well with a day off, but that wasn't the case,'' said Mauresmo, who retired from this event last year before the quarterfinals with a back injury. ''The frustrating part is that I've never worked harder in the off-season trying to prepare my body and do preventative work.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
