<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flooding Takes Toll in New Jersey And Is Blamed in Connecticut Death</title>
    <meta content="16flood" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/16/nyregion/16flood.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1710147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED7143FF935A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flooding Takes Toll in New Jersey And Is Blamed in Connecticut Death</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flooding Takes Toll in New Jersey and Is Blamed in Connecticut Death</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHADI RAHIMI; Nate Schweber contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As flood waters began to recede in parts of the Northeast early yesterday, many New Jersey residents who had fled their homes during the week returned to survey the damage. In Connecticut, meanwhile, rescue crews found the body of a 75-year-old man who had been swept away by rushing waters at a campground in Stafford Springs.</p>
        <p>The death occurred after the East Hartford man, Robert Goulet, was swept away by waters when he tried to get out of his pickup truck, which had been stuck in an area of the Roaring Brook Campground, the state police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As flood waters began to recede, many New Jersey residents who had fled their homes during the week returned to survey the damage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As flood waters began to recede in parts of the Northeast early yesterday, many New Jersey residents who had fled their homes during the week returned to survey the damage. In Connecticut, meanwhile, rescue crews found the body of a 75-year-old man who had been swept away by rushing waters at a campground in Stafford Springs.</p>
        <p>The death occurred after the East Hartford man, Robert Goulet, was swept away by waters when he tried to get out of his pickup truck, which had been stuck in an area of the Roaring Brook Campground, the state police said.</p>
        <p>Someone called 911 at 1:22 a.m. yesterday to report that Mr. Goulet, who had a seasonal residence at the campground, was missing, the police said. Rescue crews and family members found his body at 5:32 a.m., about 200 yards from his truck, the police said.</p>
        <p>In northern New Jersey, swollen rivers were beginning to subside yesterday, though some were expected to remain flooded until tomorrow, according to the National Weather Service.</p>
        <p>As the sun peeked through the clouds yesterday, warming temperatures into the 70's, New Jersey residents sloshed through waterlogged neighborhoods, removing debris from their yards and pumping water from their basements. A state of emergency ordered by Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey on Friday was lifted last night.</p>
        <p>''We seem to be turning the corner right now,'' said Neil Buccino, a spokesman for the state's Office of Emergency Management, adding that many areas of New Jersey remained flooded.</p>
        <p>Many residents of towns in Monmouth County -- including Loch Arbour, Spring Lake, Ocean Township and Bradley Beach -- were returning to homes with flooded basements and no power, said the county's director of emergency management, Harry J. Conover.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conover said swift northeast winds and high tides had caused lakes and streams to surge into streets, seeping into homes and swallowing cars, with many remaining underwater yesterday.</p>
        <p>In Spring Lake, a mandatory evacuation of 350 homes was ordered, Mr. Buccino said,</p>
        <p>and 300 were evacuated in neighboring Belmar. Residents in towns that had also been flooded by storms in April surveyed the damage from the recent storm with frustration.</p>
        <p>In Lincoln Park in Morris County, John and Linda Puleo wore matching yellow galoshes as they walked around their Riveredge Road home, which had three feet of water in the basement.</p>
        <p>''I'm helpless,'' Mr. Puleo said. ''There's nothing I can do but just sit around and wait for the water to go away.'' He said a flood in April had caused $20,000 in damages to the house.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, flood waters forced the temporary closing of Interstate 91 yesterday, and flooding caused pockets of families to evacuate, said Rich Harris, a spokesman for Gov. M. Jodi Rell.</p>
        <p>''Now the only real concern is that we're supposed to get a couple of bands of wind,'' Mr. Harris said. ''With the ground as soaked as it is, it may pose danger if the trees take out power lines.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
