<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Savings Around The Fire</title>
    <meta content="11stove" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/11/business/yourmoney/11stove.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1724093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DC1131F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Savings Around The Fire</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finding Savings Around the Fire</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL FITZGERALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ERIC GEIGER thinks of the wood stove he just bought for his family's home in Norfolk, Mass., as an investment with benefits. Because the cost of natural gas is expected to soar this winter, he has bought a fireplace insert, a wood stove designed to fit into an existing fireplace.</p>
        <p>''When we heard that fuel costs were going to go up 50 percent, that fueled us to go get it,'' said Mr. Geiger, 45, a handyman partial to puns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amid dire warnings about fuel prices, sales of wood stoves have jumped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ERIC GEIGER thinks of the wood stove he just bought for his family's home in Norfolk, Mass., as an investment with benefits. Because the cost of natural gas is expected to soar this winter, he has bought a fireplace insert, a wood stove designed to fit into an existing fireplace.</p>
        <p>''When we heard that fuel costs were going to go up 50 percent, that fueled us to go get it,'' said Mr. Geiger, 45, a handyman partial to puns.</p>
        <p>He estimates that the stove will save him about $800 a season on fuel, enough to cover the stove's cost, including installation, in about three and a half years. And if a storm knocks out electrical power, he will still have heat. The bonus is the ambience: ''We just like the idea of having that nice warm heat coming out of the fireplace,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Amid dire warnings about fuel prices, sales of wood stoves have jumped. Hearth &amp; Home, a trade magazine in Gilford, N.H., found that overall sales of stoves -- wood, wood pellet and gas -- were up 82 percent in October from the same month a year earlier. Richard Wright, the editor, said he expected that nearly all of the increase was in wood stoves. Sales probably would have been even higher, he said, if demand had not caught stove makers by surprise.</p>
        <p>Gas stoves typically outsell wood stoves by two to one because they are ignited with the flick of a switch, expel far fewer emissions and require almost no maintenance. Also gaining popularity are pellet stoves, which burn pellets made from wood scraps.</p>
        <p>That gas-wood ratio has been reversed this year at En-R-Gy Saver, the Holliston, Mass., store where Mr. Geiger bought his stove. Bob Christensen, a co-owner, whose family has run the store since 1977, says he has not seen wood stoves sell this briskly since the energy crisis of the late 1970's and early 80's.</p>
        <p>Customers want wood stoves because their fuel literally grows on trees. But that fuel is free only if you have access to a ready supply of trees or are willing to scrounge for logs; cords of wood already sell for more than $250 in some parts of the Northeast, and some people say the cost could hit $300 this winter. (Users may go through two to four cords in a winter.) And wood stoves generally do not work as a home's sole source of heat, especially in colder climates. While manufacturers may claim that a large high-end stove will heat a 2,000-square-foot house, many homes are not laid out in a way that allows a stove's heat to circulate throughout. So a furnace may be needed to ensure heat when and where you want it. Giant stoves known as wood boilers can replace a furnace, but the expenses for wood, insurance, permits and installation are higher than for wood stoves. Most people choose either fireplace inserts or stand-alone wood stove models, some of which are small enough to put on an existing hearth. Mr. Wright's magazine tracks 50 stove makers, with the three largest sellers of wood stoves being Hearth &amp; Homes Technologies, a unit of the HNI Corporation; the CFM Corporation, which makes Vermont Castings and other brands; and Lennox Hearth Products, a unit of Lennox International. Each has multiple brands and styles.</p>
        <p>Copious and useful information is available on the Internet. A good overview can be found on the Environmental Protection Agency site, at epa .gov/woodstoves. It offers a list of 623 stoves certified as meeting E.P.A. emissions standards.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. site is also a good place to start because wood stoves have environmental issues. Some communities ban wood-burning altogether at various points in the winter, and many places require permits to use a wood stove, partly because their smoke represents the largest source of winter air pollution in some areas. Retailers typically know the local requirements.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. toughened standards for new stoves in 1992, cutting typical emissions levels by two-thirds. But it estimates that of roughly 10 million stoves in use, 7 million to 8 million do not comply because they were sold before 1992. In partnership with the Hearth, Patio and Barbecue Association, a trade group based in Arlington, Va., the E.P.A. has sponsored ''change-outs'' like one earlier this year in which the industry gave free E.P.A.-compliant stoves to residents of Libby, Mont., where wood stoves are the biggest reason that its winter air pollution is among the nation's worst.</p>
        <p>Even smoke from stoves that comply with E.P.A. requirements can be bad for some people, like those with chronic conditions, the elderly and small children. And some organizations, like Clean Air Revival Inc., in Point Arena, Calif., have opposed the use of wood stoves.</p>
        <p>Joel Schwartz, an environmental epidemiologist at Harvard who once worked at the E.P.A. and is credited with helping to require the removal of lead from gasoline, said it was not clear that wood smoke was as bad for people as, say, cigarette smoke -- the few studies of wood smoke have shown mixed results. Still, he said, the scientific consensus is that wood smoke is bad for you, or more likely bad for your neighbors, and that in densely populated areas, wood stoves are ''not a reasonable way to heat homes.''</p>
        <p>Even E.P.A.-compliant wood stoves will generate much higher levels of emissions than other forms of fuel. But consumers who are worried about rising energy costs can cite some environmental advantages in wood stoves, like the lowest greenhouse gas emissions and acid levels added to the air of any major fuel source. And wood is a renewable resource. Groups like the Wood Heat Organization of Canada (woodheat.org) have outlined ways to burn wood to minimize emissions.</p>
        <p>THE choice of fuels involves environmental tradeoffs. From a systemic perspective, wood stoves have the best overall energy return on investment of any fuel source, said James E. Houck, president of Omni Environmental Services in Beaverton, Ore., which tests stoves to make sure that they meet E.P.A. standards. But even the most careful consumer using the lowest-emission stove, he said, will increase air pollution locally.</p>
        <p>No decent-sized stove is cheap. At En-R-Gy Saver, the store where Mr. Geiger spent about $2,400 for his fireplace insert, the least-expensive wood stove is $431 -- and it will heat only a small room. A big stove, capable of heating at least 1,000 square feet, runs $1,500 to $2,500. A buyer who wants a finish different from cast-iron black -- enamel, for example -- will pay extra.</p>
        <p>But the total cost is rarely limited to a stove's price. For instance, the local inspector initially refused to issue a permit for the stove installed by Mr. Geiger because the hearth did not meet the town's 16-inch length requirement. Mr. Geiger paid $300 to hire a mason to permanently extend the hearth, and the permit was received.</p>
        <p>Stand-alone stoves may need a hearth built for them, and may also need to have a chimney pipe installed, which can more than double the cost of buying the stove. Houses with an existing chimney may need to have a chimney liner installed.</p>
        <p>Longtime users of wood stoves say that there are other costs to consider -- mainly the commitment of time and effort. The joke is that a wood stove owner is warmed three times -- once when cutting the wood, once when splitting and storing it, and finally when it's burned.</p>
        <p>Sondra Feldstein, who bought a wood stove last year for her family's farm in Bondurant, Iowa, said that with the jump in the cost of liquid propane, her furnace's main fuel, the stove would pay for itself before this winter was over because she already had plenty of wood on hand. She also uses the stove to cook foods like soups. Her main complaint was that it needed annual ''curing,'' using a special heat-resistant paint to prevent rust. ''It really stunk,'' she said. ''They'll tell you to do it again every year, and I've just not done it.''</p>
        <p>Despite the costs and environmental issues, there seems to be something primal about a wood fire. Michael and Virginia Griffin, of Fairport, N.Y., bought a wood stove in September to ensure that they would have heat and a cooking surface if the power went out. Mr. Griffin, a bassist in the Rochester Symphony, said that the first time he used the stove, ''it made one room extraordinarily warm, and that was really nice.'' The next day, he said, he wanted to use it again.</p>
        <p>QUICK READ</p>
        <p>Much advice about wood stoves and responsible wood burning can be found online. Here are some organizations and agencies that offer sites:</p>
        <p>Wood Heat Organization, a Canadian nonprofit group, at woodheat.org.</p>
        <p>Bay Area Air Quality Management District, at www.baaqmd.gov/pio /wood--burning/.</p>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency, at epa.gov/woodstoves.</p>
        <p>Department of Energy, at eere.energy.gov/consumer/your--home/space--heating--cooling/index.cfm/mytopic=12570.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
