<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mixed Headlines Greet the Commander</title>
    <meta content="23REAX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/23/international/europe/23reax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BUSH IN EUROPE: CONTINENTAL COMMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Handelsblatt</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Der Spiegel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Corriere della Sera</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DD163DF930A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mixed Headlines Greet the Commander</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mixed Headlines Greet the Commander</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>MAINZ, Germany, Feb. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Europeans news media express satisfaction that Pres Bush, once seen as hostile, is showing friendlier, conciliatory side during current visit; still, most of press commentary on Bush's 'new era' speech in Brussels is heavily tinged with skepticism about whether changed tone of American pronouncements will be followed by practical trans-Atlantic cooperation; photo shows anti-Bush demonstrators in Berlin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Europeans watching President Bush's trip are clearly glad to see an American president once thought hostile showing a friendlier, conciliatory side. Still, most of the press commentary after Mr. Bush's ''new era'' speech in Brussels on Monday night was heavily tinged with skepticism about whether the changed tone of American pronouncements would be followed by practical trans-Atlantic cooperation.</p>
        <p>''The more the governments talk about a new beginning, the less one wants to believe it,'' the German business paper Handelsblatt said in an editorial on Wednesday. ''The trans-Atlantic partnership would be better off if it did not just talk up common values, but set out a common strategy. But a grand design is as far away as it was a year ago.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most of the press commentary following President Bush's speech in Brussels on Monday night was tinged with skepticism about whether it would be followed by trans-Atlantic cooperation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Europeans watching President Bush's trip are clearly glad to see an American president once thought hostile showing a friendlier, conciliatory side. Still, most of the press commentary after Mr. Bush's ''new era'' speech in Brussels on Monday night was heavily tinged with skepticism about whether the changed tone of American pronouncements would be followed by practical trans-Atlantic cooperation.</p>
        <p>''The more the governments talk about a new beginning, the less one wants to believe it,'' the German business paper Handelsblatt said in an editorial on Wednesday. ''The trans-Atlantic partnership would be better off if it did not just talk up common values, but set out a common strategy. But a grand design is as far away as it was a year ago.''</p>
        <p>In a similar vein, the conservative French paper Le Figaro allowed, ''The change in tone is spectacular.'' Mr. Bush, the paper continued, ''has suddenly discovered that Europe exists. If he took four years to do so, let us recognize the blame falls on us Europeans, for a great part. And haven't the Europeans taken four years to accept that Bush is the elected president of the U.S.?''</p>
        <p>But, the paper said, simply the fact that everybody wants the trans-Atlantic relationship to improve does not guarantee that it will. ''After his re-election, George W. Bush has understood the urgency in establishing a normal climate in trans-Atlantic relations,'' the paper said. ''This is the reason for his trip. Does he really need Europe? Despite his repeated assurances, it is not certain.''</p>
        <p>Much of the commentary after the speech provided a sort of laundry list of global trouble spots where Europe's generally more multilateral, diplomatic approach to problem-solving might cause further trans-Atlantic rifts in the future. The Iran issue was probably the most frequently mentioned, with Europeans criticizing the United States for failing to give its full backing to the European diplomatic initiative aimed at persuading Tehran not to develop nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Behind the concern over specific issues is a deeper skepticism about Mr. Bush's motives. Essentially, commentators were asking after the speech in Brussels whether Mr. Bush's call for a ''new era'' in trans-Atlantic affairs signaled a sincere willingness to listen to Europe, or whether the American president was just giving Europeans a chance, finally, to agree with the United States.</p>
        <p>''In his speech on Monday in Brussels, he used the word 'alliance' 12 times to describe the American-European relationship,'' the German weekly Der Spiegel commented in its online edition. ''Europeans are lapping up the new openness, but also wondering just what is behind it and what exactly the world's most powerful man expects from them in return.''</p>
        <p>Some commentators indicated that with the perceived success of the Iraqi elections, Mr. Bush has greater credibility in Europe than he did before, especially in his main argument that Iraq is a success in the making, not the unmitigated disaster that most Europeans have believed it to be until recently.</p>
        <p>''The president, with his second mandate and the success of the Iraqi elections, is stronger than before, while the Europe that opposed him is weak, having made too many errors,'' the Italian daily Corriere della Sera wrote in a front page editorial. ''Statements like, 'You can't export democracy through war,' are no longer fashionable.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, like many Europeans, the paper worried that trans-Atlantic differences remained real and would not be overcome by a simple warming up of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''Divergences, in interests and in culture, add up,'' the paper said. ''They are not so strong as to annul what unites America and Europe. But they are strong enough to keep the way open for new divisions.''</p>
        <p>A number of papers recalled a strategic formula commonly attributed to Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice when she was national security adviser and trans-Atlantic relations were at their lowest ebb: that American policy would be to forgive the Russians, ignore the Germans and punish the French. The mere fact that Mr. Bush will be seeing the leaders of all three of those countries on his four-day trip to Europe was seen as a welcome and major change.</p>
        <p>''This week,'' the French newspaper Libération said, ''it will be coddle the French, embrace the Germans and gently remind the Russians about their small digressions in terms of democracy and their friendship with Syria.''</p>
        <p>The paper said the change in Washington's tone was being looked at with ''a mix of interest and skepticism'' and added: ''The list of potential disputes remains long, if it is about the nuclear dreams of Iran (a nation with which the U.S. does not want to negotiate), Hezbollah (which France does not want to include on the list of terrorist groups), the European project to lift the embargo on the sale of arms to China, the Middle East crisis, the fight over climate protection, the role of multilateral organizations and the repression of war crimes.''</p>
        <p>The fact, as the paper put it, that ''the elections in Iraq went well gives Bush a little boost with Europeans,'' but the United States still ''has to show it is ready to give up unilateralism; Europe has to prove it can sustain a unified role.''</p>
        <p>BUSH IN EUROPE: CONTINENTAL COMMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
