<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weed Whackers</title>
    <meta content="07casey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/07/books/review/07casey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Gardening Books by James Dodson and William Alexander"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Casey, Constance</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dodson, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alexander, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Beautiful Madness (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">$64 Tomato, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Dodson, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alexander, William</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Beautiful Madness: One Man's Journey Through Other People's Gardens (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDA133FF934A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weed Whackers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Weed Whackers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE CASEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Casey, Constance</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Constance Casey reviews books Beautiful Madness: One Man's Journey</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEAUTIFUL MADNESS</p>
        <p>One Man's Journey Through</p>
        <p>Other People's Gardens.</p>
        <p>By James Dodson.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Dutton. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE $64 TOMATO</p>
        <p>By William Alexander.</p>
        <p>270 pp. Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>These two authors turn the planting and tending of green things into something more like extreme dirt-bike racing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEAUTIFUL MADNESS</p>
        <p>One Man's Journey Through</p>
        <p>Other People's Gardens.</p>
        <p>By James Dodson.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Dutton. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE $64 TOMATO</p>
        <p>By William Alexander.</p>
        <p>270 pp. Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill. $22.95.</p>
        <p>It was never accurate to view gardening as tame, genteel and in some ways feminine. Any activity that involves pushing nature around necessarily demands force. The pendulum, however, may have just swung too far into the testosterone zone. With these two books we have something distinctly guy-ish: gardening as extreme sport. Both James Dodson and William Alexander turn the planting and tending of green things into something more like dirt-bike racing. They push themselves hard, in fact risking injuries. Alexander has a bit more perspective than Dodson. He can see that his quest for ''a real, landscaped, eat-your-heart-out-Monet, garden-magazine-quality garden'' is unrealistic.</p>
        <p>Dodson comes to gardening from writing about golf. He is author of a biography of Ben Hogan, and he collaborated with Arnold Palmer on ''A Golfer's Life.'' Dodson's lovely book ''Final Rounds'' chronicled an elegiac trip to Britain's golf courses with his ailing father. Horticulture has only recently become Dodson's obsession -- the madness of the title -- and in his garden world there are winners and losers. His message is that we are entering a Golden Age of Gardening, though he's not exactly clear about what that age will involve. It seems to mean lots more stuff to spend money on.</p>
        <p>''Beautiful Madness'' takes us on a four-season dash through other people's gardens (with weeks off for frenetic work in his own). Dodson's year begins and ends at the Philadelphia Flower Show (''the Super Bowl of botany''). In the following months he visits Monticello, garden clubs, nurseries and his mother's garden in North Carolina. Then on to the Chelsea Flower Show in England, to South Africa to see plants in the wild, and back to Philadelphia. (Not everyone, by the way, would agree with him that the people moving thousands of plants and tons of soil around at those two colossal flower shows are really being gardeners. For that week they're set designers.)</p>
        <p>On Dodson's travels various characters whiz by, each labeled with some forcedly poetic epithet. A man whose daffodils and tulips compete in the Philadelphia show is ''the Arnold Palmer of spring gardening'' and ''the Botticelli of Bulbs.'' Now and then Dodson returns to his home in Maine, his ''Yankee Sissinghurst,'' where he battles the climate, spending major bucks on plants that would be a lot happier farther south, in Thomas Jefferson's garden, perhaps. His impetuous decision, after a tough winter, to rip up every tree and bush that looks dead will bring a chill to the heart of more seasoned gardeners. Better to give the plants a few months to recover on their own. (Or if not, then they're compost.)</p>
        <p>Unlike the restless Dodson, Alexander does not stray far from a single three-acre space in a small town in the Hudson Valley. He imagines his as-yet unplanted garden saying to him: '' 'Come, bring me your seeds and water, and I will reward you.' And it would. And also humble me, and teach me, and become a place of solace, a battleground, a source of pride, a source of frustration, a time sink, a respite.''</p>
        <p>But like Dodson, Alexander becomes obsessed, particularly about the vegetable garden where the $64 tomato of the title grows. Some garden gourmets might consider the emblematic tomato, a rich and historic and tasty Brandywine, well worth the money spent on raised beds, fencing, compost, fertilizer, tools and deer repellent.</p>
        <p>Alexander makes life hard for himself. He spends long hours weeding, but resists using weed-smothering mulch. He's especially opposed to black plastic on the soil -- ''the condom approach to prevention.'' He uses a pitchfork, not a tiller, and never wears gloves, exulting in his rich topsoil: ''I loved the feel of it. I loved the fact that on a chilly but sunny spring day the soil was warmer than the air, that kneeling in it was comforting and warming.''</p>
        <p>Alexander may be overly driven. (He ends up looking at a very discouraging M.R.I. scan. ''No heavy lifting,'' his neurologist said, words that ''sent a chill down my herniated spine.'') But his writing is engaging, well paced and informative. Not so true, unfortunately, of Dodson's voice. The clearest message in ''Beautiful Madness'' is that the author had a great time.</p>
        <p>As a recent convert, Dodson finds everything new and fabulous and falls into cheerleading. His visit to the famous retail nursery White Flower Farm, for example, inspires uncritical prose only a little less polished than that nursery's own advertising copy. Enthusiasm leads Dodson to scatter through ''Beautiful Madness'' the phrase ''gardenlust,'' and to repeatedly use his fun new word -- ''hortgasm.'' His plant hunting companions on the South African trip repeatedly experience ''multiple hortgasms.'' We know everyone's excited and, apparently, satisfied, but we never learn the significance of the finds.</p>
        <p>In the midst of this ecstasy the reader remains puzzled about the purpose of the trip. At one point Dodson says he wanted to spend ''a year traveling through other people's gardens in search of green wisdom.'' Unfortunately he emerges at the end of the odyssey not much more thoughtful or enlightened than when he began.</p>
        <p>Dodson's title comes from an entry he finds in a yellowing logbook at a Welsh castle: ''This task has become a holy thing, a beautiful madness that consumes this learner's soul.'' We're told that this is the garden book of an obscure middle-aged monk named Brother John. Dodson neglects to give us a clue to the date of the observation. Was Brother John middle-aged in the Middle Ages, or last year?</p>
        <p>To my surprise, Dodson's specialty, the subject of golf, popped up in Alexander's book. After five years of garden toil (nights and weekends; he does have a good day job) Alexander begins to have doubts: ''My early-morning drives to the garden center for yet more mulch or to the stable for yet more horse manure took me past a golf club, where on any given day, dozens of men my age were passing their mornings socializing and (mildly) exercising and apparently having one hell of a good time. Why had I locked myself in a self-imposed purgatory of endless weeding, pruning and harvesting?''</p>
        <p>Alexander's questioning led him not, after all, to the golf club, but to moderation. In gardening he and Dodson have each had some golf-ish experiences. Both gardening and golf strain your back and weather your skin, and they involve the wearing of unflattering clothing. Both activities tend to attract people over 50, like these authors, who may not yet feel they have one foot in the grave but are nevertheless drawn closer to the soil (and to holes in the ground). Both provide a ritual. Golfers and gardeners go through the same motions year after year, but with slight changes that inspire hope that things will go better this time. The great advantage and solace of gardening is that there doesn't have to be a scorecard.</p>
        <p>Gardening Books by James Dodson and William Alexander Constance Casey, a former New York City Parks Department gardener, writes about gardening for Slate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Constance Casey, a former New York City Parks Department gardener, writes about gardening for Slate.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
