<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greater Role for Nonscientists In E.P.A. Pollution Decisions</title>
    <meta content="08pollution" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/08/washington/08pollution.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1810285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peacock, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Petroleum Institute</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DB1731F93BA35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greater Role for Nonscientists In E.P.A. Pollution Decisions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Greater Role for Nonscientists in E.P.A. Pollution Decisions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency changes way it sets standards to control dangerous air pollutants, enhancing role of agency's political appointees in scientific assessments and postponing required review by independent scientific experts; change is announced by agency's deputy administrator Marcus Peacock; he says it would streamline cumbersome process; decision draws scathing response from various environmental groups (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has changed the way it sets standards to control dangerous air pollutants like lead, ozone and tiny particles of soot, enhancing the role of the agency's political appointees in scientific assessments and postponing the required review by independent scientific experts.</p>
        <p>The change, which largely tracks the suggestions of the American Petroleum Institute but also adopts some recommendations of the agency's independent scientific advisers, was announced yesterday afternoon by the agency's deputy administrator, Marcus Peacock. Mr. Peacock said it would streamline a cumbersome process and bring it ''into the 21st century.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The changes to the way the E.P.A. sets standards to control air pollutants largely track the suggestions of the American Petroleum Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has changed the way it sets standards to control dangerous air pollutants like lead, ozone and tiny particles of soot, enhancing the role of the agency's political appointees in scientific assessments and postponing the required review by independent scientific experts.</p>
        <p>The change, which largely tracks the suggestions of the American Petroleum Institute but also adopts some recommendations of the agency's independent scientific advisers, was announced yesterday afternoon by the agency's deputy administrator, Marcus Peacock. Mr. Peacock said it would streamline a cumbersome process and bring it ''into the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>He also said the E.P.A. ''is committed to a timely and transparent process that uses the most up-to-date science available.'' Under the new system, he said, it will ''continue to adhere to the highest scientific standards and ensure we meet the agency's mission'' of protecting public health.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act requires that every five years, the agency review existing standards for the six air pollutants considered most dangerous to health. Two standards, for lead and ground-level ozone, are currently under review. A third, for lethal particles of soot, was left partly intact two months ago, a decision that ignored the consensus recommendation of the agency's scientific advisers that it be tightened.</p>
        <p>The decision announced yesterday, the culmination of months of review and comment, drew a scathing response from environmental groups like the Sierra Club and Clean Air Watch, as well as the American Lung Association. Vickie Patton, a senior lawyer with Environmental Defense, said ''the establishment of health-based standards are one of the single most important scientific decisions'' the E.P.A. made.</p>
        <p>The changes, Ms. Patton said, will compromise two aspects of the process ''integral to scientific integrity and independence.''</p>
        <p>For one thing, agency scientists will no longer produce their own independent review of the latest science to start the process of deciding whether a pollution standard -- for lead, say, or ozone -- is tough enough to protect public health. Instead, initial reviews will now involve both agency scientists and their political bosses and will produce a synopsis of ''policy-relevant'' science, agency officials said.</p>
        <p>''They are using this idea of streamlined and expedited decision-making as a Trojan horse to infect the most important decisions the administrator makes with politics,'' Ms. Patton said.</p>
        <p>In addition, she said, the role of the independent panel of scientific advisers -- who act as auditors, reviewing the document produced by agency scientists and advising top management -- has been diminished. The panel, the Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee, will now comment on the agency's proposed actions after the public has been notified of them, giving the scientists essentially the same kind of participation as industry lobbyists and environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Rogene Henderson, the advisory committee chairwoman, said she believed that agency scientists could continue to provide recommendations they thought most appropriate, ''but they will assuredly be asked to include some recommendation that is acceptable to upper-level management.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Henderson said the agency had accepted her group's recommendation that the review process include an early public workshop to review the current science and that the documents that result from the review be more concise.</p>
        <p>Still, she said, ''They will come out with their policy before we have a chance to comment on it.'' But she added quickly, ''They weren't taking our advice'' even under the old system, at least in the recent soot decision.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
