<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glimpses Of Greatness In Sturdy Arm Of Teenager</title>
    <meta content="11matsuzaka" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/11/sports/baseball/11matsuzaka.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1825657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Seibu Lions</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matsuzaka, Daisuke</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DF1F3FF932A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glimpses Of Greatness In Sturdy Arm Of Teenager</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Matsuzaka Masterpiece: Glimpses of Greatness in Arm of Teenager</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka had dirt on both knees of his gray uniform pants, dirt splattered on the front of his jersey and dirt smudges near his right elbow. He had pitched 16 innings, thrown well over 200 pitches, and now this stained, resilient athlete was warming up for inning No. 17.</p>
        <p>Eight and a half years ago, Matsuzaka established his legendary status in Japan with a feat of endurance that is still hard to fathom in the context of Major League Baseball, where pitch counts are closely monitored and even 100 pitches by a starter is considered substantial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight and a half years ago, Daisuke Matsuzaka established his legendary status in Japan with a feat of endurance that is still hard to fathom in the context of Major League Baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka had dirt on both knees of his gray uniform pants, dirt splattered on the front of his jersey and dirt smudges near his right elbow. He had pitched 16 innings, thrown well over 200 pitches, and now this stained, resilient athlete was warming up for inning No. 17.</p>
        <p>Eight and a half years ago, Matsuzaka established his legendary status in Japan with a feat of endurance that is still hard to fathom in the context of Major League Baseball, where pitch counts are closely monitored and even 100 pitches by a starter is considered substantial.</p>
        <p>Yet here was Matsuzaka, throwing pitch after pitch and barely resting between innings. With the 17th looming and Matsuzaka needing to get his 49th, 50th and 51st outs of the game, he stayed loose by tossing a ball along the left-field foul line.</p>
        <p>Of the countless details that can be culled from analyzing a videotape of Matsuzaka's performance that day in Japan's prestigious Koshien high school tournament, the sight of him warming up when many pitchers would have been falling down was as revealing as any. There would be no rest for this 17-year-old.</p>
        <p>After he unleashed his 250th pitch, he kept his right leg dangling in the air at the end of his delivery to see if his slider would finally end the game. When it was called a strike, when Matsuzaka had secured Yokohama's 9-7 victory over PL Gakuen, he simply lowered his head. It might have been his only option, a gesture of relief.</p>
        <p>''I had used every last bit of energy, and didn't have enough left to even celebrate,'' Matsuzaka said in a recent e-mail message in which he discussed his feat.</p>
        <p>A lot has changed for Matsuzaka since that day. He became a professional star in Japan and last March helped the Japanese national team win the first World Baseball Classic. This winter, the Boston Red Sox bid $51.1 million for the right to negotiate with him, then signed him to a six-year contract worth an additional $52 million.</p>
        <p>When pitchers and catchers report to spring training at 30 major league sites this week, Matsuzaka will be scrutinized as much as anyone. As the spring progresses, only Barry Bonds is likely to receive as much attention. But Matsuzaka, now 26, will be used to the spotlight and the pressure, partly because of what he achieved that one summer at Koshien.</p>
        <p>In the two-week nationally televised tournament that features nearly 50 high school teams, attracts more than 40,000 fans a game and may have more percolating intensity than March Madness does here, Matsuzaka was extraordinary. He pitched often and he pitched incredibly.</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka appeared in all six of Yokohama's games in that tournament, going 5-0 with a 1.17 earned run average, with five complete games and one save. On the day after the 250-pitch outing, Matsuzaka saved the semifinal victory for his team. On the day after that, he pitched a no-hitter in the championship game.</p>
        <p>By that point, Matsuzaka was willing to celebrate. After the final out, he clenched both fists and pumped them, then was mobbed by his teammates. Soon, the players lifted him off the ground, carrying him the way he had carried them for days. Across the last four steamy days of the tournament, he threw an astounding 535 pitches.</p>
        <p>''When he was finished at Koshien,'' said Craig Shipley, Boston's vice president for professional and international scouting, ''he was a legend.''</p>
        <p>How good can Matsuzaka be for the Red Sox? Will he stifle hitters in the United States the same way he silenced Japanese hitters on an amateur and a professional level? Did the Red Sox make a shrewd decision in spending so lavishly on a pitcher who has never worked an inning in the major leagues? Shipley, like others, can only speculate. The real answers will be coming soon enough.</p>
        <p>But the images from that tournament linger, a testament to Matsuzaka's durability, dedication, athleticism, swagger and prowess, all of which will presumably come to bear as he tries to make his mark in the majors and navigate his way in the intense rivalry between the Red Sox and Yankees.</p>
        <p>In the Koshien tournament, Matsuzaka showed an impeccable delivery, pausing after raising his hands over his head, then dropping and driving toward the plate. He threw multiple pitches for strikes, moving from fastballs to sliders to curveballs to changeups like a young Pedro Martínez. His demeanor mixed stoicism with a dash of cockiness.</p>
        <p>''As the team's ace,'' Matsuzaka said in the e-mail message, ''I knew I had the responsibility to pitch.''</p>
        <p>And pitch and pitch. The 17-inning game was not a statistical masterpiece for Matsuzaka, who allowed 7 earned runs and 13 hits, while striking out 11 and walking 6. Matsuzaka's team trailed by 3-0 after two innings, and he twice lost one-run leads in extra innings.</p>
        <p>But in so many ways, the game was a masterpiece. Only one run that Matsuzaka surrendered was driven in by a hit that traveled more than 200 feet. He permitted three runs in the last 13 innings. In the 17th, Matsuzaka's fastball was still buzzing past hitters at speeds that appeared to be over 90 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>It was the type of draining test that Matsuzaka, who was schooled in the Japanese tenet that hard work conquers all, was suited to pass. When Matsuzaka was being groomed to be a pitcher, he routinely threw as many as 250 pitches a day to perfect his mechanics, paying extra attention to his breaking pitches.</p>
        <p>''It's a testament to his delivery that he didn't blow out after that game,'' Shipley said. ''You put that on a lot of guys and it's the end or the beginning of the end.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka said that the most pitches he had thrown before that marathon game was about 150 and that the most he threw afterward was about 150, with the Seibu Lions, his professional team in Japan. He said that during his 17-inning epic he was never concerned about injuring himself.</p>
        <p>''In a sense, I had been trained to throw many, many pitches,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Robert Whiting, an author who is an expert on Japanese baseball, said that teams usually ride one pitcher through the Koshien and that since the quarterfinals, the semifinals and the championship are played on three straight days, the ace of the staff is asked to do an immense amount.</p>
        <p>Whiting said there were some questions raised after Matsuzaka's herculean effort and some suggestions that there be days off between the last three games. But nothing has changed, he said.</p>
        <p>''Some people think it's a worthwhile price to pay,'' Whiting said. ''It's like the life of the cherry blossom, short but glorious.''</p>
        <p>Matsuzaka said Manager Motonori Watanabe ''expected me to throw from beginning to end.'' Yasuko Yanagita, a reporter who covered the 17-inning game, said Motonori felt that ''only Matsuzaka could pitch for them to win.''</p>
        <p>Al Leiter, a former major league pitcher, once struck out 32 batters in a 14-inning high school game in New Jersey. He said no pitch count was kept. He did not know how many pitches he threw, but he knows he was exhausted.</p>
        <p>''How do you think I felt?'' Leiter said. ''I couldn't lift my arm for three days.''</p>
        <p>If Leiter watched videotape of Matsuzaka's game, which took place Aug. 20, 1998, he would see the Yokohama fans crowded into Koshien Stadium, with hats on their heads and towels around their necks to combat the sun. Many wore the team's full uniform and barked into yellow bullhorns. Drumbeats backed up their chants.</p>
        <p>The tape reveals the intensity of the day, with fans overcome with emotion as the game stretched into extra innings. One opposing player, weeping and slumped over, had to be helped off the field after the game.</p>
        <p>In the middle of it all was Matsuzaka. Lanky and confident, he was consistent in his movements. He adjusted his sweat-stained blue-and-red cap before almost every pitch. He grabbed the resin bag, tossing it like a juggling ball. He sprinted on and off the mound, wearing uniform No. 1. When he faced trouble early, he smiled slyly.</p>
        <p>When Matsuzaka whiffed the last batter in the sixth, he screamed ''Yeah!'' in a rare display of emotion. He singled in the 11th and scored the go-ahead run by sliding into the catcher. In the bottom of the inning, he was one out away from victory when he surrendered a run-scoring single. Matsuzaka's Yokohama team took a 7-6 lead in the top of the 16th, but PL Gakuen tied the score when the Yokohama first baseman held the ball as a runner dashed home. At that point, Matsuzaka could be seen muttering.</p>
        <p>As Matsuzaka warmed up for the 17th, a two-out error gave Yokohama a chance. Ryota Tokiwa, the next batter, hit a two-run homer. Yokohama had a 9-7 edge and Yokohama had Matsuzaka.</p>
        <p>Needing a final out to end the marathon, Matsuzaka's 247th pitch was a sizzling fastball for a called strike, the 248th was another fastball for a ball and the 249th was a fastball for another strike. Matsuzaka grabbed the rosin bag again before his 250th pitch, squeezed it and then slammed it in the dirt. He tossed the slider, waited for the final strike call, then bowed his head.</p>
        <p>''I was relieved,'' Matsuzaka said, ''that the game was over and we had won.''</p>
        <p>Two days later, Matsuzaka was brilliant again, with a no-hitter in the title game against Kyoto Seisho. Almost 18 years earlier, Matsuzaka's mother had named him after Daisuke Araki, a pitcher who had excelled at Koshien. Now another Daisuke was the king of Koshien.</p>
        <p>After Yokohama's victories, the players lined up side by side and sang the team song. Matsuzaka showed more emotion as a singer than as a pitcher, singing long and loud. He was a teenage legend in Japan back then, a pitching machine. Now that pitching machine, that artist, is trying to become a legend here.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
